<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="2"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 2 - Adjectival Passives.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">16</page>
<page type="last">60</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="1"/>
<count type="table" count="34"/>
<count type="formula" count="0"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="61"/>
<count type="page" count="45"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20051103"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 2&ensp;Emonds: Adjectival Passives</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 2&ensp;Emonds: Adjectival Passives</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">2&ensp;Adjectival Passives: The Construction in the Iron Mask</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>JOSEPH</forenames><x> </x><surname>EMONDS</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>
<p>Introduction: what counts as a passive?</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Two types of passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Two variants of &lsquo;analytic passives&rsquo;</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>Verbal vs. adjectival passives: their differences</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>The interpretive difference: ongoing vs. completed activity</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Selection by different classes of V</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Degree words freely modify only (certain) adjectival passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Passives with the adjectival prefix <i>un-</i>
</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.5&ensp;</number>
<p>Only verbal passives have the full internal structure of surface VPs</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.6&ensp;</number>
<p>Only verbal passives have external arguments</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.7&ensp;</number>
<p>Idiomatic object nouns passivize freely only in verbal passives</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>Adjectival properties of all passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>An AP pattern inside passive phrases?</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The choice of the passive auxiliary</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>The adjectival character of participial morphology</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.4&ensp;</number>
<p>The AP distribution of passive participles</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>Lexical redundancy rules vs. Anderson&apos;s &lsquo;Theme Rule&rsquo;</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>The relation of passive participles to case assignment</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Chomsky&apos;s case-driven analysis</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Rethinking the full internal VP structures</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Passive participle contrasts in Dutch verb raising</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>6&ensp;</number>
<p>Evidence for Move in adjectival passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>6.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Levin and Rappaport: relating deep direct objects to adjectival passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>6.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Reformulating Levin and Rappaport&apos;s &lsquo;Sole Complement Generalization&rsquo;</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>6.3&ensp;</number>
<p>A non-problem for Move with adjectival passives</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>7&ensp;</number>
<p>Lexical notation for dual level or polyfunctional morphology</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>8&ensp;</number>
<p>Consequences of adjectival agreement in passives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>8.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Lexical agreement of <i>-en</i> with objects</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>8.2&ensp;</number>
<p>External theta-role suppression (dethematicization)</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>8.3&ensp;</number>
<p>An additional consequence of the Head Accessibility Constraint</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>9&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusion: the unity of syntax and morphology</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1&ensp;Introduction: what counts as a passive?</heading>
<p>Perhaps the first task in any work on passives is to set down what this elusive term is meant to cover. <link rid="b1">Keenan&apos;s (1985a</link>) broad but quite detailed overview insists that passives are operations on verb phrases rather than on sentences (p. 247) for which a characteristic morphological marking is central (p. 251). <link rid="b2">&Aring;farli (1992</link>: 8) summarizes this research in the following concise statement:</p>
<p>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;every sentence one might reasonably want to call a passive may be minimally characterized as follows:</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<thead>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Relative to its active counterpart, the passive sentence is marked with special verb morphology.</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The subject of the active sentence never remains subject in the passive counterpart.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This characterization of passives lays stress on the role of the subject phrase and its relation to passive morphology. The general approach to characterizing passive in terms of &lsquo;dethematized&rsquo; subjects (those whose expected theta-role is suppressed) stems from <link rid="b3">Roberts (1987</link>).</p>
<subsection id="ss3" level="2">
<heading id="h2" level="2">1.1&ensp;Two types of passives</heading>
<p>&Aring;farli goes on to cite <link rid="b1">Keenan (1985a</link>: 251) who &ldquo;distinguishes between two broad types of passive according to the verbal morphology involved: Periphrastic passives, which necessarily make use of a passive auxiliary verb, and strict morphological passives, which do not.&rdquo; Periphrastic passives are also sometimes called &lsquo;analytic&rsquo; and strict morphological passives &lsquo;synthetic&rsquo;.</p>
<p>In these traditional terms, an &lsquo;analytic passive&rsquo; is constructed with an auxiliary verb and a non-finite form of the main verb. In the bracketed passive clauses below, the usual place of the subject (underlined) contains either a noun phrase with the semantic role of what would otherwise be the main verb&apos;s object (1a) or some dummy pronoun (a null or overt &lsquo;expletive&rsquo;), as in (1b). The passive auxiliaries are italicized and the non-finite main verbs are in bold.</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>The fact that &lsqb;<u>the door</u> <i>was</i> &lcub;<b>repainted/taken</b> off&rcub; by the tenant&rsqb; upset her.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>It seems that &lsqb;<u>John&apos;s requests</u> are <i>getting</i> &lcub;<b>satisfied/written</b> down&rcub;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<u>It</u> might <i>be</i> quickly <b>concluded</b> that Mary is ill&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsqb;<u>Det</u> <i>vart</i> <b>sunge</b>&rsqb;. &lsquo;It was sung.&rsquo; (Norwegian, from &Aring;farli 1992: 85)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The non-finite passive form in English, the &lsquo;passive participle&rsquo;, combines a verbal stem with a past participle suffix, thus yielding complex analytic or periphrastic passives such as <i>be repaint-ed</i>, <i>be tak-en</i>, <i>get satisfi-ed</i>, <i>get writt-en</i>; this pattern is very common throughout Indo-European languages. This suffix is (often) referred to as past, not because of the passive, but because many languages also combine this participle with different auxiliaries to form composed past tenses (the English perfect tenses <i>have taken</i>, the French <i>pass&eacute; compos&eacute;</i>, the Italian <i>passato prossimo</i>).<link rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup></link> Because of the suffix&apos;s distinctive form in many irregular English verbs (<i>broken</i>, <i>done</i>, <i>eaten</i>, <i>flown</i>, <i>gone</i>, <i>taken</i>, <i>written</i>), it has usually been notated as -<i>en</i>, even when spelled <i>-ed</i>, since the earliest transformational work.</p>
<p>At least in the realm of what <link rid="b4">Baker (1988a</link>: ch. 1) terms &ldquo;grammatical function changing&rdquo; rules, this analytic passive certainly reigns as &lsquo;king&rsquo; of transformations. It is one of three singled out in <link rid="b5">Chomsky (1957</link>) for extensive treatment and has maintained a center stage position in research ever since. This constant attention is in large part due to the fact that the correct analysis for any kind of passive remains uncertain; indeed much debate has turned on to what extent across languages and within one language the many variations on the &lsquo;passive&rsquo; can even be considered a unitary phenomenon (<link rid="b1">Keenan 1985a</link>; <link rid="b6">Postal 1986</link>).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss4" level="2">
<heading id="h3" level="2">1.2&ensp;Two variants of &lsquo;analytic passives&rsquo;</heading>
<p>Contributing to the uncertainty about the limits on the passive is an interesting dichotomy, widely exemplified in Indo-European systems, between what are termed verbal and adjectival passives. The construction most familiar from transformational literature is in fact a &lsquo;verbal passive&rsquo;. But a second type of passive, often homonymous with the first, is called &lsquo;adjectival&rsquo;. <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>) draws several grammatical distinctions in English, which we will review as we proceed, between verbal passives as in (2a) and adjectival passives as in (2b):</p>
<p>(2)&ensp;<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>During my visit, that door was quickly <i>taken off</i> by the tenant.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John&apos;s requests are getting <i>satisfied</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>At my arrival, that door was already completely <i>taken off</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John now seems very <i>(un)satisfied</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>A rough semantic characterization is that a verbal passive (2a) refers to an activity and an adjectival passive (2b) to an already attained state.</p>
<p>This study is devoted to sketching the history of treatments of adjectival passives in generative grammar and to selecting the elements among these treatments that seem to provide a satisfactory analysis for the construction. As the adjectival passive has much in common with periphrastic verbal passives and is often of the same form, we will necessarily be treating aspects of the latter construction.<link rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup></link> However, we can exclude strict morphological (synthetic) passives from this study, relying on &Aring;farli&apos;s conclusions: &ldquo;Among Germanic languages, the &lsqb;strict morphological&rsqb;-passive is unique to the Scandinavian languages&rdquo; (1992: 13). &ldquo;It is important to note that s-passives never have an adjectival reading&rdquo; (1992: 12).</p>
<p>Between the periphrastic passives, the adjectival variant certainly arrived later on the generative scene (for reasons we will review), and has never become the focus of attention in the same way as the verbal passive. It has been instead confined to a relatively unexamined lexicon where its properties are supposedly relevant only to the development of &lsquo;lexical semantics&rsquo;.<link rid="fn3">
<sup>3</sup></link> Yet a review of literature and argumentation about the adjectival passive suggests rather that it is the more basic, minimal and diachronically constant representative of the two types.<link rid="fn4">
<sup>4</sup></link>
</p>
<p>In the terms of syntactic theory, this review will finally conclude not only that verbal and adjectival periphrastic passives are formed from a single lexical item, the participial suffix, but also that <i>both involve transformational movement from object to subject for exactly the same reason</i>. That is, I will argue that both uses of the passive suffix relate similarly to &lsquo;NP movement&rsquo; and that neither is connected to any lexical device which relates arguments of verbs to semantic or &lsquo;theta&rsquo;-roles.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss5" level="1">
<heading id="h4" level="1">2&ensp;&ensp;Verbal vs. adjectival passives: their differences</heading>
<p>I first review the properties that differentiate the two types of passives, summarizing material that also appears in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5). The differences in sections 2.2, 2.3, and 2.5 were brought under generative scrutiny in <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>). In this study of the generative history of adjectival passives, it is important to keep in mind that the specifically adjectival properties reviewed below were never taken as crucial considerations in formulating early versions of the passive transformation.</p>
<subsection id="ss6" level="2">
<heading id="h5" level="2">2.1&ensp;The interpretive difference: ongoing vs. completed activity</heading>
<p>We began by examining a property that is taken in both traditional and generative grammar to distinguish passive participles with an activity sense (2a, 3a) from those indicating a resultant state (2b, 3b). The verbal passives in (2a, 3a) lack the sense of completed activity conveyed by the adjectival passives in (2b, 3b):</p>
<p>(3)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>The door &lcub;got/was&rcub; <i>closed</i> during the noon hour.</entry>
<entry>(door can be open at noon)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The door is being <i>(*un)painted</i>.</entry>
<entry>(painting incomplete)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>The door &lcub;remained/was&rcub; <i>closed</i> during the noon hour.</entry>
<entry>(door closed by noon)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The door looked <i>(un)painted</i>.</entry>
<entry>(painting complete)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Certain verbs are incompatible with this &lsquo;completed sense&rsquo; and hence do not appear in adjectival passives. Consequently, such V can be passivized only as <i>verbal</i> passives; they cannot appear as complements of most verbs subcategorized as &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP:<link rid="fn5">
<sup>5</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(4)&ensp;<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*New York seems (very) &lcub;<i>approached</i>/<i>left</i>&rcub; in the tourist season.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*That good dinner felt &lcub;<i>accompanied</i>/<i>followed</i>&rcub; by too much drink.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Many polluted cities remain &lcub;<i>(un)avoided</i>/<i>escaped</i>&rcub; during the summer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*The clay looked (too) &lcub;<i>handed</i> around to students/<i>pressed</i> into a bowl&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*The message appeared &lcub;<i>slipped</i> to the spy/<i>put</i> in the drawer&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Some basketballs sounded &lcub;<i>dribbled</i> across the floor/<i>thrown</i> against the wall&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The sense of completed activity in (2b, 3b), i.e., of a property, seems nothing more than the characteristic Logical Form (LF) interpretation of the syntactic category A. Moreover, interpretation as a property seems to be exactly what verbal passives lack.<link rid="fn6">
<sup>6</sup></link> I thus propose the following at least descriptive relation between the morphology of the passive and its interpretation. Following the right hand head analysis for bound suffixes in <link rid="b9">Lieber (1980</link>), the suffix <i>-en</i> is the head of the passive participle. Then, while -<i>en</i> is obviously present in Phonological Form (PF) in all passives:</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<thead>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>In adjectival passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is present in both LF and PF.</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>In verbal passives, &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is absent in LF and present only in PF.<link rid="fn7">
<sup>7</sup></link>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Many empirical differences between adjectival and verbal passives correlate with and can be largely explained by (5). Of course, we also wish to develop a better theoretical perspective on (5).</p>
<p>We will see as we proceed that there is no need to invoke any further category distinction or change between the two types of passives as long as we maintain a contrast during some part of a derivation, whereby verbal but not adjectival passives lack the filled lexical head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub><i>-en</i>&rsqb; at LF.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss7" level="2">
<heading id="h6" level="2">2.2&ensp;Selection by different classes of V</heading>
<p>In most of the paradigms from <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>), the distributions of adjectival passives and underived lexical adjectives are essentially identical. This general fact follows from the presence of adjectival <i>-en</i> at all levels of a derivation (5a). In contrast, he considers the lack of the category A in verbal passives to be a crucial indicator of their transformational genesis. That is, while adjectival passives instantiate a category change of the stem for Wasow (morphological &lsquo;derivation&rsquo; from V to A), verbal passives do not and could not effect a category change, because transformations lack this capability. Thus, verbal passives must be of category V. <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>: 50) takes a somewhat different tack, proposing a special &lsquo;neutralized category&rsquo; status for verbal passives, presumably to keep them separate from the (undiscussed) adjectival passives (see <link rid="ss20">section 5.1</link>).</p>
<p>Empirically, both types of Germanic and Romance passive phrases are selected by verbs whose subcategorization frames include AP, but there is a difference between adjectival and verbal passives. Adjectival passives are selected by essentially <i>all</i> V that select AP complements (Wasow mentions English <i>act</i>, <i>appear</i>, <i>be</i>, <i>become</i>, <i>look</i>, <i>remain</i>, <i>seem</i>, <i>smell</i>, and <i>sound</i>), while only one or two such &lsquo;auxiliary&rsquo; V in each language select verbal passives. Under either Wasow&apos;s or Chomsky&apos;s categorial proposals, (5a) certainly explains at least the first part of this statement. Nonetheless, neither proposal clarifies why Indo-European verbal passives are compatible with only one or two &lsquo;passive auxiliaries&rsquo; otherwise specified as &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP (e.g., <i>be</i> and <i>get</i>).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss8" level="2">
<heading id="h7" level="2">2.3&ensp;Degree words freely modify only (certain) adjectival passives</heading>
<p>There are not fully understood differences among adjectival passives as to which permit a full range of characteristic adjectival modifiers, so-called &lsquo;degree words&rsquo;, as in (6a).<link rid="fn8">
<sup>8</sup></link> In any case, verbal passives do not tolerate them. By using either a progressive or the verbs in (4) (<i>approached</i>/<i>avoided</i>/<i>handed</i>, etc.) to ensure that a passive is verbal rather than adjectival, we create ungrammatical combinations with adjectival modifiers (6b).</p>
<p>(6)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="3">a.</entry>
<entry>The garden seemed too overplanted.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>New York remains more affected by strikes than other cities.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>That region doesn&apos;t seem very inhabited.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>How spotted with food did those clothes look?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry>The garden is being (*too) overplanted.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*New York is more avoided by tourists than other cities.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*That prison doesn&apos;t seem very escaped these days.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*How handed around to students did the clay feel?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Though a full theory of grammatical modification remains to be worked out, the following seems to be a minimal requirement: Many, perhaps all, items that modify only lexical category X<sup>0</sup> (here A) require that this X<sup>0</sup> be lexicalized throughout a derivation. The structural contrast (5) then lays the basis for correlating free adjectival modification with the presence of a lexical entry under A. Since the <i>-en</i> suffix on a verbal passive is absent in LF (5b), these forms don&apos;t tolerate degree words.</p>
<p>The distinction between lexicalized passive adjectives and those resulting from productive syntactic derivation is studied in more detail in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5), in relation to determining possible modifiers of adjectival passives. In that approach, fully lexicalized members of this class (<i>affected</i>, <i>inhabited</i>, <i>restricted</i>, <i>worried</i>) are suffixed in the lexicon and hence throughout a derivation, and so can be modified by degree words. Other adjectival passives (<i>destroyed</i>, <i>lost</i>, <i>painted</i>, <i>planted</i>) are formed in the syntax, i.e., they are not adjectives throughout a derivation, and hence do not tolerate degree words.<link rid="fn9">
<sup>9</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss9" level="2">
<heading id="h8" level="2">2.4&ensp;Passives with the adjectival prefix <roman>un-</roman>
</heading>
<p>This test distinguishing verbal from adjectival passives dates from <link rid="b11">Siegel (1973</link>). Passives prefixed with <i>un-</i> can appear as complements of verbs that take APs as in (7a), while verbal passives cannot. So prefixing <i>un-</i> to the verb stems in (4), which are compatible with only verbal passives, creates the impossible italicized combinations (7b), no matter what the wider context:</p>
<p>(7)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>That work seemed &lcub;unknown/unpainted/unrewarded&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Those books should remain &lcub;untouched/unfinished/unsold&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*That work &lcub;was/seemed&rcub; &lcub;<i>unleft</i> in good hands/<i>unfollowed</i> by others&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Those books should &lcub;get/remain&rcub; &lcub;<i>unthrown</i>/<i>unhanded</i>&rcub; to any customers.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As in the previous subsection, it appears that if a prefix modifies only members of lexical category X<sup>0</sup>, then X<sup>0</sup> should be lexicalized throughout a derivation.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b12">Bresnan (1978</link>: 6&ndash;9) claims that this pattern precludes using transformational movement in adjectival passives in, e.g., (7a). However, the assumptions of her argument seem to be that passive movement is restricted to V-headed clauses (begging the question) and that all operations contributing to a transformed passive surface structure occur simultaneously (which is currently not assumed).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss10" level="2">
<heading id="h9" level="2">2.5&ensp;Only verbal passives have the full internal structure of surface VPs</heading>
<p>As observed by <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>: 341), verbal passives essentially recreate the full range of structures found in active VPs, except that the passive VP contains one gap <i>e</i> for the DP which is &lsquo;passivized&rsquo;: <i>Mary was (being) elected e President; Sue was sent e the letter</i>. They are thus unlike adjectival passives, which fail to appear in such contexts: Mary felt &lcub;<i>happy</i>/*<i>elected President</i>&rcub;; <i>*Sue was unsent the letter.</i>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b2">&Aring;farli (1992</link>: chs. 3&ndash;4) shows that Norwegian passives with expletive subjects in fact exhibit a full range of active VP structures. Similarly, the &lsquo;gapless&rsquo; Japanese passive VPs analyzed in <link rid="b13">Kubo (1992</link>) contain one or two object DPs exactly like their active counterparts; and Japanese &lsquo;gapped&rsquo; passive VPs also contain direct objects and other complements, except for the single &lsquo;passivized&rsquo; DP.</p>
<p>In contrast, adjectival passives exhibit a significantly smaller range of syntactic patterns. In particular, they tolerate no overt bare complement DPs not in surface PPs: <i>*Bill sounded offered a dinner.</i> Nor can their subjects correspond to derived rather than deep direct objects: <i>*John sounds considered to be a scoundrel</i>; <i>*There seems believed to be corruption in high places</i> (<link rid="b7">Wasow 1977</link>: 344). We return in <link rid="ss21">section 5.2</link> to an account of these limitations. I will suggest that the best currently available analysis depends in part on the morphological distinction in (5a, b) and in part on other independently justified aspects of grammatical theory.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="2">
<heading id="h10" level="2">2.6&ensp;Only verbal passives have external arguments</heading>
<p>Many studies (to name some: <link rid="b14">Chomsky 1965</link>: ch. 2; <link rid="b7">Wasow 1977</link>, section 4.3; <link rid="b15">Jaeggli 1986a</link>, <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>; <link rid="b16">&Aring;farli 1989</link>, section 1.2.2.1; <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer 1995</link>, section III.1.1) have contributed to establishing a widely accepted claim that a verbal passive is always related to a syntactically present noun phrase that acts as its logical subject, either a <i>by</i> phrase or a covert DP. Verbal passives (8) thus contrast with adjectival passives (9), which lack such arguments.</p>
<p>(8)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The meeting was started on time (by Susan) (in order) to please the host.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The chairs were moved around on purpose (by the guests).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>This corn has been grown voluntarily (&lcub;by peasants/to stave off famine&rcub;).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Our workers are better paid intentionally (by the new boss).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>e.</entry>
<entry>Art classes are being restored (by the Board) in order to qualify for funding.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>That series of meetings sounds completed (*by the committee).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Most of our furniture is still unmoved (*by the company).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>We judge the corn fully grown (&lcub;*voluntarily/*to stave off famine&rcub;).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Our workers remain better paid (*intentionally).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>e.</entry>
<entry>Some art classes seem restored (*in order to qualify for funding).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The works just cited propose that an overt <i>by</i> phrase or corresponding covertly represented logical subject accounts for two widely recognized properties of verbal passives:</p>
<p>(10)&ensp;This logical subject may (not necessarily must) control the optional PRO subject of a &lsquo;higher&rsquo; infinitive of purpose, optionally introduced by <i>in order</i>, as in (8a, c, e).</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;A syntactically present animate subject seems to be a necessary condition for adverbs of intentionality, as in (8b, c, d), and for that matter, for adjunct purpose clauses as well.</p>
<p>Given this &lsquo;special location&rsquo; of the external argument in passives, we want to know why verbal passives <i>must</i>, but adjectival passives <i>must not</i>, have such a structurally represented overt or covert DP subject. (We are not yet accounting for the &lsquo;dethematicization&rsquo; property, i.e., why these external arguments are located in a <i>by</i> phrase rather than in the surface position that potentially agrees with the verb; this will be discussed in <link rid="ss30">section 8.2</link>.)</p>
<p>We know that verbs generally require subjects in LF &ndash; this follows from the Extended Projection Principle (&lsquo;EPP&rsquo;) of <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>). (12) seems like a workable formulation of this idea:</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;<b>Extended Projection Principle at LF (EPP).</b> A verb must have a structural subject phrase if and only if the verb is a <i>lexical head</i> of a constituent in LF.</p>
<p>This formulation exempts &lsquo;empty auxiliaries&rsquo; such as passive and perfect auxiliaries from the EPP; on their own such verbs plausibly lack inherent content, and concomitantly they seem to impose no requirement of having their own subject. Perhaps more to the point here, verbs in compounds and derivational morphology such as those in bold in <b><i>meet</i>
</b><i>ing place</i>, <i>dish</i> <b><i>wash</i>
</b><i>ing</i>, <b><i>think</i>
</b> <i>tank</i>, <b><i>go</i>
</b> <i>cart</i>, <b><i>infest</i>
</b><i>ation</i>, <b><i>bereave</i>
</b><i>ment</i>, etc. also lack syntactically specified subject phrases, overt or covert.</p>
<p>To see how (12) applies to passive structures, let us look again at the preliminary characterization (5) of the difference between adjectival and verbal passives.</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>In adjectival passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is present in both LF and PF.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>In verbal passives, &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is absent in LF and present only in PF.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(5a) straightforwardly exempts adjectival passives from (12), because the V stem of an adjectival passive is <i>not the lexical head</i> of the construction at LF. The V stems in adjectival passives resemble rather the subjectless initial V in compounds and derivational morphology. In fact, this construction is traditionally treated as an example of the latter. That is, a V inside a passive adjective is simply not subject to the EPP, which accounts for the pattern (9).</p>
<p>On the other hand, according to (5b), the stem V is the only candidate for being the lexical head of a verbal passive phrase in LF, precisely because &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is absent. This V then is subject to the EPP (12), which forces the presence of a subject. As mentioned above, we return in <link rid="ss30">section 8.2</link> to why this subject is not realized in the usual &lsquo;nominative&rsquo; position but must rather be covert or in a <i>by</i> phrase.<link rid="fn10">
<sup>10</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="2">
<heading id="h11" level="2">2.7&ensp;Idiomatic object nouns passivize freely only in verbal passives</heading>
<p>There remains a final contrast between adjectival and verbal passives concerning idiomatic V-NP combinations. That is, adjectival passives disallow any semantic relation other than &lsquo;pure argumenthood&rsquo; between a subject DP and the participle&apos;s V stem, as seen in the contrasts in (13).</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Some advantage may finally &lcub;be/*feel&rcub; taken of our new wealth.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A great deal &lcub;was/*sounded&rcub; made of your visit.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>No attention &lcub;is being paid/*seems paid&rcub; to minor officials.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Actually, this kind of contrast can be related to a difference between so-called &lsquo;inflectional&rsquo; and &lsquo;derivational&rsquo; morphology, although the confusion over the nature of this distinction limits the usefulness of this reduction. Thus, a verb formed with another fully productive inflection, the <i>-ing</i> of the gerund or present participle, allows idiomatic combinations like <i>maintain silence</i>, <i>pay attention</i>, <i>please DP no end</i> and <i>bore DP to tears</i> in (14).</p>
<p>(14)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>During the trial, all were impressed by John&apos;s maintaining silence.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>His paying &lcub;bribes/attention&rcub; to minor officials was foolish.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>This show is pleasing local kids no end.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>They heard Mary boring us to tears.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But in derivational formations such as the nominals and adjectives in (15), idioms don&apos;t survive.</p>
<p>(15)&ensp;<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*During the trial, all were impressed by John&apos;s maintenance of silence.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>His payment of &lcub;bribes/*attention&rcub; to minor officials was foolish.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>This show seems pleasing to local kids (*no end).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary sounded so boring (*to tears).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Consequently, the contrasts in passive paradigms with idioms as in (13) suggest that verbal passives are inflectional like gerunds, while adjectival passives are not.</p>
<p>The explanation seems to be that idiomatic combinations of heads and arguments tolerate no intervening heads in LF.<link rid="fn11">
<sup>11</sup></link> Once again in accord with the structure (5a), the intervening lexical item &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; at LF blocks idiomatic combinations of Vs and phrasal complements in adjectival passives, whereas the absence of &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; in the verbal passive LFs (5b) has no effect and hence allows them.<link rid="fn12">
<sup>12</sup></link>
</p>
<p>We have now reviewed seven differences between adjectival and verbal passives, which have been discussed in various works on passives in English and other languages. We have been able to attribute six of these differences, at least in part, to the distinction between a structure for adjectival passives (5a), in which a lexicalized A is present in LF, and one for verbal passives (5b), whose adjectival head is <i>not</i> lexicalized at LF, but only at PF.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the genesis of the distinctive properties of the two kinds of passives in the terms just developed remains somewhat mysterious. We have not elucidated what is perhaps syntactically the most important of these differences, that of <link rid="ss10">section 2.5</link>: only verbal passives have the full internal structure of surface VPs. Moreover, we would like to understand better the structural difference (5) that underlies several of the others. Finally, there remains the question of formally accounting for &Aring;farli&apos;s &lsquo;essential property of the passive&rsquo;: how does the special morphology of a passive guarantee that the subject of an active sentence never remains an (agreeing) subject in either kind of passive? In my view a satisfactory answer can be given (only) by treating verbal and adjectival passives together.</p>
<p>The next four sections follow the history of the treatments of adjectival passives, and will provide an account of why verbal passives have the internal structure of surface VPs rather than of APs. Then, the last two sections of the study will situate (5) in a theory of lexical insertion and propose an account of the passive&apos;s essential &lsquo;dethematicization&rsquo; of an active verb&apos;s subject.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss13" level="1">
<heading id="h12" level="1">3&ensp;Adjectival properties of all passives</heading>
<p>For two decades prior to <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>), transformational grammar was largely content to treat verbal passives as the only passives worthy of the name. In particular, Chomsky&apos;s early analyses of the passive (1957: ch. 5; 1965: ch. 2) laid particular stress on properties just reviewed in <link rid="ss6 ss10">sections 2.1 and 2.5</link>: verbal passive clauses are transformationally derived because they are largely synonymous with corresponding actives, and the characteristic constituent sequences one finds in verbal passive clauses are systematically related to base configurations. Passive sequences are exactly those we expect if VPs have precisely one NP transformationally &lsquo;removed&rsquo; from them.</p>
<p>However, certain theoretical developments in the early 1970s led to questioning this claim that the passive involves movement. Although the revisionist view seems in retrospect to have been a &lsquo;mistake&rsquo; &ndash; moreover one quickly rectified via <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>) &ndash; correcting this mistake led to a second misconception concerning adjectival passives that persists today.<link rid="fn13">
<sup>13</sup></link>
</p>
<p>An alternative analysis of the English verbal passive in <link rid="b18">Hasegawa (1968</link>) had faulted Chomsky&apos;s earlier formulations as implausible amalgams of &ldquo;too many elementary transformations,&rdquo; including movement leftward, movement rightward, auxiliary insertion, and optional deletion of an agent phrase. Under the influence of this critique, <link rid="b19">Chomsky (1970</link>) reanalyzed the passive as two independent subrules, preposing of a deep object into a subject position (NP-preposing), and demotion of a deep subject into a postposed PP headed by the P <i>by</i> (agent-postposing). At the same time, these two operations were used in <link rid="b20 b21">Emonds (1970, 1976</link>) to illustrate the notion of &lsquo;structure-preservation&rsquo;, namely, categories generated in the base component were moved into positions where the phrase structure rules of the base could actually also generate these same categories.<link rid="fn14">
<sup>14</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Now the motivations for postulating transformationally derived status, widely circulated at this time and later published in <link rid="b22">Lakoff and Ross (1976</link>), were (i) possible simplifications in the base component, (ii) allowing simpler definitions of grammatical relations in terms of base structures, and (iii) permitting simplified statements of co-occurrence restrictions on lexical insertion. If transformational outputs of NP-preposing and agent postposing could be generated by independently needed base rules, there remained only two possible (nonetheless non-trivial) motivations for them, (ii) and (iii).</p>
<p>This led some analysts to hypothesize that the passive constructions derived by structure-preserving operations, and thus lacking the motivation (i) for transformations, might simply be base-generated constructions full stop. <link rid="b23">Freidin (1975</link>: <link rid="ss5">section 2</link>) argued that certain aspects of Chomsky&apos;s two NP movement rules, especially the agent postposing rule, were problematic. He further claimed that certain passive properties were similar to, and should be subsumed under, those of base-generated adjective phrases. I now treat each of these four adjectival properties of verbal passives in separate subsections.</p>
<subsection id="ss14" level="2">
<heading id="h13" level="2">3.1&ensp;An AP pattern inside passive phrases?</heading>
<p>The phrase structure of adjective phrases is generally taken to preclude the possibility of multiple NP sisters to the adjectival head. <link rid="b23">Freidin&apos;s (1975</link>: 401) rule (47) expresses this:</p>
<p>(16)&ensp;AP &rarr; A (NP) (PP)&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</p>
<p>If a passive participle is analyzed as an A, many varied examples of passive constructions indeed conform to his rule. The brackets represent AP boundaries:</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>The letter was &lsqb;given to Ann&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The station was (being) &lsqb;approached from two sides&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>How much unfair advantage was &lsqb;taken of Bill&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Ann was &lsqb;given the letter&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Who got &lsqb;taken such unfair advantage of&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A lot of vacation was (being) &lsqb;allowed the workers&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The workers were (being) &lsqb;allowed a lot of vacation&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>That letter was &lsqb;sent all the candidates&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter was (being) &lsqb;forgiven his sins&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter&apos;s sins were (being) &lsqb;forgiven him&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>He was (being) &lsqb;charged a lot of money&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>: 341) however sharply criticizes (16), claiming: &ldquo;There is no other construction in English that requires rule (47),&rdquo; and supports his criticism with extensive argument (his long note 10). Note that most of the overt surface NPs in Freidin&apos;s putative APs in (18) are typically and crucially &lsquo;bare&rsquo;, i.e., they lack an overt P. Such a complement type is quite unusual with head As in English and many languages, and thus the lack of a structural PP for these complements seems unexplained.<link rid="fn15">
<sup>15</sup></link>
</p>
<p>A descriptive generalization (19) that better covers the range of complements observed in (17&ndash;18) is unrelated to the range of structures lexically chosen by head As:</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;English passive verbs take exactly the same range of complement combinations as active verbs, except that one noun phrase is missing in a passive structure.</p>
<p>Thus, the variation in passive verb complement types in (17&ndash;18) matches that of identical active verbs in (20), except for the presence in each example of (20) of an additional italicized noun phrase.</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;give <i>the letter</i> to Ann, approach <i>the station</i> from two sides, take <i>such unfair advantage</i> of Bill, give <i>Ann</i> the letter, allow the workers <i>a lot of vacation</i>, send all the candidates <i>that letter</i>, forgive Peter <i>his sins</i>, charge <i>him</i> a lot of money.</p>
<p>It is of course the correlation in (19) that originally led Chomsky to propose a transformational treatment of the passive, although it is unclear how many construction types he had in mind. This same correlation led most syntacticians in Chomsky&apos;s surround back to a movement analysis of verbal passives, despite the challenges in <link rid="b23">Freidin (1975</link>) and <link rid="b12 b24">Bresnan (1978, 1982d</link>).</p>
<p>In the meantime, however, this challenge and <link rid="b7">Wasow&apos;s (1977</link>) response succeeded in making the field aware of the adjectival properties of analytic passives, three more of which will now be discussed. As will be seen later in this study, only after quite a long period of ambivalence about the categorial status of participles have analyses of the passive emerged which use a synthesis of both transformational movement and a central role for the category A.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss15" level="2">
<heading id="h14" level="2">3.2&ensp;The choice of the passive auxiliary</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b23">Freidin (1975</link>: 402) observes that the English &lsquo;passive auxiliary&rsquo; <i>be &ndash;</i> the same can be said for its second passive auxiliary <i>get</i> &ndash; is in any case subcategorized for taking AP complements (cf. <link rid="ss7">section 2.2</link> above). This lexical property follows from analyzing passives as base-generated adjectives. In contrast, if the passive auxiliary is generated separately in a base rule for an AUX constituent, it is subject to several ad hoc restrictions. Moreover, if it is transformationally inserted, its resemblance to other base-generated auxiliary structures seems strangely fortuitous.</p>
<p>More generally, <i>both</i> types of passives are selected by verbs that have the lexical frame &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP. In fact, <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>) notes that adjectival passives appear as complements of almost all Vs whose subcategorization frames include&nbsp;&plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP or &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>DP^(AP). For example, English intransitives such as <i>act</i>, <i>appear</i>, <i>be</i>, <i>become</i>, <i>feel</i>, <i>look</i>, <i>remain</i>, <i>seem</i>, <i>smell</i>, <i>sound</i>, <i>stay</i>, and <i>taste</i> all accept APs, including adjectival passives:</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;She &lcub;felt/seemed/sounded/found him/considered Bill&rcub; &lcub;ill/betrayed/cared for&rcub;.</p>
<p>Although verbal passives are selected by only two linking verbs, Freidin correctly observes that these also have the frame &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP.<link rid="fn16">
<sup>16</sup></link> Thus, analyzing all analytic passives as adjectives at least explains why both variants inevitably appear as complements of Vs that are &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP or &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>DP^(AP). But still, one wonders why so few verbs select verbal passive complements.</p>
<p>An account of this puzzle is presented in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5). Passive auxiliaries, i.e., those V that select <i>verbal</i> passives, are invariably among the &lsquo;grammatical V&rsquo; of a given language, that is, those V which lack purely semantic features and hence, in that framework, can be inserted late in a derivation. Now clearly, it is the passive participle morpheme &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; itself that creates an insertion context<u>&emsp;</u>AP for passive auxiliaries, and the insertion of this purely grammatical element is itself part of PF. Consequently, a V can select a verbal passive only if it is (i) uninterpreted at LF (i.e., inserted in PF), and also (ii) has the frame &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP. <i>Be</i> and <i>get</i> are the only such V. I know of no other principled account of why so few verbs can select verbal passive complements.<link rid="fn17">
<sup>17</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="2">
<heading id="h15" level="2">
3.3 The adjectival character of participial morphology</heading>
<p>By taking the passive participle as simply an adjective, <link rid="b23">Freiden (1975</link>) also explains certain aspects of the morphology of a range of Germanic, Romance, and Slavic analytic passives. First, as <link rid="b9">Lieber (1980</link>) and <link rid="b24">Bresnan (1982d</link>: 21&ndash;24) discuss in some detail, the irregular forms in verbal passives almost exactly mimic items of the same form that are clearly adjectival.<link rid="fn18">
<sup>18</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;being written, seems written; being done, seems done; being stung, seems stung; etc.</p>
<p>Exceptional: being &lcub;burned/*burnt&rcub;; looks &lcub;?burned/burnt&rcub;</p>
<p>The full similarity leads them to endorse a rule of &lsquo;conversion&rsquo;, which adds the category A by brute force to verbal participles for the formation of passive adjectives, a procedure also endorsed in <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport (1986</link>). That is, these authors argue that separate lexical formation rules would miss a generalization that the same morphological structure is involved.</p>
<p>Second, in whichever contexts an adjective agrees with a modified nominal in Romance and Germanic languages, both adjectival and verbal uses of the passive participle agree as well. For example, Romance adjectives typically agree in number and gender with modified nominals in both attributive and predicative positions. Therefore, both adjectival (23a) and verbal passives (23b) in French exhibit feminine (plural) agreements via the bold -<b><i>e(s)</i>
</b> in exactly the same positions.<link rid="fn19">
<sup>19</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(23)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>A</entry>
<entry>mon</entry>
<entry>arriv&eacute;e,</entry>
<entry>ces</entry>
<entry><i>joli<b>es</b>
</i>
</entry>
<entry>portes</entry>
<entry>semblaient</entry>
<entry>d&eacute;j&agrave;</entry>
<entry>&lcub;<i>repeint<b>es</b>
</i>/<i>gris<b>es</b>
</i>&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>at</entry>
<entry>my</entry>
<entry>arrival,</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>pretty</entry>
<entry>doors</entry>
<entry>seemed</entry>
<entry>already</entry>
<entry>&lcub;repainted/gray&rcub;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;At my arrival, those pretty doors seemed already &lcub;repainted/gray&rcub;.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="13">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Cette</entry>
<entry><i>joli<b>e</b>
</i>
</entry>
<entry>porte</entry>
<entry>&eacute;tait</entry>
<entry>vite</entry>
<entry><i>repeint<b>e</b>
</i>
</entry>
<entry>par</entry>
<entry>le</entry>
<entry>locataire</entry>
<entry>pendant</entry>
<entry>ma</entry>
<entry>visite.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>that</entry>
<entry>pretty</entry>
<entry>door</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>quickly</entry>
<entry>repainted</entry>
<entry>by</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>renter</entry>
<entry>during</entry>
<entry>my</entry>
<entry>visit.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col13">&lsquo;That pretty door was quickly repainted by the renter during my visit.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When only attributive adjectives agree, as in German, then both uses of the passive participle agree in and only in the same attributive contexts. Further, both German adjectives and passive participles agree in number, gender, <i>and case.</i> Within some Slavic systems, similar inflectional parallels between verbal and adjectival passive participles are also common. For Russian, they are outlined in <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer (1995</link>: section IV.1.1).</p>
<p>Uniformly analyzing all passive participles as adjectives thus explains the fact that adjectival and passive agreements share both their morphology and their syntax in several language systems. Note further that adjectival agreement is unlike verb agreement in the languages in question (verbs agree with subjects in person but <i>not</i> in gender), and so the argument goes beyond an appeal to undifferentiated &lsquo;agreement&rsquo;.</p>
<p>In view of <link rid="b9">Lieber&apos;s (1980</link>) right hand head analysis of bound morphology, the morpho-syntactic properties of participles reviewed in this section suggests a partial lexical entry (24) for all passive participles, both verbal and adjectival.</p>
<p>(24)&ensp;Passive participles (partial lexical entry): <i>en</i>, A, &plus; V<u>&emsp;</u>,&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</p>
<p>The realizations of this entry at the PF and LF interfaces are those given above in (5):</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>In adjectival passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is present in both LF and PF.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>In verbal passives, &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is absent in LF and present only in PF.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>One means of expressing (24) and (5b) together is to postulate that a structure &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> V &minus; &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> &Oslash;&rsqb;&rsqb; can be generated syntactically and be lexically filled in either syntax (5a) or only at PF (5b).<link rid="fn20">
<sup>20</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss17" level="2">
<heading id="h16" level="2">3.4&ensp;The AP distribution of passive participles</heading>
<p>Phrases with heads of passive form and lexical adjective phrases appear to modify nouns and verbs as &lsquo;adjuncts&rsquo; under basically the same conditions. Passive participles can be adjuncts of sentences (25a), of verb phrases (25b) and attributive modifiers of nouns (25c), all of which are characteristic positions of predicate adjectives:</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lcub;<i>Desolate</i>/<i>Unwanted</i>/<i>Rejected</i>&rcub;, the child turned to crime.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The child spent its school years &lcub;<i>hungry</i>/<i>uncared for</i>/<i>bullied</i>&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>Church bells &lcub;<i>silent</i>/<i>rung</i>&rcub; at noon reflect the status of the clergy.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>It&apos;s patients &lcub;<i>unable</i> to pay/<i>left</i> to wait/<i>examined</i> hastily&rcub; that leads to problems.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>An additional distributional argument for the adjectival status of passive participles can be constructed around the usage of the particle <i>as</i> as a &lsquo;prepositional copula&rsquo;. Like the copula <i>be</i>, non-comparative <i>as</i> takes a predicate attribute NP or AP; cf. <link rid="b26">Emonds (1985</link>: ch. 6). The fact that passive participles can be complements to this prepositional copula then becomes another argument for their adjectival status.</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;He &lcub;struck us/treated them&rcub; as &lcub;<i>intelligent</i>/<i>ill</i>/<i>experienced</i>/<i>undernourished</i>&rcub;.</p>
<p>We can thus conclude with Freidin that all passive clauses share in the morphology and the syntax of adjective phrases AP, especially as regards their interaction with material <i>external</i> to AP: agreement with a subject, selection by external heads, and distribution as adjuncts. The differences between verbal and adjectival passives reviewed in <link rid="ss5">section 2</link> turn rather around the syntax <i>internal</i> to passive phrases: how they are interpreted, whether they can contain idioms, how their heads can be modified, how they internally arrange phrases, and whether they contain interpreted subjects.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss18" level="1">
<heading id="h17" level="1">4&ensp;Lexical redundancy rules vs. Anderson&apos;s &lsquo;Theme Rule&rsquo;</heading>
<p>Given the several adjectival properties of <i>all</i> analytic passives, it is not surprising that Freidin proposed to assimilate both types passives to the category of base-generated adjective phrases. In fact, the arguments above in sections 3.2 through 3.4 retain some force. But then, as observed in <link rid="b23">Freidin (1975</link>: 291), if &ldquo;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;the synonymy of active&ndash;passive pairs is not explicitly accounted for by a rule in the syntactic or semantic component, a grammar that captures the active&ndash;passive relation must include a rule that does so.&rdquo; As a consequence, he looked elsewhere to explain the second motivation for a transformational movement: why do main lexical verbs assign a semantic function (theta-role) to the surface subject of passives in the same way as they assign a role to an object NP in active sentences? Once this explanation was found, it supposedly would simultaneously explain any selectional and subcategorization co-occurrence restrictions on lexical insertion of passive forms, thus removing the third possible motivation (cf. p. 26) for movement in passives.</p>
<p>The device first favoured by this line of research was the &lsquo;lexical redundancy&rsquo; condition or rule, based on extending certain ideas for complex lexical entries in <link rid="b19">Chomsky (1970</link>). <link rid="b23">Freidin (1975</link>: <link rid="ss13">section 3</link>) develops such a system, including a general condition for assigning synonymy to projections from similar lexical entries, a general specification of the form of multi-category entries, and a specific redundancy condition that stipulates positional relations between the semantic functions of an active verb and those of a passive verb.<link rid="fn21">
<sup>21</sup></link> Similarly, for adjectival passives only, <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>: section 4.2) endorses a type of lexical redundancy rule developed in <link rid="b27">Jackendoff (1976</link>).</p>
<p>The field did not take long to react against a second type of formal device for assigning the same predicate&ndash;argument relations to differently situated arguments, however. On the one hand, <link rid="b28">Anderson&apos;s (1977</link>) commentary on Wasow&apos;s essay (peer responses follow the papers in this ground-breaking volume) endorses a lexical treatment at least of adjectival passives, in line with grammatical thinking of the time: &ldquo;The criteria Wasow proposes for distinguishing rules of the two types &lsqb;lexical and transformational&rsqb; are entirely natural and well-motivated ones within the general conception of grammar developed as the Extended Standard Theory&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;There is an obvious advantage to making the subclass of lexical redundancy rules as large as possible&rdquo; (p. 364). On the other hand, however, his main aim is to &ldquo;arrive at a narrower and more interesting conception of the lexical redundancy rules, &lsqb;so&rsqb; that some of the problems arising in Wasow&apos;s paper receive a satisfying account&rdquo; (p. 366).</p>
<p>Anderson then proceeds to implement the following critique of lexical redundancy rules. &ldquo;The association between grammatical and thematic relations, then, ought not to be stated in each lexical entry, but ought rather to be stated once and for all as a general rule: part of the semantic component of a grammar of English, or (conceivably) part of a semantic meta theory&rdquo; (p. 367). His main proposal then follows: the semantic roles of NPs in adjectival passive clauses are determined by what he terms the Theme Rule (and states only informally): &ldquo;the Theme is quite generally to be found in Subject position if the verb is intransitive, and in Direct Object position if the verb is transitive&rdquo; (p. 367). The task of the lexicon then reduces to separately listing intransitive forms such as, e.g., <i>break</i>, <i>broken</i>, <i>close</i> and <i>closed</i>, and (let me add) <i>taken</i>, <i>eaten</i>, <i>painted</i>, <i>(over)planted</i>, <i>(un)inhabited</i>, but not verbs such as <i>take</i>, <i>eat</i>, <i>paint</i>, <i>(over)plant</i>, or <i>inhabit</i>:</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The door may &lcub;break/seem broken/close/seem closed&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>This apartment may seem &lcub;taken/painted&rcub; during your visit.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The park will soon look &lcub;(over)planted/(un)inhabited&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*This apartment may &lcub;take/paint&rcub; during your visit.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*The park will soon &lcub;(over)plant/inhabit&rcub;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But Anderson&apos;s lexical entries would not have to say anything, via item-particular stipulations and/or lexical redundancy rules, about how subjects and objects receive thematic roles; that would be the province of the Theme Rule. and in fact, <link rid="b29">Williams (1981a</link>) soon postulates a more formal version of the Theme Rule, positing a direct relation between bound morphemes such as <i>-en</i> and the syntactic position of thematic roles, i.e., with <i>-en</i>, the Theme must be the external argument.</p>
<p>Lest terminology confuse the issue, we should emphasize that for Anderson the italicized phrases in (28) are Themes, unlike many lexical semantic treatments that would assign them Locational type theta-roles.</p>
<p>(28)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>A vandal smeared <i>my house</i> with the paint. (p. 369)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The result annoyed <i>John</i>. (p. 372)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><i>The garden</i> swarmed with bees. (p. 369)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>George Washington slept in <i>this bed</i>. (p. 373, with the passivizable sense of &lsquo;affecting&rsquo; the bed)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Anderson&apos;s proposal and Williams&apos;s Theme Externalization are thus close to expressing a generalization (29) that will be important below:</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;The subject of (always intransitive) adjectival passives relates semantically to the verb root like the direct object of corresponding transitive verbs.</p>
<p>We should keep in mind that various formulations of the Theme Rule don&apos;t explain, without having recourse to redundant stipulations, why passive adjectives are more easily formed than intransitive verbs. We return to this in <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>. Nonetheless, Anderson&apos;s proposal, to the extent it was appreciated, obviated the need for syntactic theory to countenance a type of lexical redundancy device which &lsquo;doubles&rsquo; the grammatical function changing work of transformations.</p>
<p>Another response to the momentary focus on adjectival passives was more direct. In his seminal article on trace theory, <link rid="b30">Fiengo (1977</link>) proposed deriving them by using Chomsky&apos;s object-preposing inside AP. While his brief formal treatment for interpreting these passives seems inadequate, he nonetheless finds a weak spot in the lexicalist opposition: contemporary argument against deriving adjectival passives via movement seemed to beg the question; it <i>assumed without argument</i> that NP movement doesn&apos;t apply in an AP domain.</p>
<p>In any case, works like <link rid="b28">Anderson (1977</link>) led to transformationalists losing interest in lexical redundancy rules, though of course a framework that lost interest in transformations, namely Lexical Functional Grammar, continued to develop the notion of &lsquo;lexical relatedness&rsquo; in terms of lexical &lsquo;functional structures&rsquo; (<link rid="b12">Bresnan 1978</link>) and &lsquo;predicate argument structures&rsquo; (<link rid="b24">Bresnan 1982d</link>).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="1">
<heading id="h18" level="1">5&ensp;The relation of passive participles to case assignment</heading>
<p>Before continuing to review analyses specific to adjectival passives, let us investigate the relation of passives to abstract case, a factor which could have &ndash; but did not &ndash; figure in distinguishing the two types of passive. Traditional grammars of European inspiration have frequently related passive structures to the failure of accusative case assignment. In turn, this failure seems somehow related to the adjectival nature of all passive participles and the fact that adjectives do not in general assign accusative case. A role for case along these lines became a central aspect in government and binding analyses of the verbal passive in the eighties, and in my view, could have led to quicker progress had it been formulated with the properties of adjectival passives in mind.</p>
<subsection id="ss20" level="2">
<heading id="h19" level="2">5.1&ensp;Chomsky&apos;s Case-driven analysis</heading>
<p>In his initial authoritative treatise on government and binding, <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>: 48&ndash;50) observes that the fundamental property of (verbal) passives may be either one of two options:</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;Something forces a passivized object NP to move away from its base position.</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;Something deprives a passive subject position of its usual theta-role and thereby renders it a landing site for movement.</p>
<p>In terms of the then recent incorporation of abstract case into generative syntax, a plausible motivation for forcing movement could be lack of case on a passive verb&apos;s object NP, in turn due to the verb&apos;s adjectival morphology. <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>) thus opts to develop (30) on the basis of a &lsquo;Case Filter&rsquo;, by virtue of which overt noun phrases lacking case at the end of a derivation render a structure ill-formed.<link rid="fn22">
<sup>22</sup></link> The contemporary debates about the relation of passive participles to the category A most likely played a role in attributing forced movement in passives to the adjectival form of the V.</p>
<p>However, if one straightforwardly claimed that verbal passive participles <i>are</i> As, then essentially nothing would structurally differentiate verbal from the adjectival passives, which had been consigned to the distant lexicon; Wasow&apos;s defense of a transformational passive seemingly depended on <i>maintaining a difference</i> between verbal passive participles and the category A. Thus, verbal passive participles should &lsquo;act like&rsquo; As and yet be not quite entirely As. The solution suggested by <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>: 50) is to assign them to a special, &ldquo;unspecified for &plusmn;N&rdquo; neutralized category. In Case Theory, whose Case Assigning categories are V and P (in terms of features &minus;N), the &plus;N categories N and A fail to assign case (<link rid="b31">Stowell 1981</link>). Chomsky&apos;s implied revision of Case Theory is that the categorial features of verbal passive participles, namely &lsqb;&plus;V, unspecified for N&rsqb;, do not assign case either, which then accounts for (30).</p>
<p>This proposal turns into an equivocation, however, because on the next page <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>: 51) suggests that <i>of</i> in the context N___NP has the features &lsqb;&minus;V, unspecified for N&rsqb; and <i>does</i> assign case. Hence, an ad hoc &lsquo;neutralized category&rsquo; (unspecified for N) of highly defective distribution (with only two members, <i>-en</i> and <i>of</i>) leads not to a definition of a natural class of case assigners somehow related to &lsqb;&minus;N&rsqb;), but rather to item-particular stipulations.</p>
<p>In spite of this shaky foundation, the voluminous literature of government and binding in the eighties maintains (and proclaims) this analysis with almost one voice: the mantra was &lsquo;lack of case forces movement in the passive&rsquo;. This literature also uniformly presupposes Wasow&apos;s conclusion that only verbal passives involve movement; cf. again note 3. More than a decade later, <link rid="b2">&Aring;farli (1992</link>: section 1.2.3.1) reviews the unchanged &lsquo;Orthodox Analysis&rsquo;, including the factor that the participle is a &ldquo;neutralized &lsqb;&plus;V&rsqb; category&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;and like adjectives, it is a bad Case assigner.&rdquo;</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss21" level="2">
<heading id="h20" level="2">5.2&ensp;Rethinking the full internal VP structures</heading>
<p>Government and binding analyses of the passive were slow to challenge Chomsky&apos;s choice of (30) over (31). <link rid="b3">Roberts (1987</link>: ch. 2) reformulated the relation to case assignment in terms of a passive verb assigning &lsquo;all but one&rsquo; of its cases, and began to focus more on properties of a passive&apos;s &lsquo;dethematized&rsquo; subject. Cross-linguistic studies of passives, including &Aring;farli&apos;s, finally undermined the choice of (30) over (31).<link rid="fn23">
<sup>23</sup></link> They reason on the basis that verbal passive constructions in several languages can exhibit overt direct objects, even with morphological accusative case.</p>
<p>Some examples include <link rid="b32">Sobin (1985</link>) on the impersonal passives of Ukrainian, <link rid="b16 b2">&Aring;farli (1989, 1992</link>) on the wider range of such constructions in Norwegian, and <link rid="b13">Kubo (1992</link>) on the &lsquo;adversative&rsquo; and dative passives of Japanese. <link rid="b16">&Aring;farli (1989</link>: 23) rejects (30), arguing &ldquo;on the basis of Norwegian data that passive verbs assign Case just like their active counterparts do&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;and&rsqb; that this is also essentially correct for English&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rdquo; He concludes (1989: 102) rather in favor of (31): &ldquo;the essential property of the passive phenomenon is that the subject position of a passive clause is theta-free and thus becomes a possible landing site for NP movement.&rdquo;<link rid="fn24">
<sup>24</sup></link> In what follows, I will refer to this as &lsquo;the essential property of the passive&rsquo;.</p>
<p>More prosaically, even very familiar facts of English cast doubt on whether a verbal passive in any way interferes with case assignment. The examples of (18), repeated here, contain a range of italicized objects to which prima facie, <i>a passive V assigns case</i>.<link rid="fn25">
<sup>25</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Ann was &lsqb;given <i>the letter</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Who got &lsqb;taken <i>such unfair advantage of</i>&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A lot of vacation was (being) &lsqb;allowed <i>the workers</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The workers were (being) &lsqb;allowed <i>a lot of vacation</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>That letter was &lsqb;sent <i>all the candidates</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter was (being) &lsqb;forgiven <i>his sins</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter&apos;s sins were (being) &lsqb;forgiven <i>him</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>He was (being) &lsqb;charged <i>a lot of money</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Put differently, since verbal passives have the full internal structure of VPs (the property noted in <link rid="ss10">section 2.5</link>), all these VPs with a single gap are well-formed.<link rid="fn26">
<sup>26</sup></link>
</p>
<p>In interesting contrast to these verbal passives, the corresponding adjectival passives based on the &lsquo;double object constructions&rsquo; in (32), as observed in <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>), are always ill-formed. <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport (1986</link>: <link rid="ss18">section 4</link>) also note these effects for adjectival passives, but do not pursue the implications of the contrast with verbal passives.</p>
<p>(32)&ensp;<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Ann seemed given the letter.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*That letter sounded sent all the candidates.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Who acted taken such unfair advantage of?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Peter felt (un)forgiven his sins.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Peter&apos;s sins stayed forgiven him.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Those workers appeared allowed a lot of vacation.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*He felt (un)charged too much money.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Had syntacticians retained an interest in adjectival passives, they could have concluded that the Case Filter accounts naturally for this regular ungrammatical pattern, because an A can assign case neither to an NP that moves nor to one that stays in its base position. The fact the Case Filter successfully excludes these examples suggests that a proper movement analysis, counter to the government and binding consensus, might be capable of explaining the other systematic syntactic restrictions on adjectival passives: that they are incompatible with derived, non-deep direct objects (<link rid="ss10">section 2.5</link>) and idiomatic objects (<link rid="ss12">section 2.7</link>).</p>
<p>Summarizing, like other adjectives, the participles in (32) with right hand word-internal A heads simply fail to assign case to any VP-internal DPs not targeted by NP movement. Consequently, adjectival passive phrases can&apos;t contain such DPs. In contrast, nothing stops a verbal passive from assigning case to these &lsquo;second DPs&rsquo;. This contrast in case-assigning capability is actually another property that follows from the earlier partial structural characterizations of the two passive types:</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>In adjectival passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is present in both LF and PF.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>In verbal passives, &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is absent in LF and present only in PF.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>That is, in (5a) the A head prevents case assignment, but in (5b) the V head assigns case normally. What causes movement in passives is thus not lack of case.</p>
<p>As in note 7, there are different ways to realize this LF distinction in passives (5): (i) Derivation &ndash; a participial suffix could be entirely absent in verbal passives in the syntax, with &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; added to a V in PF. (ii) LF Feature Checking &ndash; the suffix &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> -<i>en</i>&rsqb; is present in both passives in the syntax, but is checked off (i.e., deleted) in LF only in verbal passives. (iii) Late Insertion &ndash; the suffixal A node is present in both passives; it is already lexicalized in syntax as -<i>en</i> in adjectival passives, but in verbal passives it is empty in the syntax and lexicalized only in PF.</p>
<p>For understanding the history of passive analyses, the choice among (i&ndash;iii) need not concern us. The Derivation alternative (i) reflects an early generative impulse, but seems unlikely because it does not explain why verbal passives are selected by auxiliaries with a feature &plus;<u>&emsp;</u>AP and generally appear in syntactic AP positions (<link rid="ss15 ss17">sections 3.2 and 3.4</link>).<link rid="fn27">
<sup>27</sup></link> Alternatives (ii) and (iii) are currently more plausible accounts of (5). The next section briefly examines empirical grounds for favoring Late Insertion (iii), but this is not crucial for our overall review of adjectival passives.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss22" level="2">
<heading id="h21" level="2">5.3&ensp;Passive participle contrasts in Dutch verb raising</heading>
<p>The difference between a feature checking approach to <i>-en</i> (ii) and its late insertion (iii), i.e., inserting the verbal passive <i>-en</i> under a suffixal A in PF, can be tested empirically in the syntax. Under late insertion, verbal passive participles are expected to show some transformational behaviour of V not shared by As, whereas under LF feature checking of <i>-en</i>, a verbal passive participle should have the same syntax as an A, because verbal and adjectival passives then come to differ only in LF.</p>
<p>In Dutch sequences of final verbs (where all but the underlyingly highest must be non-finite), verbal and adjectival passive participles behave differently. Verbal participles can move from their base position, italicized in (33a), over higher final verbs as in (33b), but adjectival participles must remain in their italicized base position in (34a). H. Van Riemsdijk has provided these examples:</p>
<p>(33)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>brief</entry>
<entry><i>verzonden</i>
</entry>
<entry>moest</entry>
<entry>worden.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>letter</entry>
<entry>sent</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>get</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that the letter must be sent.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat de brief moest worden <i>verzonden</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(34)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>brief</entry>
<entry><i>onverzonden</i>
</entry>
<entry>moest</entry>
<entry>blijven.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>letter</entry>
<entry>unsent</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>remain</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that the letter must remain unsent.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">*.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat de brief moest blijven <i>onverzonden</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Under the verb-raising analysis advocated in <link rid="b33">Haegeman and Van Riemsdijk (1986</link>), one may say that verbal passive participles undergo reanalysis and subsequent verb raising, while adjectival ones cannot. Furthermore, verb raising, which most likely applies at PF, is optional for a verbal passive participle (33). In contrast, Dutch verb raising to final position is obligatory for an infinitive, as italicized in (35).</p>
<p>(35)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat Henk de brief <i>zenden</i> zal moeten.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat Henk de brief zal <i>zenden</i> moeten.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;dat</entry>
<entry>Henk</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>brief</entry>
<entry>zal</entry>
<entry>moeten</entry>
<entry><i>zenden</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that</entry>
<entry>Henk</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>letter</entry>
<entry>will</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>send</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;that Henk will have to send the letter.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These observations suggest that verb raising and/or movement is obligatory (in some contexts and dialects) for an item analyzed as a V, but impossible for an item analyzed as an A. That is, at the point in the derivation at which this operation applies, (a) an infinitive is unambiguously a V, (b) a verbal passive participle is analyzable as either a V or an A, and (c) an adjectival passive participle is unambiguously an A. Now according to the late insertion alternative of -<i>en</i> (iii), the verbal passive in a syntactic derivation (and early in PF) is precisely a V stem with an empty suffixal head A. Hence an operation such as verb raising/movement can see (&lsquo;analyze&rsquo;) the verbal passive as either a V or as an A, correctly yielding both variants in (33). By contrast, an adjectival passive is unambiguously an A, with a syntactically invisible V stem inside it throughout a derivation; it must then remain in situ as in (34). Finally, an infinitive is a V and nothing else, so it must undergo verb raising/movement as in (35).</p>
<p>Under the feature-checking approach, the two types of passive are the same in the syntax and shouldn&apos;t differ in behavior at all. We thus see that the explanatory contrasting LF structures in (5) are more likely due to the possibility of inserting grammatical morphemes at different derivational levels than to any differences in LF feature checking of a V that moves in syntax or PF.<link rid="fn28">
<sup>28</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss23" level="1">
<heading id="h22" level="1">6&ensp;Evidence for Move in adjectival passives</heading>
<subsection id="ss24" level="2">
<heading id="h23" level="2">6.1&ensp;Levin and Rappaport: relating deep direct objects to adjectival passives</heading>
<p>Despite their many surface differences, we can nonetheless descriptively characterize adjectival and verbal passive phrases in very similar terms. To appreciate the empirical import of this, let&apos;s first briefly examine a class of &lsquo;active&rsquo; adjectives derived from verbs where we <i>cannot</i> descriptively characterize the two classes in similar terms. Consider a large class of lexical adjectives in <i>-ive</i> that attach to V stems, i.e<i>.</i>, <i>attractive</i>, <i>attentive</i>, <i>corrosive</i>, <i>decisive</i>, <i>defensive</i>, <i>derisive</i>, <i>dismissive</i>, <i>evasive</i>, <i>exhaustive</i>, <i>invasive</i>, <i>obtrusive</i>, <i>offensive</i>, <i>perceptive</i>, <i>(re)active</i>, <i>receptive</i>, <i>repulsive</i>, <i>seductive</i>, <i>selective</i>, etc. In just about every case, the types of permitted arguments with the verb and the corresponding adjective differ.</p>
<p>First, <i>decide</i>, <i>defend</i>, <i>dismiss</i>, <i>evade</i>, and <i>perceive</i> are transitive, but their adjectival counterparts are preferably intransitive, with <i>of</i>-phrase complements being marginal at best, e.g. *<i>John is &lcub;decisive</i>/<i>defensive&rcub; of his own actions</i>. Second, selection restrictions on corresponding arguments differ unpredictably: <i>Magnets &lcub;attract</i>/ *<i>are attractive &lcub;to</i>/<i>of&rcub;&rcub; metals</i>; <i>America &lcub;often invades</i>/*<i>is often invasive of&rcub; the Caribbean</i>; <i>Those weapons were offensive &ne; Those weapons offended; Mary &lcub;repels</i>/<i>is repulsive to&rcub; John</i> vs. <i>Mary &lcub;repels</i>/*<i>is repulsive to&rcub; John&apos;s advances</i>; <i>We are selective about cheeses</i> vs. <i>We select (*about) cheeses</i>, etc., etc.</p>
<p>The variation between adjectival passives and corresponding active verbs is nothing on this scale. In fact, the possible subjects of adjectival passives seem to be precisely those deep direct objects of verbs <i>whose obligatory subcategorizations are otherwise respected in the passive phrases</i>. <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport (1986</link>: sections 2&ndash;3) explicitly demonstrate that any individual theta-roles, whether or not Theme is understood as in <link rid="b28">Anderson (1977</link>), are irrelevant for determining well-formed passive adjectives. They use the following type of data to establish this generalization.</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>verb:</entry>
<entry>They stuffed the feathers *(into the pillow).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>adjective:</entry>
<entry>The feathers remained stuffed *(in the pillow).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">verb:</entry>
<entry>They crammed the freezer (with food).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>We crammed food *(into the freezer).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">adjective:</entry>
<entry>The freezer remained crammed (with food).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The food remained crammed *(into the freezer).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>verb:</entry>
<entry>We are placing our company records *(where they belong).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>adjective:</entry>
<entry>Our company records are placed *(where they belong) by now.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">verb:</entry>
<entry>The trees are being stripped &lcub;of/*with&rcub; bark.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The bark is being stripped &lcub;from/*on&rcub; those trees.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">adjective:</entry>
<entry>The trees look stripped &lcub;of/*with&rcub; bark.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The bark remains unstripped &lcub;from/*on&rcub; those trees.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In essence, Levin and Rappaport&apos;s results establish a syntactic passive relation between a direct object and a subject. The import of their findings is straight-forward: <i>the theta-role of the subject of an adjectival passive is always that of the corresponding verb&apos;s deep direct object.</i> However, they avoid reference to syntactic structure in describing these findings, as they are convinced that theta-role specifications should replace subcategorization in lexical representations.<link rid="fn29">
<sup>29</sup></link> They therefore paraphrase references to the fact that passive adjectives preserve verbal subcategorization, speaking for example of a &ldquo;basic insight: the properties of an AP headed by an adjectival passive participle are determined by the complement structure of the base verb&rdquo; (p. 637). and they summarize &ldquo;the theta-role assigned to the direct argument internal to the VP headed by the verb is assigned external to the AP headed by the related adjectival passive participle&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rdquo; (p. 643).</p>
<p>A little reflection shows that the syntactic generalization for adjectival passives, above in italics, is exactly what holds for verbal passives, except that &lsquo;direct argument&rsquo; (&equals; deep direct object) for adjectival passives is replaced for verbal passives with &lsquo;direct object at Spell Out&rsquo;. In my view, this relation is best captured, as it has been throughout the history of generative grammar, by using object to subject NP movement in adjectival passives, as suggested in <link rid="b30">Fiengo (1977</link>). The subsequent inability to even conceive of this option is the unfortunate legacy of <link rid="b7">Wasow (1977</link>) mentioned in introducing <link rid="ss13">section 3</link>.</p>
<p>Deriving adjectival passives from transformational movement immediately explains the problem faced by <link rid="b28">Anderson (1977</link>) exemplified in (27): why adjectival passives are easier to form than middle verbs. The latter apparently require lexical specification, which comes with a cost-per-item not assessed for transformational passivization.</p>
<p>Let us see in more detail how Move can derive adjectival passives and account for their differences with verbal passives.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss25" level="2">
<heading id="h24" level="2">6.2&ensp;&ensp;Reformulating Levin and Rappaport&apos;s &lsquo;Sole Complement Generalization&rsquo;</heading>
<p>We have seen that in the perspective of <link rid="b28">Anderson (1977</link>), the generalization (29) of <link rid="ss18">section 4</link> should be expressed by principles of grammar, not in individual lexical items.</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;The subject of (always intransitive) adjectival passives relates semantically to the verb root like the direct object of corresponding transitive verbs.</p>
<p>Small changes in (29) can lead to a central descriptive generalization about adjectival passives that encompasses the other systematic syntactic restrictions on adjectival passives: their compatibility with only deep direct objects (<link rid="ss10">section 2.5</link>) and their incompatibility with idiomatic objects (<link rid="ss12">section 2.7</link>).</p>
<p>First, it is the presence <i>in the syntax</i> of the participial stem &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; that somehow forces an adjectival passive&apos;s subject to relate to a <i>deep</i> object rather than a derived object. Second, as argued in <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport (1986</link>: section 4.5), theta-roles are plausibly interpretations provided only to argument phrases, so that parts of idioms generally lack theta-roles.<link rid="fn30">
<sup>30</sup></link> These two considerations lead us to restate (29) as (37):</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;<b>Passive Adjective Condition (PAC).</b> The subject of adjectival passives receives the theta-role that its verb root assigns to a deep direct object in an active VP. In other respects adjectival passives respect the subcategorization of the verb root.<link rid="fn31">
<sup>31</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The conclusion (37) is almost the same as <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport&apos;s (1986</link>: 631) summary of their empirical findings for adjectival passives:</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<b>Sole Complement Generalization (SCG).</b> An argument that may stand as sole NP complement to a verb can be externalized &lsqb;become the subject&rsqb; by Adjectival Passive Formation (APF).</p>
<p>The SCG as formulated is inaccurate, however. As discussed in note 5, certain sole NP complements cannot become subjects of adjectival passives. Moreover, NP subjects of adjectival passives can only relate to direct objects; they cannot correspond to predicate nominals or measure phrases (e.g., <i>We seemed to remain almost three weeks</i>/*<i>Almost three weeks seemed remained</i>). Therefore, having a sole NP complement is not a sufficient condition for APF.</p>
<p>Nor is the SCG a necessary condition for APF. For example, (38) fails to predict the existence of the adjectival passives in (39a), because their subjects are not potential sole complements to verbs. These APF verbs require <i>two</i> complements, as the active counterparts (39b) show.</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Roses looked strewn everywhere.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Their balconies stayed bedecked with flags for a week.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>That application seems worded with exceptional care.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>The children have strewn roses *(everywhere).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Fans were bedecking their balconies *(with flags).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary worded that application *(with exceptional care).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The SCG (38) is not a necessary condition for APF because adjectival passive phrases, like verbal passive phrases, must respect the subcategorization of the head verb. The descriptively adequate reformulation of the SCG is therefore the PAC (37). and if the term &lsquo;theta-role&rsquo; is replaced by the more general term &lsquo;interpretation&rsquo;, then the PAC is nothing other than a description of deriving adjectival passives by movement of a deep direct object.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss26" level="2">
<heading id="h25" level="2">6.3&ensp;A non-problem for Move with adjectival passives</heading>
<p>Even though Levin and Rappaport show that individual theta-roles are irrelevant for characterizing adjectival passives, there remains another legacy of lexicalist treatments that could prevent acceptance of using Move for this construction.</p>
<p>A number of researchers feel that the idiomatic lexicalized meanings of many passive adjectives, as evidenced in (40), somehow undermine any account of them in terms of transfomational movement of the object DP.</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>deeply &lcub;moved/*shoved&rcub;</entry>
<entry>so lost in &lcub;thought/*fear&rcub;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how &lcub;overplanted/*planted&rcub;</entry>
<entry>unheard *(of) outrage</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But this conclusion is a non sequitur. <link rid="b19">Chomsky&apos;s (1970</link>) long accepted analysis of derived nominals, which also exhibit a notorious range of idiomatic and lexicalized meanings, uses &ndash; indeed is the source of using &ndash; the NP-preposing transformation for objects. The lexicalized meanings of many passive adjectives are thus no barrier to deriving adjectival passives by &lsquo;NP movement&rsquo;.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss27" level="1">
<heading id="h26" level="1">7&ensp;&ensp;Lexical notation for dual level or polyfunctional morphology</heading>
<p>Throughout this chapter, I have claimed that the LF difference in (5a, b) between phonologically identical adjectival and verbal passives underlies several of their surface differences. If Move can be used in deriving both passive types, the distinction in (5) should somehow correlate with how Move interacts differently with object NPs in the two constructions.</p>
<p>In both passives, the participial head <i>-en</i> can be said to agree with a moved passive subject, as this agreement is morphologically overt in many languages (<link rid="ss16">section 3.3</link>). This agreeing surface subject has its source in different pre-movement positions, however:</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;In adjectival passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; agrees with the <i>deep</i> direct object of the verb, by virtue of the PAC (37). This morpheme is present at LF (5a).</p>
<p>(42)&ensp;In verbal passives, the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; agrees with a noun phrase that is a <i>derived</i> object of the verb, i. e., the object in the predicate phrase subsequent to transformational computation. This morpheme is absent at LF (5b).</p>
<p>Aside from this difference both uses of the English and other passive participle morphemes can be expressed in a single lexical entry (43). As is standard, phi-features refer to NUMBER, GENDER, and PERSON features on nominal projections:</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;<b>Passive participle:</b> <i>-en</i>, A, &plus;V__, phi-features of an (empty) nominal projection sister<link rid="fn32">
<sup>32</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The second sentences in (41) and (42) are just (5a, b) rephrased. I assume that these LF differences are simply inherited from the corresponding syntactic representations, so that &lsquo;present/absent at LF&rsquo; is equivalent to &lsquo;present/absent in syntax&rsquo; and &lsquo;absent in syntax/LF&rsquo; means &lsquo;present only in PF&rsquo;. I thus rephrase (41) and (42) as follows:</p>
<p>(44)&ensp;Adjectival Passives. An item &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; in the context V__ in the syntax agrees with V&apos;s <i>deep</i> direct object.</p>
<p>(45)&ensp;Verbal Passives. An item &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; in the context V__ only in PF agrees with V&apos;s <i>surface</i> object.</p>
<p>The links between &lsquo;deep&rsquo; and &lsquo;present in syntax&rsquo; in (44), and &lsquo;surface&rsquo; and &lsquo;present only in PF&rsquo; in (45) now seem suggestive. We want to correlate these two properties of participial <i>-en</i>, and thus reduce all the differences between adjectival and verbal passives to one.<link rid="fn33">
<sup>33</sup></link> The sort of dual behavior of grammatical morphemes expressed in (44) and (45) has in recent years been the focus of increasing theoretical interest, for example in <link rid="b34 b35">Borer (1991, 1993</link>), <link rid="b36 b8">Emonds (1991a, 2000</link>), <link rid="b37">Grimshaw (1990</link>), and <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer (1995</link>).</p>
<p>For example, Schoorlemmer&apos;s thorough study of the Russian participles examines what she terms the &lsquo;polyfunctionality&rsquo; of several grammatical morphemes in Slavic systems. Among them one prominent example is the Russian adjectival passive ending and the homonymous &lsquo;PPP&rsquo; (past passive participle in verbal passives), which is basically the counterpart of the polyfunctionality in (44) and (45). Most of the differences she discusses between Russian adjectival and verbal passives are similar to or even identical with the differences for English: (i) Certain Russian adjectival passives undergo degree word modification and show &lsquo;semantic drift&rsquo;, i.e., they are part of the permanent lexicon. These aspects of English adjectival passives are discussed in slightly different terms in <link rid="ss8">section 2.3</link> above. (ii) Adjectival passives have no external argument (implicit or explicit); cf. <link rid="ss11">section 2.6</link>. (iii) A Russian counterpart to <i>un-</i> prefixation, namely <i>ne-</i> prefixation, occurs with adjectival but not verbal passives; cf. <link rid="ss9">section 2.4</link>. (iv) The verbal passive reports an event (with a possible durative adverb), while the adjectival passive reports a state; cf. <link rid="ss6">section 2.1</link>. (v) Adjectival passives can be complements of <i>stat&rsquo;</i> &lsquo;become, get&rsquo; whereas verbal passives cannot be; cf. <link rid="ss7">section 2.2</link>.<link rid="fn34">
<sup>34</sup></link>
</p>
<p>She summarizes these results as follows: &ldquo;The PPP is adjectival only with respect to its inflection, everything else is verbal, as shown by its behaviour in the diagnostics for adjectival passives&rdquo; (1995: 217&ndash;222). In an earlier passage, Schoorlemmer characterizes this type of grammatical behavior as follows:</p>
<quotation>
<p>there seem to be two kinds of morphological processes: those that can be argued to be presyntactic &lsqb;e.g., in passive adjectives&rsqb; and those that can be argued to be non-presyntactic &lsqb;e.g., in verbal passives&rsqb;&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;the morphological output of both rules is almost entirely uniform. (<link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer 1995</link>: 163&ndash;164)</p>
</quotation>
<p>The formulations (44) and (45) reflect the same dichotomy between &lsquo;presyntactic&rsquo; and &lsquo;non-presyntactic&rsquo;.</p>
<p>In order to provide a theoretically satisfactory basis for expressing the polyfunctionality of the Russian PPP (i.e. <i>-en</i>), Schoorlemmer uses an approach developed by H. Borer:</p>
<quotation>
<p>for a unitary morphological module that runs parallel to syntax and also precedes and follows it, an approach to morphology named Parallel Morphology in <link rid="b35">Borer (1993</link>)&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;Morphology&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;is a set of rules that can apply anywhere. It derives Lieber type head-adjoined structures (<link rid="b9 b38">Lieber 1980, 1992</link>)&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;The product of these morphological rules may be inserted at both D- and S-structure. Borer argues that the difference between two kinds of nominals (like Hebrew and English process and result nominals) is one of the levels at which the product of the morphological rules enters syntax. (1995: 171&ndash;173)<link rid="fn35">
<sup>35</sup></link>
</p>
</quotation>
<p>This relatively new approach to morphology, though doubtlessly still in need of refinement, seems capable of capturing the dual functionality of the passive participle morpheme &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb; expressed above as (44) and (45). We want to derive it from the single lexical entry (43).</p>
<p>Adjectival passives require the Lieber type head-adjoined structure &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> V &minus; &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-en</i>&rsqb;&rsqb; that results from (43) to enter a derivation <i>presyntactically</i>, at the beginning of a computational &lsquo;phase&rsquo;. Presyntactic insertion naturally implies that the item <i>-en</i> satisfies its lexical specification <i>at that level</i>, i.e., it must agree with a nominal projection that is its <i>pretransformational</i> sister. This can only be a deep direct object, so (44) follows. Moreover, since the head of the predicate phrase is a lexicalized adjective <i>-en</i>, no case can be assigned to any DP sister of the head. The same <i>-en</i> blocks any idiomatic V-Complement readings by virtue of <link rid="b39">O&rsquo;Grady&apos;s (1998</link>) Continuity Constraint; cf. note 11.</p>
<p>Verbal passives instantiate this same structure and lexical specification, but applied in PF. Consequently, they enter the derivation &lsquo;nonpresyntactically&rsquo;. We can improve on this rather vague term by specifying Spell Out as the appropriate input for the insertion operation. The output of the insertion is then part of PF. Satisfying its lexical requirement at Spell Out implies that <i>-en</i> agrees with any nominal phrase that is its sister <i>after</i> the (visible) transformational computation. From this follows (45).<link rid="fn36">
<sup>36</sup></link> Moreover, since the A head is not lexicalized <i>at</i> Spell Out (but only <i>after</i> insertion in PF), V is the visible head of the construction and both case assignment and idiom interpretation can proceed normally. The different types of agreements of <i>-en</i> are thus derived from its two levels of insertion (44) and (45) into the computation.</p>
<p>The only thing that remains to stipulate for <i>-en</i> is the dual level insertion itself. Apropos, <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer (1995</link>: section 3.3.3) rightly observes: &ldquo;A related question is why there are so few morphological processes with dual properties&rdquo; (p. 180). This empirical observation suggests that polyfunctionality is a marked lexical option, perhaps partly motivated diachronically; cf. note 4. What the lexical entry for <i>-en</i> then needs to indicate is that A can optionally, in the marked case, remain <i>uninterpreted in LF</i> &ndash; the property (5b) of verbal passives so frequently called on earlier to explain differences in the two passive types.</p>
<p>In a study attempting to develop some appropriate notations for the special lexicon of grammatical formatives, <link rid="b40">Emonds (2002</link>) argues that while syntactic categories are never optional (every morpheme in a tree has a category), they may <i>optionally be ignored at the LF interface</i>. The marked option of not interpreting a category at LF can then be simply notated by parenthesizing it. If further an element so parenthesized has no other interpretable features (and <i>-en</i> does not, since agreement features are not interpreted), then the item optionally plays no role at LF. But items without interpretations should be inserted into the derivation only in PF, which is precisely what is needed in order to derive the results of this study. Revising (43) in this way, we derive a final and parsimonious lexical entry for the polyfunctional passive participle morpheme:</p>
<p>(46)&ensp;<b>Revised Passive participle:</b> <i>-en</i>, (A), &plus;V__, phi-features of an empty sister</p>
<p>In the reading without parentheses, A is a normal LF-interpreted syntactic category, as needed in the adjectival passive. As expected, A is interpreted as a property of the subject DP that it modifies. In the marked reading with parentheses, the category A (i.e., a &lsquo;state&rsquo; or &lsquo;property&rsquo;) is ignored at LF; therefore <i>-en</i> is inserted in PF, and the verbal passive results.<link rid="fn37">
<sup>37</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Certain languages such as Ukrainian (<link rid="b32">Sobin 1985</link>) and Norwegian (<link rid="b16 b2">&Aring;farli 1989, 1992</link>) have &lsquo;transitive impersonal passives&rsquo; in which the participle has phi-features of an <i>overt</i> noun phrase sister. In these languages, &lsquo;empty&rsquo; in (46) is an option rather than a necessity as in English. Various formal analyses of such distinctions are given by these authors and in <link rid="b41">Baker, Johnson, and Roberts (1989</link>), <link rid="b42">Lappin and Shlonsky (1993</link>), and <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5).</p>
<p>Two last details: since phi-features can originate only with nominal projections, (46) does not mention the latter. Moreover, the fact that sisterhood is the favored source for agreement is plausibly also to be derived from Universal Grammar and need not be stipulated in a lexical entry.</p>
<p>We thus seem to have successfully accounted for all differences between adjectival and verbal periphrastic passives with a single polyfunctional lexical entry (46) that specifies an inflection, exactly in accord with the rather bold research program for language particular properties proposed in <link rid="b43">Borer (1984a</link>: 29).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss28" level="1">
<heading id="h27" level="1">8&ensp;Consequences of adjectival agreement in passives</heading>
<p>There still remains the issue of how to best characterize what passive structures have in common: the verbal stem of a passive participle cannot assign an external theta-role to the participle&apos;s grammatical subject, even when the verb&apos;s objects remain in situ (as in Norwegian and Ukrainian). The key to these &lsquo;dethematicized&rsquo; subjects lies, I believe, in understanding the crucial role of adjectival agreement. While this agreement is not universal, it is typical of the Indo-European family whose periphrastic passives we are trying to understand. Moreover, it has certain systematically recurring characteristics (phi-features of gender and number, interaction with case marking, absence in adverbial APs) that suggest some common cross-linguistic basis.<link rid="fn38">
<sup>38</sup></link>
</p>
<subsection id="ss29" level="2">
<heading id="h28" level="2">8.1&ensp;Lexical agreement of -<roman>en</roman> with objects</heading>
<p>The lexical entry (46) stipulates that a certain verbal suffix, the passive participle, agrees with that verb&apos;s object. That is, the phi-features on the inserted item <i>-en</i> must be the same as those of any nominal projection sister at the moment of insertion, which can be pre-transformational (44) or exactly at Spell Out (45). Notice that (46) is indifferent between (i) insuring that the phi-features of A&apos;s sister are <i>those independently assigned to A</i>, due to the general agreement of adjectives with their subjects, and (ii) assigning the phi-features of A&apos;s sister to <i>a featureless empty A</i> (which then appear on <i>-en</i> in PF).</p>
<p>Some puzzling related but non-passive paradigms in several Romance and Slavic systems strongly suggest that the reference to object agreement in (46) is on the right track. As mentioned in <link rid="ss3">section 1.1</link>, many of these languages additionally use their passive participle morpheme to form an active periphrastic past tense (e.g., the French <i>pass&eacute; compos&eacute; and</i> Italian <i>passato prossimo</i>), in which <i>the participle does not agree with the subject</i>. With some language-particular restrictions, the participial morpheme <i>-en</i> in this active tense nonetheless agrees in phi-features with a deep object, i.e., a DP sister, just as stated in (46).</p>
<p>Exact determination of the variable conditions on this non-passive object agreement is orthogonal to our concerns here. At one extreme, Modern Spanish active perfective participles, also based on the passive form, never agree with an object. In other systems only empty objects trigger agreement, e.g., in Standard French they must be bound by a clitic or a fronted constituent such as a clefted or questioned direct object. Agreement of <i>-en</i> in adult Standard Italian generally requires empty DPs in deep object position, under conditions that are similar though not identical to Standard French. We see the relevant contrast in French in (47), where bold indicates feminine plural suffixes; t<sub>i</sub> is a trace of the moved direct object.</p>
<p>(47)&ensp;<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Cette</entry>
<entry>femme</entry>
<entry>a &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>vite</entry>
<entry>repein-&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> t<b>-&lcub;&Oslash;/*es&rcub;</b>&rsqb;&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>ces</entry>
<entry>bell<b>es</b>
</entry>
<entry>port<b>es</b>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>that</entry>
<entry>woman</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>quickly</entry>
<entry>repaint-ed</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>beautiful</entry>
<entry>doors</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;That woman has quickly repaint-ed those beautiful doors.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="13">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>C&rsquo;est</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>ces</entry>
<entry>bell<b>es</b>
</entry>
<entry>port<b>es</b>&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>
</entry>
<entry>que</entry>
<entry>cette</entry>
<entry>femme</entry>
<entry>a &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>vite</entry>
<entry>repein-&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> t-<b>&lcub;*&Oslash;/es&rcub;&rsqb;</b>
</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it&apos;s</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>beautiful</entry>
<entry>doors&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>woman</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>quickly</entry>
<entry>repaint-ed</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP </sub>t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col13">&lsquo;It&apos;s those beautiful doors that that woman has quickly repaint-ed.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In yet other systems, <i>-en</i> agrees even with overt objects. Perhaps the most striking contrast is within Italian. <link rid="b44">Antinucci and Miller (1976</link>) and <link rid="b45">Volterra (1976</link>) report that at a certain stage of child Italian, the agreement of participial <i>-en</i> with all direct objects in the <i>passato prossimo</i> is uniform.<link rid="fn39">
<sup>39</sup></link> <link rid="b46">Borer and Wexler (1992</link>: 153) describe this as follows: &ldquo;Presumably, the learner initially tries a &lsquo;simple&rsquo; rule, like &lsquo;agree with the D-structure object&rsquo;.&rdquo;<link rid="fn40">
<sup>40</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The active participle ending <i>-en</i> thus seems exceptional only in being an adjective that does not agree with subjects, as seen in (47a).<link rid="fn41">
<sup>41</sup></link> Otherwise though, its lexical entry must be an extension of (46), since it shares every other characteristic of the passive participle: its category (A), its host (V), and its phonological form. In addition, the object agreement of <i>-en</i> in active tenses that has led several authors to conclude that <i>its central property in all its uses</i> is potential agreement with a verb&apos;s object, precisely as specified in (46), albeit at different levels and under different conditions. Among the passive constructions, this apparent object agreement is obviated just in those cases where the language allows expletive subjects (without phi-features), which in, e.g., Norwegian and Ukrainian include even VPs that contain overt object noun phrases.</p>
<p>We find in the literature at least four mechanisms for effecting the phi-feature agreement mandated in (46) between deep object noun phrases and participial <i>-en</i>. In each case the mechanism extends beyond passive constructions; all extend agreement with null objects to other uses of <i>-en</i>. While I am a partisan of this general approach, the exact conditions determining these limitations on agreement clearly lead outside the domain where adjectival passives have a special role, so my summary of these four mechanisms is cursory.</p>
<p>A first proposal in <link rid="b47">McA&rsquo;Nulty (1990</link>) limits itself to generalizing in French over object traces in passives and A-bar bound traces, as suggested by the paradigms just mentioned. Second, <link rid="b48">Lefebvre (1988</link>) develops a more general system in terms of &lsquo;Move Case&rsquo;, thus making precise government and binding&apos;s often vague concept of &lsquo;case absorption&rsquo; by <i>-en.</i> She summarizes, &ldquo;agreement morphology on the past participle spells out the features of the trace of the NP governed by the past participle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A third proposal is the widely adopted hypothesis that all phi-feature agreements are defined on Specifier&ndash;Head configurations. Since the non-passive uses of <i>-en</i> agreement involve deep objects (e.g., the French and Italian paradigms cited above), <link rid="b49">Kayne (1989a</link>) proposes that it takes place after the agreeing object nominals move to relatively low Specifier positions within extended verbal projections. Borer and Wexler also follow this approach (1992).<link rid="fn42">
<sup>42</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Finally, <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 4) argues that morphological inflections instantiate a widespread phenomenon called &lsquo;Alternative Realization&rsquo;. Under this view, grammatical features are <i>interpretable only in certain base positions</i> (e.g., phi-features are interpreted only on D). However, they can also occur in non-base positions on lexically stipulated closed class elements (usually on an adjacent head) if they thereby contribute to Economy of Derivation. Accordingly, the entry for <i>-en</i> stipulates (only) that it &lsquo;alternatively realizes&rsquo; phi-features of objects, with differences among the passive systems of English, German, and Norwegian attributed to slightly different lexical specifications. A general restriction to local contexts in the definition of (unmarked) Alternative Realization renders unnecessary any mention of &lsquo;empty sister&rsquo; in (46).</p>
<p>We need not decide among these four alternatives. However this agreement of <i>-en</i> with an object is finally formalized, the analytic passive sub-case of (46), robustly overt in several grammatical systems, fully unifies adjectival and verbal passives. All their differences are due to the levels of insertion of <i>-en</i>, as explicated in <link rid="ss27">section 7</link>. and somewhat surprisingly, we will see in the next section that (46) also leads directly to explaining &Aring;farli&apos;s &lsquo;essential property of (all) passives&rsquo;, the suppression of external theta-roles in SPEC(IP).</p>
<p>Needless to say, object agreement in participles still leaves unanswered questions: (i) Why and under what conditions do expletive subjects cancel the need for it? (ii) Why do only certain grammars exhibit it in active composed pasts with overt object noun phrases? (iii) How is this <i>-en</i> agreement (46) related to expressing what is familiarly called &lsquo;object to subject movement&rsquo;, i.e., is &lsquo;subject&ndash;object agreement&rsquo; possibly a <i>prerequisite</i> for the latter? (Cf. <link rid="b8">Emonds 2000</link>: ch. 5.) But since these intriguing questions lead well outside the realm of specifically adjectival passives, this study leaves them for future research.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss30" level="2">
<heading id="h29" level="2">8.2&ensp;External theta-role suppression (dethematicization)</heading>
<p>If adjectival passives are derived by movement, they show that the common property of passives has nothing to do with some subject position &lsquo;losing&rsquo; an ability to express a theta-role, since the works cited in <link rid="ss11">section 2.6</link> show that no such underlying position or theta-role is ever part of a derivation of adjectival passives. Rather, what makes the subject of <i>any</i> (verbal or adjectival) passive clause &lsquo;theta-free&rsquo; (and hence, when expletives are unavailable, forces movement of some DP to this position) is the fact that agreement with a subject simply makes the latter <i>inaccessible</i> for being interpreted within any phrase headed by a passive participle. That is, nothing outside a phrase whose head V <i>has adjectival morphology</i> can serve as an argument of that V. If we can explain why &ndash; why the feature specification of the A head of the passive participle should block theta-role assignment to SPEC(IP) &ndash; we thereby account for &Aring;farli&apos;s &lsquo;essential property of the passive&rsquo;.</p>
<p>We want to do this with no stipulation about passive structures, using only generally justifiable statements of grammatical theory. The key distinction, overtly morphological in several Romance languages, lies in the adjectival agreements of <i>-en</i>. The following French examples from <link rid="ss16">section 3.3</link> show a typical situation: <i>all passive participles overtly agree with the surface subject</i> as shown in bold brackets in (48a, b) while <i>active participles do not</i> (48c).</p>
<p>(48)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>A</entry>
<entry>mon</entry>
<entry>arriv&eacute;e,</entry>
<entry>ces</entry>
<entry>joli<b>es</b>
</entry>
<entry>portes</entry>
<entry>semblaient &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>d&eacute;j&agrave;</entry>
<entry>repein-&lsqb;<sub>A</sub><b> t-es</b>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>at</entry>
<entry>my</entry>
<entry>arrival,</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>pretty</entry>
<entry>doors</entry>
<entry>seemed</entry>
<entry>already</entry>
<entry>repainted</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;At my arrival, those pretty doors seemed already repainted.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="13">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ces</entry>
<entry>joli<b>es</b>
</entry>
<entry>portes</entry>
<entry>&eacute;taient &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>vite</entry>
<entry>repein-&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <b>t-es&rsqb;</b>
</entry>
<entry>par</entry>
<entry>le</entry>
<entry>locataire&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>pendant</entry>
<entry>ma</entry>
<entry>visite.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Those</entry>
<entry>pretty</entry>
<entry>doors</entry>
<entry>were</entry>
<entry>quickly</entry>
<entry>repainted</entry>
<entry>by</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>renter</entry>
<entry>during</entry>
<entry>my</entry>
<entry>visit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col13">&lsquo;Those pretty doors were quickly repainted by the renter during my visit.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ces</entry>
<entry>femmes</entry>
<entry>ont &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>tout de m&ecirc;me</entry>
<entry>pein-<b>&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> t-&lcub;&Oslash;/*es&rcub;&rsqb;</b>
</entry>
<entry>seulement</entry>
<entry>par</entry>
<entry>n&eacute;cessit&eacute;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>those</entry>
<entry>women</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>all the same</entry>
<entry>painted</entry>
<entry>only</entry>
<entry>by</entry>
<entry>necessity</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Those women have all the same painted only by necessity.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Using the representations for adjectival agreement just developed, we can account for this contrast with what is actually a generalization of the Head Movement Constraint (<link rid="b50">Travis 1984</link>). The HAC (49) is motivated by the same paradigms as the HMC but is also more general than the HMC.</p>
<p>(49)&ensp;<b>Head Accessibility Constraint (HAC).</b> In a structure&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;X<sup>j</sup>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>YP</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;Z<sup>0</sup>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb;, X<sup>j</sup> can be related only with the least embedded Z<sup>0</sup> specified for inherent features within YP.<link rid="fn43">
<sup>43</sup></link>
</p>
<p>There are two cases, j &equals; 0 and j &equals; 1. The case that j &equals; 0 is Travis&apos;s HMC, with the slight and welcome modification that a completely featureless intervening head doesn&apos;t trigger the HMC; a computational step can relate two heads X<sup>0</sup> and Z<sup>0</sup> over an intermediate head Y<sup>0</sup> only if Y<sup>0</sup> completely lacks features. In particular, a lexical stem V of a participial AP can relate to a higher head in LF, e.g., a tense or modal in I, only if both the head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> &Oslash;&rsqb; of AP <i>and</i> any auxiliary V have no features. This occurs in derivations where the lexical entry (46) assigns phi-features to A only in PF, i.e., in active perfects and certain reflexive clauses.<link rid="fn44">
<sup>44</sup></link> In contrast, participles in all analytic passive clauses agree in phi-features with their subject DPs <i>in the syntax</i>, so that the role of (46) is to verify that phi-features <i>already on &lsqb;</i><sub><i>A</i>
</sub> <i>&Oslash;&rsqb;</i> are compatible with those of an object.</p>
<p>What accounts for dethematicization in passives is the case where j &equals; 1 in the HAC, e.g., where X<sup>j</sup> is a subject DP position.<link rid="fn45">
<sup>45</sup></link> As desired, (49) says that a subject in SPEC(IP) is inaccessible to V<sup>0</sup> (&equals; Z<sup>0</sup>) in the syntax whenever the head of the participle (&equals; Y<sup>0</sup>) is specified for features, as in fact the A<sup>0</sup> head is in the syntax of both types of periphrastic passives. Consequently, <i>ces jolies portes</i> in SPEC(IP) in (48a, b) simply cannot relate to the verb stem <i>repein-</i>, as external argument or in any other way. This prediction of the HAC then finally expresses the &lsquo;essential property of the passive&rsquo; that we have been hoping to derive throughout this study.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the DP <i>ces jolies portes</i> in (48a, b) does indeed receive an LF iterpretation: it has the property expressed by the adjectival head <i>-en</i> that modifies it. The agreeing phi-features of <i>-en</i> transmit to the subject the property of playing the role of the phrase Y it agrees with, namely the object noun phrase in the proposition expressed entirely within the AP: &lsquo;X repaints Y, where Y &equals; the direct object&rsquo;.</p>
<p>In contrast to passives, the right hand morphological head &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-t</i>&rsqb; of the French active participle in (47a, b) and (48c) is an exceptional non-agreeing adjective, like those in the idioms <i>avoir chaud</i> &lsquo;feel hot&rsquo;, <i>tenir bon</i> &lsquo;hold on&rsquo;, <i>peser lourd</i> &lsquo;weigh a lot&rsquo;, etc., it is lexically specified to not agree with a subject DP. This participle can thus acquire phi-features only in PF, due to the object agreement induced by (46). Hence the HAC (53) allows the stem V <i>(re)pein-</i> to relate to the DPs in a higher SPEC(IP) outside the AP in these examples, because the PF features on -<i>t</i> are not part of the syntax or LF. The only factor which could inhibit such a relation would be an intervening head V <i>specified for features</i>. But the intervening auxiliary head <i>avoir</i> &lsquo;have&rsquo; with an active participle is precisely a V that is also empty except in PF. Therefore, the DPs <i>cette femme</i>/<i>ces femmes</i> in (47a, b) and (48c) relate to the Vs <i>(re)pein-</i> as their subject, even though these Vs are contained in both a higher VP headed by <i>a</i>/<i>ont</i> &lsquo;have&rsquo; and an AP headed by <i>-t</i> &lsquo;-en&rsquo;.<link rid="fn46">
<sup>46</sup></link>
</p>
<p>In this section, we have been able to account for &Aring;farli&apos;s &lsquo;essential property of the passive&rsquo; (31) by generalizing Travis&apos;s Head Movement Constraint to the &lsquo;Head Accessibility Constraint&rsquo; (49). The crucial &lsquo;dethematicization&rsquo; of the external argument position in passive phrases is crucially due to the fact that both types of passives are <i>inflected adjectives</i>, i.e., they have feature specifications in syntax that make impossible any relation between their subject and the V stem to which they are attached. The HAC thus prevents any of a verb&apos;s theta-roles from being realized outside the passive AP. Nothing in this explanation of dethematicization requires reference to any special passive properties, once we understand both the syntactic nature of adjectival agreement and the far-reaching syntactic effects of the passive morpheme&apos;s unified lexical entry (46).<link rid="fn47">
<sup>47</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss31" level="2">
<heading id="h30" level="2">8.3&ensp;&ensp;An additional consequence of the Head Accessibility Constraint</heading>
<p>We can examine a different adjectival construction to see how the HAC fares when confronted with possibly disconfirming data. Let us again consider the class of lexical adjectives formed by attaching <i>-ive</i> to V stems, i.e<i>.</i>, <i>attractive</i>, <i>corrosive</i>, <i>decisive</i>, <i>defensive</i>, etc. French cognate counterparts of many of these, like other French adjectives, agree with their subjects: masculine <i>d&eacute;fensif(s)</i> and feminine <i>d&eacute;fensive(s)</i>. For many adjectives in this class, it seems like the subject of the adjective is also the subject of the verb stem: one who is decisive also decides, something that is offensive also offends, etc.</p>
<p>According to the HAC (49), however, the subjects of these APs cannot directly relate to these V as subjects, because the agreeing suffixes &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>-if/-ive</i>&rsqb; block accessibility between V and these subject phrases. and the fact that the restrictions on the subjects of corresponding Vs and As are so different suggests that this is correct. As reviewed in <link rid="ss24">section 6.1</link>, one who receives visitors or gifts is not receptive, one who repels attacks is not repulsive, the goal phrases for <i>attractive</i> must be animate, etc.</p>
<p>There is a regularity, however: the adjective seems appropriate for a <i>subset</i> of cases where the verb stem can be used as a bare predicate. Thus in most cases, if &lsquo;X is V-ive&rsquo;, then typically &lsquo;X V-s&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rsquo; in a subset of contexts in which &lsquo;X-V-s&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rsquo; is appropriate. Plausibly, the lexical entry of a V in this formation associates the suffixation frame ___ &plus;<i>ive</i> with both these limitations and also a subject variable X, possibly sometimes giving the latter a &plusmn;ANIMATE value. (Only people seem perceptive and selective, although animals can perceive and climactic conditions can select.) In this way, <i>the adjectival ending serves to transmit to its own subject the external theta-role</i> of the V stem. The subject of the adjective then has the property of one who fulfills that role X in the associated proposition (e.g., &lsquo;X repels people&rsquo; but not &lsquo;X repels attacks&rsquo;).<link rid="fn48">
<sup>48</sup></link> But in all this, the V itself does not need to directly relate to the subject DP in, e.g., SPEC(IP). So it seems that the HAC is not undermined by typical adjectival modification, which does not involve passive &lsquo;dethematicization&rsquo;.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss32" level="1">
<heading id="h31" level="1">9&ensp;Conclusion: the unity of syntax and morphology</heading>
<p>We have reviewed the history of treatments of the adjectival passives, concluding that <link rid="b30">Fiengo&apos;s (1977</link>) basic idea was correct: this construction should be derived by NP movement, just like verbal passives. The many differences between adjectival and verbal periphrastic passives, which reproduce themselves cross-linguistically, are due not to their genesis in different grammatical components but rather to their morphological structure entering a syntactic derivation at different levels. Adjectival passive <i>-en</i> is inserted essentially at the outset of transformational computation (causing it to be mistaken for a base construction). Verbal passive <i>-en</i> is inserted only at Spell Out, with the result that it has been mistaken for a VP when it is in fact an AP of a special sort, one whose head A is not interpreted in LF.</p>
<p>We have found that almost every well-known property of either type of periphrastic passive is intimately connected to its participial morphology. Its category A and the insertion level of its morphemic realization <i>-en</i> determine (i) the suppression of the external theta-role, (ii) the missing external argument and unavailability of case in (only) adjectival passives, (iii) the type of verb which selects each passive type, (iv) the types of modifiers which each type tolerates, and (v) their general syntactic distribution<i>.</i> To the extent these conclusions are warranted, we must conclude that studying the passive independent of its morphology is as fruitless as studying its morphology in isolation. The unity of morphology and syntax is not only an a priori desideratum based on parsimony but apparently a methodological necessity.</p>
<p>A somewhat more exotic conclusion of this study has been that the verbal passive, considered in early generative grammar to be the &lsquo;true passive&rsquo; and straightforwardly taken as the basis of the adjectival passive in several studies (e.g., <link rid="b24">Bresnan 1982d</link>; <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport 1986</link>), is rather the lexically marked and diachronically later variant of the construction, as proposed in <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer (1995</link>: 180&ndash;183). This conclusion is expressed formally by the use of parentheses in (46). That is, parenthesizing a grammatical element&apos;s syntactic category opens the way for its use as a semantically empty &lsquo;inflection&rsquo; (if a bound morpheme) or &lsquo;function word&rsquo; (if a free morpheme).</p>
<p>This conclusion brings us back around to the chapter&apos;s subtitle, from Dumas&apos;s <i>Man in the Iron Mask</i>. The verbal passive, king of transformations in the domain of syntax, has for decades shaped the beliefs and practices of the loyal subjects, to say nothing of the cabinet&apos;s. Examples: movements give rise to co-indexed chains rather than vice versa; syntax can be fruitfully pursued with at most lip service to &lsquo;autonomous&rsquo; morphology. But the king has a double, and this double carries the same traits as the king: it is adjectival, it is a verbal suffix, and it agrees with object nominals. Moreover, it is adjectival in meaning, not just in exterior form. So the double doesn&apos;t look like the king but rather the king looks like the double, and derives its kingship precisely from being a look-alike. Strangely, the double has been locked in an impregnable fortress, the lexicon, where few transformationalists have cared to venture; and the kingdom&apos;s beliefs and practices have developed during this imprisonment. When we now bring the double out of this fortress, the king will have two faces and the loyal subjects may lose their bearings. The beliefs and practices established during the kingship, perhaps even those of the cabinet, may have to change.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss33" level="1">
<heading id="h32" level="1">NOTES</heading>
<p>
<span id="fn1">
<number>1&emsp;</number>Moreover, this participial suffix and the finite past tense are the same in Standard English for all but a closed set of irregular verbs. In many spoken dialects, the past participle and the finite past tense have the same form even <i>with</i> these verbs: <i>they(&apos;ve) took it</i>, <i>they(&apos;ve) done it</i>, <i>they(&apos;ve) wrote it</i>, <i>they(&apos;ve) broke it</i>, <i>they(&apos;ve) sung it</i>, <i>they(&apos;ve) hid it</i>.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn2">
<number>2&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b51">Fassi-Fehri (1993</link>) reserves the term verbal passive for an Arabic construction more akin to the Latin synthetic passive. He refers to the Arabic construction corresponding to an English verbal passive as an adjectival passive because it is &ldquo;internally verbal but externally adjectival.&rdquo; This study will focus on the adjectival properties of Germanic and Romance periphrastic verbal passives and try to integrate them in the final analysis.</span>
</p>
<p>It is only an accident of academic history that we do not use Fassi-Fehri&apos;s terms, i.e., what we call here throughout the verbal passive could be called the &lsquo;syntactic adjectival passive&rsquo; and what we call the adjectival passive could be called the &lsquo;lexical adjectival passive&rsquo;.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn3">
<number>3&emsp;</number>For example, <link rid="b15">Jaeggli&apos;s (1986a</link>) landmark Government and Binding article &ldquo;Passive&rdquo; mentions adjectival passives only on the last page, essentially as an afterthought. <link rid="b41">Baker, Johnson, and Roberts&rsquo; (1989</link>) treatise on the passive refers to them with scare quotes in the last footnote and does not cite literature on the topic.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn4">
<number>4&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b52">Ackema (1995</link>) proposes that dual or second usages of suffixes such as English passive <i>-en</i> may arise &ldquo;because they serve to fill in the gaps in the morphological system in diachronic change&rdquo; (cited in <link rid="b17">Schoorlemmer 1995</link>: 181). For example, when the suffixes of the Latin synthetic passives were lost (Romance languages typically show no reflexes of them), Latin analytic perfect passives formed from the copula plus an adjectival passive participle were extended to a second use in Romance, that of a verbal passive, thereby filling the morphological gaps. Thus, Romance adjectival passives seem historically the prior type.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn5">
<number>5&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport&apos;s (1986</link>) study of adjectival passives might attribute some of the examples in (4), e.g., with verbs like <i>hand</i> and <i>slip</i>, to their &lsquo;Sole Complement Generalization&rsquo; (SCG):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;Sole Complement Generalization. An argument that may stand as sole NP complement to a verb can be externalized by Adjectival Passive Formation.</p>
<p>However, the SCG can&apos;t be the <i>only</i> restriction on forming adjectival passives, since in view of the examples in (ii), those in (4) <i>all</i> counter-exemplify (i).</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;They &lcub;approached/left&rcub; New York. Drinks &lcub;accompanied/followed&rcub; dinner. During the summer, we try to &lcub;avoid/escape&rcub; cities. They practiced &lcub;dribbling/throwing&rcub; the ball.</p>
<p>So some other characteristic of verb classes must be incompatible with adjectival passives.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn6">
<number>6&emsp;</number>The fact that adjectival passives describe a property is mentioned in <link rid="b24">Bresnan&apos;s (1982d</link>) lexical rule of conversion, which adds this interpretation as well as the category A to verbal participles. It seems obvious that &lsquo;property&rsquo; or &lsquo;state&rsquo; is simply the unmarked interpretation of A.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn7">
<number>7&emsp;</number>The formulation (5) is neutral as to how syntax derives this LF alternation. It could be that <i>-en</i> is present in both types of syntactic derivation, with its uninterpretable A feature checked off prior to LF in verbal passives (in the terminology of <link rid="b53">Chomsky 1995c</link>), or that the <i>-en</i> of verbal passives is inserted under A only in PF (as in <link rid="b8">Emonds 2000</link>: ch. 5). Sections 3.3, 5.2, and 7 return to these alternatives.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn8">
<number>8&emsp;</number>In general, adjectival passives can themselves be divided into lexicalized adjectives, which like most other adjectives are compatible with a full range of degree words, and those that seem &lsquo;created anew&rsquo; at each use. The latter often sound unacceptable with adjectival modifiers and in this sense resemble verbal passives.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn9">
<number>9&emsp;</number>Similarly, <link rid="b36">Emonds (1991a</link>) claims that a range of quantifiers and determiners which modify only nouns cannot modify English gerunds headed by V &plus; &lsqb;<sub>N</sub> <i>ing</i>&rsqb; because this N is empty in LF.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn10">
<number>10&emsp;</number>Authors who agree that verbal passives contain covert agent phrases (which is all that is necessary for the analysis here) disagree as to its nature. <link rid="b54">Chomsky (1986b</link>) and <link rid="b3">Roberts (1987</link>) argue that it cannot be the same as the PRO subject of infinitives. <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 10) claims that Chomsky&apos;s examples are inconclusive because they are based on properties of &lsquo;obligatory PRO&rsquo;, while a covert agent phrase has discourse-bound properties of so-called &lsquo;optional&rsquo; PRO.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn11">
<number>11&emsp;</number>This restriction on idiom formation is a slight strengthening of <link rid="b39">O&rsquo;Grady&apos;s (1998</link>: 284) well researched &lsquo;Continuity Constraint&rsquo; on idioms (i), where he defines &lsquo;chain&rsquo; as in (ii):</span>
</p>
<listgroup id="l2" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>The Continuity Constraint. An idiom&apos;s component parts must form a chain.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>The string x&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;y&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;z&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;(order irrelevant) forms a chain iff x licenses y and z, or if x licenses y and y licenses z.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>
<span id="fn12">
<number>12&emsp;</number>In other words, the italicized phrasal complements XP of adjectival passives in (i), like those of morphologically derived nominals in (ii), must be non-idiomatic:</span>
</p>
<listgroup id="l3" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>The dinner seemed made <i>from leftovers</i>.</p>
<p>They sounded fully informed <i>of your intentions</i>.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>The maintenance <i>of these roads</i> is costly.</p>
<p>His payment <i>of huge sums</i> didn&apos;t result in any entertainment <i>of poor children</i>.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>
<span id="fn13">
<number>13&emsp;</number>Calling a step in the history of generative analyses a &lsquo;mistake&rsquo; refers only to how it has been ultimately evaluated by most Chomskyan practitioners. Adherents of other frameworks may consider such a step as a crucial breakthrough.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn14">
<number>14&emsp;</number>The structure-preserving constraint (SPC) of <link rid="b21">Emonds (1976</link>) is more than an observation that operations such as the passive movements reproduce base structures; it also specifies the exact conditions for when landing sites do <i>not</i> require base structures. In mimimalist terms, part of structure preservation (in the original stronger sense of category preservation) means that the possible non-vacuous outputs of Merge and Move are structurally identical at given points in a derivation. In one sense, feature checking may predict this: if in any given position <i>Move and Merge necessarily check the same features</i>, this part of the SPC may follow.</span>
</p>
<p>But the SPC further specifies conditions under which structure preservation does not occur, i.e., the conditions under which Move and Merge do <i>not</i> have the same effects. In other words, certain Moves at the root of a tree prevent further Merges. The promissory note on structure preservation in <link rid="b53">Chomsky (1995c</link>: section 7.2) seems to shed no light on how feature checking addresses this issue.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn15">
<number>15&emsp;</number>The exceptional English A-NP combination in <i>very near the station</i> may be a hybrid of an AP <i>very near to the station</i> and a PP <i>right near the station.</i>
</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn16">
<number>16&emsp;</number>In particular, &lsquo;passive auxiliaries&rsquo; are those V with the frame ___AP that are <i>least semantically specific</i>: <i>be</i> and <i>get.</i> Most of the Germanic and Romance languages with similar analytic passives use translations of one or both of these.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn17">
<number>17&emsp;</number>While it is obvious that <i>be</i> does not contribute to LF, it might seem that <i>get</i> does. <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5) argues that while the <i>distribution</i> of <i>get</i> seems restricted by a following verb&apos;s &lsquo;change of state&rsquo; feature (<i>?get owned</i>, <i>?get hated</i>, <i>?get known</i>), no difference in <i>interpretation</i> is observed in pairs such as <i>&lcub;get/be&rcub; examined by</i>, <i>&lcub;get/be&rcub; built by</i>, <i>&lcub;get/be&rcub; scared by</i>, etc.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn18">
<number>18&emsp;</number>Archaic and sometimes semantically irregular options such as <i>burnt</i>, <i>proven</i>, and <i>suppos&eacute;d</i> are sort of &lsquo;exceptions that prove the rule&rsquo;.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn19">
<number>19&emsp;</number>In contrast, the composed past of a verb in French does <i>not</i> agree with a subject when the auxiliary is <i>avoir</i> &lsquo;have&rsquo;:</span>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">(i)</entry>
<entry>Cette</entry>
<entry>femme</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>tout</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>m&ecirc;me</entry>
<entry><i>peint(*e)</i>
</entry>
<entry>seulement</entry>
<entry>par</entry>
<entry>n&eacute;cessit&eacute;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>that</entry>
<entry>woman (FEM)</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>all</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>same</entry>
<entry>painted (*FEM)</entry>
<entry>only</entry>
<entry>by</entry>
<entry>necessity</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;That woman has all the same painted only by necessity.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These kinds of patterns are commonplace in traditional grammars of languages such as French, German, and Spanish, and so will not be exemplified in detail here.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn20">
<number>20&emsp;</number>An alternative to such insertion would be for a separate morphological operation to &lsquo;add on&rsquo; an A-headed structure in PF to a simple syntactic V. But this ad hoc solution for the morphology explains neither the selection of verbal participles by <i>be</i> and <i>get</i>, nor their more general syntactic distribution reviewed in the next subsection. In addition, derivationally changing a V to &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> V &minus; &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> <i>en</i>&rsqb;&rsqb; would contravene <link rid="b53">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) programmatic Inclusiveness Condition (transformational operations can&apos;t introduce new material) more violently than late insertion into an independently justified syntactic slot. Consequently, the optimal <i>syntactic</i> target for the verbal passive participle seems to be &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> V &minus; &lsqb;<sub>A</sub> &Oslash;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn21">
<number>21&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b23">Freidin claims (1975</link>: 395) that passive rather than active verbs are listed in the lexicon and (p. 396) that his formalism &ldquo;must be stated in terms of semantic functions rather than syntactic categories.&rdquo; A consequence is that verbs with two passives (<i>give</i>, <i>take advantage of</i>, <i>allow</i>, etc.) each require two lexical passive verbs in the lexicon.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn22">
<number>22&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b55">Van Riemsdijk (1983a</link>) provides an important bridge linking a generative perspective on abstract case to the traditional understanding that accusative case is unavailable in the absence of V.</span>
</p>
<p>He further questions the standard version of the Case Filter, based on the availability of apparent &lsquo;default morphological cases&rsquo; in many constructions in many languages, e.g., German. Rephrasing his concern, why are some noun phrases lacking categories which assign them case ill-formed, while default case allows other such noun phrases to be well-formed? This study retains a Case Filter of the original sort, assuming that any default cases are limited to noun phrases in Specifiers not linked by movement to argument (A-) positions. This formulation partly answers Van Riemsdijk&apos;s objections, but detailed justification is not straightforward and would lead us too far afield.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn23">
<number>23&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b41">Baker, Johnson, and Roberts (1989</link>: <link rid="ss18">section 4</link>) discuss and try to circumvent, almost desperately it seems to me, the mounting evidence against attributing case a central role in accounting for the passive; cf. especially their note 10. In the twilight of government and binding, they &ldquo;are forced to conclude, following <link rid="b32">Sobin (1985</link>), that the absorption of accusative Case is a cross-linguistically more variable property of passive than the absorption of a &thgr;-role&rdquo; (p. 236).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn24">
<number>24&emsp;</number>Minimalism itself, to the extent it is based on empirical paradigms, can be traced to abandoning a case-based &lsquo;forced government&rsquo; account (30) and embracing an &lsquo;attract&rsquo; account of passives (31), under the at least tacit influence of the cited studies. Passive movement in minimalism is universally motivated by the &lsquo;EPP property&rsquo; of the landing site, satisfied by Movement in a situation where it cannot be satisfied by Merge. But a deeper examination of these issues would lead squarely into the territory of the verbal passive, and away from the particular focus of this study.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn25">
<number>25&emsp;</number>These paradigms and arguments are from <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 5 - Affectedness.xml" type="file">chapter 5</externallink></related>). Government binding treatments mention this type of example from time to time, often suggesting that some kind of ad hoc inherent case can be assigned to the italicized noun phrases. This line of thought sheds no light on the problem, however. Since noun phrase complements of lexical adjectives typically can have &lsquo;inherent case&rsquo; cross-linguistically, one remains at a loss to explain why the adjectival counterparts (32) of (18) are nonetheless uniformly out (i.e., why inherent case is unavailable just where we most expect it).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn26">
<number>26&emsp;</number>One can still maintain that noun phrases moved in passives don&apos;t receive case, if one holds that structural cases are always assigned <i>optionally</i>. <link rid="b26">Emonds (1985</link>: ch. 1) develops this perspective on case assignment; if a DP doesn&apos;t receive case from V (whether or not the V <i>may</i> assign case), this DP may move to get case, e.g., into the surface position of SPEC(IP).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn27">
<number>27&emsp;</number>A variant on (i) relates adjectival and verbal passive participles via unaffixed &lsquo;conversion&rsquo;, as in <link rid="b24">Bresnan (1982d</link>) and <link rid="b25">Levin and Rappaport (1986</link>: section 4.3). That is, the two constructions would share a common stem but be syntactically distinct like a noun-verb pair <i>smoke</i>/<i>smoke</i>; one would derive from the other by zero affixation. There are reasons to reject this approach, however. First, conversion only rarely affects morphologically derived forms: while the noun <i>commission</i> doubles as a verb, the more typical <i>transmission</i>, <i>contraction</i>, <i>communion </i>and<i> contrition</i> do not. Second, conversion typically relates two phonologically identical and semantically close forms that do <i>not</i> share syntax. But as seen in <link rid="ss13">section 3</link>, adjectival and verbal passives share a <i>lot</i> of syntax. Third, Schoorlemmer (section III.2.3.2) provides extensive arguments against using conversion to express the morphological relatedness of Russian adjectival passives and passive perfective (verbal) participles, drawing on special properties of its tense and aspect systems. The participial syntax of Germanic and Slavic languages is similar enough to expect that conversion cannot be completely wrong for the Slavic systems and yet right for Germanic.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn28">
<number>28&emsp;</number>In any case, feature checking in LF of a V that itself doesn&apos;t move in LF seems essentially incoherent.</span>
</p>
<p>One can of course both reject late insertion and insist that the feature-checking in both kinds of passives is the same, but then one has no account of any differences between them, i.e., such a theory ends up with nothing to say about any of the contrasting passive paradigms. Recent studies often insist on theoretical simplicity of this and that sort, at the cost of accounting for few if any paradigms.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn29">
<number>29&emsp;</number>Thus, Levin and Rappaport begin their section 4.1: &ldquo;In accordance with the program initiated in <link rid="b10">Chomsky (1981</link>), we eschew the explicit use of subcategorization frames in lexical entries as a representation of the complement structure of verbs.&rdquo; Consequently, after establishing their empirical conclusion, the second half of their essay reformulates their result in terms of theta-grids (taking issue with various competing semantic formulations). In my view, their choice of a semantics-based lexical framework makes it impossible to express their main result in a natural way, namely, that adjectival passive phrases lack exactly that overt DP that is licensed by the lexical frame &plus;___DP.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn30">
<number>30&emsp;</number>Levin and Rappaport&apos;s vague term &lsquo;argument&rsquo; should perhaps be replaced by a more testable concept such as &lsquo;potentially referring phrase&rsquo;. NPs in some idioms may exceptionally potentially refer, consequently receiving a theta-role and appearing in adjectival passives. Thus ?<i>Sam will spill the beans before anyone else spills them</i> sounds at least marginally acceptable, so <i>the beans</i> may be a theme. This would license the idiom in adjectival passives: <i>?The beans now seem spilled.</i>
</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn31">
<number>31&emsp;</number>&lsquo;Object&rsquo; in (37) can also refer to objects of stranded P. I have not made an analysis here of stranded prepositions in passives found in English in both verbal (i) and adjectival (ii) variants:</span>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>(i)</entry>
<entry>This problem is being attended to.</entry>
<entry>That couch got sat on soon afterwards.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(ii)</entry>
<entry>It is a long unattended to problem.</entry>
<entry>That couch looks more sat on than I thought.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The stranded P in the first example in (ii) is puzzling because English pre-nominal adjective phrases typically terminate in a head A, i.e., such an A must be adjacent to the N-projection it modifies. Perhaps the required adjacency forbids only intervening phrases. (Along similar lines, postverbal particles do not interfere with the adjacency usually required between English verbs and their object.)</p>
<p>In any case, the approach here removes a problem posed by &lsquo;P-stranding&rsquo; for a case account of passive movement, since stranded Ps generally assign case. Since movement here is not caused by lack of case, the fact of movement with stranded Ps becomes unremarkable.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn32">
<number>32&emsp;</number>Pseudo-passives fall under this formulation if they are derived by &lsquo;detaching&rsquo; a governing P from its object (or otherwise rendering it invisible) in the context V___.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn33">
<number>33&emsp;</number>Recall that a lexicalized A blocks all case-assignment in adjectival passives (44), while the V in verbal passives (45) can assign case to objects, including double objects. Moreover, non-referential object phrases in idioms are compatible with (45) but not (44). These independent factors reviewed earlier should be consequences of imposing the agreements in (44) and (45) at different levels.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn34">
<number>34&emsp;</number>I omit three further distinctions analyzed by Schoorlemmer, which represent specifically Russian reflexes of polyfunctionality and are interesting in their own right. They would require preliminary discussion of Russian morphology (the genitive of negation), stylistics (the long form of adjectives), and aspect (her &lsquo;perfectivity restriction&rsquo;, to which she devotes most of her <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 4 - Adverb Classes and Adverb Placement.xml" type="file">chapter 4</externallink></related>), and thus take us too far afield.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn35">
<number>35&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b34">Borer (1991</link>) is an earlier, more accessible reference on Parallel Morphology. In her (43), Schoorlemmer exemplifies a Lieber type head adjoined structure with a Polish result nominal:</span>
<object id="fu1" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_2_fu1.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu1_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>A similar theory of morphological analysis, but one that denies the need to distinguish a separate morphological component, is presented in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: chs. 3&ndash;5). Under this view, &lsquo;morphology&rsquo; is simply the name of what results phonologically when lexical items composed entirely of grammatical features are additionally specified as &lsquo;bound&rsquo;, i.e., requiring a sister within an X<sup>0</sup> domain.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn36">
<number>36&emsp;</number>My version of dual level lexical insertion (cf. <link rid="b8">Emonds 2000</link>: ch. 4) tries to respect the spirit of <link rid="b53">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) Inclusiveness Condition: new structure should not be added during a derivation. Therefore, even though the morpheme <i>-en</i> is itself absent from verbal passive participles during the first part of a derivation, its category A should be present and empty; cf. sections 2 and especially 3.3 above.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn37">
<number>37&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b56">Borer and Wexler (1987</link>) propose a government and binding analysis of passives whereby verbal passives contain traces (A-chains) and adjectival passives do not. They attribute the later acquisition of verbal passives to a difficulty with acquiring A-chains. In the analysis of passives based directly on the lexical formulation (46), the later acquisition of verbal passives is due to the marked nature of &lsquo;cancelling&rsquo; syntactic categories at the LF interface by means of the parenthesis notation.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn38">
<number>38&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5) argues that much of the grammar of APs derives from their being subject to the Case Filter, as in <link rid="b31">Stowell (1981</link>). Non-agreeing adjectives, including perfective <i>-en</i>, are in general those endowed with an inherent case feature that obviates subject agreement. Other realizations of case are adverbial <i>-ly</i> and agreement itself<i>.</i> This particular mode of explanation is not at issue here.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn39">
<number>39&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b46">Borer and Wexler (1992</link>) cite the following summary of <link rid="b44">Antinucci and Miller (1976</link>): &ldquo;Up to a certain age, variable from child to child and ranging roughly from 2;0 to 2;5, the rule of agreement between transitive past participles and their grammatical object is never violated.&rdquo;</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn40">
<number>40&emsp;</number>Borer and Wexler&apos;s simple rule is precisely (46), which I claim is at the centre of passive phenomena as well. They reject verbal agreement with objects, however, since they wish to subsume this agreement under SPEC&ndash;HEAD agreement, along the lines of <link rid="b49">Kayne (1989a</link>); see below in the text.</span>
</p>
<p>As they observe, a partisan of (46) has to explain why the adult rule is restricted to only empty objects. In the framework in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 4), agreement patterns &lsquo;alternatively realize&rsquo; features away from their canonical LF positions; sometimes these features are also spelled out in the canonical positions and sometimes they are not. Unmarked Alternative Realization in fully developed adult grammars is used mainly to achieve economy; that is, for avoiding &lsquo;doubling.&rsquo; Thus the child Italian rule, whereby <i>-en</i> doubles overt objects, would be a marked option for adults and so is superseded by a more restricted variant.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn41">
<number>41&emsp;</number>Several instances of exceptional non-agreeing adjectives in French are discussed in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 5): <i>avoir chaud</i> &lsquo;be hot&rsquo;, <i>peser lourd</i> &lsquo;weigh heavy&rsquo;, <i>tenir bon</i> &lsquo;hold on&rsquo;, etc.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn42">
<number>42&emsp;</number>The material in this study seems orthogonal to the question of whether traditional VPs should all be analyzed as functional category projections (so-called &lsquo;small vPs&rsquo; of some sort) with object noun phrases located in some Specifier, as Kayne&apos;s proposal requires.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn43">
<number>43&emsp;</number>Contextual features on Z<sup>0</sup>, for example whatever differentiates <i>be</i> and <i>have</i>, are irrelevant.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn44">
<number>44&emsp;</number>French and Italian have active participles whose auxiliary, like the passive auxiliary <i>&ecirc;tre/essere</i>, &lsquo;be&rsquo; agrees with their surface subject in, for example, reflexive sentences. Such agreements might seem to counterexemplify the HAC, since in these sentences the verb&apos;s agent theta-role is assigned to this subject, as in French <i>Cette femme s&rsquo;est peinte</i> &lsquo;That woman has painted herself.&rsquo;</span>
</p>
<p>But in this construction, <i>-en</i> acquires agreement features only <i>after &ecirc;tre</i> is inserted in PF as a result of the reflexive clitic. (Spanish reflexives which don&apos;t trigger a change in auxiliary exhibit no agreement.) Since these reflexive-induced agreement features on <i>-en</i> don&apos;t appear in the derivation of LF, they are irrelevant (invisible) for a principle blocking a theta-role relation between a subject and a V (respectively X<sup>j</sup> and Z<sup>0</sup> in the HAC).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn45">
<number>45&emsp;</number>If VP and NP have more than one functional projection in their maximal &lsquo;extended projections&rsquo; (IP and DP respectively), then (53) should perhaps include all but the topmost extended projections of YP, since I and SPEC(IP) need access to V, and D and SPEC(DP) to N.</span>
</p>
<p>We might also decide to include <i>all</i> extended projections of VP and NP under the term YP in (53). This would permit directly relating C to V (as in analyses countenancing &lsquo;long head movement&rsquo; of V to C) and also V to the N heads of direct objects, as in <link rid="b4">Baker&apos;s (1988a</link>) noun incorporation. Moreover, it would allow selection restrictions to pair V with object Ns, skipping D. All these seem like acceptable, even welcome consequences.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn46">
<number>46&emsp;</number>I will not try here to recast everything in terms of some kind of &lsquo;XP-internal subject hypothesis&rsquo;, where XP includes any type of phrase. The VP-internal subject hypothesis of <link rid="b57">Zagona (1982</link>) has indeed played an important role in improved analyses of causative and restructuring complements. However, the analyses of these constructions in <link rid="b8">Emonds (2000</link>: ch. 6) indicates the inadequacy of a commitment to uniform phrase internal subjects.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn47">
<number>47&emsp;</number>The reason this explanation has been a long time coming is the agreed &lsquo;division of labor&rsquo; between &lsquo;syntactic theorists&rsquo; and &lsquo;morphological specialists&rsquo;, as advocated for example in <link rid="b58">Aronoff (1994</link>: 134): &ldquo;But within a lexeme-based framework in which morphology and syntax are autonomous, what Passive consists of syntactically is not directly relevant to its morphological realization&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;For my purposes, the question is just not interesting. Conversely, its morphology has no bearing on its syntax and should not be used as evidence for one syntactic analysis or another.&rdquo;</span>
</p>
<p>This study has shown that satisfactory descriptions of all the main grammatical components of Indo-European periphrastic passives require a tight integration of morphology and syntax. Along similar lines, <link rid="b13">Kubo (1992</link>) shows that the much wider range of passivizable NP positions in Japanese is directly linked to the V category of its passive morphology, which contrasts with the adjectival nature of the Indo-European periphrastic passives.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn48">
<number>48&emsp;</number>On similar lines, the lexical entry for the adjectival suffix <i>-able</i>, which is often said to also form passive adjectives, transmits to its subject not an external theta-role but that of a direct object.</span>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss34" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h33" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference id="b52" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ackema</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Peter</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Syntax below Zero<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Utrecht University</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>&Aring;farli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tor<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive in Norwegian and in English</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">101</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">108</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>&Aring;farli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tor<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Norwegian Passive Constructions</title><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Anderson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Stephen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1971">1971</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Role of Deep Structure in Semantic Interpretation</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Foundations of Language</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">387</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">396</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Anderson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Stephen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Comments on Wasow</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Syntax</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter<x> </x>W<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Culicover</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Thomas</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wasow</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Adrian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Admajian</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">361</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">377</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b44" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Antinucci</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Francesco</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ruth</forenames><x> </x><surname>Miller</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">How Children Talk About What Happened</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Child Language</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">167</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">189</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b58" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Aronoff</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Morphology by Itself: Stems and Inflectional Classes</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Incorporation: A Theory of Grammatical Function Changing</title><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Kyle</forenames><x> </x><surname>Johnson</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Roberts</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive Arguments Raised</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">219</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">251</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hagit</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Parametric Syntax: Case Studies in Semitic and Romance Languages</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hagit</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Causative-Inchoative Alternation: A Case Study in Parallel Morphology</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">The Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>8</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">119</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">158</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hagit</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Parallel Morphology. Unpublished manuscript, Utrecht University</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b56" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hagit</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Kenneth</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wexler</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Maturation of Syntax</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Parameter Setting</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Thomas</forenames><x> </x><surname>Roeper</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Edwin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Williams</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b46" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hagit</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Kenneth</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wexler</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Bi-Unique Relations and the Maturation of Grammatical Principles</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>10</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">147</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">189</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Realistic Transformational Grammar</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Linguistic Theory and Psychological Reality</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Morris</forenames><x> </x><surname>Halle</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Joan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bresnan</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>George<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Miller</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">59</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982d</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Passive in Lexical Theory</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Mental Representation of Grammatical Relations</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Joan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bresnan</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">3</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">86</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Burzio</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Italian Syntax: A Government-Binding Approach</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1957">1957</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Syntactic Structures</title><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1965">1965</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Aspects of the Theory of Syntax</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Remarks on Nominalization</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Readings in English Transformational Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Roderick</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jacobs</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rosenbaum</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">184</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">221</page><x>. </x><address>Boston</address><x>: </x><publisher>Ginn.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Lectures on Government and Binding</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b54" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Knowledge of Language: Its Nature, Origin and Use</title><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Praeger.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b53" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Minimalist Program</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Root and Structure-Preserving Transformations<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A Transformational Approach to English Syntax: Root, Structure-Preserving and Local Transformations</title><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A Unified Theory of Syntactic Categories</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Autonomy of the (Syntactic) Lexicon and Syntax</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Interdisciplinary Approaches to Language: Essays in Honor of S<x>.</x>-Y<x>. </x>Kuroda</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Carol</forenames><x> </x><surname>Georgopoulos</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Roberta</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ishihara</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Lexicon and Grammar: The English Syntacticon</title><x>. </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Formatting Lexical Entries: Interface Optionality and Zero</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at Kobe Shoin</title><x> </x><volume>5</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">22</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b51" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fassi-Fehri</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Abdelkader</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Issues in the Structure of Arabic Clauses and Words</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fiengo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Trace Theory</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>8</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">35</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">61</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Freidin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1975">1975</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Analysis of Passives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>51</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">384</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">405</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grimshaw</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Argument Structure</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haegeman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Liliane</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>van</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Riemsdijk</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Verb Projection Raising, Scope and the Typology of Rules Affecting Verbs</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">417</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">466</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hasegawa</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Kinsuke</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1968">1968</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Passive Construction in English</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>44</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">230</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">243</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jackendoff</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ray</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Toward an Explanatory Semantic Representation</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">89</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">150</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jaeggli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Osvaldo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">587</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">622</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b49" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Facets of Romance Past Participle Agreement</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Dialect Variation on the Theory of Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Paola</forenames><x> </x><surname>Beninc&agrave;</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">85</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">104</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Keenan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edward</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive in the World&apos;s Languages</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Language Typology and Syntactic Description I</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Tim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shopen</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">243</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">281</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kubo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Miori</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Japanese Passives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language and Culture</title><x> </x><volume>23</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">231</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">301</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lakoff</surname><x>, </x><forenames>George</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>John</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ross</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Is Deep Structure Necessary?</title>
<miscellaneoustext> In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Notes from the Linguistic Underground</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>McCawley</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">159</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">164</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lappin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Shalom</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ur</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shlonsky</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Impersonal Passives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>31</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">5</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">24</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b48" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lefebvre</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Claire</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Past Participle Agreement in French: Agreement &equals; Case</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="other">Advances in Romance Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>David</forenames><x> </x><surname>Birdsong</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jean-Pierre</forenames><x> </x><surname>Montreuil</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">233</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">251</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Levin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Beth</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Malka</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rappaport</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Formation of Adjectival Passives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">623</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">661</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lieber</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Rochelle</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1980">1980</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). On the Organization of the Lexicon. PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lieber</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Rochelle</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Deconstructing Morphology</title><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Mateos</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Arancha</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Role of Agreement in Romance Nominal Projections<i>.</i> MA dissertation, University of Durham</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b47" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McA&rsquo;Nulty</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Judith</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Moving Features of &lsqb;e&rsqb;</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Binding in Romance</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anne-Marie</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>di</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Sciullo</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Anne</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rochette</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Ottawa</address><x>: </x><publisher>Canadian Linguistic Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>O&rsquo;Grady</surname><x>, </x><forenames>William</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntax of Idioms</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>16</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">279</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">312</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Postal</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul<x> </x>M<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Studies of Passive Clauses</title><x>. </x><address>Albany</address><x>: </x><publisher>State University of New York Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b55" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Case of German Adjectives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Linguistic Categories: Auxiliaries and Related Puzzles</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Frank</forenames><x> </x><surname>Heny</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Barry</forenames><x> </x><surname>Richards</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">223</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">252</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Roberts</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ian</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Representation of Implicit and Dethematized Subjects</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b17" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Schoorlemmer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Maaike</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Participial Passive and Aspect in Russian<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Utrecht, Research Institute for Language and Speech</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b11" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Siegel</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dorothy</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1973">1973</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Nonsources of Unpassives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Syntax and Semantics 2</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>John</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kimball</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</namegroup><x> </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Seminar Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sobin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Nicolas</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Case Assignment in the Ukrainian Morphological Passive Construction</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>16</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">649</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">662</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Stowell</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tim</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Origins of Phrase Structure<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b50" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Travis</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Lisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Parameters and Effects of Word Order Variation<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b45" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Volterra</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Virginia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Few Remarks on the Use of the Past Participle in Child Language</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Italian Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">149</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">157</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wasow</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Thomas</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Transformations and the Lexicon</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Syntax</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Culicover</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Thomas</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wasow</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Adrian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Akmajian</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">327</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">360</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Williams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edwin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Argument Structure and Morphology</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">81</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">114</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b57" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zagona</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Karen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Government and Proper Government of Verbal Projections<i>.</i> PhD dissertation, Seattle, University of Washington</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
