<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="27"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 27 - Free Relatives.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">338</page>
<page type="last">382</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="5"/>
<count type="table" count="76"/>
<count type="formula" count="0"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="108"/>
<count type="page" count="45"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20051110"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 27&ensp;Riemsdijk: Free Relatives</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 27&ensp;Riemsdijk: Free Relatives</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">27 Free Relatives</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>HENK</forenames><x> </x><surname>VAN RIEMSDIJK</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>
<p>Introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>Where is the relative pronoun?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>The status of the empty head</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>Matching effects</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ensp;4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Category matching</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>The normal case</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Missing prepositions</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ensp;4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Case matching</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Full matching</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Mismatches</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Case syncretism</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>&ensp;&ensp;4.2.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Case attraction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>Types of free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ensp;5.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Questions vs. free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ensp;5.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The interpretation of free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ensp;5.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Transparent free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>6&ensp;</number>
<p>Matching and the syntactic representation of free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>7&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusion</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1 Introduction</heading>
<p>A relative clause is a clause that modifies a phrasal constituent, generally a noun phrase.<link rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup></link> We call the noun phrase that is so modified the head of the relative clause. There are two main positions in which the head can be found with respect to the modifying clause: internal and external. In internally headed relatives, the head NP is inside the relative clause in the position it is expected to have according to the laws governing the syntactic behavior of elements within that clause. This is so despite the fact that the same NP must also satisfy the needs of the matrix clause. English and, more generally, Indo-European languages do not have any internally headed relatives (but see <link rid="ss17">section 5.3</link> for a qualification of this statement). Japanese, however, does, as is shown in the following example from <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>):<link rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&lsqb;John-ga</entry>
<entry><b>ronbun-o</b>
</entry>
<entry>kaita-no&rsqb;-ga</entry>
<entry>Linguistic</entry>
<entry>Inquiry-ni</entry>
<entry>notta.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John-nom</entry>
<entry>article-acc</entry>
<entry>wrote-NM-nom</entry>
<entry>Linguistic</entry>
<entry>Inquiry-loc</entry>
<entry>appeared</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col6">&lsquo;The article that John wrote appeared in Linguistic Inquiry.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (1) the NP <i>ronbun-o</i> &lsquo;the article&rsquo; is in every respect the object of the verb <i>kaita</i> &lsquo;write&rsquo; in the embedded clause. But in addition, it functions as the subject of <i>notta</i> &lsquo;appear&rsquo; in the matrix clause. In this respect, internally headed relative clauses are in sharp contrast with the externally headed relative clauses which are much more familiar from the Indo-European languages. The typical grammatical way of forming relative clauses in English is (2):</p>
<p>(2)&ensp;I returned <i>the book</i> &lsqb;(that) you finished reading &lsqb;e&rsqb; to your children&rsqb; to the library.</p>
<p>In (2), the head is in its matrix position, while the corresponding position inside the relative clause is empty, indicated by &lsqb;e&rsqb; here. There is a sense, then, in which the head has to satisfy a dual set of requirements: those of the relative clause and those of the matrix clause. How does the grammar solve this problem? In an example like (2), the answer is not immediately obvious, since all we have is a complementizer (<i>that</i>) at the beginning of the clause and a missing element inside it. But there are alternative ways of expressing the external relative that reveal what is going on:</p>
<p>(3)&ensp;I returned the book<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;which<sub>i</sub> you finished reading &lsqb;e&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> to your children&rsqb; to the library.</p>
<p>The relative pronoun <i>which</i> is the element that originates in the embedded object position.<link rid="fn3">
<sup>3</sup></link> The relative pronoun is moved from that position by the standard case of A&prime;-movement, generally referred to as <i>wh</i>-movement, into the initial position of the relative clause, next to the external head. Relative clauses without an overt relative pronoun such as (2) are derived in very much the same way as (3), the only difference being that the relative pronoun is either deleted or phonologically null. The question which arises immediately is what the relation is between the head and the (overt or covert) relative pronoun. Clearly, the relation is not arbitrary. If we say that the relative element is a pronoun, what we mean is that it is a kind of place holder for, a link to, the head noun phrase. To put it differently, we say that the head is the antecedent of the relative pronoun. One of the ways in which this relation, indicated by the co-indexation of the head with the relative pronoun in (3), manifests itself is the fact that the nature of the head determines, in part, the choice of the relative pronoun. The fact that in (3) <i>which</i> must be chosen instead of <i>who</i> is a consequence of the fact that its antecedent is non-human, for example.</p>
<p>With this much as background, consider now an example like (4):</p>
<p>(4)&ensp;You should return <i>what you have finished reading</i> to the library.</p>
<p>What we seem to have here is a relative clause without a head. That is, there is neither an internal nor an external head to be found. Such relative clauses are usually called &lsquo;headless relatives&rsquo; or &lsquo;free relatives&rsquo;, and they are the central topic of the present chapter. Before turning to a more detailed description of the main properties of free relatives (FRs), however, we must address an alternative analysis which immediately suggests itself. Why can&apos;t we say that the italicized clause in (4) is an embedded (or indirect) question? In other words, why can&apos;t we equate a sentence like (4) with a superficially similar one such as (5)?</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;Could you tell me <i>what you have finished reading</i>?</p>
<p>The difference has to do with the selectional behavior of the two matrix verbs. They differ in that <i>return</i> selects noun phrases while <i>could you tell me</i> selects questions. This becomes clear immediately if we replace the <i>wh</i>-clause with an unequivocal question (one introduced by <i>whether</i>, for example) or by a real noun phrase such as <i>War and Peace</i>:</p>
<p>(6)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*You should return <i>whether you have finished your book</i> to the library.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>You should return <i>War and Peace</i> to the library.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(7)&ensp;<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Could you tell me <i>whether you have finished your book</i>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Could you tell me <i>War and Peace</i>?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similarly, a preposition like <i>with</i> cannot take a question as its object, but an NP object is permitted and so is an FR:</p>
<p>(8)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*I am going to swat this fly with <i>whether you have finished your book</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I am going to swat this fly with <i>War and Peace</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>I am going to swat this fly with <i>what you have finished reading</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As a preliminary conclusion,<link rid="fn4">
<sup>4</sup></link> we may record that questions are pure clauses, CPs, while FRs are noun phrases, that is, NPs or DPs, which contain a CP. This conclusion immediately raises a number of questions, however. If an FR is a DP, which contains a CP, then what exactly is the structure? More specifically, the obvious question to ask is if there is a head at all. In other words, is the structure essentially as in (9a) or as in (9b)?</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> CP&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> DP CP&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>And if there is a head, as in (9b), is it entirely empty or is it phonetically realized in some way? Both options can be interpreted in a number of ways:</p>
<p>(10)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry morerows="1">Head is empty:</entry>
<entry>(i)</entry>
<entry>If the DP is truly empty, then this is indistinguishable from (or identical to) (9a).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(ii)</entry>
<entry>There is an empty element in the head position &ndash; most likely PRO or pro.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry morerows="1">Head is filled:</entry>
<entry>(iii)</entry>
<entry>There could be a pronominal element in the head position which ends up being coalesced with the <i>wh</i>-element, e.g., <i>it/that</i> &plus; <i>wh</i> &rarr; <i>what</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(iv)</entry>
<entry>The <i>wh</i>-word (or -phrase) could be in the head position instead of being in its canonical Spec, CP-position.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We may schematically represent these options in the following manner:</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;<object id="fu1" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_fu1.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu1_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The main discussion has been about the choice between (ii) and (iii/iv). That will be the topic of <link rid="ss3">section 2</link>. The conclusion will be that, at least in many cases, the <i>wh</i>-word/phrase is in the Spec, CP position. This conclusion leads immediately to the question of whether the head position is filled by some phonetically unrealized element, as in (ii), or is entirely absent, as in (i). The general aspects of this issue are dealt with in <link rid="ss4">section 3</link>. In this discussion, one set of phenomena has played a principal role, viz. matching vs. non-matching; that is, the extent to which the <i>wh</i>-pronoun/phrase must satisfy in and by itself the requirements (selection, subcategorization, case marking) of both the embedded clause and the matrix clause. These matching effects are discussed in <link rid="ss5">section 4</link>. In determining what the nature of the missing head is, semantic considerations play a considerable role. In fact, many FRs are ambiguous. An example like (4), repeated here as (12a), can be paraphrased as either (12b) or (12c):</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You should return <i>what you have finished reading</i> to the library.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>You should return that (the thing, sc. the book) which you have finished reading to the library.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>You should return anything (whatever it is) which you have finished reading to the library.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These readings, and the relevance they might have for the determination of the nature of the missing head, constitute the topic of <link rid="ss14">section 5</link>. Some of these semantic issues reactivate the question of whether FRs and questions are really that different, and consequently what the structural representation of FRs is. This issue is the central topic of <link rid="ss18">section 6</link>.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss3" level="1">
<heading id="h2" level="1">2 Where is the relative pronoun?</heading>
<p>One of the main questions that arise in the context of FRs, as stated in (9) and (10) above, is whether the <i>wh</i>-word, or, more generally, the relative pronoun, occupies the position of the head of the relative clause or is in its canonical complementizer (Spec, CP) position. The former analysis, which has come to be called the Head Hypothesis<link rid="fn5">
<sup>5</sup></link> (HH), came to fame by an article by <link rid="b2">Bresnan and Grimshaw (1978</link>). And the opposition to this hypothesis, gathered under the name of COMP Hypothesis (CH),<link rid="fn6">
<sup>6</sup></link> was initiated in <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>).</p>
<p>The main reason why this debate was fairly heated and achieved a certain notoriety is to be found in the role that it played in one of the major issues that raged through the field in the late 1970s. This was the question of whether unbounded processes exist in grammar. One of the results in the early 1970s, in particular the theory outlined in <link rid="b4">Chomsky (1973</link>), was that long-distance processes could be decomposed into chains of successive, local steps in a derivation, the standard example being the analysis of long <i>wh</i>-movement in terms of a series of successive-cyclic movements from COMP to COMP. The idea that transformational processes were limited to local domains was embodied in the Subjacency Condition, the cornerstone of Bounding Theory. Suppose now that the HH is correct. This would mean that an FR like the one in (12a) has a structure roughly like that in (13):</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> <i>what</i><sub><i>i</i>
</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> you have finished reading &lsqb;e&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>Clearly, there is a relationship between the <i>wh</i>-head and the gap in the FR. This relationship is marked here by co-indexation for expository purposes. The question is, what is the nature of the rule responsible for this dependency? Presumably, it is not movement, since the <i>wh</i>-word is in the head position and the null hypothesis would be that, like the heads of regular headed relative clauses, it is base generated there.<link rid="fn7">
<sup>7</sup></link> <link rid="b2">Bresnan and Grimshaw (1978</link>) proposed to describe the dependency in question in terms of a deletion rule which they call Controlled Pro Deletion. The idea of the rule is that the position of the gap in (13) is underlyingly occupied by a pronominal element, a (resumptive) element like <i>it</i>, <i>him</i>, <i>them</i>, <i>then</i>, or <i>there</i>, which is subsequently deleted under referential identity with the head.</p>
<p>Observe now that this rule of Controlled Pro Deletion must be able to apply to head&ndash;pronoun pairs over an arbitrary distance, as shown in examples like (14):</p>
<p>(14)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> <i>what</i><sub><i>i</i>
</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> you told Bill that Mary said he should have finished reading &lsqb;e&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>On the basis of this observation, Bresnan and Grimshaw concluded that unbounded transformational processes could not be entirely eliminated from the theory of grammar. But, of course, the conclusion depended heavily on the validity of the arguments supporting the HH. These arguments have to do with one of the most salient properties of FRs: the matching effects which they exhibit.</p>
<p>Consider the following paradigm:</p>
<p>(15)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>We should interview the woman with whom he goes out?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*We should interview with whom/whoever he goes out?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(16)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>We should talk to the woman whom he dates.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>We should talk to whom/whoever he dates.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>We should talk to the woman with whom he goes out.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*We should talk to with whom/whoever he goes out.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>We should talk to the woman to whom he talks.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>We should talk to whom/whoever he talks.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (15) the head of the relative clause is a DP while the <i>wh</i>-phrase is a PP. When the head is missing, the result is ungrammatical. This is due to the fact, somehow, that the verb <i>interview</i> can only take DP direct objects, not PPs. This is confirmed by the fact that in (16) the situation is reversed. Here we have a matrix preposition, which takes a DP object, and the FR in (16b) indeed starts with a <i>wh</i>-phrase, which is a DP. Apparently the categorial requirements in the matrix clause and in the relative clause can be different in the case of headed relatives, but must be identical in the case of FRs. This categorial matching effect is further confirmed by (17), where the matrix preposition cannot take an FR which is introduced by a PP. On the other hand, if the two prepositions (the matrix one and the embedded one) are identical, the result is again (more or less) grammatical, though one of the two prepositions disappears (see <link rid="ss8">section 4.1.2</link> for more discussion of the missing P phenomenon).</p>
<p>This categorial matching effect is elegantly explained if we assume the HH. The <i>wh</i>-phrase is in the head position and must, therefore, satisfy matrix requirements just as regular heads do. The fact that it must also satisfy the embedded requirements follows from the identity requirement on the rule of Controlled Pro Deletion. A DP-head cannot cause the deletion of a PP-pronominal, etc.</p>
<p>In addition to the categorial matching effect, matching can also be observed in the domain of case marking. German serves as a language which exhibits case matching. Consider the following examples:<link rid="fn8">
<sup>8</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Wer<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>nicht</entry>
<entry>stark</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>strong</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>must </entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Who is not strong must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Wen/*wer</entry>
<entry>Gott</entry>
<entry>schwach</entry>
<entry>geschaffen</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>/who<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>God</entry>
<entry>weak</entry>
<entry>created</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Who God has created weak must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Wem/*wer</entry>
<entry>Gott</entry>
<entry>keine</entry>
<entry>Kraft</entry>
<entry>geschenkt</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who<sub>DAT</sub>/who<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>God</entry>
<entry>no</entry>
<entry>strength</entry>
<entry>given</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;Who God has given no strength must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>wen</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>mir</entry>
<entry>empfiehlst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>recommend</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I take whom you recommend to me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>*wem/*wen</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>vertraust.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>who<sub>DAT</sub>/whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;I take who you trust.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>*wer/*wen</entry>
<entry>einen</entry>
<entry>guten</entry>
<entry>Eindruck</entry>
<entry>macht.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>who<sub>NOM</sub>/whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>impression</entry>
<entry>makes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;I take who makes a good impression.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>wem</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>vertraust.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;I trust who you trust.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>*wen/*wem</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>mir</entry>
<entry>empfiehlst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>/who<sub>DAT</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>recommend</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I trust who you recommend to me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>*wer/*wem</entry>
<entry>einen</entry>
<entry>guten</entry>
<entry>Eindruck</entry>
<entry>macht.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>who<sub>NOM</sub>/who<sub>DAT</sub>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>impression</entry>
<entry>makes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;I trust who makes a good impresion.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (19) the FR is in the subject position, in (20) it is in a direct object position, and in (21) it is in a dative object position. In other words, the matrix case requirements are nominative, accusative, and dative respectively. The a-sentences show that the FR is well-formed if the relative clause case requirement is identical to the matrix requirement: nominative in (19), accusative in (20), and dative in (21). Whenever the relative clause case requirement does not match the matrix requirement, as illustrated in the b- and c-examples, the result is ungrammatical. That is, the corresponding meaning cannot be expressed by means of an FR &ndash; instead a headed relative clause construction must be used.</p>
<p>The same reasoning as was used in the case of categorial matching applies here. By assuming that the <i>wh</i>-phrase of the FR is in the head position, we explain why it must meet the matrix case requirements, while the matching with the embedded case requirements follows from the identity condition imposed on the rule of Controlled Pro Deletion.</p>
<p>Against this analysis of FRs and, concomitantly, against this argument in favor of the view that unbounded deletion rules exist, <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>) presented strong evidence that at least in some languages the <i>wh</i>-phrase occupies the Spec, CP position in FRs. The main argument that these authors present is based on the way in which relative clause extraposition (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 25 - Extraposition.xml" type="file">chapter 25</externallink></related>) applies to FRs. The argument is based on German and Dutch. Illustrations will be exclusively from German. Consider the following placement possibilities for headed relative clauses:</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Der</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;das</entry>
<entry>Geld,</entry>
<entry>das</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>gestohlen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;,</entry>
<entry>zur&uuml;ckgegeben.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>money,</entry>
<entry>which</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>stolen</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>returned</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;Hans has returned the money that he has stolen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Der</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;das</entry>
<entry>Geld&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>zur&uuml;ckgegeben,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;das</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>gestohlen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>money</entry>
<entry>returned</entry>
<entry>which</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>stolen</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;Hans has returned the money that he has stolen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Der</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>zur&uuml;ckgegeben,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;das</entry>
<entry>Geld,</entry>
<entry>das</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>gestohlen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>returned</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>money</entry>
<entry>which</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>stolen</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;Hans has returned the money that he has stolen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (22a), the whole DP, including the relative clause, is in the canonical direct object position. In (22b), the relative clause is extraposed. What (22c) shows, however, is that the whole DP cannot be extraposed, a process that would generally be referred to as Heavy NP Shift. Basically, Dutch and German do not have Heavy NP Shift.<link rid="fn9">
<sup>9</sup></link> With this in mind, consider now the question of how we expect FRs to behave, depending on whether we adopt the HH or the CH. On the HH, we expect the <i>wh-</i>phrase to remain in situ to the left of the verb under relative clause extraposition, while the rest of the clause would extrapose. On the CH, however, we expect to find all of the phonetically realized elements together undergoing extraposition, while the empty head would remain (invisibly) in situ. The latter is what we actually find:</p>
<p>(23)&ensp;<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Der</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;was&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>zur&uuml;ckgegeben,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;er</entry>
<entry>gestohlen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>returned</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>stolen</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Hans has returned what he has stolen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Der</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>hat &lsqb;e&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>zur&uuml;ckgegeben,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;was</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>gestohlen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>returned</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>stolen</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Hans has returned what he has stolen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This straightforwardly shows that the HH cannot account for FR-extraposition in German (and Dutch).<link rid="fn10">
<sup>10</sup></link> And in view of the fact that these languages exhibit categorial matching effects in very much the same way as English does, and that German in addition is subject to full-scale case matching, we must conclude that another way must be found to derive matching effects in FRs.</p>
<p>There are several other considerations which favor the CH over the HH, of which one deserves to be mentioned that has to do with the absence of the complementizer in the FR on the HH. If the <i>wh</i>-phrase is in the head position, then what follows it must be the relative clause. The null hypothesis would be that this clause, as in the case of headed relatives, is a CP (an S&prime; in older versions). Taking things a step further, the null hypothesis would then be that the canonical positions under CP, viz. Spec, CP and C<sup>o</sup>, have the same properties as in headed relatives. In other words, we would expect the following two paradigms to be fully identical:</p>
<p>(24)&ensp;I put &lsqb;the pie&rsqb; &lsqb;which/*which that/that/&Oslash; you prepared&rsqb; in the refrigerator.</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;I put &lsqb;what&rsqb; &lsqb;*which/*which that/*that/&Oslash; you prepared&rsqb; in the refrigerator.</p>
<p>In actual fact, they are not. In the case of the FR, (25), both positions must be empty. Similarly, if the position relativized is the subject position,<link rid="fn11">
<sup>11</sup></link> we get a reverse paradigm, as shown in the following two examples:</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;&lsqb;The pie&rsqb; &lsqb;which/*which that/that/*&Oslash; was in the refrigerator&rsqb; tasted bad.</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;&lsqb;What&rsqb; &lsqb;*which/*which that/*that/&Oslash; was in the refrigerator&rsqb; tasted bad.</p>
<p>The bracketing given in examples (24) through (27) is, of course, that of the HH. <link rid="b2">Bresnan and Grimshaw (1978</link>) are perfectly aware of this problem. They propose to solve it by assuming that the clause that follows the free relative head is not a full CP (in their terms: S&prime;) but rather a reduced clause, IP (in their system: S). The stipulative nature of such an assumption<link rid="fn12">
<sup>12</sup></link> compels us to look for a more principled solution, however.</p>
<p>If, indeed, we now contrast the above examples with the corresponding bracketings under the CH, a rather different picture results:</p>
<p>(24&prime;)&ensp;I put &lsqb;the pie&rsqb; &lsqb;which/*which that/that/&Oslash; you prepared&rsqb; in the refrigerator.</p>
<p>(25&prime;)&ensp;I put &lsqb;&mdash;&rsqb; &lsqb;what/*what that/*that/*&Oslash; you prepared&rsqb; in the refrigerator.</p>
<p>(26&prime;)&ensp;&lsqb;The pie&rsqb; &lsqb;which/*which that/that/*&Oslash; was in the refrigerator&rsqb; tasted bad.</p>
<p>(27&prime;)&ensp;&lsqb;&mdash;&rsqb; &lsqb;What/*what that/*that/*&Oslash; was in the refrigerator&rsqb; tasted bad.</p>
<p>While this way of presenting the paradigm does not bring out a full parallelism between the headed and the headless relative, one perfectly natural auxiliary hypothesis will do the trick. This is to say that in a free relative, unlike in a headed relative, the <i>wh</i>-word may not be absent for reasons having to do with recoverability. Thereby, the ungrammaticality of the third and fourth options in (25&prime;) and (27&prime;) is accounted for, and full parallelism is achieved.</p>
<p>These considerations make it very difficult to maintain the idea that the HH could be correct for either English or languages like Dutch and German. While this does not exclude the possibility that FRs in some other languages might be constructed according to the HH, or, in fact, that both structures might be available in some languages, two main analytical questions arise from the adoption of the CH:</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;What is the status of the empty head? (see <link rid="ss4">section 3</link>)</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;How do we now account for matching effects? (see <link rid="ss5">section 4</link>)</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss4" level="1">
<heading id="h3" level="1">3 The status of the empty head</heading>
<p>The early work on FRs, up to <link rid="b2">Bresnan and Grimshaw (1978</link>) and <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>), had been carried out in a framework preceding Government and Binding Theory (GB). In this pre-GB framework, traces and PRO did exist, but no systematic account of their contrasting properties had yet been given. This must be at least part of the reason why these authors are not very explicit as to the nature of the empty head on the CH. Bresnan and Grimshaw assume, without further discussion, that the structure of FRs on the CH would have to be as in &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> CP&rsqb; (9a), while Groos and Van Riemsdijk assume a structure more like (9b), graphically shown here as (28):</p>
<p>(28)&ensp;<object id="fu2" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_fu2.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu2_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But they too largely ignore the issue of what this empty DP is like, because in their account the <i>wh</i>-phrase in Spec, CP fulfills all the functions which the head of a headed relative clause normally fulfills. <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) calls this the &ldquo;head bypass analysis.&rdquo; Somewhat more specific versions of this type of approach have been presented in <link rid="b5 b6">Hirschb&uuml;hler and Rivero (1981, 1983</link>) and <link rid="b7">Harbert (1983b</link>). But if the empty category representing the DP head has no properties at all, then it is as if the head is absent, and we are back with (9a), that is, with a structure like &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> CP&rsqb;. But if that is the case, then why not go one step further and assume that the FR is simply a CP whose Spec is accessible to government from the outside? This is indeed a logical possibility. But the type of argument presented in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> concerning the distribution of FRs as opposed to regular complement or adjunct CPs suggests otherwise. If the FR as a whole can have the distribution of a DP, then how can this fact be derived in a pure CP analysis? We would have to assume that the accessibility of a DP in the Spec, CP suffices to determine the distribution of the CP, but the question is how. One way in which this could be done is explored in <link rid="ss18">section 6</link>.</p>
<p>It should be noted at this point that any head bypass approach is subject to one major line of criticism: any such analysis violates the theta-criterion. Consider a simple case like <i>I ate what you cooked</i>. Here <i>what</i> heads a chain whose foot is the direct object of the verb <i>cook</i>; hence the chain is theta-marked by the verb. But now, if we say that <i>what</i> (and not the whole FR or its empty head) is the target of theta-government by the matrix verb <i>eat</i> as well, that chain will be assigned two theta-roles and thus constitutes a theta-criterion violation. <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>) were not concerned about this because their analysis was pre-GB, but subsequent work tried to explore ways to avoid this problem. The three-dimensional approach, which we will return to in <link rid="ss18">section 6</link>, may well be a way out, but first we will address a number of more orthodox ways to deal with the problem.</p>
<p>The obvious alternative to the head bypass approach is to assume that the empty head DP in (28) is filled with an empty category of an identifiable kind. Clearly, the empty category cannot be a trace, as there is no plausible candidate for anything having been moved out of the head position. Hence the empty category must be either PRO or pro. One might think that PRO can be dismissed immediately, since the FR can occur in governed positions, and then PRO, being the head of the containing DP, would be governed. This is valid reasoning only up to a certain point. Recall that we are still assuming that Spec, CP is subject to government (for category selection and for case) from outside the DP. Now, if we assume that the Spec, CP absorbs government entirely, the empty head of the DP would be ungoverned in all cases, and hence PRO would be tolerated. Observe first, however, that this approach will not avoid the theta-criterion problem. Furthermore, we would have to ask what the control properties of this PRO are. Since actual control by an identifiable controller does not seem to obtain, the only option is to interpret PRO as being arbitrary. As will be discussed in somewhat greater detail in <link rid="ss14">section 5</link>, FRs are either definite/specific, as in (29) or universally quantified, as in (30):</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;You can&apos;t make a pancake with what you bought (&equals;with the thing(s) that you bought).</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;I will invite who(ever) you tell me to (&equals;everybody that you tell me to invite).</p>
<p>It is an interesting question whether PRO<sub>arb</sub> can be assumed to cover exactly this range of cases. The answer, at first sight, seems to be no, but so far, modulo some discussion in <link rid="b8">Grosu (1989</link>), <link rid="b7">Harbert (1983b</link>), and <link rid="b9">Su&ntilde;er (1984b</link>), the issue still remains to be investigated in detail.</p>
<p>Turning now to the second option, could the empty head be pro? This seems a more likely road to success in that pro can occur in governed positions. Exploiting this property, we are led to assume that the pro is identified (or licensed) by some outside element, and that any sensitivity of the <i>wh</i>-word in Spec, CP to matrix influences must be mediated by this pro. This is essentially the approach that has been pursued in <link rid="b9">Su&ntilde;er (1984b</link>) and <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>). In view of the fact, however, that matching is a wide-spread phenomenon, and, moreover, that it is a phenomenon that is rather tightly linked to the morpho-phonological shape of the <i>wh</i>-words in question (cf. <link rid="ss10">section 4.2.1</link>), mediation by means of some kind of agreement relation between pro and the <i>wh</i>-word in Spec, CP seems problematic.<link rid="fn13">
<sup>13</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss5" level="1">
<heading id="h4" level="1">4 Matching effects</heading>
<p>As was shown in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> in connection with examples (15&ndash;18) and (19&ndash;21), matching effects are among the most salient and crucial properties of FRs. The present section will discuss the relevant phenomena in greater detail.</p>
<subsection id="ss6" level="2">
<heading id="h5" level="2">4.1 Category matching</heading>
<subsection id="ss7" level="3">
<heading id="h6" level="3">4.1.1 The normal case</heading>
<p>The discussion about the nature of the head of the FR in <link rid="ss4">section 3</link>, most notably the graphic representation in (28), was simplified in one crucial respect in that it suggested that DPs were the only potential candidates for the status of heads of FRs. In actual fact, FRs can apparently be headed by DP, AP, or PP, as shown in the following examples:</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The police arrested <i>who</i> the witness identified. (DP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>They tend to live <i>in whatever town</i> their parents used to live. (PP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>She will make you <i>however happy</i> your ex made you. (AP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>I&rsquo;ll play my music <i>however loudly</i> you play yours. (AP)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Here the italicized phrases are of the matching type. That is, their category is appropriate for categorial selection both in the matrix clause and in the relative clause. In (31a) <i>arrest</i> selects a DP object, and so does the embedded verb <i>identify</i>. Similarly, the PP in (31b) is selected both by the matrix instance of <i>live</i> and by the embedded instance of this verb. And the same thing is true for the APs (adverbial or not) in (31c, d). This type of matching is absent in regular relative clauses, of course:</p>
<p>(32)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The police arrested the man to whom the witness pointed.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>They live in the town that their parents live in.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (32a) the head is a DP while the <i>wh</i>-phrase is a PP. As for PP, (32b) could be a non-matching case, but this is impossible to tell because we do not know whether the head is the DP or the PP. Since APs cannot head relative clauses, non-matching is impossible to illustrate. Non-matching will indeed result in ungrammaticality, as shown in (33) and (34):</p>
<p>(33)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*The police arrested <i>who</i> the witness pointed.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Zij</entry>
<entry>wonen</entry>
<entry>waarnaast</entry>
<entry>hun</entry>
<entry>ouders</entry>
<entry>gekocht</entry>
<entry>hebben.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>they</entry>
<entry>live</entry>
<entry>where next-to</entry>
<entry>their</entry>
<entry>parents</entry>
<entry>bought</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;They live next to what their parents have bought.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*She will make you however happy your ex married.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*I&rsquo;ll play my music however loudly you listen to.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(33) represents the case in which the <i>wh-</i>phrase properly satisfies the selectional requirements of the matrix, but not those of the relative clause. The ungrammaticality is caused by the following mismatches:</p>
<p>(33&prime;)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>matrix DP vs. RelCl PP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>matrix PP vs. RelCl DP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>matrix AP vs. RelCl DP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>matrix AP (adv.) vs. RelCl DP</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In the PP case (33b) we encounter again the problem that we do not know whether the preposition is part of the head of the relative clause or outside it. But in a language like Dutch, in which forms equivalent to <i>whereby</i> are fully productive, this problem can be overcome. <i>Waarnaast</i> &lsquo;next to which&rsquo; is a PP, properly selected by the matrix verb <i>wonen</i> &lsquo;live&rsquo; but unsuitable as a direct DP object of the embedded verb <i>gekocht</i> &lsquo;bought&rsquo;. In the AP cases, again, the AP is properly selected or interpreted in the matrix, but cannot satisfy the categorial selection requirements of the relative clause.</p>
<p>Similarly, if the <i>wh-</i>phrase is appropriate for the relative clause but not for the matrix we again get ungrammatical results, as shown in (34):</p>
<p>(34)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*The witness pointed <i>who</i> the police had arrested.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The police arrested to <i>who(m)</i> the witness pointed.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*She will marry however happy her ex made her.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>*I&rsquo;ll play my music whatever rock opera you are listening to.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The mismatches are as follows:</p>
<p>(34&prime;)&ensp;<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>matrix PP vs. RelCl DP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>matrix DP vs. RelCl PP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>matrix DP vs. RelCl AP</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>matrix AP (adv.) vs. RelCl DP</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>There is, nevertheless, a certain asymmetry between the DP cases on the one hand and the PP/AP cases on the other hand. This has to do with two additional restrictions that are imposed on the latter but not on the former. Recall that there are two main semantic types of FRs: definite/specific and universally quantified (cf. (29/30) and <link rid="ss16">section 5.2</link>). Observe now that the DP-FRs come quite readily in both types but that for the PP/AP-FRs there is a very strong bias in favor of the universally quantified type. In fact, when the context strongly imposes the definite/specific reading, the result tends to be quite degraded.<link rid="fn14">
<sup>14</sup></link> Consider (34&Prime;):</p>
<p>(34&Prime;)&ensp;<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>Tomorrow I will speak to who(m) you spoke last night.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>You can&apos;t word your letter how rudely they worded theirs.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The second restriction is that the matching requirement, if anything, seems to go beyond the identity of the head of the relative clause. Note, indeed, that in all the above examples of AP/PP-FRs the matrix verb and the embedded verb were identical. Choosing different verbs with identical categorial selection requirements also tends to result in less than fully acceptable examples:</p>
<p>(35)&ensp;<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>Why don&apos;t you ever dance with whomever I come to parties?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>She always dotes on whomever you can&apos;t count.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>I&rsquo;ll keep my bedroom however dark you paint your study.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In view of these restrictions, most of the literature has concentrated on DP-FRs, with the exception of so-called &lsquo;missing P FRs&rsquo;, which we return to in <link rid="ss8">section 4.1.2</link>. Before doing so, however, we also need to address the question as to whether categorial matching is an absolute and inviolable requirement. The answer appears to be that it is not.</p>
<p>Consider an English example like the following:</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;a.&ensp;*On whatever mattress I sleep gives me a terrible back ache.</p>
<p>Clearly, the FR is headed by a PP and since it occupies a DP-position (the subject position) the sentence is ungrammatical. In English, the effect is quite straightforward, partly because there is a simple way of choosing a matching variant:</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;b.&ensp;Whatever mattress I sleep on gives me a terrible back ache.</p>
<p>If we strand the preposition, we end up in Spec, CP with only the <i>wh</i>-phrase, which is a DP. But other languages don&apos;t allow preposition stranding (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 51 - Preposition Stranding.xml" type="file">chapter 51</externallink></related>), and in such languages, sometimes, the non-matching variant corresponding to (36a) is acceptable. Consider the following example from Romanian, taken from <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>):</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Cu</entry>
<entry>ciene</entry>
<entry>iese</entry>
<entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>e</entry>
<entry>deobicei</entry>
<entry>un</entry>
<entry>om</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>nimic.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>with</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>goes-out</entry>
<entry>Mary</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>usually</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>man</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>nothing</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col10">&lsquo;Who Mary goes out with is usually a no-good.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It should be noted, however, that even in languages that do allow such non-matching FRs, their status tends to be rather marginal and subject to several further conditions. Most importantly, non-matching seems to be largely limited to ungoverned or at least weakly governed positions. Among the latter, we may include the subject position, as opposed to the object position, for example. With pure adjuncts, of course, there is nothing in the matrix to match with, so this case is untestable. But what we do find is cases of correlatives which can often be analyzed as left- or right-dislocated FRs. (38) is an example of such a construction from Spanish, taken from <link rid="b9">Su&ntilde;er (1984b</link>):</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Con</entry>
<entry>quien</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>quiero</entry>
<entry>casar,</entry>
<entry>&eacute;se</entry>
<entry>ni</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>da</entry>
<entry>la</entry>
<entry>hora.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>with</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>want</entry>
<entry>to-marry</entry>
<entry>that-one</entry>
<entry>not-even</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>gives</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>time</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col11">&lsquo;The one with whom I want to get married does not even give me the time of day.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Another condition mentioned in <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) is that the <i>wh</i>-word may not be too deeply embedded within the <i>wh-</i>phrase:</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Con</entry>
<entry>la</entry>
<entry>foto</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>quien</entry>
<entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>se</entry>
<entry>fu&eacute;</entry>
<entry>es</entry>
<entry>muy</entry>
<entry>simp&aacute;tico.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>with</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>Mary</entry>
<entry>self</entry>
<entry>went</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>very</entry>
<entry>pleasant</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col11">&lsquo;(The person) with whom Mary went away is very pleasant.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Finally, it is noted that the best examples of categorially non-matching FRs tend to be proverbs. <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) notes, for example, that all examples of non-matching FRs in subject position in Catalan, as provided in <link rid="b5">Hirschb&uuml;hler and Rivero (1981</link>), are proverbs, as illustrated in (40):</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>A</entry>
<entry>qui</entry>
<entry>l&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>adulaci&oacute;</entry>
<entry>halaga,</entry>
<entry>si</entry>
<entry>la</entry>
<entry>pren</entry>
<entry>la</entry>
<entry>paga.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>to</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>flattery</entry>
<entry>pleases</entry>
<entry>if</entry>
<entry>her</entry>
<entry>takes</entry>
<entry>her</entry>
<entry>pays</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col10">&lsquo;He who likes flattery, if he accepts it he pays for it.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>For further comments on non-matching, see also <link rid="ss11">section 4.2.2</link> below.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss8" level="3">
<heading id="h7" level="3">4.1.2 Missing prepositions</heading>
<p>Returning now to examples like (34a), notice that you might say that a preposition has disappeared. Consider some other examples of this type:</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>He&rsquo;ll remain in whatever town he has been living all his life.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Children worry about whatever their parents worry.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In both examples, the preposition appears to fulfill a double role in that it is required both by the matrix clause and by the FR. In (41a) both verbs (<i>remain</i> and <i>live</i>) select a locative PP, and similarly, in (41b) the <i>about</i>-phrase seems to serve as a complement both to the matrix-<i>worry</i> and to the embedded <i>worry</i>. The impression of a missing preposition is reinforced when we consider variants of (41) in which the preposition in question is actually present:</p>
<p>(42)&ensp;<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>He&rsquo;ll remain in whatever town he has been living in all his life.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Children worry about whatever their parents worry about.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>From another perspective, however, the absence of the preposition in (41) is hardly surprising, since sharing is what matching is all about. If in simple FRs like <i>I eat what you cook</i> the <i>wh</i>-word is both the embedded object and the matrix object, then why can&apos;t a whole <i>wh</i>-PP have a double function in precisely the same way? The question in other words is whether such examples have structure (43a) or (43b):</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;V &lsqb;<sub>PP</sub> P &lsqb;<sub>FR</sub> &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub><i> wh-</i>word&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;V&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;<b><i>P</i>
</b> &lsqb;e&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb;&rsqb;&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;V &lsqb;<sub>FR</sub> &lsqb;<sub>PP</sub> P <i>wh</i>-word&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;V&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;e&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb;&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (43b) there is no missing P, or rather, there is no P that has to mysteriously disappear. On the other hand, in (43a) the <b><i>P</i>
</b> is supernumerary and has to disappear somehow. And given that we already need a mechanism to account for matching in the simple case, the most straightforward way of analyzing these cases would be to extend this mechanism to PPs.</p>
<p>There is actually quite a controversy on this point, which is still ongoing. The main protagonists are Larson and Grosu. <link rid="b10">Larson (1987</link>) defends the analysis with the missing preposition, i.e., (43a), and <link rid="b11">Grosu (1996</link>) argues against Larson in favor of (43b). For details about this controversy, the reader is referred to these texts.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss9" level="2">
<heading id="h8" level="2">4.2 Case matching</heading>
<p>As in the case of categorial matching effects, the case on the <i>wh</i>-word or <i>wh</i>-phrase must generally match; that is, the case requirements of the matrix context and those of the FR-context must be identical. The overall approach which we have been pursuing is that the <i>wh</i>-phrase is, in fact, a shared constituent: a constituent that originates inside the FR, is moved into the Spec, CP of that FR, and, in that position, serves to satisfy some matrix requirement, be it selection or case government. The phenomenon of case matching, like that of categorial matching, is directly relevant to the choice between the two main approaches to FRs, the HH and the CP, cf. (19&ndash;21).</p>
<subsection id="ss10" level="3">
<heading id="h9" level="3">4.2.1 Full matching</heading>
<p>The full matching paradigm is exhibited in the following examples from <link rid="ss3">section 2</link>:</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Wer<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>nicht</entry>
<entry>stark</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>strong</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>must </entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Who is not strong must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Wen/*wer</entry>
<entry>Gott</entry>
<entry>schwach</entry>
<entry>geschaffen</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>/who<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>God</entry>
<entry>weak</entry>
<entry>created</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Who God has created weak must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Wem/*wer</entry>
<entry>Gott</entry>
<entry>keine</entry>
<entry>Kraft</entry>
<entry>geschenkt</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>muss</entry>
<entry>klug</entry>
<entry>sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who<sub>DAT</sub>/who<sub>NOM</sub>
</entry>
<entry>God</entry>
<entry>no</entry>
<entry>strength</entry>
<entry>given</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>clever</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;Who God has given no strength must be clever.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>wen</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>mir</entry>
<entry>empfiehlst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>recommend</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I take whom you recommend to me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>*wem/*wen</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>vertraust.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>who<sub>DAT</sub>/whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;I take who you trust.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme</entry>
<entry>*wer/*wen</entry>
<entry>einen</entry>
<entry>guten</entry>
<entry>Eindruck</entry>
<entry>macht.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>who<sub>NOM</sub>/whom<sub>ACC</sub>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>impression</entry>
<entry>makes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;I take who makes a good impression.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>wem</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>vertraust.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;I trust who you trust.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>*wen/*wem</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>mir</entry>
<entry>empfiehlst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>whom<sub>ACC</sub>/who<sub>DAT</sub>
</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>recommend</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I trust who you recommend to me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>vertraue</entry>
<entry>*wer/*wem</entry>
<entry>einen</entry>
<entry>guten</entry>
<entry>Eindruck</entry>
<entry>macht.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
<entry>who<sub>NOM</sub>/who<sub>DAT</sub>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>impression</entry>
<entry>makes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;I trust who makes a good impresion.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>One may wonder, of course, how a language can get away with this tight a restriction. The richer the case system, the fewer the chances that the upstairs and the downstairs requirements can be made to match. The answer to this puzzle is twofold. First, if the <i>wh</i>-phrase is truly a shared constituent, then matching is the only option available. Second, all languages in question have the possibility of using what <link rid="b12">Citko (1999</link>) calls a &lsquo;light-headed relative&rsquo; instead. That is, mismatches can be accommodated by making use of a semantically minimally specified head, generally a pronoun. In German, demonstrative or d-pronouns are normally used for this purpose. For (19&ndash;21) the grammatical counterparts of the ungrammatical examples would then be the following:</p>
<p>
<object id="tu35" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu35_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>(19)</entry>
<entry>b&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Der, den Gott schwach geschaffen hat muss klug sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>c&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Der, dem Gott keine Kraft geschenkt hat muss klug sein.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(20)</entry>
<entry>b&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Ich nehme den, dem du vertraust.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>c&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Ich nehme den, der einen guten Eindruck macht.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(21)</entry>
<entry>b&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Ich vertraue dem, den du mir empfiehlst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>c&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Ich vertraue dem, der einen guten Eindruck macht.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In addition to this strategy of using &lsquo;light-headed relatives&rsquo;, there are a few other ways in which languages resolve the problem of case mismatches, and this is a topic which is discussed in <link rid="ss12">sections 4.2.3</link> and <link rid="ss13">4.2.4</link>.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="3">
<heading id="h10" level="3">4.2.2 Mismatches</heading>
<p>As in the case of category matching (<link rid="ss6">section 4.1</link>), mismatching does occur with case marking as well. There are three main aspects to be considered here. First, there are situations in which mismatches appear to be tolerated. Second, mismatches can be resolved under circumstances of syncretism (see <link rid="ss12">section 4.2.3</link>). And third, mismatches may sometimes be resolved by means of case attraction (see <link rid="ss13">section 4.2.4</link>).</p>
<p>A substantial number of cases have been invoked in the literature (see among others <link rid="b1">Grosu 1994</link>; <link rid="b13">Pittner 1995</link>). Consider the following examples:<link rid="fn15">
<sup>15</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(44)&ensp;<object id="tu36" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu36_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>liebe<sup>acc</sup>
</entry>
<entry>wer<sub>nom</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Gutes</entry>
<entry>tut</entry>
<entry>und</entry>
<entry>hasse<sup>acc</sup>
</entry>
<entry>wer<sub>nom</sub>
</entry>
<entry>mich</entry>
<entry>verletzt.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I </entry>
<entry>love</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>does</entry>
<entry>and</entry>
<entry>hate</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>me</entry>
<entry>offends</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;I love whoever does good and hate whoever offends me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>nehme<sup>acc</sup>
</entry>
<entry>wem<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>immer</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>vertraust<sup>dat</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>take</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>ever</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>trust</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I take whomever you trust.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="13">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Was<sub>nom</sub>
</entry>
<entry>ein</entry>
<entry>M&auml;dchen</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>von</entry>
<entry>gutem</entry>
<entry>Gef&uuml;hl</entry>
<entry>m&uuml;ssen</entry>
<entry>dergleichen</entry>
<entry>Sachen</entry>
<entry>zuwider</entry>
<entry>sein<sup>dat</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>girl</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>good</entry>
<entry>feeling</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>such</entry>
<entry>things</entry>
<entry>repugnant</entry>
<entry>be</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col12">&lsquo;To whoever is a girl of good sense such things must be repugnant.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>NB: subscripts indicate the case of a form, superscripts indicate the case imposed by some predicate.</p>
<p>It is quite clear that such examples constitute prima facie problems for the idea that the <i>wh</i>-phrase of the FR is a shared element. A number of remarks are in order, however. First, the data situation is rather complicated here. Some of these examples have a distinctly archaic flavor to them. To the present author, all three are fully ungrammatical. More importantly, the case system of spoken German is subject to considerable decay. Dutch has completely lost morphological case on full noun phrases. In many German dialects, surface case has been lost to varying degrees. Swiss German, for example, has lost the genitive, has a dative that is only marginally distinct from a PP, and the distinction between nominative and accusative, when present at all, is probably more a hypercorrection from Standard German than part of the language itself. Other dialects in the German-speaking countries are less radical, but the dative/accusative distinction is lost in many of them, sometimes with the dative surviving as in the Berlin dialect and sometimes with the accusative winning out as in many Bavarian dialects. This observation may well account for some of the above. If (44a) were from a speaker of Swiss German, for example, we could immediately trace the example&apos;s grammaticality to the Swiss dialect situation. In actual fact, the sentence is from Schiller, so the question remains open. Similarly, (44b) is a case of dative&ndash;accusative confusion, which may possibly be traced to dialectal factors. (44c) is from Goethe and, to the present-day ear, completely impossible. In his discussion of such examples, <link rid="b14">Paul (1920</link>: IV, &sect;411) repeatedly points out that such examples are rare, archaic, marked, and not part of present-day German (his grammar came out in 1920).</p>
<p>The second point that needs to be made here concerns the difficulty that arises from such examples for an approach in which the <i>wh</i>-phrase is a constituent &lsquo;shared&rsquo; by the matrix and by the FR. If one wants to maintain such an analysis, some way must be found to account for the asymmetry between the upstairs and downstairs environment in terms of their impact on case checking. In all three of the examples cited, the case of the <i>wh</i>-word is that imposed within the FR. And indeed, <link rid="b14">Paul (1920</link>) notes that this is the only type of deviation from matching found in New High German. One way of looking at this would be to say that case is checked inside the relative clause and that (in certain varieties of German) it need not be checked again in the matrix environment. We will not pursue the details of such an approach here. Note, in fact, that an alternative approach in which the head is occupied by some empty element (say pro) does not fare any better, loosely speaking. On such an approach, the null hypothesis would be to say that we find the same patterns that are found with overt pronominal heads (light-headed relatives). The latter exhibit no matching whatsoever. Hence, we would face the task of explaining why much tighter restrictions on the agreement relation between the pronominal head and the <i>wh-</i>phrase of the FR come into play when the pronominal head is an empty category. The reader is referred to <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) for an account along such lines.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="3">
<heading id="h11" level="3">4.2.3 Case syncretism</heading>
<p>It is a well-known fact that in case paradigms of a certain complexity, syncretism may be found. That is, a certain morphological case form may be used for two or even more abstract case features. Take the simplex question words in German. These constitute the following paradigm:</p>
<object id="tu37" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu37_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>Masc./Fem.</entry>
<entry>Neuter</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Nominative</entry>
<entry><i>wer</i>
</entry>
<entry><i>was</i>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Genitive</entry>
<entry><i>wessen</i>
</entry>
<entry><i>wessen</i>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Dative</entry>
<entry><i>wem</i>
</entry>
<entry>&mdash;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Accusative</entry>
<entry><i>wen</i>
</entry>
<entry><i>was</i>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>This table shows that there is syncretism in two respects: the genitive forms syncretize for gender: same form for masc./fem. and for neuter, while the nominative and the accusative forms are identical in the neuter.</p>
<p>If we wish to test, now, whether case matching is affected by syncretism, we must immediately conclude that the genitive syncretism (<i>wessen</i>) cannot be tested because the gender switch cannot be tolerated or forced. That is, in an example like (45) it is impossible to force an interpretation in which <i>wessen</i> is taken to be, say, feminine in the matrix but neuter in the FR:</p>
<p>(45)&ensp;<object id="tu38" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu38_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>bediene</entry>
<entry>mich</entry>
<entry>wessen</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>dich</entry>
<entry>erinnerst.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>avail</entry>
<entry>myself</entry>
<entry>whose</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>refl.</entry>
<entry>remember</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I avail myself of who you remember.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Due to the identity required between the head of the relative clause and the relative pronoun, here conflated into one word, the genitive object of <i>sich bedienen</i> could never be taken to be a feminine noun, while at the same time the genitive object of <i>sich erinnern</i> is interpreted as a neuter noun.</p>
<p>Turning to the second instance of syncretism, the test can be successfully constructed. Take the following two fully matching examples:</p>
<p>(46)&ensp;<object id="tu39" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu39_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Was</entry>
<entry>im</entry>
<entry>K&uuml;hlschrank</entry>
<entry>liegt</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>schimmlig.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what</entry>
<entry>in-the</entry>
<entry>refrigerator</entry>
<entry>lies</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>moldy</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col6">&lsquo;What is in the refrigerator is moldy.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(47)&ensp;<object id="tu40" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu40_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Ich</entry>
<entry>esse</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>gekocht</entry>
<entry>hast.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>eat</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>cooked</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col6">&lsquo;I eat what you cooked.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (46) <i>was</i> is a nominative subject both in the matrix and in the FR, while in (47) <i>was</i> is an accusative object both in the matrix and in the FR. Consider now, however, what happens when we invert the FRs with respect to the two matrix contexts:</p>
<p>(48)&ensp;Was du gekocht hast ist schimmlig.</p>
<p>(49)&ensp;Ich esse was im K&uuml;hlschrank liegt.</p>
<p>Both examples are fully grammatical despite the fact that in abstract case feature terms we have a non-matching combination: matrix nominative &plus; FR-accusative in (48), and matrix accusative &plus; FR-nominative in (49). We must conclude that the case-matching effect is concerned with the actual morpho-phonological shape of the case form in question, not with the abstract case features that it represents in a specific syntactic context.</p>
<p>With this in mind, let us go back to the main choices listed in (9):</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu41" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu41_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP </sub>CP&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> DP CP&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>One way of characterizing the difference between these two analyses is to say that in (9a) the <i>wh</i>-element in Spec, CP is &lsquo;shared&rsquo; between the relative clause structure and the containing matrix structure, while in (9b) the DP-head is part of the matrix and the Spec, CP is part of the relative clause, the relation between the two being mediated by agreement. Accordingly, we may call the former hypothesis the Shared Structure Hypothesis (SSH) and the latter the Distributed Structure Hypothesis (DSH). The case syncretism phenomena just discussed have considerable relevance for the choice between the SSH and the DSH. On the DSH one would not expect the actual morpho-phonological shape of the <i>wh</i>-word to play any role, since agreement processes such as those found between the head of a relative clause and the <i>wh</i>-word of the relative clause are in terms of features, not in terms of phonetic identity. Agreement as we understand it works in terms of morphosemantic features, not in terms of phonetics.<link rid="fn16">
<sup>16</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss13" level="3">
<heading id="h12" level="3">4.2.4 Case attraction</heading>
<p>If case matching is the norm, then the richer a case system, the poorer the options for FRs. In other words, if a language has <i>n</i> cases, there are <i>n</i><sup>2</sup> possible combinations out of which only <i>n</i> yield a grammatical output (modulo syncretism). Again, this is not tragic, since a light-headed relative clause construction can always be chosen to avoid the case-matching restriction. But actually there is another way in which languages can, sometimes, escape this case-matching restriction: case attraction. Consider again the examples discussed under the heading &lsquo;case mismatches&rsquo; in (44). In these examples, the case of the <i>wh</i>-word is the case imposed within the relative clause. But sometimes the case required by the matrix context is, as it were, superimposed on the <i>wh</i>-word. This is a pattern found in Classical Greek, as shown in <link rid="b15">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1976a</link>), whose data have been amply used in the later literature. Consider the following:<link rid="fn17">
<sup>17</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(50)&ensp;<object id="tu42" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu42_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Deitai</entry>
<entry>sou</entry>
<entry>touton</entry>
<entry>ekpiein</entry>
<entry>sun</entry>
<entry>hois<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>malista</entry>
<entry>phileis.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>he-requests</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>this</entry>
<entry>to-drink</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>best</entry>
<entry>you-love</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;He requests you to drink this (sc. wine) with (those) who you love best.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Deitai sou touton ekpiein</entry>
<entry>sun</entry>
<entry>toutois<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>hous<sub>acc</sub> malista phileis.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;<object id="tu43" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu43_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Par&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>h&ocirc;n<sub>gen</sub>
</entry>
<entry>bo&ecirc;theis</entry>
<entry>ouch</entry>
<entry>apoleipsei</entry>
<entry>charin.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>from</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>you-help</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>you-get</entry>
<entry>help</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;From who you help you get no help.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Par&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>ekein&ocirc;n<sub>gen</sub>
</entry>
<entry>hois<sub>dat</sub> bo&ecirc;theis ouch apoleipsei charin.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>from</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The b-examples show the corresponding light-headed relative with the distributed case forms. As the a-examples show, the matrix case wins: in (50a) the FR-accusative is superseded by the matrix dative, and in (51a) the FR-dative is superseded by the matrix genitive. The way this is generally expressed is to say that the case of the relative pronoun is attracted to the case of the matrix (the head). From this perspective, we might be tempted to reinterpret the mismatches discussed in <link rid="ss11">section 4.2.2</link> as constituting the direct counterpart of the attraction cases in (50) and (51). We might then say that in cases like (50) and (51) attraction is downward, while in the cases shown in <link rid="ss11">section 4.2.2</link>. attraction is inverse or upward. By this we mean that the matrix case is imposed (attracted) in a downward direction to the <i>wh</i>-element in the FR, or transmitted (attracted) upward from the FR into the matrix context.</p>
<p>If we try to interpret these phenomena from the point of view of the two main hypotheses that we are comparing, the Shared Structure Hypothesis (SSH) and the Distributed Structure Hypothesis (DSH), a certain amount of stipulation seems to be required on both views. On an SSH view, we have to say that two independent structures are glued together in the shared element, but that these two structures are not equivalent: one is dominant and the other is recessive. This is feasible, and comparable phenomena can be found in other areas of grammar, for example case attraction under long <i>wh</i>-movement in Hungarian. On the alternative DSH view, we have to say that the agreement process applying between the (empty) head and the <i>wh</i>-element in the FR sometimes does not require full identity of cases but that sometimes the head wins, sometimes the <i>wh</i>-element.</p>
<p>It must be recognized, however, that the latter view (the DSH) receives considerable support from the fact that the attraction phenomena just shown are also attested in headed relative clauses. Downward attraction is attested in the following example from Classical Greek, where the b-example shows what the unattracted version would be:<link rid="fn18">
<sup>18</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(52)&ensp;<object id="tu44" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu44_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Phoboimen an</entry>
<entry>t&ocirc;i</entry>
<entry>hegemoni<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>h&ocirc;i<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>doi&ecirc;</entry>
<entry>hepesthai.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I-should-fear</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>leader</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>he-might-give</entry>
<entry>to-follow</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;I should fear to follow the leader whom he might give.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">Phoboimen an &lsqb;t&ocirc;i hegemoni<sub>dat</sub> &lsqb;hon<sub>acc</sub> doi&ecirc;&rsqb;&rsqb; hepesthai.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Upward attraction, though reported to be rarer in Classical Greek, is also found:</p>
<p>(53)&ensp;<object id="tu45" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu45_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="14">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="14" colname="col14"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>T&ecirc;n</entry>
<entry>ousian<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>h&ecirc;n<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>katelipe</entry>
<entry>ou</entry>
<entry>pleionos</entry>
<entry>aksia<sub>nom</sub>
</entry>
<entry>estin</entry>
<entry>&ecirc;</entry>
<entry>tettar&ocirc;n</entry>
<entry>kai</entry>
<entry>deka</entry>
<entry>talant&ocirc;n.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>estate</entry>
<entry>which</entry>
<entry>he-left</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>more</entry>
<entry>worth</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>than</entry>
<entry>four</entry>
<entry>and</entry>
<entry>ten</entry>
<entry>talents</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col14">&lsquo;The estate which he left is not worth more than fourteen talents.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col14">H&ecirc; ousia<sub>nom</sub> h&ecirc;n<sub>acc</sub> katelipe ou pleionos aksia<sub>nom</sub> estin &ecirc; tettar&ocirc;n kai deka talant&ocirc;n.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similar examples of upward attraction are also found in Latin:<link rid="fn19">
<sup>19</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(54)&ensp;<object id="tu46" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu46_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Naucratem<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>quem<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>convenire</entry>
<entry>volui</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>navi</entry>
<entry>non</entry>
<entry>erat.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Naucrates</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>join</entry>
<entry>I-wanted</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>ship</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Naucrates, whom I wanted to join, was not on the ship.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">Naucrates<sub>nom</sub> quem<sub>acc</sub> convenire volui in navi non erat.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Upward attraction appears to be rather exceptional (cf. note 18) but downward attraction is frequent enough to permit some generalizations. In particular, it appears that the more marked case must win. In other words, if the matrix case is, say, a dative and the case on the <i>wh-</i>word is a nominative, then downward attraction is possible, but not vice versa. <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>: 108) formulates the case hierarchy as follows:</p>
<p>(55)&ensp;NOM &lt; ACC &lt; DAT &lt; GEN &lt;&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lt; P-CASE</p>
<p>Here, P-Case can be extended to various highly oblique cases in richly case-marking languages. The idea is that a case lower on the hierarchy can replace a case higher on the hierarchy under downward attraction, but not the other way around. As <link rid="b15">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1976a</link>) notes, however, there may be asymmetries within one language. In particular, he notes, in Classical Greek<link rid="fn20">
<sup>20</sup></link> attraction is more liberal in FRs than in headed relative clauses. In his formulation, an accusative may be attracted to a genitive or dative in headed relatives, but in FRs, neuter nominatives, accusatives, and datives may be attracted to datives or genitives.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss14" level="1">
<heading id="h13" level="1">5 Types of free relatives</heading>
<subsection id="ss15" level="2">
<heading id="h14" level="2">5.1 Questions vs. free relatives</heading>
<p>Since FRs are clauses with an initial <i>wh</i>-word, they look like questions. As was pointed out in the introduction (examples (5) ff.), FRs can generally be distinguished from questions without any problems since they differ in their subcategorizational properties. Nevertheless, when an FR occurs in a non-subcategorized position, say as an adjunct, then the distinction tends to be blurred. Consider:</p>
<p>(56)&ensp;<i>Whatever Bill says</i>, it always comes out wrong.</p>
<p>Is the italicized part of this example a question or an FR? Subcategorization is not a factor here. The presence of -<i>ever</i> would seem to suggest that this is an FR, since embedded <i>wh</i>-questions do not take -<i>ever</i>. On the other hand, a close paraphrase of (56) has <i>no matter</i> prefixed to the <i>wh-</i>word, which is generally impossible in argument FRs:</p>
<p>(57)&ensp;<object id="tu47" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu47_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>No matter what Bill says, it always comes out wrong.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><sup>?</sup>*This dog attacks no matter who crosses its path.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Furthermore, <i>whether</i> can occur in this type of clause, and <i>whether</i> is normally limited to questions and excluded in FRs:</p>
<p>(58)&ensp;(No matter) whether Carl talks or not, he will be convicted.</p>
<p>Semantically, such subordinate clauses appear to be a special subtype of concessive clauses, which does not help much if we try to determine whether they are questions or FRs.</p>
<p>There are, indeed, a number of other indications that FRs are closer to questions than headed relative clauses are. Consider first the fact that adjunct clauses like the ones above can sometimes contain multiple <i>wh-</i>phrases:</p>
<p>(59)&ensp;<object id="tu48" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu48_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Whichever CD you buy in whatever store, you always pay too much.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*This dog attacks whoever crosses whatever street.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*a person who crosses what street.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Who crossed what street?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As these examples show, there are multiple questions (59d) but no multiple relative clauses (59c), but multiple <i>wh</i>-phrases in the concessive clauses under consideration are possible.<link rid="fn21">
<sup>21</sup></link>
</p>
<p>More generally, a second indication that FRs are closer to questions than headed relatives comes from the choice of pronoun that we find in them. In some languages such as German, questions are constructed by means of <i>w</i>-words, while headed relatives clauses make use of <i>d</i>-words (demonstrative pronouns):</p>
<p>(60)&ensp;<object id="tu49" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu49_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>fragte</entry>
<entry>wen</entry>
<entry>ich</entry>
<entry>vorziehe.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>asked</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>prefer</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;Peter asked whom I prefer.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>hasst</entry>
<entry>den</entry>
<entry>Mann</entry>
<entry>den</entry>
<entry>ich</entry>
<entry>vorziehe.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>hates</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>man</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>prefer</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Peter hates the man whom I prefer.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>hasst</entry>
<entry>wen</entry>
<entry>ich</entry>
<entry>vorziehe.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>hates</entry>
<entry>whom(ever)</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>prefer</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;Peter hates whomever I prefer.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As (60c) shows, FRs pattern like questions and not like headed relative clauses in that they uniformly take <i>w</i>-words.</p>
<p>In German, what is at stake is essentially a morphological choice,<link rid="fn22">
<sup>22</sup></link> but there are languages in which the syntax of relative clauses and questions is more radically different. This is the case, for example, in Swiss German. Swiss German forms relative clauses by means of an invariable complementizer element <i>wo</i> and a resumptive personal pronoun in situ, which is sometimes deleted (cf. Van <link rid="b16">Riemsdijk 1989b</link>). Questions, on the other hand, are formed by means of <i>w</i>-phrases that are moved to the front of the clause in the same way as in English or Standard German. Again, we find that FRs pattern with questions in this respect:</p>
<p>(61)&ensp;<object id="tu50" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu50_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>De</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>wet</entry>
<entry>w&uuml;sse</entry>
<entry>mit</entry>
<entry>wem</entry>
<entry>s</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>redet.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>wants</entry>
<entry>know</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>talks</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;Peter wants to know with whom Susi talks&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="13">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>De</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>redet</entry>
<entry>mit</entry>
<entry>em</entry>
<entry>maa</entry>
<entry>wo</entry>
<entry>s</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>mit</entry>
<entry>em</entry>
<entry>redet.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>talks</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>man</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>him</entry>
<entry>talks</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col13">&lsquo;Peter talks with the man that Susi talks with.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>De</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>redet</entry>
<entry>mit</entry>
<entry>wem</entry>
<entry>s</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>redet.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
<entry>talks</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>Susi</entry>
<entry>talks</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Peter talks with whoever Susi talks.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In conclusion, there is a variety of phenomena that suggest that FRs as a construction occupy a position somewhat intermediary between questions and (headed) relative clauses.<link rid="fn23">
<sup>23</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="2">
<heading id="h15" level="2">5.2 The interpretation of free relatives</heading>
<p>The main distinction among different types of headed relatives that comes to mind is the one between restrictive relatives on the one hand and non-restrictive or appositive relatives on the other. But this distinction is not helpful in coming to grips with the essential semantics of FRs.<link rid="fn24">
<sup>24</sup></link> It is more helpful to contemplate what types of (pronominal) heads we use when we paraphrase FRs. Consider the following examples with their paraphrases:</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;<object id="tu51" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu51_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I ate what the waiter put on my plate.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I ate the thing that the waiter put on my plate.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(63)&ensp;<object id="tu52" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu52_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I will eat whatever the waiter will put on my plate.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I will eat anything/everything that the waiter will put on my plate.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It appears, then, that there are two main subtypes of FRs, definite FRs and universally quantified FRs. Note that the addition of -<i>ever</i> to the <i>wh</i>-word tends to disambiguate potentially ambiguous examples, since -<i>ever</i> pretty much forces the universally quantified reading. The opposite is not true, however. <i>Wh</i>-words without the suffix -<i>ever</i> can nevertheless have universal force, as in:</p>
<p>(64)&ensp;I will eat what happens to be on the menu.</p>
<p>On closer inspection, in fact, even an example like (62a) can be interpreted with universal force: at that time my condition was such that I would eat whatever the waiter put on my plate. Furthermore, as the two alternatives in (63b) show (everything vs. anything), there is some question as to the precise nature of the type of universal quantification that is involved. By (63a) we mean either that I will eat all the food items that the waiter puts on my plate, or that I will eat any item from a larger set of items that the waiter chooses to put on my plate. The latter interpretation is often referred to as &lsquo;free choice <i>any</i>&rsquo;. This observation also leads us to re-evaluate the above statement that -<i>ever</i> forces the universally quantified meaning, since a <i>wh-ever</i> FR sometimes also has a meaning that comes close to that of a definite noun phrase, but one that the speaker of the sentence is not able to identify at the point of speaking. This is illustrated in (65):<link rid="fn25">
<sup>25</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(65)&ensp;Everyone who went to whatever movie the Avon is now showing said it was very boring.</p>
<p>As noted in <link rid="b17">Jacobson (1995</link>), this differentiates such an FR from truly universally quantified noun phrases, since the latter cannot be referred to by <i>it</i>:</p>
<p>(66)&ensp;*Everyone who went to every movie the Avon is now showing said it was very boring.</p>
<p>The observation that the two subtypes of FRs are, at least sometimes, quite close to each other invites the question as to whether it is possible to unify the two. <link rid="b17">Jacobson (1995</link>), which the following account paraphrases closely, suggests that this can be done by means of the notion of a maximal plural entity. It is important that the term <i>plural</i> is used in a broad way here: if in a given domain there is only one atomic individual with a given property, then the maximal plural entity with that property is the one consisting of just this atomic individual. We may then assume that an FR like <i>what Mary recommended</i> denotes the set of maximal plural entities that Mary recommended (rather than any set of individuals that Mary recommended). Given the fact that this set may be limited to a single atomic entity, we now have an account for the fact that FRs at times seem to be singular definites and at times universals: we always have a singleton set. If there is only a single entity that Mary recommended, then the FR will be equivalent to a singular definite. And if there is more than one entity, then the FR will denote the single entity composed of all entities that Mary recommended, which amounts to a universal interpretation.<link rid="fn26">
<sup>26</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss17" level="2">
<heading id="h16" level="2">5.3 Transparent free relatives</heading>
<p>Intuitively speaking, we may say that the <i>wh</i>-element in a FR constitutes the link between the relative clause CP and the containing matrix structure. This is true regardless of whether this link is mediated by some empty pro-head or by anything else. There is, however, a very special type of free relative in which the initial <i>wh</i>-element (always <i>what</i>) is almost like a dummy element, while the relative clause contains a small-clause predicate that has most of the properties of the pivotal element, the element that provides the link between the relative clause CP and the matrix structure. Without prejudice to the formal analysis of such free relatives, which will be discussed in <link rid="ss18">section 6</link>, I will call this pivotal or link element the &lsquo;shared element&rsquo; or &lsquo;shared structure&rsquo;. This type of relative clause, which has been dubbed &lsquo;transparent free relative&rsquo; (TFR) by <link rid="b18">Wilder (1999</link>), can be exemplified by (67):<link rid="fn27">
<sup>27</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(67)&ensp;<i>What appeared to be <b>a jet airliner</b>
</i> had landed on the freeway.</p>
<p>The TFR is in italics, and the boldfaced noun phrase is the shared constituent. TFRs are different from regular FRs in a variety of ways, and most of the differences have to do with the presence of a shared element that is distinct from the <i>wh</i>-element. The following is a succinct list of such properties:<link rid="fn28">
<sup>28</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<b>Indefinites allowed.</b> FRs are either definite or universal (cf. <link rid="ss16">section 5.2</link>), but an indefinite predicate nominal expression can turn a TFR into an indefinite. (67) does not mean &lsquo;the thing that looked like a jet&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rsquo; but rather &lsquo;something that looked like a jet&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&rsquo; or even, more directly, &lsquo;a jet airliner had landed on the freeway&rsquo;. That this is so is demonstrated further by the fact that TFRs are permitted in contexts that are diagnostic for indefinites, such as <i>there</i>-insertion constructions:</p>
<p>(68)&ensp;<object id="tu53" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu53_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>There was a jet on the freeway.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*There was the jet on the freeway.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*There was what had incurred extensive engine failure on the freeway.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>There was what appeared to be a jet on the freeway.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;<b>Intensional modifier.</b> The meaning of the TFR minus the shared constituent is that of a hedge or an intensional modifier. In that sense, the TFR is similar to that of adjectives like <i>alleged</i>:</p>
<p>(69)&ensp;<object id="tu54" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu54_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>They served me what they euphemistically referred to as a steak.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>They served me an alleged steak.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Both (69a) and (69b) leave open the possibility that the entity in question is not what the noun says it is. That is, in both cases this entity may well not be a steak.</p>
<p>(iii)&ensp;*<b>-<i>ever</i>.</b> As is to be expected on the basis of property (i), -ever cannot be suffixed to the wh-element in a TFR:</p>
<p>(70)&ensp;*There was whatever appeared to be a jet on the freeway.</p>
<p>(iv)&ensp;<b>Plural agreement.</b> When used as a subject, the <i>what</i> of a TFR can trigger plural agreement on the verb, which it can never do in regular FRs:</p>
<p>(71)&ensp;<object id="tu55" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu55_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>What *seems/seem to be several jets *was/were landing on the freeway.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>What pleases/*please me most adorns/*adorn the living room wall.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(v)&ensp;<b>Reference to &lsqb;&plus;human&rsqb;</b>. In TFRs, <i>what</i> can refer to humans, which is impossible in regular FRs:</p>
<p>(72)&ensp;<object id="tu56" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu56_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>She invited what I took to be a policeman to stay overnight.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*She invited what was carrying a baton and a gun to stay overnight.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(vi)&ensp;<b>No island sensitivity under extraction.</b> Extraction, for example by <i>wh</i>-movement, out of some constituent contained in a headed relative or a FR is prohibited by island constraints (specifically, the Complex Noun Phrase Constraint subsumed under Bounding Theory). However, extraction out of a TFR is acceptable or only weakly deviant:<link rid="fn29">
<sup>29</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(73)&ensp;<object id="tu57" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu57_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Who did you order a picture that represented the sole possession of?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Who did you order what represented the sole possession of?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Who did you order what was advertised as a first-rate picture of?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(vii)&ensp;<b>Conjunction of (un-)likes.</b> As is well known, only constituents of identical categorial status can be conjoined under coordinate conjunction. Consider now a TFR with a predicate adjective. If we interpret such a relative clause from the point of view of a regular FR, the categorial status will be determined by the <i>wh</i>-word (<i>what</i>); that is, it will count as a noun phrase. But if the predicative adjective determines the categorial status, the clause will have the distributional properties of an AP. With this in mind, consider (74):</p>
<p>(74)&ensp;<object id="tu58" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu58_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*He dislikes trains and what I consider inconvenient.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>He dislikes trains and what I consider an equally inconvenient alternative.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>He dislikes trains and what the government proposes to replace them with.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(74a, b) are TFRs, while (74c) is a regular FR. On the assumption that it is the predicate that counts, (74b) is OK since two noun phrases are conjoined, while (74a) is ungrammatical because an NP is conjoined with an AP. Note, in fact, that (74a) can, with some difficulty, be interpreted as a regular FR: he dislikes trains and anything that I consider inconvenient. While such a reading may not be the most plausible one, (74a) is grammatical on that reading. There is a complication here, however. The verb <i>dislike</i> subcategorizes NPs and not APs. Hence, on the TFR-reading, (74a) is ungrammatical regardless of conjunction of unlikes because it includes the substatement *<i>he dislikes inconvenient</i>. This is important in its own right, of course, but the full force of the &lsquo;conjunction of unlikes&rsquo; argument can be seen in an example like the following:</p>
<p>(75)&ensp;<object id="tu59" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu59_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*The creature changed from a frog and slimy into a prince and radiant.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The creature changed from a frog and what can only be termed slimy into a prince and what truly deserves to be called radiant.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>The creature changed from a frog and a slimy abomination into a prince and a prospective lover.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>The creature changed from a frog and what can only be termed a slimy abomination into a prince and what truly deserves to be called a prospective lover.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(viii)&ensp;<b>Idiom chunks.</b> The small-clause predicate in the TFR can be an idiom chunk that is part of a matrix idiom expression:</p>
<p>(76)&ensp;<object id="tu60" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu60_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Nick<sub>i</sub> lost what according to the dictionary are called his<sub>i</sub> marbles.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>(*)Nick<sub>i</sub> lost what his<sub>i</sub> marbles cost in the store.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Note that (76b) is in principle grammatical as a regular FR, but the idiomatic reading disappears completely.</p>
<p>(ix)&ensp;<b>Bound anaphors.</b> Similarly, bound anaphors that are part of the small-clause predicate can be bound by an antecedent in the matrix structure, which is impossible in regular FRs:</p>
<p>(77)&ensp;<object id="tu61" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu61_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>They<sub>i</sub> live in what is often referred to as each other&apos;s<sub>i</sub> backyard.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*They<sub>i</sub> live in what Fred uses each other&apos;s<sub>i</sub> backyard for.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(x)&ensp;<b>Case matching.</b> While in regular FRs it is the wh-word/phrase that is subject to case-matching requirements (cf. <link rid="ss9">section 4.2</link>), in TFRs it is the predicate nominal in the small clause that is subject to such a restriction. Predicate nominals only occur in the nominative and in the accusative, hence dative and genitive play no role here:</p>
<p>(78)&ensp;<object id="tu62" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu62_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="12">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Gestern</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>als</entry>
<entry>ein<sub>nom</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Meteorit</entry>
<entry>identifiziert</entry>
<entry>wurde<sup>nom</sup>
</entry>
<entry>bei</entry>
<entry>uns</entry>
<entry>eingeschlagen<sup>nom</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>yesterday</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>as</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>meteorite</entry>
<entry>identified</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>near</entry>
<entry>us</entry>
<entry>struck</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col12">&lsquo;Yesterday, what was identified as a meteorite struck at our place.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="12">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Gestern</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>Experten</entry>
<entry>als</entry>
<entry>
<formula id="mu1" format="inline">
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_mu1.gif" type="gif"/>
</formula>
</entry>
<entry>identifiziert</entry>
<entry>haben<sup>acc</sup>
</entry>
<entry>bei</entry>
<entry>uns</entry>
<entry>eingeschlagen<sup>nom</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>yesterday</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>experts</entry>
<entry>as</entry>
<entry> a &thinsp;&thinsp;meteorite</entry>
<entry>identified</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>near</entry>
<entry>us</entry>
<entry>struck</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col12">&lsquo;Yesterday, what experts identified as a meteorite struck at our place.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Wir</entry>
<entry>haben</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>als</entry>
<entry>
<formula id="mu2" format="inline">
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_mu2.gif" type="gif"/>
</formula>
</entry>
<entry>identifiziert</entry>
<entry>wurde<sup>nom</sup>
</entry>
<entry>gesehen<sup>acc</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>we</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>as</entry>
<entry> &thinsp;a &thinsp;meteorite</entry>
<entry>identified</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;We have seen what was identified as a meteorite.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>Wir</entry>
<entry>haben</entry>
<entry>was</entry>
<entry>Experten</entry>
<entry>als</entry>
<entry>einen<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Meteoriten<sub>acc</sub>
</entry>
<entry>identifiziert</entry>
<entry>haben<sup>acc</sup>
</entry>
<entry>gesehen<sup>acc</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>we</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>experts</entry>
<entry>as</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>meteorite</entry>
<entry>identified</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">&lsquo;We have seen what experts identified as a meteorite.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(79)&ensp;<object id="tu63" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu63_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Gestern ist was als eine<sub>nom</sub> Sternschnuppe identifiziert wurde<sup>nom</sup> bei uns eingeschlagen<sup>nom</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Gestern ist was Experten als eine<sub>nom/acc</sub> Sternschnuppe identifiziert haben<sup>acc</sup> bei uns eingeschlagen<sup>nom</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Wir haben was als eine<sub>nom/acc</sub> Sternschnuppe identifiziert wurde<sup>nom</sup> gesehen<sup>acc</sup>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Wir haben was Experten als eine<sub>acc</sub> Sternschnuppe identifiziert haben<sup>acc</sup> gesehen<sup>acc</sup>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (78a, d) the matrix and the TFR case requirements (both indicated by superscripts on the verbal complex) are identical. Hence, matching is satisfied. In (78b, c) we have conflicting requirements. No matter what case we have on the predicate nominal, the result is degraded. There does seem to be a contrast, however in that the TFR requirement is absolute, while non-matching in the matrix yields only mild deviance.<link rid="fn30">
<sup>30</sup></link> (79) contrasts minimally with (78) in that the masculine noun <i>Meteorit</i> has been replaced by the feminine noun <i>Sternschnuppe</i>. In the feminine paradigm, there is no distinction between the nominative and the accusative forms. In other words, we have case syncretism. As observed before for regular FRs, syncretism resolves the case conflict, and hence we have a grammatical result for all examples.</p>
<p>(xi)&ensp;<b>Inflection.</b> The predicate constituent in the TFR sometimes inflects as if it were part of the matrix rather than part of the relative clause. A straightforward case of this phenomenon is found with adjectives in Dutch. Predicate adjectives in Dutch are uninflected, but attributive adjectives must be inflected. Roughly speaking the rule is that an attributive adjective must be inflected by the suffix -<i>e</i> (&lsqb;<formula id="mu3" format="inline">
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_mu3.gif" type="gif"/>
</formula>&rsqb;) unless the noun it modifies is indefinite neuter singular:</p>
<p>(80)&ensp;<object id="tu64" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu64_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Deze</entry>
<entry>auto</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>duur/*dure.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this</entry>
<entry>car</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>expensive</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col5">&lsquo;This car is expensive.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>een</entry>
<entry>*duur/dure</entry>
<entry>auto</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>an</entry>
<entry>expensive</entry>
<entry>car</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col4">&lsquo;an expensive car&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This pattern shows up in identical fashion in TFRs:<link rid="fn31">
<sup>31</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu65" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu65_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Deze</entry>
<entry>auto</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>wat</entry>
<entry>je</entry>
<entry>duur/*dure</entry>
<entry>zou kunnen</entry>
<entry>noemen.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this</entry>
<entry>car</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>expensive</entry>
<entry>could</entry>
<entry>call</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;This car is what you could call expensive.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>een</entry>
<entry>wat</entry>
<entry>je</entry>
<entry>zou kunnen</entry>
<entry>noemen</entry>
<entry>*duur/dure</entry>
<entry>auto</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>could</entry>
<entry>call</entry>
<entry>expensive</entry>
<entry>car</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;a what you could call expensive car&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>From the point of view of adjectival inflection, then, we may say that the adjective, which is ostensibly inside the relative clause, acts as if it were fully a constituent of the matrix structure. Observe, however, that the adjective must also be a constituent of the relative clause, because otherwise the relative clause is incomplete: &lsqb;<i>what you could call *(expensive)</i>&rsqb;. This then is another simple, straightforward piece of evidence that the small-clause predicate in a TFR is &lsquo;shared&rsquo; between the matrix and the relative clause.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss18" level="1">
<heading id="h17" level="1">6 Matching and the syntactic representation of free relatives</heading>
<p>Matching phenomena are among the most salient properties of FRs (cf. <link rid="ss5">section 4</link>), and accordingly one of the main analytical questions is how these matching phenomena are to be accounted for. Perhaps the most salient issue here is whether the link between the relative clause and the matrix is a direct one or an indirect one. Consider a simple example (cf. (4)):</p>
<p>(82)&ensp;You should return <i>what you have finished reading</i> to the library.</p>
<p>On the direct approach, the <i>wh</i>-word/phrase of the relative clause is at the same time part of, or at least accessible to, whatever syntactic and semantic requirements the matrix clause imposes, in this case subcategorization of a direct object and accusative case. The alternative is to assume that there is an empty head, which acts as an intermediary between the relative clause and the matrix. As before (cf. <link rid="ss12">section 4.2.3</link>), we may call the former type of analysis the Shared Structure Hypothesis (SSH) and the latter type the Distributed Structure Hypothesis (DSH). On the DSH, the relevant properties of the <i>wh-</i>element (category, case, person, number, etc.) are present as features on the empty head, and it is the empty head which is responsible for any checking or licensing processes that are relevant for the matrix structure. On the SSH, the empty head plays no such role and may well be entirely absent in that the <i>wh-</i>element is directly accessible to any checking or licensing imposed by the matrix. Both hypotheses can be defended and have been defended, as was shown in <link rid="ss4">section 3</link>.</p>
<p>The existence and the properties of TFRs, which were discussed in <link rid="ss17">section 5.3</link>, shed new light on this issue, however. As was shown, it is the small-clause predicate which constitutes the link with the matrix environment, whereas the clause-initial <i>wh</i>-element is, in a sense, a dummy element, which plays no role in the matching process. The question then is whether it is plausible to assume that there could be a relation, a kind of agreement process, between the small-clause predicate and the empty head of the TFR. If we examine again the various properties of TFRs listed in <link rid="ss17">section 5.3</link>, we immediately see that such an indirect approach is quite implausible. Perhaps the single most impressive argument comes from the fact that the small-clause predicate can be inflected like a matrix element, as shown in (81). Without further discussion, we will therefore assume that the SSH is to be preferred for TFRs. Furthermore, given that we have to find a way to implement the SSH, we will also assume that regular FRs are to be accounted for in terms of the SSH.<link rid="fn32">
<sup>32</sup></link> A further extension of the SSH, and of the insights derived from TFRs in particular, is that internally headed relatives may now be directly interpreted as relative clauses in which the internal head is shared with the matrix structure (cf. (1)).<link rid="fn33">
<sup>33</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The implementation of the SSH is far from trivial. In order to see this, consider the case of a TFR with a shared attributive adjective such as the one in (81), repeated here for convenience:</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu66" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu66_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Deze auto is wat je duur/*dure zou kunnen noemen.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>een wat je zou kunnen noemen *duur/dure auto</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The DP in (81b) consists, linearly, of the following constituents:</p>
<p>(83)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> D<sup>o</sup> CP N&rsqb;</p>
<p>But what is missing here is the fact that the noun in (81b) is modified by an attributive adjective. Hence, perhaps the correct way of describing the structure is (84):</p>
<p>(84)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> D<sup>o</sup> CP AP N&rsqb;</p>
<p>But both of these structures are very problematic. First, both assume that full, finite CPs are permissible in the prenominal position, even though in the languages in question (English, Dutch, etc.), regular relative clauses always have to follow the noun. Second, as we have seen, there is an AP missing in (83), whereas in (84) the AP, that is, the small-clause predicate in the TFR, is missing inside the CP, which is therefore incomplete and should be as ungrammatical as, say, <i>*a man whom Mary described as</i>.<link rid="fn34">
<sup>34</sup></link> One way to put this problem is that from the point of view of the DP, the CP should be invisible (except for its AP), whereas from the point of view of TFR (the CP), the AP should not be missing. That is, we have a classical case of conflicting tree structures here, and one way to resolve such conflicts is to assume that, just as in the case of reanalysis, a single string of terminal elements (words) can be associated with more than one tree structure.<link rid="fn35">
<sup>35</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Pursuing this idea, consider the following TFR, adapted from an example by <link rid="b19">Kajita (1977</link>):</p>
<p>(85)&ensp;He carried what the crew took to be a can of gasoline.</p>
<p>Such a TFR could then be represented by the following &lsquo;multidimensional&rsquo; tree structure:</p>
<p>(86)&ensp;<object id="fu3" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_fu3.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu3_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The arguments for such an approach have been explored in Van <link rid="b20 b21 b22">Riemsdijk (1998d, 2000, 2001</link>). In these works, a terminology is also suggested to describe complex tree structures such as (86). For this purpose, the botanical metaphor of &lsquo;grafting&rsquo; has been used. Accordingly, we can call the shared constituent the &lsquo;callus&rsquo;, the host tree is called the &lsquo;stock&rsquo;, while the subtree which is grafted onto the stock is called the &lsquo;graft&rsquo; or the &lsquo;scion&rsquo;. Graphically:</p>
<p>(87)&ensp;<object id="fu4" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_fu4.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu4_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Needless to say, a proposal along such lines is far from unproblematic. First of all, a more formal theory of such representations must be developed. It is believed that a framework such as that presented in <link rid="b23">Moltmann (1992</link>) would be a likely candidate for this task. The formalism which is chosen will then have to form the basis for substantive restrictions on the types of representations that are allowed under such a theory of grafting. Among many other considerations, it is important to recognize that there is an asymmetry between the stock and the scion, in that the former constitutes the matrix structure and the latter the embedded insert. One important aspect of this asymmetry shows up when we consider linearization. Indeed, if we look at a structure like (86), the question immediately arises as to how the conflicting lines of terminals should be linearized: the upper before the lower or vice versa? The answer has to be that the terminal elements constituting the scion are pronounced adjacent to, that is, directly before and after, the callus.</p>
<p>A second aspect that must be taken into account is the fact that matching is sometimes not fully realized. The simple assumption would be that for two syntactic trees to be grafted together by the &lsquo;fusion&rsquo; of two substrings of terminal elements, the terminals in question have to be fully identical. But that is too simple. Consider again, for example, the Dutch example (81). In (81b) we have an apparent mismatch in that the stock (the matrix) requires the inflected form of the attributive adjective (<i>dure</i>), while the scion (the TFR) requires the uninflected form of the predicative adjective (<i>duur</i>). But in this case, we might be able to solve the problem by taking into account the morphological structure. Suppose the relevant part of the stock has a structure something like &lsqb;<sub>DegP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub> <i>duur</i>&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>INFL</sub> <i>-e</i>&rsqb;&rsqb;. We might then say that the predicative adjective in the scion has the structure &lsqb;<sub>DegP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>AP</sub> <i>duur</i>&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>INFL</sub> -&phis;&rsqb;&rsqb; and that the grafting process affects just the AP, not the DegP, leaving the INFL markers in the respective substructures. Needless to say, this would only be possible if one of the two morphological markers is -&phis;. It is unlikely, however, that the cases of imperfect matching in which either the stock or the scion is dominant in imposing its morphology, as discussed in <link rid="ss11">section 4.2.2</link> as well as in connection with example (78) and note 29, can all be accounted for in this manner. It is important to recognize, though, that such cases of imperfect matching require stipulative solutions on the alternative analysis according to the DSH.</p>
<p>But once we have taken the radical step of adopting the grafting approach, it is natural to extend the theory of grafting to regular FRs as well, thereby implementing the Shared Structure Hypothesis for FRs. A simple FR such as (88) will then be represented as in (89):<link rid="fn36">
<sup>36</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(88)&ensp;John ate what Mary cooked.</p>
<p>(89)&ensp;<object id="fu5" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_27_fu5.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu5_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="1">
<heading id="h18" level="1">7 Conclusion</heading>
<p>Free relatives exhibit a considerable number of properties that deserve the attention of syntacticians. The most salient of these is a variety of types of matching phenomena which raise a number of fundamental questions as to whether they have a head at all, and, if they do, what the nature of that head is. Depending on the answer to this question, we may be led to revise the theory of phrase structure in such a way that grafted structures with multiple connected trees such as those discussed in <link rid="ss18">section 6</link> must be permitted to exist.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss20" level="1">
<heading id="h19" level="1">NOTES</heading>
<p>Thanks are due to Alex Grosu and Paul Hirschb&uuml;hler for helpful discussion and suggestions for improvement respectively. My knowledge of and thinking about free relatives has been influenced by literally dozens of colleagues and friends over almost a quarter century now. To all of them I can now only extend a collective thank you.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn1">
<number>1&emsp;</number>Within certain limitations, PPs, CPs, and APs can also be modified by a relative clause, as in:</span>
</p>
<listgroup id="l2" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>They left the books downstairs, which is not the safest place for them to be.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>John wondered whether to trust the FBI, which is a rather stupid thing to ask yourself.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(iii)&ensp;</number>
<p>Bill turned out to be quite intelligent, which is a quality not often found in his family.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Note, however, that these are constructed most easily if the relative clause contains a noun (here: <i>place</i> and <i>quality</i> respectively) which, in a sense, translates the PP or AP into an NP. Furthermore, relative clauses of this kind are always non-restrictive. Free relatives (FRs), on the other hand, can be formed on NP/DP, AP, and PP, though various restrictions apply there as well (see, for example, <link rid="ss5">section 4</link>).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn2">
<number>2&emsp;</number>It should be noted, however, that this is not the only way to construct relative clauses in Japanese. In fact, internally headed relative clauses are rather restricted in their use. See, among many others, <link rid="b24">Kurosawa (2003</link>) for discussion and references.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn3">
<number>3&emsp;</number>In other languages, the embedded position is occupied by a so-called resumptive pronoun, and there is no special pronoun which is moved to a position adjacent to the head of the relative clause (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 55 - Resumption.xml" type="file">chapter 55</externallink></related>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn4">
<number>4&emsp;</number>In actual fact, the distinction between questions and FRs is not quite as unproblematic as the text argument suggests. See <link rid="ss15">section 5.1</link> for more discussion.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn5">
<number>5&emsp;</number>The Head Hypothesis has precursors in <link rid="b25">Bresnan (1973a</link>) and <link rid="b26">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1976b</link>). <link rid="b27">Rooryck (1994b</link>) points out that the term &lsquo;Head Hypothesis&rsquo; is potentially misleading, since it might suggest that the head is a category of type X<sup>o</sup> rather than XP; in the present text we will continue to use the term Head Hypothesis, however.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn6">
<number>6&emsp;</number>The COMP Hypothesis was first introduced in <link rid="b28">Kuroda (1968a</link>). It was also defended in <link rid="b29">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1978</link>) and received further support in <link rid="b27">Rooryck (1994b</link>), and in <link rid="b17">Jacobson (1995</link>) and earlier unpublished materials by the same author cited there. This hypothesis has been adopted most frequently in the current literature.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn7">
<number>7&emsp;</number>If a raising analysis of relative clauses is assumed, this assumption is challenged.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn8">
<number>8&emsp;</number>The examples are taken from <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>: 177). In these examples, genitives have not been included because of the severe limitations on their occurrence in modern German.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn9">
<number>9&emsp;</number>Things are slightly more complex in that it might be better to say that Heavy NP Shift does exist but is limited to stylistically highly marked contexts. The text argument is not affected by this complication, however, since the extraposition of FRs is not stylistically limited in any way.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn10">
<number>10&emsp;</number>It might be objected that (23a) is ungrammatical for independent reasons, namely the fact that the extraposed relative clause lacks a complementizer. That is, (23a) could be ungrammatical for the same reason as (ib) without <i>that</i> is:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu67" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu67_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I&rsquo;ll take the book (that) you gave me into consideration.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I&rsquo;ll take the book into consideration *(that) you gave me.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Note, however, that the argument rests primarily on the grammaticality of (23b), and note furthermore that the obligatory absence of the complementizer in FRs on the HH is a puzzling aspect of that analysis in the first place, as will be discussed in the text directly.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn11">
<number>11&emsp;</number>This was pointed out in <link rid="b3">Groos and Van Riemsdijk (1981</link>). See also <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) for discussion.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn12">
<number>12&emsp;</number>The relevance of this particular consideration in the present context is attributed in <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) to an unpublished talk by Polly Jacobson.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn13">
<number>13&emsp;</number>For a much more differentiated and detailed discussion, see <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn14">
<number>14&emsp;</number>I am using a single question mark here to accommodate the more liberal speakers, but in actual fact many speakers would find &lsquo;?*&rsquo; or even &ldquo;*&rdquo; more appropriate. Furthermore, languages tend to differ considerably with respect to the extent to which such restrictions are imposed. See <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) for an overview of a range of languages including German, Hebrew, French, and Romanian.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn15">
<number>15&emsp;</number>The examples given here are cited in <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>). (44a, c) are taken from <link rid="b14">Paul (1920</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn16">
<number>16&emsp;</number>One might object that the lexical representation of a form like <i>was</i> could be an underspecified feature matrix. Suppose, for example, that nominative and accusative are &lsqb;&ndash;oblique&rsqb; in German, as opposed to genitive and dative. Suppose furthermore that there is a second feature, say &lsqb;accusative&rsqb;, that distinguishes the nominative and the accusative. A form like <i>wer</i> would then be &lsqb;&ndash;obl, &ndash;acc&rsqb;, but <i>was</i> could be underspecified and have the representation &lsqb;&ndash;obl&rsqb;. By non-distinctness, &lsqb;&ndash;obl&rsqb; would satisfy both nominative and accusative contexts. An approach along such lines is questionable, however, for a number of reasons. To mention just one, <i>was</i> must be fully specified for the purposes of subject&ndash;predicate agreement, as shown by the following contrast:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu68" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu68_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Was<sub>nom</sub> ist ein<sub>nom</sub> guter Wagen?</entry>
<entry morerows="1">a&prime;.</entry>
<entry morerows="1">*Was<sub>nom</sub> ist einen<sub>acc</sub> guten Wagen?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what is a good car</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Was<sub>acc</sub> nennst Du ein<sub>nom</sub> guter Wagen?</entry>
<entry morerows="1">b&prime;.</entry>
<entry morerows="1">Was<sub>acc</sub> nennst du einen<sub>acc</sub> guten Wagen?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what call you a good car</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Beyond such considerations, theoretical questions may be asked about the degree of language specificity of the feature systems involved in case morphology, about the compatibility of underspecification with checking and/or assignment approaches to case features, etc. But such considerations are beyond the scope of the present survey.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn17">
<number>17&emsp;</number>The examples from Classical Greek in this section are cited from <link rid="b15">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1976a</link>). The sources he gives are as follows. (50) is X.A.1.9.25, cited from J. Hadley and F. Allen, <i>A Greek Grammar</i>, New York 1912, section 996, a, 2. (51) is Aesch. 2,117, cited from W. Goodwin, <i>A Greek Grammar</i>, Ginn 1892, &sect; 1033. (52) is X.A.1.3.17, cited from H. Smyth, <i>Greek Grammar</i>, Cambridge: Harvard University Press 1956, &sect; 2522, b. And (53) is L.19.14. cited from Goodwin, <i>Greek Grammar</i>, &sect; 1035. The Latin example (54) I have taken from <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>), who cites it from F. Schwyzer, <i>Griechische Grammatik</i>, Munich 1950, section II, 641.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn18">
<number>18&emsp;</number>See note 17.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn19">
<number>19&emsp;</number>See note 17. <link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) also cites some examples from what he calls archaic German, the examples again being taken from Schwyzer, <i>Griechische Grammatik</i>, 16, as well as from H. Paul, <i>Mittelhochdeutsche Grammatik</i>, T&uuml;bingen 1904, &sect; 345. Without going into details, these examples are indicative of the limitations that such cases of upward attraction are subject to. Four of the five cases are correlative in nature, which means that it is the correlative pronoun which occupies the matrix position and has the appropriate, i.e., unattracted, case. The head of the relative clause is correspondingly a kind of left-dislocated noun phrase and much freer to have its case determined by outside forces. Also, in four of the five cases the competing case is the nominative.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn20">
<number>20&emsp;</number>Interestingly, the sensitivity of subject&ndash;predicate agreement noted in note 16 is also found in cases of downward attraction. An instructive example is discussed in <link rid="b30">Quicoli (1972</link>), who took it from <link rid="b31">Andrews (1971</link>). The importance of such examples for the theory of FRs was discovered in <link rid="b15">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1976a</link>). Consider the following example (P.C. 50, a, cited in Smyth, <i>Greek Grammar</i>, 16:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu69" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu69_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>emmenomen</entry>
<entry>hois<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>h&ocirc;molog&ecirc;samen</entry>
<entry>dikaiois<sub>dat</sub> ousi<sub>dat</sub>
</entry>
<entry>&ecirc; ou</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>we abide</entry>
<entry>by- those</entry>
<entry>we-have-agreed</entry>
<entry>just being</entry>
<entry>or not</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;Do we abide by those things which we consider just, or not?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">emmenomen toutois<sub>dat</sub> ha<sub>acc</sub> h&ocirc;molog&ecirc;samen dikaia<sub>acc</sub> onta<sub>acc</sub> &ecirc; ou</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It would appear that any analysis in which the case on the relative pronoun starts out as an accusative and is then attracted to a dative under influence of the matrix structure must be problematic, because subsequent (re)application of case agreement between that <i>wh</i>-element (or its trace) and the predicative modifier will flagrantly violate the strict cycle condition, or what replaces it in more recent syntactic frameworks.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn21">
<number>21&emsp;</number>More generally, as argued in <link rid="b32">Izvorski (2001</link>), such concessive free relative clauses have the status of free adjuncts. Izvorski argues that these should be analyzed as bare CPs, thereby accounting for the possibility of multiple <i>wh</i>-elements, which are absent in other types of FRs. It should be noted here that under an analysis in terms of grafts, as suggested in <link rid="ss18">section 6</link>, and in particular in connection with (89), all FRs are considered to be bare CPs. The difference would then be that free adjunct FRs, unlike the other types of FRs, do not have their <i>wh</i>-word grafted onto some XP-position in the matrix clause.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn22">
<number>22&emsp;</number>See <link rid="b33">Wiltschko (1998</link>) for some related discussion.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn23">
<number>23&emsp;</number>There are several other distinctions between headed relative clauses and FRs that deserve to be mentioned. First, the structure of the <i>wh</i>-phrase tends to be more limited in FRs than in headed relatives. For English, such differences are minimal, but in Dutch and German, for example, only simplex <i>w</i>-words can introduce an FR. The following examples are from German:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu70" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu70_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Ich esse</entry>
<entry>was/*welche Speisen</entry>
<entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>mir serviert.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I eat</entry>
<entry>what/whichever dishes</entry>
<entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>me serves</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col4">&lsquo;I eat whatever (dishes) Maria serves me.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>A second remarkable difference concerns the finite vs. infinitival distinction. In many languages, including English, relative clauses can sometimes be infinitival. FRs however, at least in English, cannot be infinitival, as shown by the following contrasts:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;<object id="tu71" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu71_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="3">a.</entry>
<entry>The books that/which you should read are lying on the table.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The books (*that/*which) (for you) to read are lying on the table.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>What/whichever books you should read is/are lying on the table.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*What (for you) to read is lying on the table.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn24">
<number>24&emsp;</number>There is a second distinction that is more or less tangential to our main concern, viz. the distinction between realis FRs and irrealis FRs (cf. <link rid="b34">Grosu and Landman 1998</link>). This distinction is not found in English or any of the other Germanic languages, which only have the normal, realis, type of FR, but it does exist in Romance, Slavic, and Semitic. Irrealis FRs look like normal FRs except that they exhibit an irrealis verb form. (i) is an example from Romanian, example (78b) in <link rid="b34">Grosu and Landman (1998</link>):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu72" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu72_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Nu mai</entry>
<entry>avem</entry>
<entry>ce locuri moi</entry>
<entry>s&#x01CE;</entry>
<entry>vizit&#x01CE; m.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not more</entry>
<entry>have-we</entry>
<entry>what places new</entry>
<entry>SUBJUNCTIVE</entry>
<entry>visit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col5">&lsquo;There are no longer any places for us to visit.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b1">Grosu (1994</link>) argues that irrealis FRs differ in a number of significant ways from ordinary FRs:</p>
<listgroup id="l3" type="symbol">
<li>
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>There are no matching effects such as those found in regular (realis) FRs; cf. <link rid="ss5">section 4</link>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Unlike realis FRs, irrealis FRs allow multiple <i>wh</i>-phrases (and in this sense the adjunct FRs discussed in <link rid="ss15">section 5.1</link> are perhaps more like irrealis FRs):</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>(ii)&ensp;<object id="tu73" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu73_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Nu mai</entry>
<entry>avem</entry>
<entry>pe cine</entry>
<entry>cu cine</entry>
<entry>&icirc;mperechia.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not more</entry>
<entry>have-we</entry>
<entry>ACC who</entry>
<entry>with who</entry>
<entry>to-match</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col5">&lsquo;We no longer have any pairs to match.&rsquo; (said by an unsuccessful matchmaker)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Note, finally, that the absence of infinitival FRs remarked upon above does not extend to irrealis FRs. This is shown in (ii), and a French example such as (iii) may also be an instance of an irrealis FR:</p>
<p>(iii)&ensp;<object id="tu74" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu74_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Je</entry>
<entry>n&rsquo;ai pas</entry>
<entry>o&ugrave;</entry>
<entry>aller.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>have not</entry>
<entry>where</entry>
<entry>go</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col4">&lsquo;I do not have any place to go to.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn25">
<number>25&emsp;</number>The main references for the semantics of FRs are <link rid="b17">Jacobson (1995</link>) and <link rid="b34">Grosu and Landman (1998</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn26">
<number>26&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b34">Grosu and Landman (1998</link>) build on this proposal and extend it to an overall typology of relative clauses. More specifically, they define a type of relative clause which they call <i>maximalizing relatives</i> and which they show includes degree or amount relatives, free relatives, (certain) internally headed relatives, and correlatives. <link rid="b35 b36">Dayal (1995, 1997</link>) further argues that definite FRs (identity FRs) and universal FRs (free-choice FRs) are both definite, and that -<i>ever</i> contributes a modal dimension to the interpretation of the definite description by ensuring that it denotes a generalized quantifier that includes only those properties that are true of the bearer, regardless of identity.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn27">
<number>27&emsp;</number>The special status of TFRs has apparently first been noticed by <link rid="b37">Nakau (1971</link>). Further discussion can be found in <link rid="b19">Kajita (1977</link>), <link rid="b38">McCawley (1988</link>), <link rid="b39 b18">Wilder (1998, 1999</link>), Van <link rid="b20 b21 b22">Riemsdijk (1998d, 2000, 2001</link>), and <link rid="b40">Grosu (2002</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn28">
<number>28&emsp;</number>Properties (ii) and (vii) are from <link rid="b38">McCawley (1988</link>) and <link rid="b19">Kajita (1977</link>) respectively. Properties (i) and (iii&ndash;vi) are from <link rid="b39 b18">Wilder (1998, 1999</link>), while properties (viii&ndash;xi) are from Van <link rid="b21 b22">Riemsdijk (2000, 2001</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn29">
<number>29&emsp;</number>A similar and in certain ways even more instructive case concerns rightward detachment of PPs out of noun phrases in Dutch, a necessary condition in order for extraction of <i>wh</i>-elements out of such a PP to be possible. In other words, in order for extraction to be possible in (ia), the PP must be detached as in (ib), while extraction in (ic) is prohibited. See Van <link rid="b41">Riemsdijk (1997b</link>) for discussion:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu75" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu75_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Waar</entry>
<entry>heb je</entry>
<entry>de conceptversie</entry>
<entry>(gisteren)</entry>
<entry>___ van</entry>
<entry>afgewezen?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what</entry>
<entry>have you</entry>
<entry>the draft version</entry>
<entry>(yesterday)</entry>
<entry>___ of</entry>
<entry>rejected</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;What did you reject the draft version of?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">wh<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> X&rsqb;&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>PP</sub> e<sub>i</sub> <i>van</i>&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">*wh<sub>i</sub>&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> X &lsqb;<sub>PP</sub> e<sub>i</sub> <i>van</i>&rsqb;&rsqb;<sub>NP</sub>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>If we apply this rightward detachment of the PP to a PP that is part of the predicate nominal in a TFR, it turns out that the landing site of the detached PP must be in the matrix structure in order for extraction to be possible, whereas extraction out of a rightward-detached PP inside the relative clause yields strongly ungrammatical results:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;<object id="tu76" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu76_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Waar</entry>
<entry>heb je</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;wat</entry>
<entry>hij</entry>
<entry>een conceptversie</entry>
<entry>noemde&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>gisteren</entry>
<entry>van</entry>
<entry>afgewezen?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>what</entry>
<entry>have you</entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>a draft</entry>
<entry>called</entry>
<entry>yesterday</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>rejected</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">&lsquo;What did you reject what he called a draft version of?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col10">*Waar heb je &lsqb;wat hij een &lsqb;conceptversie ___ &rsqb; &lsqb;___van&rsqb; noemde&rsqb; afgewezen?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn30">
<number>30&emsp;</number>It is not entirely clear whether this contrast is comparable to the phenomena of imperfect matching observed in <link rid="ss11">section 4.2.2</link>, or whether the contrast is rather an illusion that stems from the fact that the apparent TFR can also be interpreted as a regular FR, in which case the <i>was</i> is the element that trivially (due to nom/acc-syncretism) satisfies the conflicting case requirements.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn31">
<number>31&emsp;</number>Note, incidentally, that the word order within the relative clause is different in the two cases because in (81a) the predicative adjective precedes the verb while in (81b) it follows it. As a matter of fact, in the predicative case (81a) both orders are possible, while in the attributive case only the order V-PRED is possible. There is a simple reason for this contrast. As is the case in many languages, including English, prenominal attributive adjectives must be adjacent to the noun (*<i>the proud of his father boy</i>). German, which, like Dutch, is verb final, lacks this possibility of extraposing the small-clause predicate of the TFR. Consequently, attributive adjectives in German can never be modified by a TFR.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn32">
<number>32&emsp;</number>See <link rid="b40">Grosu (2002</link>) for a defense of the DSH.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn33">
<number>33&emsp;</number>It is interesting to note that the notion of &lsquo;shared elements&rsquo; also plays a central role in the analysis of Japanese (internally and externally) headed relative clauses within the framework of Dynamic Semantics presented in <link rid="b24">Kurosawa (2003</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn34">
<number>34&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b18">Wilder (1999</link>) proposes to adopt (84), but with a second, identical, occurrence of the small-clause predicate inside the CP. Backward deletion then applies to that small-clause predicate. Such an analysis is problematic, however (cf. Van <link rid="b22">Riemsdijk 2001</link>). One of the problems concerns the position of the deletion site. Backward deletion (like Right Node Raising, for example) is subject to the constraint that backward deletion can only apply to right-peripheral elements. But the shared element in TFRs need not be clause-final at all, as is shown among other things by German examples such as (78) and (79).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn35">
<number>35&emsp;</number>In addition to reanalysis (as frequently assumed for pseudo-passives like <i>this must be looked into</i> or <i>John was taken advantage of</i>), there are various other syntactic phenomena of this kind (see <link rid="b42">Lakoff 1974b</link> for an early discussion of such phenomena). A simple example from <link rid="b19">Kajita (1977</link>) illustrates a case which is quite similar to that of TFRs: the <i>far from</i> construction. In examples like (i):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;a far from simple matter</p>
<p><i>simple</i> is the semantic head, and it is also the syntactic head in that it is adjacent to the noun, as required by the general adjacency requirement on attributive adjectives. Nevertheless, if <i>simple</i> is the head, then what could <i>far from</i> be? It is a non-constituent, and it certainly looks as if <i>far</i> takes a PP-complement, as it regularly does, and that the preposition <i>from</i> takes an adjectival complement, as it is known to do. As is argued in Van <link rid="b22">Riemsdijk (2001</link>), this case can also be resolved by means of multiple tree structures being associated with a single string of terminals.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn36">
<number>36&emsp;</number>A proposal for a multidimensional analysis of FRs which is quite similar to the proposal sketched here is <link rid="b43">Citko (1998</link>).</span>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss21" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h20" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Acquaviva</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paolo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Aspetti della Complementazione Frasale. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>University of Pisa</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Alexiadou</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Artemis</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Spyridoula</forenames><x> </x><surname>Varlokosta</surname>
</name><x> (</x>
</namegroup>
<date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntactic and Semantic Properties of Free Relatives</title><x> in </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Modern</forenames><x> </x><surname>Greek.</surname>
</name><x> </x><title type="journal">ZAS Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>5</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">31</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Andrews</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Avery</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1971">1971</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Case Agreement of Predicate Modifiers in Ancient Greek</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">127</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">151</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Auwera</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Johan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup>
<miscellaneoustext> van der (</miscellaneoustext>
<date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Layered Structure and Reference in a Functional Perspective</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Michael</forenames><x> </x><surname>Fortescue</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Harder</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Lars</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kristoffersen</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">329</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">354</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bader</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Thomas</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Zvi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Penner</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Das Complementizer-System der Freien Relative im Berndeutschen unter Ber&uuml;cksichtigung universalgrammatischer Aspekte</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">DET, COMP und INFL: Zur Syntax funktionaler Kategorien und grammatischer Funktionen</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Olsen</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Gisbert</forenames><x> </x><surname>Fanselow</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">137</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">154</page><x>. </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carl<x> </x>L<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="book">English Syntax<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Battye</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Adrian</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives, Pseudo-Free Relatives and the Syntax of CP in Italian</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Rivista di Linguistica</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">219</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">250</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bausewein</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Karin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Haben Kopflose Relativsaetze Tatsaechlich Keine Koepfe?</title>
<miscellaneoustext> In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Strukturen und Merkmale syntaktischer Kategorien</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Gisbert</forenames><x> </x><surname>Fanselow</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Sascha</forenames><x> </x><surname>Felix</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">144</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">158</page><x>. </x><address>Tuebingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Narr</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bonneau</surname><x>, </x><forenames>J.</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Logical Form and an Analysis of the Matching Effect in Free Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">McGill Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">13</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">166</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borgato</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gian<x> </x>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Frase Relative Libere in Tedesco e Italiano</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Parallela 2: Aspetti della Sintassi dell&rsquo;Iitaliano Contemporaneo</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Klaus</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lichem</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Edith</forenames><x> </x><surname>Mara</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Susanne</forenames><x> </x><surname>Knaller</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">75</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">83</page><x>. </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Narr</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Borsley</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives in Polish and English</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Trends in Linguistics: Contrastive Linguistics: Prospects and Problems</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jacek</forenames><x> </x><surname>Fisiak</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">18</page><x>. </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1972">1972</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Theory of Complementation in English Syntax. PhD dissertation, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1973">1973a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Headless Relatives</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher><x>, </x><address>University of Massachusetts</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Jane</forenames><x> </x><surname>Grimshaw</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntax of Free Relatives in English</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>9</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">331</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">391</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Browning</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Margaret</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Null Operator Constructions<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Garland</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bury</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dirk</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Is What You Get What You See?: Matching Effects and the Derivation of Free Relatives. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>University College London</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cann</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ronnie</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Mary</forenames><x> </x><surname>Tait</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Free Relatives Revisited. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>University of Edinburgh</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Carlson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Lauri</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Remarks on the Syntax of Free Relative Clauses. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge</address><x>, </x><publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chila-Markopoulou</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Despina</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Problems of Diachronic Syntax: Free Relatives in Medieval and Modern Greek</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Glossologia</title><x> </x><volume>9/10</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">30</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1973">1973</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Conditions on Transformations</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">A Festschrift for Morris Halle</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Stephen</forenames><x> </x><surname>Anderson</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Paul</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kiparsky</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">232</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">286</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holt, Rinehart, and Winston</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Citko</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Barbara</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">ATB Analysis of Free Relative Clauses</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Papers from the Thirty-fourth Regional Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>M<x>. </x>Catherine</forenames><x> </x><surname>Gruber</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Derrick</forenames><x> </x><surname>Higgins</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Kenneth<x> </x>S<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Olson</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Tamra</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wysocki</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">69</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">81</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Chicago Linguistic Society</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Citko</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Barbara</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Light Headed Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">University of Pennsylvania Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>6/1</volume>
<page type="first">
</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cooper</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Quantification and Syntactic Theory<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Daalder</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Saskia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Over Relatieve Zinnen met Ingesloten Antecedent</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Spektator</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">401</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">407</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dayal</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Veneeta</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Quantification in Correlatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Quantification in Natural Languages</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Emmon</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bach</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eloise</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jelinek</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Angelika</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kratzer</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Barbara<x> </x>H<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Partee</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">179</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">205</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dayal</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Veneeta</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Locality in <roman>Wh</roman>-Quantification: Questions and Relative Clauses in Hindi</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dayal</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Veneeta</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives and <i>Ever</i>: Identity and Free Choice Readings</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of SALT VII</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Aaron</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lawson</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eun</forenames><x> </x><surname>Cho</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">99</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">116</page><x>. </x><address>Ithaca</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Delaveau</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Annie</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pronom Relatif Sans Antecedent et Pronom Interrogatif: La Forme</title><x> </x><title type="journal">Qui<x>. </x>Linx</title><x> </x><volume>16</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">5</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">26</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fassi-Fehri</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Abdelkader</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Comparatives and Free Relatives in Arabic</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Recherches Linguistiques de Vincennes</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">47</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">88</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Gee</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jim</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Notes on Free Relatives</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher><x>, </x><address>Stanford University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Groos</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anneke</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>van</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Riemsdijk</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Matching Effects in Free Relatives: A Parameter of Core Grammar</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Theory of Markedness in Generative Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Adriana</forenames><x> </x><surname>Belletti</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Luciana</forenames><x> </x><surname>Brandi</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Luigi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rizzi</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Pisa</address><x>: </x><publisher>Scuola Normale Superiore</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pied-Piping and the Matching Parameter</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">41</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">58</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Three Studies in Locality and Case<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>London</address><x>: </x><publisher>Routledge</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives with Missing Prepositions in Romanian and Universal Grammar</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Advances in Romanian Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Guglielmo</forenames><x> </x><surname>Cinque</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Giuliana</forenames><x> </x><surname>Giusti</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b11" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Proper Analysis of Missing-P Free Relative Constructions</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>27</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">257</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">293</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Semantic Diversity of Internally-Headed Relative Clauses</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Naturally! A Festschrift for Wolfgang U<x>. </x>Dressler</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Chris</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schaner-Wolles</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>John<x> </x>R<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rennison</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Friedrich</forenames><x> </x><surname>Neubarth</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Turin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Rosenberg and Sellier</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Type Resolution in Relative Constructions &ndash; Part 1: Featural Marking and Dependency Encoding</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Syntax of Relative Clauses<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Artemis</forenames><x> </x><surname>Alexiadou</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Paul</forenames><x> </x><surname>Law</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Andr&eacute;</forenames><x> </x><surname>Meinunger</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Chris</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wilder</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000c</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Type Resolution in Relative Constructions &ndash; Part 2: Competing Restrictive and Maximalizing Construals</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Interface Strategies</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hans</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bennis</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Martin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Everaert</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002</date><x>). </x><title type="document">&lsquo;Transparent&rsquo; Free Relatives as a Special Instance of &lsquo;Standard&rsquo; Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">From NP to DP. Vol. 1: The Syntax and Semantics of Noun Phrases</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Martine</forenames><x> </x><surname>Coene</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Yves</forenames><x> </x><surname>D&rsquo;hulst</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">139</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">178</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<surname>Fred</surname><x> </x><forenames>Landman</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Strange Relatives of the Third Kind</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">125</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">170</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Harbert</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Wayne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Nature of the Matching Parameter</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">237</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">284</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Harbert</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Wayne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Note on Old English Free Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">549</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">553</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Harbert</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Wayne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Gothic Relative Clauses and Syntactic Theory</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">On Germanic Linguistics: Issues and Methods</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Irmengard</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rauch</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Gerald</forenames><x> </x><surname>Carr</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert<x> </x>L<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kyes</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Headed and Headless Free Relative Clauses: A Study in Modern French and Classical Greek</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Les Contraintes sur les R&egrave;gles</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>P.</forenames><x> </x><surname>Barbaud</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><address>Montreal</address><x>: </x><publisher>Universit&eacute; du Qu&eacute;bec &agrave; Montr&eacute;al</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Two Analyses of Free Relatives in French</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 6</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Alan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ford</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>John</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reighard</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Rajendra</forenames><x> </x><surname>Singh</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">137</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">152</page><x>. </x><address>Montreal</address><x>: </x><publisher>Universit&eacute; du Qu&eacute;bec &agrave; Montr&eacute;al</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Syntax and Semantics of <i>Wh</i>-Constructions. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Amherst</address><x>, </x><publisher>University of Massachusetts</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1980">1980</date><x>). </x><title type="document">La Syntaxe des Relatives Independentes</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Linguistique Romane et Linguistique Fran&ccedil;aise: &ndash; Hommages &agrave; Jacques Pohl</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>M.</forenames><x> </x><surname>Dominicy</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>M.</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wilmet</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">115</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">130</page><x>. </x><address>Brussels</address><x>: </x><publisher>Editions de l&rsquo;Universit&eacute; de Bruxelles</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Mar&iacute;a-Luisa</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rivero</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Catalan Restrictive Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>57</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">591</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">625</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Mar&iacute;a-Luisa</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rivero</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Remarks on Free Relatives and Matching Phenomena</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">505</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">520</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Horvath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Julia</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Alexander</forenames><x> </x><surname>Grosu</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Notion &lsquo;Head&rsquo;: Evidence from Free Relatives and Interrogatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Theoretical Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">35</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">64</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Izvorski</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Roumyana</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Non-Matching Effects in Free Relatives and Pro-Drop</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Eastern States Conference on Linguistics &rsquo;95</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Marek</forenames><x> </x><surname>Przezdziecki</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Lindsay</forenames><x> </x><surname>Whaley</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Ithaca</address><x>: </x><publisher>CLC Publications</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Izvorski</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Roumyana</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997c</date><x>)</x><x>. </x><address>Subject Free Relatives in Null-Subject Languages</address><x>: </x><publisher>Evidence from Slavic</publisher><x>.</x><miscellaneoustext> In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Approaches to Slavic Linguistics: The Cornell Meeting</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Wayles</forenames><x> </x><surname>Browne</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Ewa</forenames><x> </x><surname>Dornisch</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Natash</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kondrashova</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Draga</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zec</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">267</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">288</page><x>. </x><publisher>Ann Arbor, Mich</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Izvorski</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Roumyana</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2001">2001</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Adjunct Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Nineteenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Roger</forenames><x> </x><surname>Billerey</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Brook</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lillehaugen</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">232</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">245</page><x>. </x><address>Somerville</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cascadilla Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b17" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jacobson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Pauline</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Quantificational Force of English Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Quantification in Natural Languages</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Emmon</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bach</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eloise</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jelinek</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Angelika</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kratzer</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Barbara<x> </x>H<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Partee</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">451</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">486</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kajita</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Masaru</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Towards a Dynamic Model of Syntax</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Studies in English Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>5</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">44</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">66</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Keenan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edward</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Relative Clauses</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Language Typology and Syntactic Description</title><x>. </x><volume>Vol. 2</volume><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Tim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shopen</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kornfilt</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jaklin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Constraints on Free Relative Clauses in Turkish</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">ZAS Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>4</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">36</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">57</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kuroda</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Shige-Yuki</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1968">1968a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">English Relativization and Certain Related Problems</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>44</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">244</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">266</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kuroda</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Shige-Yuki</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Headless Relative Clauses in Modern Japanese and the Relevancy Condition</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Second Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Henry</forenames><x> </x><surname>Thompson et al.</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">269</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">279</page><x>. </x><address>Berkeley</address><x>: </x><publisher>Berkeley Linguistics Society</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kurosawa</surname><x>, </x><forenames>A.</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2003">2003</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). A Dynamic Syntax Account of Japanese Relative Clauses. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>Kings College</publisher><x>, </x><address>London</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lakoff</surname><x>, </x><forenames>George</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Syntactic Amalgams</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Tenth Regional Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>M<x>. </x>W<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>La Galay et al.</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">321</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">344</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Chicago Linguistic Society</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Larson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Missing Prepositions and the Analysis of English Free</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<address>Relative </address>
<title type="document">
</title>
<miscellaneoustext>Clauses</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>18</volume>
<page type="first">
</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Levin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Juliette</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives and the Null Head Parameter</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Papers from the First Cornell Conference on Government and Binding Theory</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<surname>Wayne</surname><x> </x><forenames>Harbert</forenames>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><address>Ithaca</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cornell University</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McCawley</surname><x>, </x><forenames>James</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntactic Phenomena of English. Vol. 2</title><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McCreight</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Kate</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Case Hierarchies: The Evidence from Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Papers from the Twenty-third Regional Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Barbara</forenames><x> </x><surname>Need</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schiller</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bosch</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">259</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">267</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Chicago Linguistic Society</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Moltmann</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Friederike</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Coordination and Comparatives. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge</address><x>, </x><publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Muller</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Charles</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Sur la Syntaxe et la Semantique des Relatives Independentes et des Interrogatives Indirectes Partielles</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Revue Romane</title><x> </x><volume>24</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">13</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">47</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>M&uuml;ller</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Stefan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">An Extended and Revised HPSG-Analysis for Free Relative Clauses in German</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Verbmobil Report 225</title><x>. </x><address>Saarbruecken</address><x>: </x><publisher>DFKI</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>M&uuml;ller</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Stefan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">An HPSG-Analysis for Free Relative Clauses in German</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Grammars</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">53</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">105</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Nakau</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Minoru</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1971">1971</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Grammar of the Pseudo-Free Relative Pronoun</title><x> </x><title type="journal">What<x>. </x>English Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">2</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">47</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Paul</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hermann</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1920">1920</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Deutsche Grammatik<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Philippaki-Warburton</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Irene</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Melita</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stavrou</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives in Modern Greek</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Studies in Greek Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">117</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">134</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pierrard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michel</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="book">La Relative Sans Antecedent en Fran&ccedil;ais Moderne<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Louvain</address><x>: </x><publisher>Peeters</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pierrard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michel</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Propos de la Determination des Classes Propositionnelles: L&rsquo;Interrogative Indirecte et ses Rapports avec la Relative sans Antecedent</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Zeitschrift f&uuml;r franz&ouml;sische Sprache und Literatur</title><x> </x><volume>102</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">237</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">251</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pittner</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Karin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Freie Relativsaetze und die Kasushierarchie</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Neue Fragen der Linguistik: Akten des 25<x>. </x>Linguistischen Kolloquiums in Paderborn</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Elisabeth</forenames><x> </x><surname>Feldbusch</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Reiner</forenames><x> </x><surname>Pogarell</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Cornelia</forenames><x> </x><surname>Weiss</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">341</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">347</page><x>. </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Max Niemeyer</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pittner</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Karin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Regeln f&uuml;r die Bildung von freien Relativs&auml;tzen: Eine Antwort and Oddleif Leirbukt</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Deutsch als Fremdsprache</title><x> </x><volume>32</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">195</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">200</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pittner</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Karin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Case of German Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>12</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">197</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">231</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Plann</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Susan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1980">1980</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Relative Clauses in Spanish Without Overt Antecedent and Related Constructions</title><x>. </x><address>Berkeley/Los Angeles</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of California Press</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Posner</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Rebecca</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Diachronic Syntax: Free Relatives in Romance</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>21</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">181</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">189</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Quer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Josep</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Mood at the Interface</title><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holland Academic Graphics</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Quicoli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carlos</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1972">1972</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Aspects of Portuguese Complementation. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge</address><x>, </x><publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ramos-Santacruz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Milagrosa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Silent Heads of Spanish Nonspecific Free Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">MIT Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>23</volume>
<page type="first">
</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rebuschi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Georges</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Types de Langues et Types de Constructions: Le Cas des Correlatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="other">Actes du Colloque de Typologie</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>Nanterre</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup>
<miscellaneoustext> van (</miscellaneoustext>
<date date="1989">1989b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Swiss Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Sentential Complementation and the Lexicon: Studies in Honour of Wim de Geest</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Dany</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jaspers</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Wim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Klooster</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Yvan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Putseys</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Pieter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Seuren</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">343</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">354</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Push Chains and Drag Chains: Complex Predicate Split in Dutch</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Scrambling</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Shigeo</forenames><x> </x><surname>Tonoike</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">7</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">33</page><x>. </x><address>Tokyo</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kurosio</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998c</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Syntax Driven (Crazy) by Morphology</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Mengelwerk voor Muysken</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Adrienne</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bruyn</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jacques</forenames><x> </x><surname>Arends</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">67</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">74</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>Instituut voor Algemene Taalwetenschap</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998d</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Trees and Scions, Science and Trees. Chomsky 70th Birthday Fest-Web-Page</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives Inside Out: Transparent Free Relatives as Grafts</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">PASE Papers in Language Studies: Proceedings of the 1999 PASE Conference</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Bo&#x017C;ena</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rozwadowska</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><address>Wroc&#x0142;aw</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Wroc&#x0142;aw</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2001">2001</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Far from Simple Matter: Syntactic Reflexes of Syntax&ndash;Pragmatics Misalignments</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Semantics, Pragmatics and Discourse: Perspectives and Connections<x>. </x>A Festschrift for Ferenc Kiefer</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert<x> </x>M<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Harnish</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Istv&aacute;n</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kenesei</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">21</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">41</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rivero</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mar&iacute;a-Luisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Diachronic Syntax and Learnability: Free Relatives in 13th Century Spanish</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">81</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">129</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rivero</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mar&iacute;a-Luisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Dialects and Diachronic Syntax: Free Relatives in Old Spanish</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>22</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">443</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">454</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Roberts</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Taylor</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pashto Free Relatives and Triply-Filled COMP: Evidence for a Headed Analysis</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Lingua</title><x> </x><volume>102</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">77</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">85</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rooryck</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Johan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Generalized Transformations and the <i>Wh</i>-Cycle: Free Relatives as Bare <i>Wh-</i>CPs</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Minimalism and Kayne&apos;s Asymmetry Hypothesis</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>C<x>. </x>Jan-Wouter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zwart</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">195</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">208</page><x>. </x><address>Groningen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Groningen University</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rudin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Catherine</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Aspects of Bulgarian Syntax: Complementizers and <roman>Wh</roman>-Constructions<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Columbus, OH</address><x>: </x><publisher>Slavica</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Srivastav</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Veneeta</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntax and Semantics of Correlatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>9</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">637</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">686</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Stavrou</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Melita</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Irene</forenames><x> </x><surname>Philippaki-Warburton</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Matching Parameter and Free Relatives in Greek</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Studies in Greek Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>8</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">311</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">332</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Su&ntilde;er</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Margarita</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives and the Matching Parameter</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">363</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">387</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Su&ntilde;er</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Margarita</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Apparent Non-Matching Relative Clauses in Spanish</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Selected Papers from the XIIIth Linguistic Symposium on Romance</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Larry<x> </x>D<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>King</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Catherine<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Maley</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Tredinnick</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Victoria</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Interpretation and Distribution of -<i>Ever</i> in English Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of ConSole II (T&uuml;bingen)</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Regine</forenames><x> </x><surname>Eckhardt</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Veerle<x> </x>van</forenames><x> </x><surname>Geenhoven</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holland Academic Graphics</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Tsubomoto</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Atsur&ocirc;</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntax and Semantics of Free Relatives in Japanese: Pro and its Overt Counterparts</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">English Linguistics Today</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>K.</forenames><x> </x><surname>Iwabe</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>N.</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kaga</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">379</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">399</page><x>. </x><address>Tokyo</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kaitakusha</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Vergnaud</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jean-Roger</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Dependences et Niveaux de Representation en Syntaxe<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Vogel</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ralf</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2001">2001</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Case Conflict in German Free Relative Constructions: An Optimality Theoretic Treatment</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Competition in Syntax</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Gereon</forenames><x> </x><surname>M&uuml;ller</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Wolfgang</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sternefeld</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Walraven</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Corretje<x> </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Enkele Opmerkingen over de Vrije Relatieve Zin in het Nederlands</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<address>Unpublished manuscript</address><x>, </x><publisher>University of Amsterdam</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wilder</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Chris</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Transparent Free Relatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">ZAS Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>10</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">191</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">199</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wilder</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Chris</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Transparent Free Relatives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Seventeenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Kimary<x> </x>N<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shahin</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Blake</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eun-Sook</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kim</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">685</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">699</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wiltschko</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martina</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Syntax and Semantics of (Relative) Pronouns and Determiners</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">143</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">181</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wiltschko</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martina</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Free Relatives as Indefinites</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Seventeenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Kimary<x> </x>N<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shahin</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Blake</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eun-Sook</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kim</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">700</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">712</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zribi-Hertz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anne</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Jean-Fran&ccedil;ois</forenames><x> </x><surname>Hanne</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pronoms, Determinants et Relatives en Bambara de Bamako</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistique Africaine</title><x> </x><volume>15</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">91</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">135</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
