<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="50"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 50 - Pied-Piping.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">569</page>
<page type="last">630</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="2"/>
<count type="table" count="66"/>
<count type="formula" count="0"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="73"/>
<count type="page" count="62"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20051125"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 50&ensp;Horvath: Pied-Piping</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 50&ensp;Horvath: Pied-Piping</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">50 Pied-Piping</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>JULIA</forenames><x> </x><surname>HORVATH</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1 </number>
<p>Introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>A historical overview: pied-piping and theories of movement</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>The Standard Theory and Ross&apos;s Pied-Piping Convention</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Pied-piping in the GB model: X-Bar Theory and Move &alpha;</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>A Minimalist perspective: feature movement and the status of pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>Descriptive dimensions of pied-piping: <i>wh</i>-movement</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Construction-specific variation</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Restrictive and non-restrictive relative clauses vs. <i>wh</i>-questions</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Free relatives</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The phrase-internal position of the pied-piper</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Category type of the pied-piped phrase</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>Issues and proposed analyses</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>What can pied-pipe a phrase?</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The core cases: projection and the Spec&ndash;Head relation</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Some other effects</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Relative clauses and the topicalization proposal</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Free relatives and the identification of a <i>pro</i> head</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.4&ensp;</number>
<p>PP pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.5&ensp;</number>
<p>Clausal pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.6&ensp;</number>
<p>Pied-piping in non-<i>wh</i>-constructions</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>LF-movements and pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>6&ensp;</number>
<p>The Minimalist Program and further current directions</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>6.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Feature movement, economy, and generalized pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>6.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Phrasal movement vs. head movement, large-scale pied-piping, and the elimination of feature movement</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1&ensp;Introduction</heading>
<p>The notion of &lsquo;pied-piping&rsquo; has been an integral part of all versions of the theory of generative grammar that assume transformational movements since it was first introduced by <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>, from his 1967 dissertation). The term itself &ndash; attributed by Ross to Robin Lakoff &ndash; refers to the phenomenon whereby some particular movement operation T, designated to displace an element A, in fact displaces additional elements together with A; more specifically, pied-piping is involved when an application of T ends up moving some constituent B that properly contains A. Ross&apos;s Pied-Piping Convention was originally meant, for instance, to extend the application of the Relative Clause Formation transformation, so that it is able to move more than just the NP immediately dominating the relative pronoun in cases such as shown in (1&ndash;2), where (1b, c) and (2a) represent, according to <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>), instances of pied-piping by the relative <i>wh</i>-pronoun.</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>reports &lsqb;<i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of the lettering on . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>reports &lsqb;the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of the lettering on . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>reports the &lsqb;lettering on the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of . . . </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(2)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>the boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i> guardian&apos;s employer&rsqb; we elected president</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*the boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i>&rsqb; we elected guardian&apos;s employer president</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>From its inception until now the existence of pied-piping has uniformly been assumed in the literature, and it has provided a widely used descriptive tool. Yet until recently, the pied-piping phenomenon itself received surprisingly little attention as a research topic in its own right. Thus, while the closely related topics of the proper formulation of, and constraints on, transformational movement operations have always been central to research in syntactic theory, even the most basic questions regarding pied-piping were not raised and addressed in any systematic fashion at least until the early 1990s. A possible reason for this may be the highly theory-dependent nature of pied-piping, namely, the fact that by its very definition, instances of pied-piping can be identified only relative to a particular formulation of the movement operation involved.</p>
<p>Thus, in any theoretical framework in which various movement transformations are formulated in a construction-specific manner, as was the case in the early stages of generative syntax up to the mid 1970s, a general theory of pied-piping could hardly be contemplated. Due to the excessive power of the formalism of transformations, the descriptive effects attributed by Ross to pied-piping could often be easily incorporated into the formulation of the movement transformation itself. There were major discrepancies even involving the best-studied case, namely that of <i>wh</i>-movement, for instance between <link rid="b1">Ross&apos;s (1986</link>) and <link rid="b2">Emonds&apos;s (1976</link>) conception of the phenomenon of pied-piping. Under Ross&apos;s notion (see section 1.1), both cases like (1b, c) as well as cases like (2a) were analyzed as instances of the Pied-Piping Convention (given in (8) below); however, under Emonds&apos;s alternative proposal, only cases like (1b, c) were such, while those like (2a) were taken to be due to the particular formulation of the <i>wh</i>-movement transformation itself, and were claimed to involve no pied-piping. (See the formulation of <i>wh</i>-movement as moving an NP, AP, or PP with a <i>wh</i>-morpheme at its left periphery, and the analysis of the residue of Ross&apos;s pied-piping as a &lsquo;stylistic&rsquo; process in <link rid="b2">Emonds 1976</link>; on the latter idea, see also <link rid="ss7">section 3</link>). <link rid="b3">Bresnan (1976c</link>) departs from Ross&apos;s hypothesis of pied-piping even more radically; her X-Bar theory-based, category-neutral statement of the transformation forming relative clauses eliminates the need for a stipulated pied-piping convention, not only with respect to examples of the type of (2a), but also with respect to examples like (1b, c) since it specifies the constituent that the movement operation applies to as any XP with the categorial feature &lsqb;&minus;V&rsqb; (hence any NP or PP) that contains a <i>wh</i>-morpheme.</p>
<p>In the Principles and Parameters (P&amp;P) framework of the 1980s, involving the reduction of the transformational component of the model to the universal Move &alpha; schema, and the development of X-Bar theory, as a uniform theory of phrase structure extending to all phrase types, it became possible to ask more general questions regarding the range and properties of pied-piping phenomena; namely, it became in principle feasible to start exploring how general pied-piping behavior is across different constructions, different category types, and across languages, and what its properties and distribution derive from. Yet, possibly due to the highly theory-internal nature of pied-piping, such issues remained essentially uninvestigated during the 1980s as well.</p>
<p>It was only in the 1990s that the general issue of pied-piping started to receive some more comprehensive treatment (e.g., <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>). General questions like the following were raised: What is it that makes pied-piping in individual constructions and with particular phrase types possible while in other cases impossible, and what factors can make it obligatory? What makes it stylistically marked in some particular cases? What is the source of some observed cross-linguistic and cross-categorial discrepancies? What are the structural and possibly non-structural conditions on pied-piping?</p>
<p>In accordance with the modular approach to accounting for syntactic phenomena in terms of interacting principles and parameters of UG, ideally one would like to make the various observed pied-piping options, or lack of those, also fall out of independent properties of UG. Attempts in this direction have been made in the past decade, e.g., by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>), <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>), <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>), <link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>).</p>
<p>The literature on pied-piping up until recently has concentrated mostly on particular cases of A-bar movement, primarily on <i>wh</i>-movements and marginally on some other operator movements, such as negative preposing and quantifier raising. The set of languages investigated, at least with respect to overt pied-piping, has traditionally been limited to mainly English and a few other Germanic languages. Unavoidably, this will be reflected in our discussion as well: it will deal most extensively with <i>wh</i>-constructions, and will use Germanic, and primarily English, data; only some limited amount of comparative material drawn from other languages will be included where relevant.</p>
<p>It needs to be noted here that in the past few years, the above state of affairs started to change, mainly due to two recent developments. One of these, already referred to earlier, was the assumption of movement being feature-driven in the version of the MP presented in <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>), which as a consequence made all cases of movement of elements larger than the &ldquo;driving&rdquo; (attracted) features themselves be manifestations of pied-piping. The other factor contributing to the broadening of interest in pied-piping in recent years has been the body of research inspired by <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>) Antisymmetry framework, which involves significantly increased reliance on the pied-piping mechanism in the analysis of a variety of languages (see, e.g., <link rid="b9 b7">Koopman 1996, 1997</link>; <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi 2000</link>; <link rid="b11">Nkemnji 1995</link>; <link rid="b12">Pearson 2000b</link>).</p>
<p>Given the sporadic and highly theory and analysis-specific nature of the claims about pied-piping in the literature, the following discussion does not purport to be exhaustive in any sense, and will address only some of the more prominent and influential observations, proposals, and directions for research. The organization of this chapter is as follows.</p>
<p>
<link rid="ss3">Section 2</link> provides a historical perspective on approaches to pied-piping and on the role it played at successive stages in the theory, from <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>) and the Standard Theory (<link rid="b13">Chomsky 1965</link>) to the current MP framework. <link rid="ss7">Section 3</link> presents the various descriptive dimensions that pied-piping phenomena manifest, as observed with respect to the best-studied case, namely, instances of <i>wh</i>-movement. It demonstrates the existence of apparent variation according to construction-type based on (restrictive and non-restrictive) relatives, interrogatives, and free relatives, it examines the relevance of the position of the pied-piper within the larger phrase, and it outlines some observed differences relating to category type. <link rid="ss13">Section 4</link> outlines the major directions and proposals towards a modular, comprehensive, structure-dependent view of pied-piping. Proposals to account for some apparent discrepancies between construction types and for cross-categorial differences will be presented and evaluated. The discussion will include the divergent behavior of PP pied-piping and the controversial issue of clausal pied-piping, as well as some cases of pied-piping under movements other than <i>wh</i>-movement. <link rid="ss22">Section 5</link> will address the question of LF-pied-piping, that is, the issue of whether or not there is any evidence for the assumption that covert movements may also involve pied-piping. <link rid="ss23">Section 6</link>, finally, outlines the status of pied-piping and what may permit, and in fact force, it within versions of Chomsky&apos;s minimalist framework and in other current directions of research, addressing its relation to the PF-interface, to principles of economy and to the phrasal movement vs. head-movement distinction.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss3" level="1">
<heading id="h2" level="1">2&ensp;A historical overview: pied-piping and theories of movement</heading>
<subsection id="ss4" level="2">
<heading id="h3" level="2">2.1&ensp;The Standard Theory and Ross&apos;s Pied-Piping Convention</heading>
<p>The hypothesis of pied-piping by movement operations and the corresponding Pied-Piping Convention was originally introduced by <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>) as part of his proposal to replace <link rid="b14">Chomsky&apos;s (1964a</link>) A-over-A Principle &ndash; see (3) below, accounting for contrasts such as (2a) vs. (2b) &ndash; by a set of other constraints on the application of transformations, due to various empirical inadequacies he observed with respect to the former. A classic set of data Ross pointed out as crucial evidence in favor of introducing the option of pied-piping as opposed to maintaining the A-over-A Principle were the set of alternative options shown in (4&ndash;5) involving NPs contained within larger NPs moved by the Relative Clause Formation transformation:</p>
<listgroup id="l2" type="1">
<li>
<number>(3) </number>
<p><b>A-over-A Principle:</b>
</p>
<p>In a structure .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>A</sub> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb; .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb; .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, if a structural description refers to A ambiguously, then that structural description can only analyze the higher, more inclusive, node A.</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(4) </number>
<p>Reports &lsqb;<i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of the lettering on the covers of are invariably boring.</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(5)&ensp;</number>
<p>
<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Reports &lsqb;the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of the lettering on almost always put me to sleep.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Reports &lsqb;the lettering on the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes the height of are a shocking waste of public funds.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Reports &lsqb;the height of the lettering on the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes should be abolished. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Examples (5a&ndash;c) involve movement of larger NPs than just the relative <i>wh</i>-pronoun itself that is designated by the Relative Clause Formation trans-formation to undergo preposing, and at the same time, examples (4) and (5a, b) demonstrate that these data are not attributable to the A-over-A Principle since they in fact violate it. Ross&apos;s proposal, beyond his independently argued move to eliminate the A-over-A Principle, was to introduce the Pied-Piping Convention to deal with the facts in (4&ndash;5). His actual formulation of the pied-piping option was shaped by some further cases indicating that in contrast to the examples of the type in (5b, c), in certain other configurations the element designated by the transformation to move cannot carry with it, i.e., cannot pied-pipe, a larger phrase containing it. The relevant observations made by Ross, involving coordinate NPs and clauses, are illustrated in (6) and (7) respectively.</p>
<p>(6) *The boy &lsqb;Bill and <i>who</i>(<i>m</i>)&rsqb; I watched was vain.</p>
<p>(7)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>They will give me a hat &lsqb;<i>which</i>&rsqb; I know that I won&apos;t like.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*They will give me a hat &lsqb;that I won&apos;t like <i>which</i>&rsqb; I know. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Accordingly, Ross states the Pied-Piping Convention, intended as a universal convention for the application of transformations, as follows:</p>
<listgroup id="l3" type="1">
<li>
<number>(8) </number>
<p><b>The Pied-Piping Convention:</b>
</p>
<p>Any transformation which is stated in such a way as to effect the reordering of some specified node NP, where this node is preceded and followed by variables in the structural index of the rule, may apply to this NP or to any non-coordinate NP which dominates it, as long as there are no occurrences of any coordinate node, nor of the node S, on the branch connecting the higher node and the specified node.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>It needs to be noted here that the Pied-Piping Convention was crucially stated as taking along a larger phrase only optionally. This was appropriate for cases such as (4&ndash;5). However, in a well-defined set of instances, pied-piping seemed to apply obligatorily, as shown by (9a, b):</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*the boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i>&rsqb; we elected guardian&apos;s employer president</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*the boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i> guardian&apos;s&rsqb; we elected employer president</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>the boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i> guardian&apos;s employer&rsqb; we elected president</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It is this phenomenon &ndash; being essentially a residual A-over-A effect &ndash; for which Ross proposed the Left Branch Condition (10); this condition renders the application of pied-piping in such cases in effect obligatory.</p>
<listgroup id="l4" type="1">
<li>
<number>(10) </number>
<p><b>The Left Branch Condition</b> (LBC)</p>
<p>No NP which is the leftmost constituent of a larger NP can be reordered out of this NP by a transformational rule.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Ross&apos;s statement of the Pied-Piping Convention, as well as the LBC, refer only to the category NP. But at the time, his category NP crucially included also PPs; PPs were considered by Ross as NPs immediately dominating P and NP, so movements carrying along Ps were analyzed as cases of pied-piping under this formulation as well. Furthermore, APs and AdvPs too were taken by Ross to be derived from or dominated by NPs, hence their obligatory pied-piping effects were also assumed to be covered by this formulation of the convention and of the LBC. The marked increase of category types in the course of the evolution of the theory in subsequent decades had an obvious impact on the issue of identifying the set of categories involved in pied-piping.</p>
<p>Unlike the highly construction-specific transformations themselves characteristic of the Standard Theory of the 1960s assumed also by Ross, the Pied-Piping Convention clearly was conceived as applying in a general way, to all transformational movements, and irrespective of construction type. In addition to examples involving the Relative Clause Formation transformation, <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>) demonstrated the pied-piping phenomenon, and the effects of conditions on its application, with respect to transformations such as the <i>wh</i>-movement rule forming interrogatives (his Question Rule), Topicalization and Heavy NP Shift (the latter two cases are exemplified in (11) and (12), respectively).</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The boy&apos;s guardian&apos;s employer we elected president.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The boy&apos;s guardian&apos;s we elected employer president. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>We elected president the boy&apos;s guardian&apos;s employer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*We elected employer president the boy&apos;s guardian&apos;s. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As for the issue of the universal status of the convention and cases of apparent cross-linguistic variation with respect to pied-piping phenomena, Ross noted problems at least in two major areas. One such case involved the LBC, which turned out not to apply in some languages, as for instance Russian and Latin; hence Ross proposed that it is a condition specified in particular grammars. The other area that posed important problems for the Pied-Piping Convention was the variation among languages with respect to PPs: stranding vs. pied-piping of Ps seemed not to be a free choice in particular languages as would be expected based on the convention. The stranding of Ps was known to be prohibited in a variety of languages (e.g., German, French, Italian, Russian), i.e., pied-piping of P was obligatory. On the other hand, in languages like Danish and English, pied-piping of Ps was claimed to be prohibited in some specific environments, as exemplified below for English by (13a, b) (&equals;Ross&apos;s (4.211b, c)).</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?*Did you notice of which difficulties she made light?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Of whom are you trying to get hold? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Ross incorporated these cases of variation as separate stipulated conditions on pied-piping that appear in individual grammars, and left the original formulation of the convention in UG. Most of the empirical issues involved remain essentially unresolved until today.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss5" level="2">
<heading id="h4" level="2">2.2&ensp;Pied-piping in the GB model: X-Bar Theory and Move &alpha;</heading>
<p>The major shift in the theory that took place in the 1980s GB era, replacing the Standard Theory&apos;s assumption of language-particular grammars with the Principles-and-Parameters theory, naturally resulted in a change in the view of the pied-piping mechanism as well. One factor that had an important impact on the kinds of questions that could be raised with respect to pied-piping was the development of a full-fledged X-Bar theory of phrase structure. A relevant aspect of this development was the postulation of new phrasal categories with a uniform X-Bar structure for categories that previously either had been neglected &ndash; as for instance the category PP, as distinct from NP, and the subsequently introduced DP, projected by D(et) (see, e.g., <link rid="b15">Brame 1982</link>; <link rid="b16">Szabolcsi 1983</link>; <link rid="b17">Abney 1987</link>) &ndash; or had been assigned an exocentric structure, radically different from the rest of the phrasal categories, such as the clausal categories S and S&prime;, which have become known since <link rid="b18">Chomsky (1986a</link>) as IP, headed by I, and CP, headed by C. This in turn resulted in an increased number of category types which exhibited a uniform, precisely articulated internal hierarchical structure, with structurally defined relations such as Spec&ndash;Head and Head&ndash;Complement, and for which cross-categorial generalizations were expected to hold in principle, and had in fact been observed with respect to various empirical domains. Given this, the issue of whether the pied-piping phenomenon is category-neutral or not and if not, why not, became an obvious subject for empirical inquiry.</p>
<p>This direction leading towards the need for a more general, non-stipulative theory of pied-piping was further reinforced by the elimination of individual transformations in favor of the universal maximally general &lsquo;Move &alpha;&rsquo; schema for transformational movement, permitting in principle free movement of any category to any position. With construction-particular statements of transformations gone, the task of accounting for observed properties of and limitations on actual movement options got assigned to universal constraints and principles, with a limited number and kinds of open parameters, within UG. UG acquired a rich modular structure consisting of a variety of subsystems of principles (e.g., theta theory, Case theory, binding theory, locality conditions); it was the interaction of these that was supposed to derive the actual clusters of empirical phenomena recognized descriptively as &lsquo;constructions&rsquo;, which had earlier been accounted for by stipulating various individual construction-specific transformations. Since under Move &alpha; any size constituents could undergo movement in any construction, unless it resulted in violation of a UG principle or condition, the challenge with respect to pied-piping in this framework became quite different from the situation in Ross&apos;s time. For Ross, what needed explanation in the first place, and what led him to introduce the Pied-Piping Convention, was the existence of cases when a &lsquo;larger-than-expected&rsquo; constituent moved; in contrast, in the GB era, what was in need of an account was the large set of cases where pied-piping seemed to be impossible, for apparently no known reason. In other words, movements in effect became completely unlimited under the Move &alpha; schema, making the Pied-Piping Convention as such entirely redundant, and just like other instances of overgeneration by movements, cases as, e.g., those in (14&ndash;16), involving apparently illegitimate pied-piping effects, needed to be excluded in new, non-stipulative ways.</p>
<p>(14) *We wondered &lsqb;the rumors about <i>whom</i>&rsqb; shocked Mary.</p>
<p>(15) *&lsqb;Some <i>how</i> old boys&rsqb; have you met?</p>
<p>(16) *&lsqb;Read <i>what</i>&rsqb; has John?</p>
<p>The first systematic investigation into the nature and limitations of what pretheoretically continued to be referred to as pied-piping phenomena in the GB framework was presented by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>: ch. 4). Webelhuth&apos;s study explored <i>wh</i>-movements in the Germanic languages, and arrived at a set of important structure-dependent descriptive generalizations about what positions in terms of X-Bar theory and in what types of phrases can serve as pied-pipers. His actual account of the generalizations he uncovered was based on a modular view of UG, and involved the interaction of independently motivated principles, such as the theta criterion, the definition of syntactic operator, the Bijection Principle, the definition of the modification relation, and others. (For a discussion of Webelhuth&apos;s analysis, see <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>.)</p>
<p>Other work on pied-piping during the GB period concentrated on more limited issues, such as the existence of clausal pied-piping and the severe restrictions on it in languages like English and German, studied, e.g., in <link rid="b19">Nanni and Stillings (1978</link>), <link rid="b20">Ishihara (1984</link>), and <link rid="b21">Van Riemsdijk (1985</link>). (On CP pied-piping see also <link rid="ss20">section 4.5</link> below.) Another specific aspect of pied-piping addressed in the 1980s was the issue of LF-pied-piping, debated primarily (a) in relation to apparent violations of Subjacency in cases of (alleged) covert <i>wh</i>-movement of in situ <i>wh</i>-phrases by <link rid="b22">Choe (1987</link>), <link rid="b23">Nishigauchi (1990</link>), <link rid="b24">Pesetsky (1987a</link>), <link rid="b25">Fiengo et al. (1988</link>), and (b) in relation to <link rid="b26">May&apos;s (1985</link>) QR-based account of antecedent-contained deletion (ACD). (See also <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related> and a general overview of LF-pied-piping in <link rid="ss22">section 5</link>.) Some more general remarks about S-structure pied-piping phenomena involving <i>wh</i>-movement were presented by <link rid="b27">Kayne (1984a</link>: ch. 8) with reference to his notion of g-projection set.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss6" level="2">
<heading id="h5" level="2">2.3&ensp;A Minimalist perspective: feature movement and the status of pied-piping</heading>
<p>One major innovation that characterized the emerging Minimalist research program of the 1990s involved a change in the conception of movement operations. The minimalist framework (<link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link>) incorporated in a strict and systematic way the earlier idea of movement having a last-resort character. This was made precise by claiming that movement in the syntactic derivation, i.e., in the computational system (CS), must always be &lsquo;driven&rsquo;, and specifically, it is possible only for the satisfaction of abstract morphological requirements, namely, for the checking of uninterpretable formal features (such as Case, phi-features, etc.) occurring on lexical items. The assumption that all movements are feature-driven led directly to the proposal that the movement operation Move/Attract applies only to the formal features themselves. In other words, movement in the MP framework of the 1990s was conceived of as feature movement, rather than movement of full categories (but see <link rid="b28">Chomsky 2000</link> for a revision of the idea of feature movement). If so, as argued by <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>), any case in which more than just the formal features of items move is an instance of the application of pied-piping. Thus any displacement of overt material is construed in this framework as a case of pied-piping. (On what forces such pied-piping, related issues of economy and predictions regarding LF-pied-piping, see <link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link> and <link rid="ss23">section 6</link> below.) This extended notion of pied-piping is referred to in the MP literature as generalized pied-piping.</p>
<p>Observe here the contrast arising between the status of pied-piping in GB theory and pied-piping in the above version of the MP framework. While anything could in principle move under &lsquo;Move &alpha;&rsquo;, so the crucial question in the GB frameweork was how to exclude &ndash; usually by various well-formedness and interpretive conditions &ndash; unwanted instances of pied-piping, the issue is exactly the reverse under <link rid="b6">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) MP. Other things being equal, nothing can move, in accordance with the notion of derivational economy, apart from formal features, and those move only when needed for feature checking. Hence the actual occurrence of any movement of elements &lsquo;larger&rsquo; than such features not only constitutes pied-piping in this version of the MP, but more importantly, pied-piping itself needs to be accounted for in terms of what forces it under the MP notion of economy.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>) suggests the strong hypothesis that all pied-piping is forced by needs of the PF-interface. Bare feature movement results in scattered, isolated features, which as such are uninterpretable for the PF component, i.e., they cannot be pronounced. So pied-piping of (at least) the full lexical item bearing the relevant feature would be forced to take place in order to repair this, and thus to prevent the derivation from crashing at PF. The empirical challenge such a proposal faces is of course to find motivated PF-based reasons for the observed pied-piping of various larger than minimal pronounceable constituents (e.g., various phrasal categories). This unified PF-interface hypothesis of (generalized) pied-piping opens up some intriguing questions for future research, such as the problems raised by the existence of both head movement and phrasal movement in the theory, when both are assumed to be feature-driven, or for instance the question of the proper analysis of apparent cases of large-scale pied-piping and of the coexistence of alternative pied-piping options with respect to the same element (see also <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>).</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss7" level="1">
<heading id="h6" level="1">3&ensp;Descriptive dimensions of pied-piping: <i>wh</i>-movement</heading>
<p>The main body of phenomena considered as uncontroversial cases of pied-piping in the literature of the past three decades manifests variation along a number of different dimensions. Using the best-studied case, namely, pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement, the following subsections will sort out and organize the observed pied-piping phenomena along these distinct but interrelated dimensions. Each subsection will discuss one such dimension, keeping the rest of the factors of variation constant as much as possible. This outline of the relevant descriptive dimensions will be providing the empirical foundation and frame of reference for the discussion of proposed accounts in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>.</p>
<subsection id="ss8" level="2">
<heading id="h7" level="2">3.1&ensp;Construction-specific variation</heading>
<p>Contrary to what might be expected (other things being equal) under the conception of pied-piping as a unified property of movements, it turns out that at least prima facie, pied-piping applies differently to different construction types. Thus, three core cases of <i>wh</i>-movement construction of English, each involving an overt <i>wh</i>-morpheme, exhibit three distinct patterns of possible pied-piping. One such unexpected contrast holds between pied-piping options in relative clauses &ndash; of the type that led Ross to propose the Pied-Piping Convention in the first place &ndash; and pied-piping options in <i>wh</i>-questions. As will be demonstrated in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>, a specific set of pied-piping cases exist in English with respect to relative clauses formed by <i>wh</i>-movement but not with respect to corresponding interrogatives being formed by <i>wh</i>-movement. In addition to this apparent relative&ndash;interrogative <i>wh</i>-movement contrast, a third distinct pattern of pied-piping options is attested in the case of <i>wh</i>-movement forming free relatives. As will be shown in <link rid="ss10">section 3.1.2</link>, pied-piping effects in free relatives are even more limited than they are in the case of <i>wh</i>-interrogatives. In a set of well-defined subcases, pied-piping by the <i>wh</i>-word seems impossible in free relatives while the same phrase can be pied-piped both in (restrictive and non-restrictive) headed relatives and in <i>wh</i>-questions.</p>
<subsection id="ss9" level="3">
<heading id="h8" level="3">3.1.1&ensp;Restrictive and non-restrictive relative clauses vs. <roman>wh</roman>-questions</heading>
<p>Pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement has been observed to be most permissive in the case of relative clauses, and especially in non-restrictive relatives (on a contrast observed between pied-piping in restrictive and non-restrictive relatives, see the discussion of (21a, b) and (21c) below, as well as <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>). Consider first the kind of relative clause data (discussed also by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>) that was used by Ross as the initial motivation for the Pied-Piping Convention.</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Reports &lsqb;the height of the lettering on the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes should be abolished.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>He is a linguist &lsqb;articles by <i>whom</i>&rsqb; the editors always reject.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>This is the kind of woman &lsqb;proud of <i>whom</i>&rsqb; I could never be.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Crucially, it turns out that the corresponding <i>wh</i>-questions are unacceptable. (The unacceptability of such pied-piping is even sharper in embedded interrogatives than in matrix ones, possibly due to interference from echo questions in the latter cases, as noted in <link rid="b8">Kayne 1994</link>.)</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;The height of the lettering on the covers of <i>which</i> reports&rsqb; did the government prescribe?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*We don&apos;t know &lsqb;articles by <i>whom</i>&rsqb; the editors have rejected.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*I asked Bill &lsqb;proud of <i>whom</i>&rsqb; he has always been.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Descriptively speaking, what seems to characterize the <i>wh</i>-phrases that manifest contrasting pied-piping options in relatives vs. in <i>wh</i>-questions in English is that the <i>wh</i>-word itself in these types of phrases is located to the right of the head of the phrase (this will be made more precise in <link rid="ss11">section 3.2</link>). The cross-linguistic status of the above type of data suggests that it is the possibility of such (apparent) pied-piping in English relatives, rather than its unavailability in English <i>wh</i>-questions, that is special in some way, i.e., that is the unexpected aspect of the contrast. The reason is that relative clauses in the other Germanic languages uniformly fail to permit such instances of pied-piping, as shown for instance by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>: 129) examples for German, Dutch (see (19&ndash;20)), as well as for Swedish, Danish, and Norwegian.</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*der</entry>
<entry>Pr&auml;sident,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;ein</entry>
<entry>Bild</entry>
<entry>von</entry>
<entry><i>dem</i>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>an</entry>
<entry>der</entry>
<entry>Wand</entry>
<entry>hing</entry>
<entry> German</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>president</entry>
<entry> a</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>at</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>wall</entry>
<entry>hung</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*de</entry>
<entry>president,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;een</entry>
<entry>foto</entry>
<entry>van</entry>
<entry><i>wie</i>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>aan</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>muur</entry>
<entry>hing</entry>
<entry> Dutch</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>president</entry>
<entry> a</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>at</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>wall</entry>
<entry>hung</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Observe furthermore that such cases of pied-piping in English relatives as in (17) contrast not only with corresponding English <i>wh</i>-interrogatives, and not only are they ungrammatical in the other Germanic languages, but they also vary in acceptability among themselves. A systematic aspect of the latter kind of variation is pointed out by <link rid="b29">Emonds (1985</link>: 304, n. 20).</p>
<p>Emonds claims that the marginal status and variability of judgments hold for pied-piping of this type specifically within restrictive relatives, indicating that such cases when acceptable, are only &lsquo;derivatively&rsquo; generated, on the model of non-restrictive relatives. He bases this claim on restrictive relatives such as in (21a, b), where interference from non-restrictive relatives is reduced by the choice of the heads of these relatives (which would be inappropriate as heads of non-restrictive relatives), and on their contrast with the non-restrictive relative (21c). (Emonds&apos;s judgments below are not uniformly shared by speakers.)</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?We should visit only the city &lsqb;a favorable report on <i>which</i>&rsqb; Jack received.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Most students are interested in any professor &lsqb;a security file on <i>whom</i>&rsqb; the government won&apos;t release.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Most students are interested in Prof. Rotestern, &lsqb;the security file on <i>whom</i>&rsqb; the government won&apos;t release. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>He concludes that pied-piping by a post-head <i>wh</i>-word is a legitimate, though stylistically literary, option only for non-restrictive relatives.</p>
<p>In sum, pied-piping (by a <i>wh</i>-word) in English has been shown to be more limited in questions than in relatives, or at least than in non-restrictive relatives.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss10" level="3">
<heading id="h9" level="3">3.1.2&ensp;Free relatives</heading>
<p>Consider next the following contrast between <i>wh</i>-questions and headed relatives on the one hand and free relatives on the other, involving a type of pied-piping not discussed in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>, namely, pied-piping when the <i>wh</i>-word occurs to the left of the head of the relevant phrase:</p>
<listgroup id="l5" type="1">
<li>
<number>(22)&ensp;</number>
<p><b><i>Wh</i>-questions:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>what</i>&rsqb; you bought.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>whose</i> picture&rsqb; you lost.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>whose</i> mother&apos;s picture&rsqb; is hanging on the wall. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(23)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>Relatives with an overt head:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>the picture &lsqb;<i>which</i>&rsqb; you bought</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>the person &lsqb;<i>whose</i> picture&rsqb; you lost</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>the person &lsqb;<i>whose</i> mother&apos;s picture&rsqb; is hanging on the wall</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(24)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>Free relatives:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I like &lsqb;<i>what</i>&rsqb; you bought.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*I admire &lsqb;<i>whose</i> picture&rsqb; you lost.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Whose</i> mother&apos;s picture&rsqb; is hanging on the wall should be fired. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>The impossibility of pied-piping within free relatives demonstrated in (24b, c) above, and their striking contrast with the perfectly grammatical corresponding <i>wh</i>-questions and overtly headed relatives (as in (22b, c) and (23b, c)) was first pointed out and analyzed in <link rid="b30">Grosu (1989</link>). As demonstrated by Grosu, this severe limitation on free relatives with respect to pied-piping effects is not specific to English, but holds for the full range of languages (e.g., also in German, Romanian, Finnish, Latin, Classical Greek), and is independent of where the particular free relatives fall in terms of the matching parameter (see also <link rid="b31">Grosu 1994</link> and <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 27 - Free Relatives.xml" type="file">chapter 27</externallink></related>). The proposed account, based on the need of local identification for the <i>pro</i> head of the free relative, will be discussed in <link rid="ss18">section 4.3.2</link>.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="2">
<heading id="h10" level="2">3.2&ensp;The phrase-internal position of the pied-piper</heading>
<p>The phenomena introduced in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link> already suggested that the position of the potential pied-piper within a phrase is a relevant factor in determining whether that particular phrase will or will not undergo pied-piping. Specifically, we have seen that with the exception of some relative clauses in a literary register of English, pied-piping in the Germanic languages under <i>wh</i>-movement is possible only if the <i>wh</i>-word occurs to the left of the head of the phrase (see, e.g., (18), (19), and (20)). This observation needs to be made more precise by exploring the exact nature of the apparent constraint on the position of the pied-piper within the relevant phrase. Consider first the contrast shown in (25) and (26) regarding pied-piping options for DPs in English:</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>whose</i> articles&rsqb; they read.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>which</i> airport&rsqb; is the busiest. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder &lsqb;articles by <i>whom</i>/<i>which</i> linguists&rsqb; they read.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder &lsqb;the airport <i>where</i>/in <i>which</i> city&rsqb; is the busiest. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Descriptively speaking, the relevant generalization in this set of examples is that a DP can get pied-piped under <i>wh</i>-movement only when the <i>wh</i>-word is either to the left of the head, more precisely, as suggested by (29&ndash;30) below, occupying its Spec position (as in (25a)) or is the head D itself (as in (25b)). When it follows the head of the phrase, specifically, when it is a complement of the lexical head or a modifier (adjunct), as in (26a, b), then it cannot induce pied-piping of the phrase. A similar pattern is observed also in the case of pied-piping of APs.</p>
<p>(27) I wonder &lsqb;<i>how</i> proud of his achievements&rsqb; your brother is.</p>
<p>(28) *I wonder &lsqb;very proud of <i>what</i>/<i>whose</i> achievements&rsqb; your brother is.</p>
<p>At this point one may still assume that the observed generalization about the pied-piper&apos;s phrase-internal position involves linear order with respect to the head, rather than notions of hierarchical structure and corresponding grammatical relations within the phrase. But consider the following relevant data from English and German DPs, as well as APs in German, discussed in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>):</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">*&lsqb;The/Some <i>how</i> old books&rsqb; has John lost?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Die</entry>
<entry><i>wie</i>
</entry>
<entry>alten</entry>
<entry>B&uuml;cher&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>verloren?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>how</entry>
<entry>old</entry>
<entry>books</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>lost</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*&lsqb;Auf</entry>
<entry><i>wen</i>
</entry>
<entry>sehr</entry>
<entry>stolz&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>Hans?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry> of</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>very</entry>
<entry>proud</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (29a, b) the <i>wh</i>-word is to the left of the lexical head of the phrase, yet it cannot induce pied-piping. But this is precisely what one would expect if the correct generalization was based on hierarchical position in terms of X-Bar theory: unlike in (25) and (27), here the <i>wh</i>-word is not in the Spec position of the pied-piped phrase, but is in an adjunct of the noun phrase, namely, in an attributive-adjective phrase. The example in (30) provides even stronger evidence against a linear precedence-based generalization for what can be a pied-piper in a phrase. It shows that even though in German PP-complements of adjectives are possible both to the right and to the left of the head A (see <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 122), pied-piping of the AP by a pre-head <i>wh</i>-complement is still impossible, just like it is with post-head ones. Again, this suggests that it is being a complement rather than a Spec of the AP that is the crucial factor blocking pied-piping by the <i>wh</i>-word here, and not linear position.</p>
<p>Finally, one might perhaps try to claim at this point that all the above cases where the <i>wh</i>-word could not act as a pied-piper, (26), (28), (29), and (30) are due to a requirement that the pied-piper needs to be adjacent to the left periphery of the phrase, i.e., needs to be in absolute initial position. But notice that this amended linear alternative turns out to be inadequate as well, in light of the following evidence from pied-piping data involving Hungarian DPs (on a detailed analysis of the latter see <link rid="b16">Szabolcsi 1983</link> and subsequent work). The Hungarian facts indicate that in fact the pied-piper need not be initial in the pied-piped phrase.</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;J&aacute;nos</entry>
<entry><i>melyik</i>
</entry>
<entry>fi&aacute;t&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>szereted</entry>
<entry>legjobban?</entry>
<entry>Hungarian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John</entry>
<entry>which</entry>
<entry>son-3Sg Poss-Acc</entry>
<entry>like-2Sg</entry>
<entry>best</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;Which son of John&apos;s do you like most?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Az</entry>
<entry>any&aacute;d</entry>
<entry><i>h&aacute;ny</i>
</entry>
<entry>bar&aacute;tn&#x0151;j&eacute;nek&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>telefon&aacute;lt&aacute;l?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>mother-2Sg Poss</entry>
<entry>how many</entry>
<entry>woman-friend-3Sg Poss-Dat</entry>
<entry>phoned-2Sg</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;How many of your mother&apos;s friends did you call?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The type of facts presented in this subsection leads to the conclusion that the position of the (potential) pied-piper in the relevant phrase is a major factor in determining whether pied-piping will or will not be possible. Furthermore, the descriptive generalization emerging from the data so far is that specifiers and heads of phrases are able to induce pied-piping, whereas complements and adjuncts are not pied-pipers. (For further elaboration of this generalization and for proposed accounts, see <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: ch. 4 and <link rid="ss12 ss13">sections 3.3 and 4</link>.)</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="2">
<heading id="h11" level="2">3.3&ensp;Category type of the pied-piped phrase</heading>
<p>An additional dimension of variation with respect to pied-piping phenomena involves the category type of phrases undergoing pied-piping. Even if we limit ourselves to the core set of category types that were assumed already during the GB period, we find that not all phrasal categories undergo the same range of pied-piping phenomena; rather there seem to exist some category-specific differences in pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement.</p>
<p>The case of DPs, APs, and AdvPs is the most straightforward. They can get pied-piped under <i>wh</i>-movement, as expected based on what we saw in <link rid="ss8 ss11">sections 3.1 and 3.2</link>. Specifically, the general case of pied-piping attested both in <i>wh</i>-questions and in relatives shown in <link rid="ss8">section 3.1</link> (where the pied-piping <i>wh</i>-word is a specifier or a head) occurs consistently with all three of these categories. Furthermore, in languages like English, which exhibit Left Branch Condition effects, they get pied-piped obligatorily.</p>
<listgroup id="l6" type="1">
<li>
<number>(32) </number>
<p><b>Pied-piping of DP:</b>
</p>
<p>She wondered &lsqb;<i>whose</i> closest friends&rsqb; you had invited to the party.</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(33) </number>
<p><b>Pied-piping of AP:</b>
</p>
<p>I wonder &lsqb;<i>how</i> proud of his achievements&rsqb; is your brother?</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(34) </number>
<p><b>Pied-piping of AdvP:</b>
</p>
<p>I wonder &lsqb;<i>how</i> well&rsqb; she remembers her early childhood.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>The cases of PPs and of clausal projections with respect to pied-piping options are far more complex, and they exhibit some patterns that are unexpected under the generalizations reached in <link rid="ss11">section 3.2</link> above.</p>
<p>Regarding PPs, the major phenomenon to observe involves the existence of standard (not stylistically restricted) pied-piping of PP by a <i>wh</i>-word or phrase in its complement position, instantiated in <i>wh</i>-questions as well as in the various types of relatives; this is in contrast with the case of the other phrase types discussed, where complements were not pied-pipers. The pied-piping of Ps involves significant language particular variation: some languages, such as those permitting preposition stranding (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 50 - Pied-Piping.xml" type="file">chapter 50</externallink></related>), e.g., the Scandinavian languages and (colloquial versions of) English, exhibit pied-piping by the complement of P only optionally, and in certain cases not at all, whereas in a wide variety of other languages, including German, French, Spanish, and Russian, complements of P pied-pipe obligatorily under <i>wh</i>-movement. Pied-piping of PP by a <i>wh</i>-complement is illustrated below from German and Dutch.</p>
<listgroup id="l7" type="1">
<li>
<number>(35)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>PP-pied-piping by complement:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Mit</entry>
<entry><i>wem</i>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>gesprochen?</entry>
<entry>German</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>with</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>spoken</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Van</entry>
<entry><i>wie</i>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>heb</entry>
<entry>je</entry>
<entry>die</entry>
<entry>schaar</entry>
<entry>gekregen?</entry>
<entry>Dutch</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>from</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>have</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>those</entry>
<entry>scissors</entry>
<entry>gotten</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>(<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 124)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Beyond the surprising behavior of complements of P, pied-piping by <i>wh</i>-elements in Spec is possible (though contrary to Ross&apos;s Left Branch Condition, is not obligatory), and pied-piping by modifiers is impossible, as expected based on the discussion in <link rid="ss11">section 3.2</link>:</p>
<listgroup id="l8" type="1">
<li>
<number>(36) </number>
<p><b>PP-pied-piping by Spec:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&lsqb;<i>How many</i> feet behind the house&rsqb; should I put the table?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Cf. &lsqb;<i>How many</i>&rsqb; feet should I put the table behind the house?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(<link rid="b2">Emonds 1976</link>: 184)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(37)</number>
<p><b>PP-pied-piping by Modifier:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">*&lsqb;Where into the kitchen&rsqb; did John go?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">Cf. He went &lsqb;downstairs &lsqb;into the kitchen&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Wohin</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>die</entry>
<entry>K&uuml;che&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>ist</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>gegangen?</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>where</entry>
<entry>into</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>kitchen</entry>
<entry>is</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>gone</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col6" nameend="col9">(<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 125)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>What is left to examine now is the behavior of the extended projections of V (in the sense of <link rid="b32">Grimshaw 1991</link>), i.e., VP and the clausal functional projections postulated above VP. With respect to these clausal projections, we will limit our discussion here to the highest canonical clausal projection, namely to CP. (On proposals involving pied-piping of IP, in particular to Spec of CP, see, for instance, <link rid="b33">Sportiche&apos;s 1995</link> argument from French intonational yes&ndash;no questions, and <link rid="b9">Koopman&apos;s 1996</link>; <link rid="b7">1997</link> IP-pied-piping account of subject-<i>wh</i> extraction in English.)</p>
<p>Let us consider first the question of whether VPs undergo pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement. Notice that under the VP-internal subject hypothesis, the external argument of V originates in the Spec of VP and it undergoes A-movement to Spec of IP (at least in languages like English). This means that the Spec of VP is filled by a trace, hence it cannot be tested for whether a <i>wh</i>-element in it could or could not pied-pipe the VP under <i>wh</i>-movement. As for other positions in the VP, consider the set of data given below in (38) and (39) (<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 123&ndash;124); what it demonstrates is that neither a <i>wh</i>-complement nor a <i>wh</i>-adjunct may induce pied-piping of a VP.</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col5">*&lsqb;Read <i>what</i>&rsqb; has John?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Was</i>
</entry>
<entry>gelesen&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>Hans?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry></entry>
<entry>what</entry>
<entry>read</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">*&lsqb;<i>How</i> closed the door&rsqb; has John?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Wie</i>
</entry>
<entry>die</entry>
<entry>T&uuml;r</entry>
<entry>geschlossen&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hat</entry>
<entry>Hans?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry></entry>
<entry>how</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>door</entry>
<entry>closed</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The issue of pied-piping of clauses under <i>wh</i>-movement presents a less uniform situation; in the literature there are some well-known, though controversial, claims regarding particular languages, e.g. Basque and German, permitting some varieties of clausal (CP) pied-piping. In this section we will present only the basic cases, focusing on English, and return to discuss some further more controversial, and language-specific cases in the overview of CP-pied-piping in <link rid="ss20">section 4.5</link>.</p>
<p>As noted in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>: 126) based on examples from English (non-echo) <i>wh</i>-questions with a finite CP complement, such as (40) below, pied-piping of CP by a <i>wh</i>-element in its IP complement is impossible, irrespective of whether the <i>wh</i>-phrase occupies Spec, complement or adjunct position in the IP.</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;That <i>who</i> met John&rsqb; did Mary know?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;That John met <i>who</i>(<i>m</i>)&rsqb; did Mary know?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;That John left <i>when</i>&rsqb; did Mary know? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similarly, pied-piping of infinitival CPs by a <i>wh</i>-element in IP is also impossible, as shown below by the (non-echo) question in (41). The same is true for standard (not stylistically marked) relative clauses as well. (On the case of non-standard extensive pied-piping in the stylistically marked, literary versions of relatives in English introduced in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link> above, which includes also certain instances of clausal pied-piping, see <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>.)</p>
<p>(41) *&lsqb;To meet <i>who</i>(<i>m</i>)&rsqb; would Mary be very happy?</p>
<p>Finally, turning to the important issue of whether a <i>wh</i>-element occupying the Spec position in CP may or may not act as a pied-piper for the whole CP, consider the following:</p>
<listgroup id="l9" type="1">
<li>
<number>(42)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>CP-pied-piping by Spec:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">*&lsqb;<i>Which</i> boys to invite&rsqb; did John suggest?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Wer</i>
</entry>
<entry>ein</entry>
<entry>Buch</entry>
<entry>gelesen</entry>
<entry>hat&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>wusste</entry>
<entry>Hans?</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>book</entry>
<entry>read</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>knew</entry>
<entry>Hans</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>(from <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>: 127))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>This type of data seem to indicate clearly that no CP pied-piping is possible under <i>wh</i>-movement, at least in English, and according to <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>) claim, in the other Germanic languages either (on a controversial case of clausal pied-piping in German by a relative pronoun, see <link rid="ss20">section 4.5</link>). However, it is worth noting here that English still exhibits a construction which at least prima facie suggests that this statement may turn out to be too strong. Thus, although subject to a number of hitherto unexplored limitations, the sentence-type exemplified in (43) below might appear to instantiate CP-pied-piping by a <i>wh</i>-specifier in English (this case was originally pointed out by Anna Szabolcsi (p.c.), and was referred to in relation to the analysis of so-called partial <i>wh</i>-movement constructions in <link rid="b34">Horvath (1998</link>, n. 10) and <link rid="b35">Kayne (2000</link>: ch. 13, n. 107).</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Where</i> did he go&rsqb;, do you think?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Who</i> left last night&rsqb;, do you think? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Whether cases like (43a, b) indeed instantiate CP-pied-piping is however far from unequivocal. The presence of main clause properties in the allegedly pied-piped embedded CP, such as the requirement of being tensed (cf. (42a) and (43)), and most prominently the obligatory application of subject-auxiliary inversion (as in (43a)), suggests an alternative analysis involving no clausal pied-piping (on &lsquo;root phenomena&rsquo; in embedded vs. main clause contexts, see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 23 - Embedded Root Phenomena.xml" type="file">chapter 23</externallink></related>). Under the latter alternative, the bracketed clause in (43a, b) is the main clause, and the rest of the sentence (<i>do you think</i>) would be taken to be a parenthetical. However, until an in-depth systematic investigation of the topic is undertaken, no firm conclusion can be reached regarding the proper analysis of this curious construction type.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss13" level="1">
<heading id="h12" level="1">4&ensp;Issues and proposed analyses</heading>
<p>In this section we will approach the various observations regarding pied-piping effects under <i>wh</i>-movement reviewed in <link rid="ss7">section 3</link> in a systematic theory-bound manner. The section will present and discuss proposals aimed at developing a comprehensive account that could integrate the descriptive generalizations reached with respect to <i>wh</i>-movements, together with other known pied-piping phenomena, into a general theory of pied-piping, possibly involving the interaction of several independent modules of UG. Within the framework of the P&amp;P conception of UG, and in particular, assuming versions of this theory that have emerged since the early 1990s, it is helpful to organize the discussion of the observed pied-piping effects and the proposed accounts around the following two general questions:</p>
<listgroup id="l10" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>Given that by definition, any movement potentially involving pied-piping is (under current assumptions) driven by the need for some element smaller than the pied-piped phrase (e.g., a lexical item, or a formal feature) to be placed in a new position, what are the conditions that enable the pied-piping operation to take place, i.e., what makes movement of the larger constituent containing the element actually driving the movement operation possible in the first place?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>How does the particular structure arising from the application or non-application of a pied-piping operation satisfy or violate assumed general well-formedness conditions on the output of syntactic computations (such as the requirements on operator-variable chains, the Bijection Principle, the theta criterion, or the identification of phonologically null elements)?</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>The primary focus of our discussion below will be question (i), and aspects of question (ii) will be brought in only to the extent that they directly bear on the particular empirical phenomena under discussion. Otherwise, issues such as for instance what mechanisms are needed for assigning correct interpretations at the LF-interface (with respect to anaphor binding, scope, etc.) to elements within pied-piped structures, and specifically the issue of the need for and the nature of a reconstruction mechanism, will not be addressed (on the latter, see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 54 - Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope.xml" type="file">chapter 54</externallink></related>).</p>
<p>Based on the facts presented in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link>, it is clear that the answer to question (i) cannot be that pied-piping is free, i.e., that any moving element can pied-pipe any phrase dominating it. But at the outset, it also needs to be noted that the patterns of occurrence of pied-piping do not seem to be adequately accounted for based on the initially appealing idea that it is a default mechanism, namely, that pied-piping applies if and only if extraction of the smaller element driving the movement is prohibited. This type of hypothesis turns out to run into problems when we consider, for instance, cases where either a <i>wh</i>-element in Spec position of a phrase or the whole phrase itself may undergo the same movement operation, without resulting in any stylistic markedness; see, e.g., the case of English PPs with a <i>wh</i>-specifier as &lsqb;&lsqb;<i>how many</i> feet&rsqb; behind <i>the house</i>&rsqb; in example (36) above, or pied-piping options of DPs by <i>wh</i>-specifiers in languages such as Russian, where the Left Branch Condition seems not to apply, and extraction of the specifier is permitted. Furthermore, the above idea of &lsquo;free pied-piping as default&rsquo; is also shown inadequate by cases where, although the <i>wh</i>-elements occur within extraction islands such as, e.g., complex-NPs, coordinate structures, adjuncts, etc., yet the dominating large phrase cannot get pied-piped, in spite of the unavailability of <i>wh</i>-extraction (see e.g. (44b)):</p>
<listgroup id="l11" type="1">
<li><number>(44)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>Adjunct island:</b>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*They knew <i>what</i> he felt guilty &lsqb;after saying <i>t</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*They knew &lsqb;after saying <i>what</i>&rsqb; he felt guilty. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Thus, there clearly seem to be some substantive structure-sensitive prerequisites for pied-piping to take place.</p>
<subsection id="ss14" level="2">
<heading id="h13" level="2">4.1&ensp;What can pied-pipe a phrase?</heading>
<p>A logical starting point for the exploration of the essence of pied-piping, and one that also reflects the main direction of current research on the subject (such as in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: ch. 4; <link rid="b9 b7">Koopman 1996, 1997</link>) is provided by the initial descriptive generalization (see (45)) reached in <link rid="ss11">section 3.2</link> regarding the structural position of pied-pipers vs. non-pied-pipers within their phrase (manifested most transparently in the case of DPs and APs, as, e.g., (25a, b), (27) vs. (26a, b), (28&ndash;30)):</p>
<listgroup id="l12" type="1">
<li>
<number>(45)&ensp;</number>
<p>Given a phrase XP,</p>
<p>
<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>the head X and the specifier YP are pied-pipers for XP;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>complements of X and modifiers (adjuncts) are not pied-pipers for XP. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Some of the empirical phenomena reviewed in <link rid="ss7">section 3</link> represent apparently major deviations from this primary generalization. Such are, obviously, the stylistically marked heavy pied-piping cases attested in relative clauses in English (shown in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>), more importantly, the widely attested case of PP pied-piping by a complement of P, and also the case of CPs (shown in <link rid="ss12">section 3.3</link>), as well as the case of DPs in free relatives (in <link rid="ss10">section 3.1.2</link>), both of which appear not to get pied-piped even by their specifier. Each of these apparent deviations from the generalization in (45) will be reexamined and dealt with in <link rid="ss16 ss19 ss20">sections 4.3, 4.4, and 4.5</link>.</p>
<p>Further exploration of the statement in (45), reveals that it is not fully adequate in its present form even for the apparently straightforward DP and AP cases that it was primarily motivated by. Beyond examples such as (25a, b) and (27) representing cases of legitimate pied-piping, consider data of the following type, manifesting additional pied-piping options; such data argue for making the statement of (45) somewhat more general.</p>
<p>(46) They wondered &lsqb;<i>whose</i> daughter&apos;s teacher&rsqb; the school had fired.</p>
<p>In the above cases the pied-piped phrase, namely a DP, has a <i>wh</i>-word in it (<i>whose</i>), however this itself is neither the head nor the specifier of the moved phrase. In (46), the pied-piper <i>whose</i> is the specifier of the specifier of the moved DP. What this suggests is that being a pied-piper for a phrase via the specifier relation, as stated in (45), is a transitive relation, so that also a Spec of a Spec (of a Spec) of a phrase can act as a pied-piper for the phrase. In the following section we will elaborate the core pied-piping generalizations presented above, and discuss proposals for the underlying mechanism from which they may derive.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss15" level="2">
<heading id="h14" level="2">4.2&ensp;The core cases: projection and the Spec&ndash;Head relation</heading>
<p>Conceptually, the generalizations summarized in (45) and amended above based on (46) seem reasonable, given what is known about the various structural positions within phrase structure. Heads project their features, thus giving rise to higher (phrasal) categories, and, consequently, phrases by definition exhibit features of their heads. Thus any feature on a head that may be driving a movement operation is available on the phrase projected from that head, hence the particular movement operation may in principle move the phrase itself, resulting in &lsquo;pied-piping&rsquo; of a phrase by (features of) its head. The only other feature-sharing (agreement) relationship permitted in restrictive theories of phrase structure since <link rid="b18">Chomsky&apos;s <i>Barriers</i> (1986a</link>) is between the specifier and the head of the phrase. This Spec&ndash;Head agreement relation offers an obvious account for pied-piping of a phrase by its Spec, provided the additional assumption that this agreement relation is dynamic in the sense that features of a specifier that the head does not possess may be inherited by this head under the Spec&ndash;Head agreement relation. (For some empirical consequences of this latter assumption, see the discussion of operator features and CP-pied-piping by <i>wh</i> under <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>) analysis in <link rid="ss20">section 4.5</link>, as well as <link rid="b31">Grosu&apos;s (1994</link>) &lsquo;anti-pied-piping&rsquo; effects presented in 4.3.2.)</p>
<p>
<link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>) explicitly formulates the hypothesis that the pied-piped category inherits the feature relevant for the checking relation driving the movement through projection from the head. Furthermore, according to Koopman&apos;s hypothesis, as well as to <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi (2000</link>), a head can acquire such a feature in two ways (or through a combination of these two ways): the feature may originate in Spec position, and a head may inherit it through (a series of) Spec&ndash;Head agreement relations, assumed to involve a &lsquo;dynamic&rsquo; type of agreement (as illustrated in (47)); alternatively, the head may inherit a feature through head movement, i.e., through a lower head bearing the feature being raised to it (this latter way will be presented in <link rid="ss19">section 4.4</link>, in the context of PP-pied-piping by a complement of P).</p>
<listgroup id="l13" type="1">
<li>
<number>(47) </number>
<p><b>Pied-piping via Spec&ndash;Head agreement:</b>
</p>
<p>XP inherits a feature from its *specifier (where &lsquo;*specifier&rsquo; is the transitive closure of the specifier relation).</p>
<p>E.g.:&ensp;<object id="fu1" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_50_fu1.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu1_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>(<link rid="b7">Koopman 1997</link> and <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi 2000</link>: 41)</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>In this case, ZP, being the specifier of YP, agrees with the head Y; Y&apos;s features are the features of its maximal projection YP. YP itself, being the specifier of XP, agrees with the head X, and features of X are features of its maximal projection XP. Hence XP is able to get pied-piped under movement applying to phrases bearing the feature z.</p>
<p>This type of account, based on mechanisms of feature inheritance and projection, is relevant for all movement operations that are driven by the presence of some syntactically active (formal) feature; its consequences extend both to A-bar movement (operator&ndash;variable) constructions, like the case of <i>wh</i>-movement under discussion, as well as to cases of A-movement, where there is no operator, and the features involved are inflectional ones, such as, e.g., Case and phi-features. What is important to note here though is that the above proposal for deriving the observed core pied-piping generalizations makes sense only if the movements involved are feature driven. If on the other hand, the overt movement of phrases were not driven by needs of feature checking, but rather for instance by an EPP property of some functional heads requiring the merger of a Spec (as proposed in <link rid="b28">Chomsky&apos;s 2000</link> version of the MP which assumes an operation Agree), then the pattern of pied-piping facts above might not be accounted for by the applicability/inapplicability of the movement operation itself, since the latter would not depend on the moved phrase having acquired any particular feature. Thus it would be unclear why the kind of structural position occupied by the <i>wh</i>-morpheme within the moved larger phrase turns out to make a difference for grammaticality. So under the assumption of non-feature-driven movement, the observed differences, such as for instance the well-formedness of a <i>wh</i>-element in the Spec but not in the complement position of the phrase moved to Spec of CP, would have to receive an alternative account.</p>
<p>A possible attempt at such an account, namely, an attempt to derive the pied-piper status of the Spec (of Spec) position in phrases without relying on features, may be based on some independent proposals made with respect to the c-command and binding properties of the Spec position by <link rid="b8">Kayne (1994</link>), and further elaborated by <link rid="b36">Hornstein (1995</link>). In <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>) Antisymmetry theory, specifiers are taken to be an instance of adjunction. This assumption about specifiers, together with a definition of c-command crucially formulated in terms of exclusion (see (48), <link rid="b8">Kayne (1994</link>: 24), has the consequence that a specifier will c-command out of the phrase it is the specifier of. In contrast a complement, as before, will not c-command out of its phrase.</p>
<p>(48) X c-commands Y iff X and Y are categories and X excludes Y and every category that dominates X dominates Y.</p>
<p>This will immediately account, for example, for the traditionally problematic cases of bound interpretation of the pronouns (discussed by <link rid="b37">Reinhart 1983a</link>: 177) in examples like <i><u>Everyone&rsquo;</u>s mother thinks <u>he</u>&apos;s a genius,</i> or <u><i>Nobody</i>
</u><i>&apos;s students should respect <u>him</u>
</i>, where the quantifier appears in Spec of the subject DP. It will predict the contrast with the unavailability of a bound interpretation for the pronoun in otherwise similar cases when the quantifier is in complement position within the subject DP, as in cases like <i>A small part of <u>every article</u> undermined <u>it</u>
</i>, or <i>The election of <u>no one</u> to the Hall of Fame hindered <u>his</u> career</i> (from <link rid="b36">Hornstein 1995</link>: 107). Now notice that the above assumption, namely, that specifiers, and no other positions in the phrase are able to c-command, and hence bind, some element out of that phrase could potentially provide a non-feature-based account for the specifier vs. complement distinction between pied-pipers of <i>wh</i>-moved phrases. The reason is that irrespective of the issue of <i>wh</i>-feature-checking on C, the <i>wh</i>-operator dominated by the phrase moved to Spec of CP position, such as, e.g., <i>whose</i> in <i>Whose article have you read?</i> needs to bind a variable; it needs to bind a corresponding trace within the IP. Assuming the copy theory of movement, such a &lsquo;trace&rsquo; would indeed be available within the lower copy of the moved phrase. Whether this trace can or cannot be bound by the <i>wh</i>-operator dominated by the pied-piped phrase in Spec of CP depends now on whether the position of the <i>wh</i>-operator is such that it c-commands out of the Spec of CP, and hence binds the trace within the IP-internal copy. Assuming, crucially, that no additional (covert) raising of the <i>wh</i>-operator itself is stipulated, a <i>wh</i>-operator appearing in the Spec position of the pied-piped phrase will still be able to bind the corresponding trace in the copy, whereas a <i>wh</i>-operator occurring as a complement of the same phrase will clearly fail to satisfy the requirement of binding the trace in IP, due to failure of c-command.</p>
<p>However, some immediate empirical problems arise in relation to this notion of c-command and its use as an alternative to feature-inheritance accounts for the observed distinctions between positions of <i>wh</i>-pied-pipers vs. <i>wh</i>-non-pied-pipers within phrases. One of these is the fact that, based on <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>) notions of specifier and c-command (48), DP specifiers would be expected to give rise to Condition C effects (in the sense of <link rid="b38">Chomsky&apos;s 1981</link> Binding Theory), namely, disjointness of reference in cases such as (49), and strong crossover, rather than merely mild weak crossover, effects in cases such as (50a). But the (underlined) specifiers of the DPs in (49) and (50a) in fact fail to induce Condition C and strong crossover effects. The absence of strong crossover is demonstrated by the relative acceptability judgment on (50a) contrasting with an uncontroversial strong crossover case (50b) (on the variability and mildness of weak crossover effects manifested by restrictive relative clauses such as (50a), see <link rid="b39">Lasnik and Stowell 1991</link>).</p>
<p>(49) &lsqb;<u>His</u><sub>i</sub> mother&rsqb; thinks that <u>John</u><sub>i</sub> is a genius.</p>
<p>(50)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup>the girl who<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;&lsqb;<u>her</u><sub>i</sub> brother&rsqb; has hit <i>t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*the girl &lsqb;whose<sub>i</sub> brother&rsqb; &lsqb;<u>she</u><sub>i</sub> has hit &lsqb;<i>t</i><sub>i</sub> &lsqb; &rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The facts in (49&ndash;50) thus raise serious doubts about these specifiers of DP being able to c-command into the clause, and, more generally, about the claim that specifiers can c-command outside of the maximal XP that they are specifiers of. Incidentally, in contrast to this &lsquo;c-command out of Spec&rsquo; proposal, the feature-inheritance account formulated in (43) for pied-piping may also provide a way to approach the problematic discrepancy noted here between the variable-binding behavior of quantificational specifiers (as in <i>Everyone&apos;s mother thinks that <u>he</u> is a genius</i>), on the one hand, and the lack of A-binding behavior of non-quantificational specifiers (see (49)), on the other. A potential account reconciling the two structurally parallel cases may be based on the reasonable assumption that while operator features &ndash; such as &lsqb;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; or &lsqb;Distributive&rsqb; &ndash; can be freely inherited by the dominating XP via the Spec&ndash;Head configuration (as in (47)), referential properties of a DP in Spec, such as those relevant for Condition C effects, cannot be inherited since the dominating DP has independent referential properties of its own.</p>
<p>Another empirical problem arising with respect to the purely operator binding-based (i.e., c-command-based) account of the pied-piping generalizations (45) considered above involves the unexpected discrepancy manifested by adjuncts (modifiers) of DP between the possibility of binding a pronoun and being a pied-piper (see (51a, b)); this is in contrast to the parallel we noted in the case of specifiers (being both binders of pronouns outside of DP and pied-pipers of DP) and complements (being neither binders of pronouns outside of DP nor pied-pipers). While in (51a) the adjunct in the DP seems to be able to bind a pronoun outside its phrase, in a parallel configuration in the embedded clause of (51b), pied-piping by the same adjunct in DP is still not acceptable.</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Someone from <i>every small town</i>&rsqb; hates <i>it.</i> (<link rid="b36">Hornstein 1995</link>: 107)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*We wondered &lsqb;&lsqb;someone from <i>which small town</i>/<i>where</i>&rsqb; Bill met&rsqb;. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Some general questions to consider regarding this alternative, non-feature-based, account explored above are these. Is it actually sufficient for a fuller range of pied-piping cases, and, in particular, for <i>wh</i>-adjuncts (see the contrast in (51a, b)), which were shown to act systematically as non-pied-pipers? Are the assumptions made earlier regarding the way operator&ndash;variable chains are created independently supported? Do they indeed make the feature-inheritance hypothesis of pied-piping redundant, or do these two mechanisms coexist, at least in some of the constructions? Answers to these questions would need to be established based on further investigation and broader theoretical considerations, most of which are beyond the scope of this study.</p>
<p>Returning to the main line of investigation of the core pied-piping generalizations (45), namely, to the one based on the hypothesis of feature-driven movement together with feature &lsquo;inheritance&rsquo; via the Spec&ndash;Head relation such as formulated in (47), let us consider a related empirical issue not addressed so far. Other things being equal, the proposal predicts that all specifiers will be able to pied-pipe the phrase they are specifiers of. However, <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>, p. 133), in his influential work on pied-piping, calls attention to a set of facts that pose a particularly striking problem for this prediction. It involves the pied-piping behavior of English gerundive nominals with a <i>wh</i>-element in the Spec of DP position, and their contrast with parallel non-gerundive DPs, such as derived nominals, whose lexical head is N (such data were originally observed by <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>: section 4.4.2)). After presenting the relevant facts (see (52&ndash;53)), we will discuss some major aspects of Webelhuth&apos;s theory of pied-piping which enabled him to derive this phenomenon, as well as could be extended to some of the other known pied-piping generalizations.</p>
<p>(52)&ensp;<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i> loud playing of the piano&rsqb; I disliked was a student.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The boy &lsqb;<i>whose</i> playing the piano loudly&rsqb; I disliked was a student. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(53)&ensp;<object id="tu35" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu35_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder &lsqb;<i>whose</i> harsh attack on Dukakis&rsqb; the Democratic voters resented most.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder &lsqb;<i>whose</i> harshly attacking Dukakis&rsqb; the Democratic voters resented most. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As shown by the unacceptability of (52b) and (53b), DPs that contain gerundive nominals cannot get pied-piped by their <i>wh</i>-specifier. This is a puzzling phenomenon in light of the fact that specifiers were found to be the prototypical pied-pipers, and the theoretical proposals outlined above had conceptually plausible ways of incorporating this (apparent) generalization. The impossibility of pied-piping manifested by gerundive nominals is more surprising than some other known deviations from the core generalizations given in (45), since unlike, for instance, the case of PPs being pied-piped by complements of P, in cases like (52b&minus;53b) we are dealing with a DP, which is the very category that provided the primary motivation for the pied-piping generalizations. Notice also that their derived nominal counterparts in (52a) and (53a), i.e., parallel DPs but, crucially, exhibiting a lexical N as their head, do get pied-piped by the same <i>wh</i>-specifier (<i>whose</i>).</p>
<p>In view of these facts, <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>: ch. 4) develops the hypothesis that the crucial distinction between specifiers (of non-clausal categories) that are pied-pipers and those that are non-pied-pipers is a consequence of the theta criterion. In fact, Webelhuth proposes and derives the following broader descriptive generalization within his modular approach to pied-piping.</p>
<p>(54) A theta-marked phrase is not a pied-piper.</p>
<p>This hypothesis has obvious potential consequences also for the (non-)pied-piper status of complements, but here we will concentrate on (a) how (54) itself is claimed to be derived from Webelhuth&apos;s feature percolation or projection mechanism in interaction with principles of the GB theory, and (b) how it is claimed to account for the gerund&ndash;non-gerund contrast with respect to pied-piping by specifiers. (We will return to the consequences of (54) for complements in <link rid="ss19">section 4.4</link>.)</p>
<p>Webelhuth&apos;s proposed account of pied-piping is presented in the general context of his theory of syntactic saturation, more specifically, of the projection of the complementation, specification, and modification relations. In this broader framework dealing with the projection of syntactic properties in phrase structure, he also postulates conventions of feature percolation or inheritance (similarly to <link rid="b7">Koopman 1997</link> and <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi 2000</link>). However, unlike the more restrictive exclusively Spec&ndash;Head relation-based mechanism in (47) above, Webelhuth&apos;s theory stipulates that (operator) features can be inherited not only from specifiers but also from complements. Notice that since no features are assumed to be inherited under the modification relation in Webelhuth&apos;s theory, the fact that modifiers can never be pied-pipers is predicted in this system too. What is relevant for us at this point is that specifiers are assumed to be able to percolate their features to their mother nodes, unless the head projection of the phrase (i.e., X&prime;) has that particular feature (possibly inherited from the complement). Importantly, the descriptive generalization (54) is based on the output representations of this feature-percolation process being &lsquo;filtered&rsquo; by independent principles of UG, and, in particular, the Theta Criterion; Webelhuth&apos;s formulation of the relevant principles makes use of the notion of &lsquo;syntactic argument&rsquo;, which in turn involves the notion &lsquo;operator feature&rsquo; (crucially, the latter is used also in the definition of &lsquo;syntactic operator&rsquo;).</p>
<listgroup id="l14" type="1">
<li>
<number>(55)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>The Theta Criterion</b> (<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 148)</p>
<p>
<object id="tu36" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu36_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>(i)</entry>
<entry>Every syntactic argument occurs in exactly one chain that terminates in a theta position.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(ii)</entry>
<entry>Every theta position terminates a chain that is headed by exactly one syntactic argument. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(56)&ensp;</number>
<p>&alpha; is a <i>syntactic argument</i> only if</p>
<p>
<object id="tu37" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu37_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a. </entry>
<entry>&alpha; is a maximal projection </entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b. </entry>
<entry>&alpha; is not expletive, and </entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&alpha; does not carry any operator features. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<number>(57) </number>
<p>&alpha; is an operator feature iff &alpha; &isin; &lcub;&lsqb;&plus;WH&rsqb;, &lsqb;&plus;Rel&rsqb;&rcub;.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Based on the above assumptions, Webelhuth&apos;s account for the (alleged) generalization (54) goes as follows. The basic condition for a phrase to get pied-piped (under A-bar movements, like <i>wh</i>-movement, which his discussion is concerned with) is that it has to receive an operator feature by percolation from its specifier or complement. So in order to be a pied-piper, a specifier (say the DP <i>whose</i>) would need to percolate an operator feature (&lsqb;&plus;WH&rsqb;) up to its mother node (e.g., to the nominals in (52&ndash;53)). But no specifier or complement that is able to do that, namely, no specifier or complement that carries an operator feature, can be a member of a theta chain according to Webelhuth&apos;s formulation. The reason is that the Theta Criterion (55) requires that heads of theta chains be syntactic arguments, and according to his definition of syntactic argument in (56), a syntactic argument must not carry any operator feature. Thus, he concludes that no phrase that receives a theta role can be a pied-piper (since it cannot bear an operator feature without violating the Theta Criterion).</p>
<p>Given these assumptions, Webelhuth accounts for the observed contrast in the pied-piping options of DPs with gerundives vs. DPs with lexical NPs on the basis of the independently motivated (though not uncontroversial) claim that, while the specifier of a gerundive DP is theta-marked, the specifier of a derived nominal, or any other non-gerundive DP, crucially, is not theta-marked. Webelhuth supports his claim about this theta-marking distinction between gerunds and non-gerunds by observations such as for instance the contrast between *&lsqb;<i>yesterday&apos;s attacking Dukakis</i>&rsqb; and &lsqb;<i>yesterday&apos;s attack on Dukakis</i>&rsqb; (for further relevant discussion of theta-marking in nominals, see, e.g., <link rid="b17">Abney 1987</link>; <link rid="b40">Grimshaw 1990</link>; <link rid="b41">Kratzer 1996</link>). So the unacceptability of the pied-piping of gerunds by a <i>wh</i>-Spec illustrated in (52b) and (53b) is attributed by Webelhuth to a violation of the Theta Criterion; the external theta role assigned by the gerund is associated with no well-formed theta chain (due to the lack of a syntactic argument heading the chain).</p>
<p>The way generalization (54) follows in Webelhuth&apos;s system is not very natural conceptually; for instance, the reference to &ldquo;not carrying any operator features&rdquo; in the definition of &ldquo;syntactic argument&rdquo; (see (56c)) is quite ad hoc, since apart from aiming to derive (54), it may just as well be replaced by &lsquo;not being a syntactic operator&rsquo; (being a syntactic operator and being an element carrying an operator feature are crucially kept distinct in the proposed system). If (56c) were restated this way, the Theta Criterion would no longer have the consequence that a theta-marked phrase cannot be a pied-piper. Thus the real issue to consider is whether the generalization in (54) is correct empirically, i.e., whether theta-marked phrases indeed never act as pied-pipers. In <link rid="ss19">section 4.4</link> we will return to the issue of the putative correlation between theta-marking and being/not being a pied-piper, in the context of a discussion of pied-piping by complements.</p>
<p>Regarding the specific account Webelhuth&apos;s hypothesis offers for the contrast between gerundive and non-gerundive nominals, one relevant consideration in favor of finding an alternative, non-theta-theory-based account (see the discussion of (58) below) is that the degree of unacceptability of examples like (52b) and (53b) reported by speakers is very different; it is far less severe than in other cases standardly attributed to violations of the Theta Criterion, specifically, e.g., when a theta chain is headed by an expletive.</p>
<p>Finally, consider an additional set of relevant observations about pied-piping of gerunds, cited in an unrelated context by <link rid="b42">Culicover (1999</link>: 97); these data represent judgments distinct in a suggestive way from those in (52b&minus;53b):</p>
<p>(58)&ensp;<object id="tu38" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu38_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Who</i> solving the problem&rsqb; were you thinking about?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Cf. We were thinking about &lsqb;Mary solving the problem&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Whose</i> solving the problem&rsqb; were you thinking about?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Whose</i> solving of the problem&rsqb; were you thinking about? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The acceptability of pied-piping in (58b) indicated by Culicover contradicts the judgments that Webelhuth cites for parallel gerunds with a possessive (<i>whose</i>) as their specifier. What is more revealing is that gerunds do exhibit a prohibition against being pied-piped by a <i>wh</i>-specifier in Culicover&apos;s dialect too, as shown by (58a). However, this holds only for accusative-marked subjects of gerunds but not for the possessive ones. This difference represented in (58a) vs. (58b, c) suggests that at least in this variety of English, and perhaps more generally, the non-pied-piper behavior of specifiers of gerunds may be related to these specifiers occurring lower in the functional layer of the nominal than the Spec of the top (DP) projection.</p>
<p>Possessive specifiers of non-gerundive nominals occur in all dialects as the Spec of the top functional projection of the nominal (DP), hence their ability to percolate their <i>wh</i>-feature to the DP node. In contrast, at least accusative marked, i.e., non-possessive, specifiers of gerunds, and possibly in some dialects also morphologically possessive specifiers of gerunds, would appear as the Spec of a functional projection that is not the topmost one in the nominal. Specifically, either gerunds have an additional outer layer of projection compared to non-gerundive DPs (as suggested in <link rid="b8">Kayne 1994</link>: 135, n. 18), or the specifier <i>who</i>/<i>whose</i> of gerunds is a Spec of some functional complement of D. In either case, the <i>wh</i>-feature of such a specifier could not be inherited by the maximal nominal phrase under the restrictive feature inheritance mechanism based on Spec&ndash;Head agreement.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="2">
<heading id="h15" level="2">4.3&ensp;Some other effects</heading>
<p>This section will address two types of pied-piping phenomenon, introduced earlier in <link rid="ss9 ss10">sections 3.1.1 and 3.1.2</link>, which prima facie constitute major deviations, in two opposing directions, from the core pied-piping generalizations and the corresponding theoretical proposals presented in <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link> above. The discussion will demonstrate, however, that, arguably, each of these cases is attributable to the effects of independent factors and does not stem from the pied-piping mechanism itself.</p>
<subsection id="ss17" level="3">
<heading id="h16" level="3">4.3.1&ensp;Relative clauses and the topicalization proposal</heading>
<p>As shown in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>, English (lexically headed) relatives, and in particular non-restrictive relatives, seem to permit a curious, much more extensive pied-piping process than what one finds in other <i>wh</i>-constructions and in other Germanic languages. Among the relevant data we find, for instance, complements of DPs and APs that are able to pied-pipe their phrase (see (59), reproduced from <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>). Such pied-piping is not possible in the rest of <i>wh</i>-constructions (<i>wh</i>-interrogatives, exclamatives, etc.), and indeed it would be excluded both under the Spec&ndash;Head agreement based feature inheritance hypothesis (47) of <link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>), and also under <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>) system (in the latter, due to the theta marked nature of these complements).</p>
<p>(59)&ensp;<object id="tu39" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu39_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Reports &lsqb;the height of the lettering on the covers of <i>which</i>&rsqb; the government prescribes should be abolished.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>He is a linguist &lsqb;articles by <i>whom</i>&rsqb; the editors always reject.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>This is the kind of woman &lsqb;proud of <i>whom</i>&rsqb; I could never be. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that this type of data include the cases that led <link rid="b1">Ross (1986</link>) to propose the Pied-Piping Convention in the first place, already as early as <link rid="b2">Emonds&apos;s (1976</link>) it was suggested that these particular instances of apparent pied-piping constitute a special, stylistically marked phenomenon which, contrary to Ross&apos;s view, should in fact not be taken to be derived by the same grammatical device as the other cases of <i>wh</i>-pied-piping, which occur irrespective of construction type. Specifically, <link rid="b2">Emonds (1976</link>: 187) claimed that these cases (like (59)) fall outside the domain of grammar proper and proposed that the pied-piping processes involved in them belong to the stylistic component (as defined in <link rid="b43">Banfield 1973</link>). As a reason for this claim, he points to the &ldquo;marginal&rdquo; acceptability status of this particular subtype of pied-piping data. (On the occurrence of such pied-piping in non-restrictive and restrictive relatives, see the discussion of examples (21) in <link rid="ss9">section 3.1.1</link>, and for the proposal of topicalization as the source for these, see <link rid="b44">Emonds 1979</link>.)</p>
<p>Later, in the context of his general account of pied-piping presented within the framework of the GB theory, <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>) followed a conceptually similar path regarding these stylistically marked pied-piping cases. Recall that pied-piping of a phrase by its theta-marked complement (as, e.g., in (59)) or specifier was hypothesized by Webelhuth to be excluded, as we noted in our discussion of gerunds in <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link>. Webelhuth&apos;s considerations in favor of analyzing cases like (59) as irrelevant for the theory of pied-piping, and hence in favor of maintaining his pied-piping theory excluding them, were the following: (a) the phenomenon is English-particular, i.e., is limited to only one among all the Germanic languages; (b) it is attested in only one construction type, namely, in relative clauses (and for some speakers only in non-restrictive ones); and (c) it belongs to a &ldquo;literary&rdquo; style of English and is felt to be &ldquo;foreign to natural colloquial speech&rdquo; (pointed out by Webelhuth, citing Jespersen). Given his conclusion that the pied-piping mechanism should not be extended to derive these &ldquo;unusual&rdquo; cases, to avoid the obvious overgeneration problem, Webelhuth develops an account for these stylistically marked sentences with apparent pied-piping based on a topicalization analysis, suggested originally by <link rid="b44">Emonds (1979</link>). According to Webelhuth, these phenomena fall outside the core grammar (in the sense of <link rid="b38">Chomsky&apos;s 1981</link> core vs. periphery). He claims that the large phrase containing the <i>wh</i>-relative pronoun undergoes topicalization, and furthermore that this <i>wh</i>-word occurring within this preposed phrase receives interpretation as an indexical pronoun in these &ldquo;exceptional&rdquo; constructions. This option is available, he claims, due to the basic similarity in the semantic effects of relative and indexical pronouns (both may involve the formation of an open sentence and its predication of a referent). Thus the analysis draws a parallel between the relation of the relative pronoun (<i>whom</i>) to the head of the relative (<i>his wife</i>) in (60a) and that of the personal pronoun (<i>her</i>) to its discourse antecedent (<i>his wife</i>) in (60b) (see <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 131). It should be noted here that Webelhuth&apos;s proposal fails to offer an account for the impossibility of using a non-<i>wh</i> pronoun (<i>her</i>) instead of <i>whom</i> in English relative clauses such as (60a), and, even more significantly, the impossibility of using a <i>wh</i>-form (<i>whom</i>) as an alternative for the definite pronoun (<i>her</i>) in cases such as (60b) (the latter option appears to be excluded cross-linguistically). These distributional facts would need to be regarded as manifestations of some hitherto unspecified purely morphological variation in the realization of pronouns.</p>
<p>(60)&ensp;<object id="tu40" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu40_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><i>His wife</i> &lsqb;proud of <i>whom</i>&rsqb; he has never been.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><i>His wife</i> is intelligent. But &lsqb;proud of <i>her</i>&rsqb; he has never been. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Under this proposal, the reason why such &ldquo;exceptional&rdquo; pied-piping may arise in the case of relatives but not, for instance, in interrogatives is that the <i>wh</i>-words in the latter are logical operators that restrict the range of a variable, not variables that get bound. Hence they are not able to take on the function of anaphoric pronouns, in contrast to relative pronouns, for which this is more feasible.</p>
<p>As for the observed preference &ndash; and, according to <link rid="b44 b29">Emonds (1979, 1985</link>), the actual limitation &ndash; for this kind of pied-piping to occur only in non-restrictive, rather than restrictive, relatives (see (21a, b, c)), there are at least two approaches to be considered. Assuming the topicalization-based account of non-core pied-piping, <link rid="b44">Emonds (1979</link>) attributes its non-occurrence in restrictive relatives directly to the (alleged) root nature of topicalization (on root transformations, see <link rid="b2">Emonds (1976</link>) and <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 23 - Embedded Root Phenomena.xml" type="file">chapter 23</externallink></related>). Since under his approach non-restrictive relatives are root clauses, he predicts that these, but not restrictive relatives, will permit topicalization and hence the occurrence of the above pied-piping phenomenon. Another proposal that can draw the relevant distinction between non-restrictive and restrictive relatives, and moreover, do so without resorting to the problematic claim of topicalization being a root phenomenon, may be based on <link rid="b39">Lasnik and Stowell&apos;s (1991</link>) findings regarding weak crossover effects in various A-bar movement constructions. They observe a contrast between the presence of weak crossover effects &ndash; i.e., the unavailability of a bound variable construal for a pronoun &ndash; in restrictive relatives (as e.g. in <i>the</i>/<i>every man</i><sub>i</sub><i> who</i><sub>i</sub><i> his</i><sub>i</sub><i> mother loves t</i><sub>i</sub>) and the absence of weak crossover in non-restrictive relatives (as, e.g., in <i>Gerald</i><sub>i</sub><i>, who</i><sub>i</sub><i> his</i><sub>i</sub><i> mother loves t</i><sub>i</sub>). Crucially for us, their study motivates an account for the presence vs. absence of weak crossover effects in different A-bar constructions that is based on the logical status of the local A-bar binder of the pronoun: only a true quantifier (ranging over a possibly non-singleton set) gives rise to weak crossover effects, while non-quantificational A-bar binders do not. Given this, notice first that the observed inability of the <i>wh</i>-element of non-restrictive relatives to induce weak crossover effects reinforces Webelhuth&apos;s proposal of deriving the non-core pied-piping cases under discussion from the pronoun-like, i.e., non-quantificational, nature of the <i>wh</i>-element involved, though only as far as non-restrictive relatives are concerned. Furthermore, in light of (a) the presence of weak crossover effects in restrictive relatives, indicating under Lasnik and Stowell&apos;s theory that the <i>wh</i>-element in the latter is in fact quantificational and (b) Webelhuth&apos;s topicalization-based analysis for pied-piping cases as in (59&ndash;60) above, we can make sense of the contrast observed by Emonds between the availability of non-core pied-piping in non-restrictive relatives and its un-availability in restrictive relatives.</p>
<p>In sum, the proposed analysis derives this exceptional pied-piping construction, not as a true relative clause involving (pied-piping) <i>wh</i>-movement, but by the independent operation of topicalization, and, crucially, assigns an interpretation to the resulting structure in analogy to sentences with anaphoric pronouns. As the reason for their stylistically highly marked nature, Webelhuth points to the mismatch that arises between &ldquo;the form of these structures as relative clauses and their interpretation, which applies a semantic rule of discourse anaphora to relative pronouns that usually exclusively fall into the domain of sentence grammar&rdquo; (<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 132).</p>
<p>As evidence for his topicalization proposal, Webelhuth mentions the prediction that if topicalization of a phrase is impossible in a particular clause, then that phrase will not to be able to undergo stylistically marked pied-piping in the corresponding relative clause. This prediction seems to be borne out indeed, as shown by his data demonstrating the correlation between the unacceptability of topicalization in examples like *&lsqb;<i>To leave</i>&rsqb; <i>I want</i> and the unacceptability of the corresponding relative clause *<i>his wife</i> &lsqb;<i>to leave whom</i>&rsqb; <i>he wanted</i> (see <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 131). However, beyond the above type of correlation that may suggest that topicalization is involved in the appearance of stylistically marked pied-piping in relatives, the proposed account, as it stands, makes some broader, and more problematic predictions as well.</p>
<p>Webelhuth&apos;s hypothesis of the interpretation of the relative pronoun in the preposed phrase taking it to be an indexical pronoun with a discourse antecedent suggests that no extra structural or other grammatical constraints will limit its possible positions within the topicalized phrase, and it will occur as freely as an ordinary pronoun would (as, e.g., in (60a) vs. (60b)). Thus, based on the proposal, one would expect that in English any phrase that (a) can undergo topicalization in a clause and (b) contains a relative <i>wh</i>-word should be able to undergo the exceptional pied-piping process under discussion, resulting in a well-formed relative clause in the literary style. However, contrary to this expectation, a variety of phenomena have been observed in the literature indicating the existence of further clear and specific restrictions of an obviously grammatical nature that determine the acceptability status of stylistically marked pied-piping. Thus, consider for instance the contrasts between (61a, b) and (62a&ndash;d) from <link rid="b19">Nanni and Stillings (1978</link>), involving pied-piping data of the stylistically marked kind where it is a preposed clausal constituent, such as an infinitival (vs. finite) CP, a gerundive or an absolute, that contains the relative pronoun (the position of the relative pronoun is varied). Incidentally, notice that these data would uniformly be excluded by <link rid="b1">Ross&apos;s (1986</link>) formulation of the Pied-Piping Convention (given in <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link>).</p>
<p>(61)&ensp;<object id="tu41" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu41_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The elegant parties, &lsqb;to be invited to one of <i>which</i>&rsqb; was a privilege . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The strange man &lsqb;upon seeing <i>whom</i>&rsqb; Mary called the police . . . </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;<object id="tu42" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu42_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*The men, &lsqb;for <i>whom</i> to be invited to the elegant parties&rsqb; was a privilege . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The strange man &lsqb;upon John&apos;s seeing <i>whom</i>&rsqb; Mary called the police . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*The elegant parties, &lsqb;for us to be admitted to one of <i>which</i>&rsqb; was a privilege . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>*The car &lsqb;(the idea) that their son might drive <i>which</i>&rsqb; surprised them . . . </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The descriptive generalizations that emerge from the above data are that the relative pronoun in the preposed &lsquo;pied-piped&rsquo; constituents cannot be a subject, but seems to have to be a complement, and that the preposed constituent itself cannot have a lexical subject, and possibly in addition it cannot have finite Tense (as suggested by <link rid="b45">Cinque 1982</link> and <link rid="b27">Kayne 1984a</link>: 86).</p>
<p>Such data are not discussed at all in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>), even though the existence of this type of clausal pied-piping effects are actually predicted in his system, since clausal arguments as well as adjuncts (such as the ones preposed in (61) and (62)) are able to undergo topicalization. He considers only clausal pied-piping outside of the context of stylistically marked relatives, and based on that concludes that it does not exist in Germanic (see our discussion in <link rid="ss12 ss20">sections 3.3 and in 4.5</link>). The apparently &lsquo;pied-piped&rsquo; clauses above indeed involve no true instances of pied-piping by <i>wh</i>-movement; being stylistically marked and construction specific, they fall under the hypothesis presented above for cases like (59). What is relevant in the present context is that their existence, and, crucially, some specific structural constraints on them (illustrated above) were observed and analyzed in the earlier literature, in particular by <link rid="b19">Nanni and Stillings (1978</link>), <link rid="b45">Cinque (1982</link>), <link rid="b46">Hendrick (1982</link>), <link rid="b27">Kayne (1984a</link>: 186), and <link rid="b20">Ishihara (1984</link>). Furthermore, it is worth noting that Italian, a language that has been shown in <link rid="b45">Cinque (1982</link>) to exhibit pied-piping phenomena in relatives parallel to the stylistically marked cases of English mentioned earlier, also turns out to manifest the structure-based grammaticality contrasts with respect to &lsquo;pied-piped&rsquo; elements in relatives shown above for English.</p>
<p>While the facts in (61&ndash;62) demonstrate that the interpretation of the relative pronoun (occurring within a topicalized phrase) in analogy to indexical pronouns proposed by Webelhuth is clearly not sufficient to account for the stylistically marked pied-piping phenomenon, the source of the constraints manifested is not well understood. There have been several attempts in the literature to treat (at least part of) the relevant phenomena, among them <link rid="b27">Kayne&apos;s (1984a</link>: 185) proposal based on defining a &lsquo;<i>wh</i>-phrase&rsquo; that can occupy the COMP (i.e., &lsqb;Spec, CP&rsqb;) of the relative clause in terms of the notion of g-projection set of a <i>wh</i>-phrase, <link rid="b45">Cinque&apos;s (1982</link>) anaphor hypothesis, <link rid="b20">Ishihara&apos;s (1984</link>) account based on LF-raising of the <i>wh</i>-word and the ECP, and <link rid="b47">Safir&apos;s (1986</link>) proposal of LF-raising of the relative <i>wh</i>-word to satisfy a locality requirement on R-binding by the head of the relative. However, no comprehensive adequate account has emerged so far, and this stylistically marked pied-piping phenomenon with its pattern of robust grammaticality constraints obviously calls for further investigation of the underlying mechanism(s) that may be responsible for it.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss18" level="3">
<heading id="h17" level="3">4.3.2&ensp;Free relatives and the identification of a <roman>pro</roman> head</heading>
<p>The <i>wh</i>-pied-piping phenomena in (finite) free relatives introduced with respect to English in <link rid="ss10">section 3.1.2</link> represent another initially surprising case of deviation from the pied-piping generalization stated in (45). This deviation involves the opposite direction from the deviation found in the case of overtly headed stylistically marked relatives (discussed in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>): the possible range of pied-piping effects in such free relatives is more restricted than what one would expect of pied-piping by a <i>wh</i>-element based on the other <i>wh</i>-constructions. Specifically, the latter construction type was claimed in <link rid="b30">Grosu (1989</link>) not to permit pied-piping even by a <i>wh</i>-specifier (of specifier) of a DP, as shown in (24); in contrast, such pied-piping occurs freely both in interrogatives, and overtly headed relatives.</p>
<p>Notice that the unacceptability of cases like (24b, c) cannot be attributed to some limitation on the &lsquo;size&rsquo; of the preposed <i>wh</i>-constituent permitted in free relatives, in view of the perfect acceptability of examples such as (63), where the <i>wh</i>-element is the head of the preposed &lsquo;large&rsquo; DP:</p>
<p>(63) Mary will buy &lsqb;&lsqb;<i>whichever</i> portraits of friends of hers&rsqb; we can find <i>t</i> for her&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Neither can we dismiss the observed extra restriction on pied-piping in free relatives by attributing the observed unacceptability simply to a Case mismatch, as, e.g., between the possessive form <i>whose</i> in (24b, c) and the free relative itself, the latter needing to be accusative (in (24b)) or nominative (in (24c)). The reason is that the same anti-pied-piping effect shown in (24) is attested also (a) in cases where the Case matching requirement known to hold in free relatives is clearly satisfied (as in the German example (64) cited in <link rid="b31">Grosu 1994</link>: 30), as well as (b) in free relatives permitting non-matching, which occur in particular positions in languages such as Romanian (see example (65), cited by <link rid="b31">Grosu 1994</link>: 34).</p>
<p>(64)&ensp;<object id="tu43" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu43_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Ich</entry>
<entry>bedarf &lsqb;<i>pro</i><sub>Gen</sub>
</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;wessen<sub>Gen</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Bildes&rsqb;<sub>Gen</sub>
</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>auch</entry>
<entry>bedarfst&rsqb;.</entry>
<entry>German</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I</entry>
<entry>need</entry>
<entry> whose</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
<entry>you</entry>
<entry>also</entry>
<entry>need</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col8">&lsquo;I need (the person) whose picture you also need.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(65)&ensp;<object id="tu44" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu44_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*&lsqb;Al cui</entry>
<entry>c&icirc;ine</entry>
<entry>mu&#x015F;c&#x01CE;</entry>
<entry>trec&#x01CE;torii&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>trebuie</entry>
<entry>amendat.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry> whose</entry>
<entry>dog</entry>
<entry>bites</entry>
<entry>the-passers-by</entry>
<entry>must</entry>
<entry>fined</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col7">&lsquo;(The person) whose dog bites those who walk by must be fined.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to <link rid="b31">Grosu (1994</link>: ch. 3), this anti-pied-piping phenomenon is found universally across languages in realis free relatives, and is limited to this construction type. Since it cannot be dismissed as some peripheral idiosyncratic phenomenon, the question arising is, Does this apparent inability of the <i>wh</i>-specifier to pied-pipe its phrase (i.e., the DP) indicate a need to revise the general feature-inheritance mechanism based on the Spec&ndash;Head relation (see (47)) postulated in <link rid="b7">Koopman&apos;s (1997</link>) and <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>) system as the central mechanism underlying pied-piping, or, alternatively, is there some independent factor that creates the special limitations on the output of pied-piping in free relatives? In view of the fact that the apparent impossibility of pied-piping of DP by its specifier is limited to a specific subclass of free relatives (in contrast to all other varieties of <i>wh</i>-constructions), it seems obvious that the more promising option of the two is the latter one, that is to say, finding an account that can derive the phenomenon from independently motivated properties of realis free relatives and general principles of UG, while leaving the pied-piping mechanism itself unaffected.</p>
<p>This was the kind of approach taken by <link rid="b31">Grosu (1994</link>: ch. 3). In the context of a comprehensive study of the various subtypes of free relative, Grosu developed an account the essence of which is that the <i>wh</i>-element coindexed with the <i>pro</i> head of the free relative needs to locally identify this <i>pro</i>, but being in the Spec of the pied-piped DP, rather than being the Spec of CP itself, it is unable to do so. Grosu&apos;s proposal is based on the widely accepted assumptions that (a) realis, i.e., finite, free relatives have a phonologically null head, <i>pro</i>, and (b) the feature-content of <i>pro</i> needs to be identified. It is argued in the study that the only possible identifier for this <i>pro</i> is internal to the free relative; it is the <i>wh</i>-phrase (within the Spec of CP) that serves as its antecedent. Furthermore, the relation between the <i>pro</i> and its identifier in the clause is claimed to be subject to a strict locality requirement. Specifically, it is assumed that only the CP, i.e. the free relative itself, is local enough structurally to be able to identify the <i>pro</i> head, where identification is assumed to involve the set of phi-features of the <i>wh</i>-antecedent being conveyed to <i>pro</i>. Given this, the (anti-)pied-piping effects observed in free relatives above can be derived directly from the existence of a <i>pro</i> head in these structures in conjunction with the same feature-inheritance mechanism that we presented as the core mechanism underlying pied-piping in <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link> (based on <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link> and <link rid="b7">Koopman 1997</link>).</p>
<p>In order for the identifying features of the <i>wh</i>-antecedent to reach the actual local identifier (the CP) according to Grosu&apos;s proposal, feature inheritance and/or percolation needs to take place; features of the <i>wh</i>-antecedent can be transmitted to C by Spec&ndash;Head agreement and from C to CP by percolation. Thus any case where the Spec of CP position is occupied by the <i>wh</i>-antecedent itself, as in (63), satisfies the requirement of <i>pro</i> identification. But, crucially, <i>pro</i> identification seems to fail in cases where the <i>wh</i>-antecedent of <i>pro</i> occurs in the Spec (of Spec) position of the preposed DP, as in (24b, c). The reason for this under Grosu&apos;s proposal is that the phi-features of the <i>wh</i>-specifier (<i>whose</i>) needed for the identification of <i>pro</i> cannot get to the entire DP occupying Spec of CP by Spec&ndash;Head agreement because the DP itself has inherent features of the same kind as the <i>wh</i>-specifier, and an arguably independently motivated property of feature inheritance blocks transmission of these features. (A similar convention of priority of feature-percolation from the head over transmission of the same feature from the specifier is postulated in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s 1992</link>: 147 system in relation to operator features; this is of empirical significance with respect to his account of CP-pied-piping, to be discussed in <link rid="ss20">section 4.5</link>). Since the phi-features of the <i>wh</i>-specifier of DP cannot reach DP nor, consequently, CP, they fail to identify the head <i>pro</i>. (It would also need to be the case that C, in contrast to D, has no comparable features that would block transmission of the identifying features from its Spec in cases like (63).)</p>
<p>In sum, it appears that it is not pied-piping of a DP by its <i>wh</i>-specifier that is ruled out for some reason in realis free relatives. Rather, the unacceptability of free relatives like (24b, c), (64), and (65) is attributable to the presence of an improperly identified <i>pro</i>. Notice that in contrast to the case of phi-feature transmission, <i>wh</i>-feature transmission via the Spec&ndash;Head relation to DP, as used in the derivation of <i>wh</i>-pied-piping itself, would pose no problem of &lsquo;blocking&rsquo; since this feature is not an inherent feature of D in cases such as &lsqb;<i>whose</i> picture&rsqb;). Supporting evidence for the <i>pro</i>-identification account of anti-pied-piping effects in realis free relatives is provided by <link rid="b31">Grosu&apos;s (1994</link>: 142) observation regarding the contrast with irrealis/infinitival free relatives. The latter have various properties indicating that they are bare CPs, i.e., that they have no head <i>pro</i>. As expected, based on the above hypothesis for deriving the anti-pied-piping effects, these in realis free relatives turn out to manifest no such effects (see, e.g., (66) from Romanian); they in fact display the same pattern of pied-piping phenomena as infinitival embedded questions do.</p>
<p>(66)&ensp;<object id="tu45" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu45_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>nu</entry>
<entry>are</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;la</entry>
<entry>fotografia</entry>
<entry>cui</entry>
<entry>s&#x01CE;</entry>
<entry>se</entry>
<entry>uite&rsqb;.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Maria</entry>
<entry>not</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>at</entry>
<entry>picture-the</entry>
<entry>whose</entry>
<entry>SP</entry>
<entry>self</entry>
<entry>look</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col10">&lsquo;Maria doesn&apos;t have (anyone) at whose picture to look.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="2">
<heading id="h18" level="2">4.4&ensp;PP pied-piping</heading>
<p>The widely attested phenomenon of pied-piping of PPs by their complements (as shown with respect to <i>wh</i>-movement in <link rid="ss12">section 3.3</link>) seems to represent a substantive problem for the basic pied-piping generalization stated in (45). Complements of other categories fail to act as pied-pipers while the complements of P can, and in a large number of languages must, pied-pipe the PP. Combined with the fact that this takes place irrespective of construction type, indicates that the phenomenon can potentially have important implications regarding the adequacy of suggested mechanisms of pied-piping (such as the feature percolation mechanism being limited to Spec&ndash;Head agreement and projection from the head) and/or regarding constraints affecting its output (such as <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s 1992</link> formulation of the Theta Criterion and the notion of syntactic argument).</p>
<p>The question of how the complement of P can act as a pied-piper for the PP has been addressed in the literature by several different proposals, though at this point none of these seem to be supported by truly compelling empirical evidence. These proposals &ndash; to be outlined below &ndash; fall into two basic subtypes. One general direction, represented by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>: sect. 4.4.3) and <link rid="b31">Grosu&apos;s (1994</link>: sect. 1.4.1) proposals, involves the crucial claim that the category P is not a lexical head at all but is uniformly a non-theta-marking functional category, parallel to inflectional categories and in particular to Case. Such theories also presuppose a somewhat less restrictive version of the feature percolation/inheritance mechanism than the one outlined in (47), assumed for pied-piping in work such as <link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>) and <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi (2000</link>). The other direction of thought, manifested for instance in <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>) and <link rid="b7">Koopman&apos;s (1997</link>) work, involves the internal syntax of PPs and in particular the idea that what looks like a complement of P is actually not in complement, but in Spec position, at least in derived structure.</p>
<p>Webelhuth&apos;s assumption about operator-feature percolation (see <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link>) permits features to percolate up to their mother node not only from specifiers, but crucially also from complements. Given this, his system has no problem predicting that <i>wh</i>-complements of P will be able to pied-pipe the PP. However it would also predict, other things being equal, that <i>wh</i>-complements of other categories, e.g., N, A, or V, will be pied-pipers as well. To avoid this incorrect prediction, Webelhuth proposed to draw the relevant distinction between complements of P and complements of the other (lexical) heads from the conjunction of the following two assumptions: (a) a particular formulation of the Theta Criterion making crucial reference to the head of a theta chain not carrying any operator feature (see (55) and (56) above), from which he derived the generalization (stated as (54)) that no theta-marked phrase can be a pied-piper, and (b) the claim that while N, A, and V theta-mark their complement, the category P is not a theta-marker, i.e., Ps, including the semantically contentful ones, take complements yet do not assign theta roles to them. These assumptions, if tenable, would yield a distinction between P-complements being pied-pipers and complements of theta-marking heads (claimed to be V, N, and A) not being pied-pipers. The operator feature &lsqb;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; could percolate up from a <i>wh</i>-complement in all phrase-types under Webelhuth&apos;s theory; however, due to the way the Theta Criterion is stated, all cases of pied-piping by complements that are theta-marked by the head would be ruled out as Theta Criterion violations (similarly to pied-piping by specifiers of gerundive DPs discussed in <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link>).</p>
<p>Webelhuth&apos;s arguments for the claim that the category P is never a theta-marker for its complement &ndash; at most it can &lsquo;solicit&rsquo; a theta role from some theta-marking head &ndash; are based on observed differences between prepositions and the other lexical heads, and on some parallels between prepositons and (oblique) inflectional Case affixes. He notes, for instance, the functional equivalence between idiosyncratically selected Ps and case affixes in languages like German, both used, according to Webelhuth, as purely formal markers (e.g., the verbs <i>begegnen</i> &lsquo;meet&rsquo; and <i>finden</i> &lsquo;find&rsquo; require dative or accusative case-marking on their internal argument, and parallel to this, some other verbs, e.g., <i>hoffen</i> &lsquo;hope&rsquo; and <i>abh&auml;ngen</i> &lsquo;depend&rsquo;, require particular prepositions as formal markers for their internal argument, namely <i>auf</i> &lsquo;on&rsquo; and <i>von</i> &lsquo;of&rsquo;, respectively). Other properties pointed out by Webelhuth are the tendency of Ps, in contrast to members of other lexical categories, to lose their meaning in the course of diachronic change, and the fact that while the theta-marking heads N, V, and A can all be stranded by their complement across languages (for instance in all the Germanic languages), stranding of prepositions by a (non-pronominal) complement is impossible in many languages, including German. The latter cases are claimed to be due to an ECP violation (<link rid="b18">Chomsky 1986a</link>) that results from P not being a theta-governing lexical head for a trace in its complement position (on alternative accounts of P-stranding, see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 51 - Preposition Stranding.xml" type="file">chapter 51</externallink></related>). Based on these and similar observations, he concludes that prepositions are &ldquo;syntactic heads with the nonthematic marking function of affixes&rdquo;. (For a detailed study establishing the status of P as a uniformly non-theta-marking functional category, see <link rid="b48">Botwinik-Rotem 2004</link>.)</p>
<p>Accepting the well-motivated assumption that P is not a theta-assigner, Webelhuth&apos;s theory correctly yields the possibility of PP being pied-piped by its complement, while excluding pied-piping by complements of theta-marking V, N, and A heads. However, notice that this approach &ndash; in particular the idea of free feature-inheritance from complements, and the filtering of the resulting pied-piping cases only by the Theta Criterion (55&ndash;56) &ndash; makes a broader, arguably problematic, prediction. Specifically, it predicts (for operator movement cases, such as <i>wh</i>-movement) that for any head X, if X fails to theta-mark its complement YP, then YP will be able to pied-pipe XP. But is this prediction empirically justified?</p>
<p>First of all it appears to face some difficulty already in the case of the category P itself, in light of certain colloquial varieties of English. It is noted by <link rid="b8">Kayne (1994</link>: 25) that for some speakers, in colloquial register, PP-pied-piping is unacceptable (see Kayne&apos;s examples (25), including, e.g., *<i>Nobody knows to what school he goes</i>, *<i>Tell us from where you got that</i>.) If this indeed is a systematic dialect, Webelhuth&apos;s view of pied-piping by complements would not provide a plausible way to account for it. Under Webelhuth&apos;s theory, one would have to say either that this colloquial dialect has a different feature-percolation mechanism &ndash; i.e., a different projection mechanism for the complement relation &ndash; prohibiting feature-inheritance from complements, or that Ps in this variety of English are in fact theta-assigners for their complements. Clearly, neither of these are reasonable claims.</p>
<p>A different, more significant kind of counter-evidence for the above prediction is provided by the case of a subset of N heads, and their minimal contrast with locative Ps. Consider the type of nominals &ndash; such as <i>a picture of John, the legs of the chair, a gift to Mary</i> &ndash; that <link rid="b40">Grimshaw (1990</link>) refers to as &ldquo;result&rdquo; or &ldquo;simple&rdquo; nominals. As is argued extensively by Grimshaw, although such Ns are able to take complements, they have no syntactic argument structure, and, crucially for us, are not theta-assigners for their complement. (They contrast with so-called complex event nominals, which are theta-assigners, exhibiting an argument structure similar to Vs.)</p>
<p>Given <link rid="b40">Grimshaw&apos;s (1990</link>) theory, there is no theta-related difference between this set of Ns and Ps to rely on: neither are theta-assigners for their complement. Hence, based on Webelhuth&apos;s mechanism of feature percolation, we would expect complements of simple nominals and result nominals to act as pied-pipers for their phrase just like Ps do. As shown by the contrast between (67a, b) and (68a, b), this prediction turns out to be wrong.</p>
<p>(67)&ensp;<object id="tu46" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu46_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder most pictures of whom John liked.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Tell me a leg of which chair we should try to fix. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(68)&ensp;<object id="tu47" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu47_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder under whom John put some pillows.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Tell me near whom you saw a gun. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It is also worth noting here that the choice of locative Ps &ndash; rather than idiosyncratic (inflection-like) Ps considered by Webelhuth &ndash; is significant for the comparison (67&ndash;68) above, since they constitute a more minimal contrast with the Ns being tested than other kinds of P would. Locative Ps are parallel to the Ns involved in that (a) they clearly have semantic content, and (b) they constitute independent binding domains for Condition B effects, i.e., in terms of <link rid="b49">Reinhart and Reuland&apos;s (1993</link>) Reflexivity framework, they, just like Ns, can form a semantic predicate of their own (see the possibility of a pronoun in (69a, b)).</p>
<p>(69)&ensp;<object id="tu48" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu48_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>John<sub>i</sub> put some pillows under him<sub>i</sub>/himself.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Cf. John<sub>i</sub> explained Mary to *him<sub>i</sub>/himself.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>John<sub>i</sub> liked most pictures of him<sub>i</sub>/himself. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In view of the pied-piping contrast between complements of result Ns and complements of Ps exhibited by (67) and (68), we can discard the above free feature-percolation approach to pied-piping by complements.</p>
<p>Returning now to Webelhuth&apos;s argumentation regarding the parallelism between Ps and inflectional (case-marking) affixes, what it amounts to conceptually comes very close to saying that P is a functional, rather than a lexical, head. <link rid="b31">Grosu (1994</link>) makes this claim explicitly, and based on it, puts forth an alternative, empirically superior, account of PP-pied-piping by complements. He motivates his conclusion by pointing out various parallelisms between the behavior of Ps and of case affixes, in particular in free relatives in a variety of languages.</p>
<p>Importantly, given his assumption that P is a functional head, i.e., the top layer in the extended projection of N, Grosu&apos;s proposed account does not have to rely on the Theta Criterion (as in Webelhuth&apos;s version) to exclude feature percolation from complements of V, N, and A, while permitting percolation from complements of P. Instead it utilizes a different feature-percolation mechanism that is more restrictive than the one assumed by Webelhuth. Following <link rid="b32">Grimshaw (1991</link>), Grosu proposes that aside from Spec&ndash;Head agreement, features can percolate up from complements too, but, crucially, only from within the same extended projection, not from outside of it. Hence, no percolation of <i>wh</i> or other features is possible from the complements of lexical heads, for instance to NP (and DP) from the complement of N, or to VP from the complement of V. In contrast, percolation is possible from the NP complement of the functional head D to DP, and, crucially for our case, from the DP-complement of the functional head P to the whole PP, since in these cases, the features involved, namely both the &lsqb;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; feature (inducing PP pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement) and the phi-features (needed to identify the <i>pro</i> head of free relatives) would be staying within the same single extended projection.</p>
<p>Another type of approach to deriving the pied-piper status of complements of P is proposed in <link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>). This alternative is compatible with an even more restrictive feature-inheritance mechanism, which limits percolation to take place via Spec&ndash;Head agreement and only within a single, non-extended, maximal projection, from a head X up to the lowest maximal projection XP (as shown in (47) of <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link>). Importantly, no feature-percolation from any kind of complement is permitted. Instead, the proposal invokes (strictly local) head movement (see (70)). (Factors like no theta-marking by P, or P having to be a functional rather than a lexical head, play no role in the account).</p>
<listgroup id="l15" type="1">
<li>
<number>(70) </number>
<p>Head movement (and Spec&ndash;Head agreement):</p>
<p>
<object id="fu2" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_50_fu2.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu2_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Koopman&apos;s claim is essentially that a complement of P is able to pied-pipe the PP, i.e., the whole extended projection of P, due to this <i>wh</i>-complement coming to occupy actually the Spec of some head Y, which receives the <i>wh</i>-feature from it via Spec&ndash;Head agreement; crucially, this head then raises to the head of the extended projection of P, i.e., adjoins to the topmost head (the next head above it), and as a result the latter head, and hence the whole PP, receives the <i>wh</i>-feature (which originated in the complement of P). (For more on the specific assumptions regarding the internal structure and syntax of PPs, see <link rid="b50">Koopman 2000a</link>.)</p>
<p>A variant of this type of movement-based approach to pied-piping by the complement of P that had been proposed occasionally earlier (see, e.g., <link rid="b8">Kayne 1994</link>: 25) assumed that in languages that permit or require PP-pied-piping by a complement, the <i>wh</i>-complement undergoes covert movement to the Spec of the top layer of PP. The overt counterpart of the same movement had been assumed to exist too, as an intermediate step in the derivation of P-stranding, which is, as mentioned earlier, required in some versions of colloquial English. (The idea of the complement of P moving to a Spec-like position in PP when being extracted by <i>wh</i>-movement is due originally to <link rid="b51">Van Riemsdijk&apos;s 1978a</link> work on Dutch PPs.)</p>
<p>These movement-based analyses of the pied-piper status of the complement of P do not need to make the problematic connection between the lack of theta-marking and being a pied-piper, as Webelhuth&apos;s account does, and, furthermore, they are not forced to claim that P is necessarily a functional head, as under Grosu&apos;s proposal. However they would still need to address this question: Are the postulated PP-internal movements unique to this category, and if so, why? If they were not, then one would expect the same option of pied-piping by a complement to arise &ndash; as a result of phrase-internal overt/covert movement &lsquo;delivering&rsquo; the operator feature of the complement, as in (70) &ndash; also in projections of other lexical categories (V, N, A). This however is not attested, at least not in the well-studied Germanic case. Thus the movement postulated in the account of PP-pied-piping would have to be considered unique to this category-type. But then one is still left with the question, What makes the same movements &ndash; specifically, the head movement in (70) &ndash; available to projections of P and yet unavailable to projections of V, N, or A? A likely answer to this will presumably lead us back to the functional&ndash;lexical distinction between P and the other three heads.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss20" level="2">
<heading id="h19" level="2">4.5&ensp;Clausal pied-piping</heading>
<p>The mechanisms proposed to underlie pied-piping considered in the above subsections, namely, versions of a feature-percolation-based account, as well as the proposal based on c-command (binding, therefore) from the Spec of a phrase to outside of that phrase, would lead us to expect that the Spec position of CP could in principle act as a pied-piper for the CP. The questions for empirical study in this respect, then, are (a) whether Spec of CP indeed can pied-pipe the CP and (b) to the extent that it cannot, in particular languages at least, what the reason for this is.</p>
<p>Notice first that the empirical issue of clausal pied-piping was raised and discussed in the early GB framework with respect to English by <link rid="b19">Nanni and Stillings (1978</link>) and <link rid="b20">Ishihara (1984</link>). However, the clausal pied-piping cases these studies discussed were of the stylistically marked variety of pied-piping we discussed in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>. These cases are limited to relative-clause constructions whose <i>wh</i>-element occupied an IP-internal argument position; they are not part of normal colloquial English. This construction arguably involves some mechanism other than pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement, and is therefore not relevant for the issue of CP-pied-piping (see our discussion in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>, based on <link rid="b4">Webelhuth&apos;s (1992</link>) arguments for such cases of apparent pied-piping being derived by topicalization and involving a way of interpreting the <i>wh</i>-relative pronoun that falls outside of core grammar).</p>
<p>Regarding English, Webelhuth concludes that it permits no CP pied-piping, based on the ungrammaticality of the following type of data:</p>
<p>(71)&ensp;<object id="tu49" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu49_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Who</i> &lsqb;John met <i>t</i>&rsqb;&rsqb; did Mary know <i>t</i>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Who &lsqb;to talk to <i>t</i>&rsqb;&rsqb; did she forget <i>t</i>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>(<link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link>: 152)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This indeed seems to be correct; English embedded CPs with a <i>wh</i>-element occupying their Spec cannot get pied-piped to the matrix Spec of CP position under <i>wh</i>-movement no matter whether the clause is finite or infinitival. In such cases the <i>wh</i>-element in the lower Spec of CP position has only two options: either it is extracted from the embedded clause (successive cyclic movement), resulting in a matrix question, or it may stay and get interpreted in the embedded CP, provided that the selecting predicate permits an embedded question.</p>
<p>The explanation proposed by Webelhuth appears to attribute the ungrammaticality of examples like (71) to a property of feature percolation we already referred to in <link rid="ss18">section 4.3.2</link> as part of <link rid="b31">Grosu&apos;s (1994</link>) account for why the specifier of a <i>wh</i>-moved DP in free relatives cannot identify the head <i>pro</i>, in other words, why it cannot percolate its phi-features up to the DP. The relevant assumption is that a particular feature (independently of the value specified for it) that is borne both by a specifier YP and by the head projection X&prime; of a phrase XP can percolate to XP only from X&prime;; feature percolation from Spec (normally available, via the Spec&ndash;Head relation) is blocked in such cases. Thus, according to Webelhuth, pied-piping of a CP by its Spec is excluded whenever the sister node of the Spec, namely C&prime;, is marked for the feature &lsqb;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, since then the <i>wh</i>-element in Spec is unable to percolate its <i>wh</i>-operator feature up to the CP, and hence this CP cannot turn into an operator itself; as a result it cannot form a well-formed operator chain with the syntactic variable it binds (i.e., with its own trace) and, consequently, movement of such a CP would be ruled out. The specific stipulation Webelhuth makes in order to account for the (alleged) lack of CP-pied-piping in Germanic languages is that the (embedded) complementizer C is marked &lsqb;&minus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, and it is due to this property of C that the &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; feature of the phrase in Spec of CP cannot reach the CP. But in fact, given his particular definition of the notion &lsquo;syntactic operator&rsquo;, even if the &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; feature of the preposed <i>wh</i>-phrase were permitted to percolate up to the CP, the derivation would still fail to result in well-formed CP-pied-piping. As pointed out by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>: 152), if <i>who</i> in a case like (71a), for instance, were to percolate its operator feature to the CP, then it would cease to qualify as a syntactic operator, and consequently, its trace in the clause would constitute a syntactic variable that is not bound by a syntactic operator, thus violating Webelhuth&apos;s (p. 143) version of the Bijection Principle (adapted from <link rid="b52">Koopman and Sportiche 1982</link>).</p>
<p>However, when we go beyond the Germanic languages, Webelhuth&apos;s specific assumptions about the role played by the <i>wh</i>-feature of C and the reference of the Bijection Principle to syntactic operator preventing CP-pied-piping by its Spec appear to be challenged empirically, for instance, by the case of Basque as reported by in <link rid="b53">Ortiz de Urbina (1990</link>). (See also <link rid="b54">Cole 1982a</link> on CP-pied-piping in Imbabura Quechua.) Basque interrogatives exhibit <i>wh</i>-movement to the left periphery of the clause to a position that is immediately followed by the finite verbal element (allegedly a V2 phenomenon). Furthermore, Basque has two distinct overt complementizers; one <i>-</i>(<i>e</i>)<i>n</i> for interrogative, i.e., &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; complements, and another, <i>-</i>(<i>e</i>)<i>la</i>, for non-interrogative, i.e., &lsqb;&minus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, complements. Consider now the following data suggesting the existence of CP-pied-piping, pointed out by Ortiz de Urbina with respect to Basque interrogatives (corresponding to his examples (15i) and (17)):</p>
<p>(72)&ensp;<object id="tu50" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu50_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&lsqb;<i>Nor</i>
</entry>
<entry>etorriko</entry>
<entry>d-ela</entry>
<entry>bihar&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>esan</entry>
<entry>diozu</entry>
<entry>Mireni?</entry>
<entry>Basque</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who</entry>
<entry>come</entry>
<entry>Aux-that</entry>
<entry>tomorrow</entry>
<entry>said</entry>
<entry>Aux</entry>
<entry>Mary-Dat</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Who have you told Mary will come tomorrow?&rsquo; (Lit. &lsquo;That who will come tomorrow have you told Mary?&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(73)&ensp;<object id="tu51" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu51_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&lsqb;<i>Nor</i>
</entry>
<entry>etorriko</entry>
<entry>d-ela&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>esan</entry>
<entry>du</entry>
<entry>Mirenek <i>t</i>
</entry>
<entry>uste</entry>
<entry>du-ela</entry>
<entry>Peruk?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>who</entry>
<entry>come</entry>
<entry>Aux-that</entry>
<entry>said</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>Mary</entry>
<entry>think</entry>
<entry>Aux-that</entry>
<entry>Peter</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Who did Mary say that Peter thinks will come?&rsquo; (Lit. &lsquo;That who will come has Mary said (that) Peter thinks?&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Example (72) is taken to demonstrate the option in Basque for the <i>wh</i>-element (<i>nor</i>) preposed within the embedded clause to pied-pipe the whole embedded CP whose Spec position it came to occupy (the alternative option being to get extracted from it). Notice that the <i>wh</i>-phrase in the embedded CP as well as the whole pied-piped complement CP in the main clause occupy a clause-initial and immediately pre-verbal position characteristic of <i>wh</i>-moved interrogatives in Basque. Example (73) shows that the pied-piped CP can itself be extracted from the embedded Spec, i.e., move successive cyclically, to form a matrix question, in the same way as nonclausal <i>wh</i>-constituents can. Such evidence from Basque leads Ortiz de Urbina to claim that, contrary to Webelhuth&apos;s claims, <i>wh</i>-operator features can percolate from Spec of CP to the CP itself, and by this turn the CP into a <i>wh</i>-operator which after undergoing movement to Spec of CP, is able to bind a syntactic variable from there, just like any other <i>wh</i>-phrase would.</p>
<p>Thus, <link rid="b53">Ortiz de Urbina (1990</link>) proposes a radically different view of the status of CP-pied-piping across languages. Revising Webelhuth&apos;s assumption of C being uniformly marked &lsqb;&minus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, he assumes &ndash; in the spirit of the <i>wh</i>-criterion &ndash; that only a &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, i.e., interrogative C, can, and in fact must, have a <i>wh</i>-operator in its Spec. Given the option of operator-feature percolation from Spec to CP (ignoring the convention blocking percolation if the head has the relevant feature too), Ortiz de Urbina claims that a <i>wh</i>-phrase in Spec either percolates its feature to the CP, which would result in CP pied-piping, and will crucially make this <i>wh</i>-phrase lose its operator status, or it fails to percolate its feature to CP, hence it remains an operator itself, and no CP pied-piping will be licensed. From these assumptions he derives the prediction that CPs that are complements to &lsqb;&minus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; (i.e., non-interrogative) selecting heads, as well as non-selected (i.e., adjunct) CPs, may be pied-piped by their <i>wh</i>-Spec, whereas CP complements of &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; (i.e., interrogative) selecting heads cannot get pied-piped since they need a <i>wh</i>-operator present in their Spec. This appears to work well for Basque (see (74a) and (74b)), at least as far as the data considered by Ortiz de Urbina are concerned (for some further relevant facts, see <link rid="b55">Echepare&apos;s 1997</link> alternative analysis referred to below).</p>
<p>(74)&ensp;<object id="tu52" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu52_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Nor</i>
</entry>
<entry>etorriko</entry>
<entry>d-ela</entry>
<entry>bihar&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>esan</entry>
<entry>diozu</entry>
<entry>Mireni?</entry>
<entry>Basque</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>who</entry>
<entry>come</entry>
<entry>Aux-that</entry>
<entry>tomorrow</entry>
<entry>said</entry>
<entry>Aux</entry>
<entry>Mary-Dat</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Who have you told Mary will come tomorrow?&rsquo; (Lit. &lsquo;That who will come tomorrow have you told Mary?&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<i>Nor</i>
</entry>
<entry>etorriko</entry>
<entry>d-en&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>galdetu</entry>
<entry>duzu?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry> who</entry>
<entry>come</entry>
<entry>Aux-comp</entry>
<entry>asked</entry>
<entry>Aux</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">(Lit. &lsquo;Who will come have you asked?&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">Cf. the corresponding ungrammatical English *Who have you asked will come?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As for the case of Germanic, such as the examples in (71) from English, Ortiz de Urbina needs to say something additional in order to account for the fact that they are impossible even though the selecting verbs <i>know</i> and <i>forge</i>t do permit a &lsqb;&minus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, i.e., a non-interrogative CP complement. The solution he proposes for this problem relies on the difference between Germanic and Basque with respect to whether C is empty or not. Specifically, he suggests that the Germanic cases of CP-pied-piping are ruled out by the ECP (<link rid="b38 b18">Chomsky 1981, 1986a</link>) due to the lexically ungoverned nature of their empty C in the output structure, i.e., that the unacceptability of examples like (71) has nothing to do with <i>wh</i>-pied-piping per se. While it is clear that some parameter distinguishing Basque and Germanic must be involved, it seems doubtful that it could simply be the emptiness of C in Germanic preposed CPs violating the ECP. If this were so, one would not expect any possibility of a CP in a left-peripheral A-bar or subject position, having a <i>wh</i>-element in its specifier and an empty C. But such cases clearly are attested, as shown by fully acceptable topicalized <i>wh</i>-CPs, such as <i>Who Mary invited</i>, <i>I would never reveal to you</i>, or subject clauses, such as <i>What you got from whom doesn&apos;t interest me</i>. A different approach that can provide a reasonable alternative way to derive the apparent cases of CP-pied-piping in Basque, and can also account for the distinct behavior of the English-type languages, is proposed by <link rid="b55">Echepare (1997</link>) based on some novel data and generalizations he points out regarding Basque interrogatives.</p>
<p>Echepare&apos;s major observations leading to the reassessment of the alleged CP-pied-piping phenomenon of Basque are the following: (a) a pied-piped <i>wh</i>-CP cannot satisfy selection for a <i>wh</i>-interrogative, i.e., it can occur only in the Spec of a matrix question but not in an embedded one (see (75)) and (b) the set of <i>wh</i>-words that can pied-pipe a CP is limited to arguments and referential adjuncts, while non-referential <i>wh</i>-adverbials, like &lsquo;why&rsquo; and &lsquo;how&rsquo;, are not able to appear in pied-piped CPs, and can take matrix scope only by extraction (see (76)):</p>
<p>(75)&ensp;<object id="tu53" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu53_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Mikelek</entry>
<entry>galdetu</entry>
<entry>du &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>nor</i> </entry>
<entry>etorriko</entry>
<entry>dela&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>
</entry>
<entry>esan</entry>
<entry>duten <i>t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
<entry>Basque</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mikel</entry>
<entry>ask</entry>
<entry>Aux</entry>
<entry> who</entry>
<entry>come</entry>
<entry>Aux-Comp</entry>
<entry>say</entry>
<entry>Aux-Comp</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col9">&lsquo;Mikel asked who they said will come.&rsquo; (Lit. &lsquo;Mikel asked who will come said they.&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(76)&ensp;<object id="tu54" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu54_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*&lsqb;<i>Zergatik</i>
</entry>
<entry>aspertu</entry>
<entry>zela&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>
</entry>
<entry>uste</entry>
<entry>duzu <i>t</i><sub>i</sub>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>why</entry>
<entry>bore</entry>
<entry>Aux-Comp</entry>
<entry>think</entry>
<entry>Aux</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col5">&lsquo;Why do you think she/he got bored?&rsquo; (Lit. &lsquo;Why she/he got bored think you?&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These properties are completely unexpected under a hypothesis of CP-pied-piping by <i>wh</i>-movement (as, e.g., <link rid="b53">Ortiz de Urbina&apos;s 1990</link> <i>wh</i>-feature-percolation-based proposal above). <link rid="b55">Echepare (1997</link>) interprets the property demonstrated by (75) (see generalization (i) above) as indication that in fact the preposing of apparent <i>wh</i>-CPs in Basque interrogatives is not due to <i>wh</i>-movement at all, and argues that these CPs are not located in Spec of CP, but rather are topicalized phrases appearing in a projection higher than CP. Furthermore, along the same lines, the impossibility of examples like (76), i.e., &lsquo;pied-piped&rsquo; CPs being acceptable only when their wide-scope taking <i>wh</i>-element is an argument or referential adjunct, is taken as indication that the <i>wh</i>-words of Basque are not operators. Echepare argues that they undergo neither overt nor covert <i>wh</i>-movement to Spec of CP; instead, he claims, <i>wh</i>-interrogatives in Basque should be analyzed as in situ <i>wh</i>-questions of the Chinese type, and receive wide-scope construal via unselective binding, since it is this type of <i>wh</i>-construction that is known to exhibit the referentiality restrictions manifested in (76) (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related>). Thus, under Echepare&apos;s analysis, Basque would not instantiate <i>wh</i>-movement pied-piping a CP. If apparent CP-pied-piping constructions such as (72) and (73) indeed turn out to involve simply a topicalized CP that in these particular cases just happens to contain an in-situ <i>wh</i>-phrase, then Basque interrogatives would be consistent with Webelhuth&apos;s operator-feature-based theory of pied-piping that systematically excludes the possibility of clausal pied-piping.</p>
<p>Finally, there is one slightly different potential instance of CP-pied-piping by Spec within Germanic not addressed in <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>). This is the somewhat controversial case of pied-piped infinitivals occurring in relative constructions of German (see, e.g., <link rid="b21">Van Riemsdijk 1985</link> and <link rid="b56">Grewendorf 1986</link>). Unlike the clausal pied-piping cases of the English stylistically marked, literary kind discussed in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>, these sentences in German (such as in (77)), arguably involve overt movement of the relative pronoun within the pied-piped infinitival, as argued by <link rid="b21">Van Riemsdijk (1985</link>, 1993), namely, movement to the Spec position of the infinitival CP.</p>
<p>(77)&ensp;<object id="tu55" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu55_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="9">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>das</entry>
<entry>Buch,</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>das</i> PRO <i>t</i>
</entry>
<entry>zu</entry>
<entry>lesen&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>er</entry>
<entry>uns</entry>
<entry>empfohlen</entry>
<entry>hatte</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the</entry>
<entry>book</entry>
<entry> which</entry>
<entry>to</entry>
<entry>read</entry>
<entry>he</entry>
<entry>us</entry>
<entry>recommended</entry>
<entry>had</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col9">(&lsquo;the book, to read which he had recommended to us&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Apparently, this kind of alleged CP-pied-piping is induced only by the Spec position of the CP, and, consequently, it is a reasonable initial assumption that it involves feature percolation to the CP. Yet it is also possible that this case should be considered nevertheless as a counterpart of the stylistically marked pied-piping cases of English discussed in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>; the latter were claimed by <link rid="b4">Webelhuth (1992</link>) to involve simply topicalization of the constituent, rather than actual pied-piping by movement of a <i>wh</i>-operator. The reason is that it shares two important properties with the latter cases: (a) it is limited to occur only in relative clauses, and is impossible in interrogatives, suggesting that the process actually might not involve quantificational operators, and (b) it is excluded in the case of tensed clauses, which makes it similar to the English clausal-pied-piping cases shown in (61&ndash;62) of <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>. If analyzed in this latter way, one would then need to address the question of what forces the overt preposing of the relative pronoun within the infinitival, and why no such preposing is required (or in fact permitted) within the English cases such as those of <link rid="b20">Ishihara (1984</link>), shown in <link rid="ss17">section 4.3.1</link>.</p>
<p>On the basis of these observations we can only conclude that no uncontroversial evidence is available in favor of the existence of true CP-pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement, in the same sense as there is uncontroversial evidence for DP-pied-piping under <i>wh</i>-movement. Even the strongest candidate discussed in the literature, namely, the case of Basque interrogatives, raises some serious doubts due to evidence internal to the language. Furthermore, it would leave open the issue of the relevant parametric difference between Basque-type languages and languages where interrogatives do not manifest CP-pied-piping.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss21" level="2">
<heading id="h20" level="2">4.6&ensp;Pied-piping in non-<roman>wh</roman>-constructions</heading>
<p>So far our discussion has been focusing on <i>wh</i>-constructions and specifically, on accounting for the pied-piping ability of <i>wh</i>-words occupying various structural positions in their phrases. This reflects the orientation of the pied-piping literature itself, at least until recently. The obvious reason for the predominance of studies on pied-piping by <i>wh</i>-morphemes is the overtly detectable nature of this particular morpheme, and the wide range of movement operations it is involved in. Yet an uncontroversial assumption in the literature, shared by all accounts of <i>wh</i>-pied-piping reviewed above, is that the mechanisms proposed for <i>wh</i>-pied-piping generalize (at least) to the whole set of operator features in UG. Some better known cases of such operator features involved in movement, beyond &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;, are the &lsqb;&plus;neg&rsqb; feature of negative morphemes, central to <link rid="b57">Rizzi&apos;s (1991b</link>) Negative Criterion (see also <link rid="b58">Haegeman and Zanuttini 1991</link>), and within the framework of a systematically checking theory-based account of quantifier scope put forth in <link rid="b59">Beghelli and Stowell (1997</link>), also quantificational features, such as &lsqb;&plus;Dist(ributive)&rsqb;, &lsqb;&plus;Univ(ersal)&rsqb;, and others, corresponding to individual clausal functional heads and QPs. (Another potentially relevant operator feature, namely, the feature &lsqb;&plus;Focus&rsqb;, proposed in <link rid="b60">Horvath 1986</link>, and used as a crucial part of <link rid="b61">Brody&apos;s 1990a</link> Focus Criterion, is reexamined and eliminated as such in <link rid="b62">Horvath 2000</link>, in part based on considerations of pied-piping under overt Focus-movement as manifested in Hungarian.)</p>
<p>These operators are commonly assumed to involve covert (LF) movement, at least in languages like English (however, for an alternative treatment making use only of overt movements, see <link rid="b35">Kayne 2000</link>: ch. 13). Thus, for instance, QR of the GB framework, as well as its reanalyzed minimalist versions, such as those proposed by <link rid="b36">Hornstein (1995</link>), <link rid="b59">Beghelli and Stowell (1997</link>), or the movement of negative phrases to enter into a Spec&ndash;Head relation with the clausal head Neg<sup>0</sup> to satisfy the Negative Criterion (or to check the &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb; feature) are assumed to take place after Spell Out in languages such as English and French (the status of pied-piping under covert movement will be addressed in <link rid="ss22">section 5</link>). Here, however, we will consider pied-piping by such non-<i>wh</i> operators in languages and constructions where these operators undergo uncontroversially overt movements. Such cases are, for example, QR in Hungarian (<link rid="b63">Kiss 1992</link>), movement of negative phrases to Spec of NegP in Italian and West Flemish (<link rid="b58">Haegeman and Zanuttini 1991</link>; <link rid="b64">Haegeman 1995b</link>), and also the Negative Inversion construction in English.</p>
<p>To demonstrate the ability of non-<i>wh</i> operator features to pied-pipe in a way consistent with what we found with respect to <i>wh</i>-movement, first consider examples from Hungarian involving overt Quantifier Raising of the universal quantifier <i>minden</i> &lsquo;every&rsquo; to the position of Spec of DistP (postulated in <link rid="b59">Beghelli and Stowell 1997</link>):</p>
<p>(78)&ensp;<object id="tu56" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu56_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i><u>Mindenkinek</u>
</i>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>vett&uuml;nk</entry>
<entry>valamit <i>t</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>everyone-Dat</entry>
<entry>bought-1Pl</entry>
<entry>something-Acc</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col4">&lsquo;We bought something for everyone.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i><u>Minden</u>
</i>
</entry>
<entry><u>vend&eacute;gnek</u>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>vett&uuml;nk</entry>
<entry>valamit <i>t</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>every</entry>
<entry>guest-Dat</entry>
<entry>bought-1Pl</entry>
<entry>something-Acc</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col5">&lsquo;We bought something for every guest.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;&lsqb;<i><u>Minden</u>
</i>
</entry>
<entry><u>vend&eacute;g</u>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry><u>gyerek&eacute;nek</u>&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>vett&uuml;nk</entry>
<entry>valamit <i>t</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>every</entry>
<entry>guest&apos;s</entry>
<entry>child-Dat</entry>
<entry>bought-1Pl</entry>
<entry>something-Acc</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col6">&lsquo;We bought something for every guest&apos;s child.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similarly, the pied-piping generalizations found in relation to <i>wh</i>-movements are attested also in the case of overt movements involving a negative constituent. This can be seen based on the following Negative Inversion examples from English, where, unlike in other instances involving negative phrases in the language, the overt nature of the movement of the &lsqb;&plus;neg&rsqb; element (to the Spec of CP) is transparent. (On the question of how to derive their need for aux-inversion, i.e., for I-to-C movement, see <link rid="b57">Rizzi&apos;s 1991b</link> discussion of the Negative Criterion, on a par with his <i>Wh</i>-Criterion.) Consider the pied-piped phrases and the &lsqb;&plus;neg&rsqb; morpheme within them in (79), as well as the contrasting pairs (80a)&ndash;(80b) and (81a)&ndash;(81b); examples (80a, b) show the negative morpheme being able to pied-pipe its DP when occurring in Spec but not when occurring in complement position, and the contrast in (81) shows that when the head of a phrase is &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb;, it can pied-pipe the whole DP, including a complement, but when the &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb; feature is on the complement in a DP, the whole phrase cannot be pied-piped by it.</p>
<p>(79)&ensp;<object id="tu57" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu57_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>Never</i>&rsqb; have I witnessed such behavior.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Under <i>no</i> conditions&rsqb; will I leave this city.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;&lsqb;<i>No</i> student&apos;s&rsqb; thesis&rsqb; have they read so thoroughly. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(80)&ensp;<object id="tu58" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu58_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;&lsqb;<i>No</i> young girl&apos;s&rsqb; participation in the game&rsqb; can they permit.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;The participation &lsqb;of <i>no</i> young girl&rsqb; in the game&rsqb; can they permit. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu59" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu59_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<i>No</i> articles by such a reporter&rsqb; will they agree to publish.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Such articles &lsqb;by <i>no</i> reporter&rsqb;&rsqb; will they agree to publish. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In some of the recent literature, inspired by <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>) Antisymmetry framework, pied-piping of large, clausal and other functional projections (both in the nominal and in the verbal extended projections) is postulated on a much larger scale than in earlier work. The empirical evidence for such analyses often comes from surface discrepancies of word order (e.g., the appearance of head-final phrases in head-initial languages) or from various agreement phenomena, which under the restrictive theoretical assumption that agreement holds only in Spec&ndash;Head configurations, imply that large phrasal categories &ndash; possibly remnants appearing to be no more than just heads &ndash; move to Spec positions, as instances of pied-piping by the relevant agreeing feature(s). The existence of such &lsquo;heavy&rsquo; pied-piping is discussed from a conceptual point of view by <link rid="b9">Koopman (1996</link>). In addition to giving a general perspective on a theory with heavy pied-piping, Koopman also reviews some supporting empirical evidence from a variety of languages based on earlier studies (e.g., <link rid="b11">Nkemnji&apos;s 1995</link> analyses of Nweh (Grassfield Bantu)). To the extent that these large-scale movements are indeed driven by the need for feature-checking and/or agreement (which in these analyses is not always obvious), they would constitute true cases of pied-piping and would raise the obvious question of what induces the apparent language-particular variation with respect to this option, or at least what the properties and mechanisms are that make such heavy pied-piping more easily detectable in some languages than in others.</p>
<p>Most of the earlier literature on pied-piping considered cases of operator movement. Yet there is clearly no reason not to expect pied-piping also when the feature/morpheme-triggering movement is inflectional or categorial in nature rather than an operator; in other words, one may in principle expect pied-piping to occur under A-movements as well. Finding appropriate test-cases for A-movement pied-piping, however, is indeed more difficult, at least in the obvious canonical A-movement cases, such as noun phrase movements to A-positions (e.g., to Spec of IP). One factor limiting the range of testable cases is that having no Case, or in MP terms, having an unchecked Case feature, is a necessary condition for a DP to be eligible for A-movement (see <link rid="b6 b28">Chomsky 1995c, 2000</link>). However, DPs occurring, for instance, within the Spec position of a larger DP such as <i>some student</i> in &lsqb;<i>some student&apos;s parents</i>&rsqb; (see (82a)) are already Case-licensed inside the DP; the same is true for complements of N, which bear inherent Case. Thus these DPs cannot undergo A-movement to begin with, hence obviously could not be expected to be potential pied-pipers of their phrase. Another factor that might reduce cases of A-movement pied-piping is that, in contrast to operator movements, the types of features triggering classical A-movements (familiar from Raising or Passive constructions) are precisely those known independently not to be inheritable via the Spec&ndash;Head relation, at least when the head is marked for the same features (see <link rid="ss18">section 4.3.2</link> on <i>pro</i> identification by phi-features inducing an anti-pied-piping effect in free relatives, as well as <link rid="b4">Webelhuth 1992</link> on <i>wh</i>-feature percolation). So under a feature-percolation-based view of pied-piping, commonly assumed for operator movements, one would not expect a DP in Spec of DP position to be a pied-piper for its phrase under A-movement.</p>
<p>What we find when turning to the assessment of the actual empirical facts is that pied-piping indeed is attested, in the canonical A-movement cases examined, only when the pied-piper is the head of the phrase, as in (82a) and (82b) below. DPs in Spec of DP position can get pied-piped by the head, but they themselves cannot act as pied-pipers (see (82b)). (Feature inheritance from the head, and hence pied-piping of the maximal projection, is unproblematic, as expected.)</p>
<p>(82)&ensp;<object id="tu60" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu60_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Some/no student&apos;s &lsqb;parents&rsqb;&rsqb; are waiting in the office.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Some/no student&apos;s &lsqb;parents&rsqb;&rsqb; is waiting in the office. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This is contrary to what we find in the case of operator movements such as <i>wh</i>-movement. But as pointed out above, the apparent impossibility of pied-piping by Spec under A-movement in (82b) is in fact independent of the pied-piping mechanism itself, since such DP specifiers cannot undergo A-movement at all as shown in (83) below. (Note that under <i>wh</i>-movement, possessive Spec of DPs in English pied-pipe the rest of the DP obligatorily, putatively for PF-related reasons, discussed in <link rid="ss24">section 6.1</link>).)</p>
<p>(83) *Some/no student(&lsquo;s) are &lsqb;<i>t</i> (&lsquo;s) parents&rsqb; waiting in the office.</p>
<p>The ungrammaticality of (83) cannot be attributed simply to the lack of phi-feature checking (i.e., lack of appropriate agreement) on the clausal head I and of Case on the DP &lsqb; .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;parents&rsqb;, since such phi-feature-checking by a Case-bearing DP would be possible without movement, i.e., when the relevant phrase is in post-V rather than in Spec of IP position (see <link rid="b28">Chomsky 2000</link> on Agree). This possibility is demonstrated in <i>there</i> expletive constructions, such as (84):</p>
<p>(84) There are some student&apos;s parents waiting in the office.</p>
<p>Some versions of the earlier GB theory though would indeed have excluded cases such as (83) above by the lack of Case on the post-V DP in (83), while permitting examples like (84) via expletive replacement.</p>
<p>A distinct contrast of interest involving DP-pied-piping (pointed out by an anonymous referee) is provided by the post-nominal possessive construction of English. The construction exemplified in (85) may represent an instance of DP-pied-piping by its Spec under A-movement (a case we failed to find with pre-nominal possessives as in (82&ndash;83)).</p>
<p>(85)&ensp;<object id="tu61" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu61_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Some students of John&apos;s&rsqb; are waiting in the office.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Some students&rsqb; are &lsqb;<i>t</i> (of) John&apos;s&rsqb; waiting in the office. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Pied-piping here is obligatory &ndash; i.e., (<i>of</i>) <i>John&apos;s</i> cannot be left stranded by the preposed phrase (85b). Naturally, if the string <i>some students</i> in this construction does not form a constituent, we would not expect it to be able to move independently, and thus strand the rest of the DP. But if <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1994</link>: 86) analysis of this construction &ndash; shown schematically in (86) &ndash; is right, then <i>some students</i> is clearly a constituent, one that has been preposed to the Spec of the topmost DP in the structure.</p>
<p>(86) &lsqb;some students<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;&lsqb;<sub>D</sub> of&rsqb; &lsqb;John &lsqb;&lsquo;s &lsqb;<i>t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>Thus, assuming the structure (86) motivated by Kayne, pied-piping of <i>of John&apos;s</i> by the phrase <i>some students</i> occupying the Spec position of the highest DP projection is predicted to be possible, and this indeed seems borne out by (85a). Such examples may, under the above analysis, instantiate the case we have been searching for, namely, pied-piping of a DP under A-movement by a phrase in its Spec position. The question remaining under the above analysis is: why is pied-piping obligatory here (see 85b)? The reason for this may have to do with the fact that the preposed phrase in Spec of DP (<i>some students</i>) in this construction is arguably not a DP, but rather a QP/NP (see <link rid="b8">Kayne 1994</link>). If the EPP driving movement to Spec of IP is in fact a requirement of checking an uninterpretable D feature of the head I (as proposed in <link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link>), then this would automatically explain why the phrase <i>some students</i> itself could not satisfy the EPP, and hence could not move by itself, only the whole DP could, as shown in (85a, b). (If so, then, technically, the movement would again be DP-pied-piping by its head D, not by its Spec.) However, according to an alternative, more recent, conception the EPP-requirement is not construed as categorial feature-checking, but as the need of the I (&equals;T) head to have a Spec position realized (see <link rid="b28">Chomsky 2000</link>). Under this approach, there appears to be no obvious reason for the impossibility of (85b), given that the phrase in Spec of DP is a maximal projection (QP or NP) which is demonstrably able to undergo movement by itself in Kayne&apos;s account. Possibly, however, this problematic phenomenon could fall together with some observations made in relation to the notion &lsquo;phase&rsquo; in <link rid="b28">Chomsky (2000</link>) involving the impossibility of extracting substantive, i.e., &lsquo;non-phase&rsquo;, categories from within their functional layer constituting a phase (i.e., from their extended projection). For instance, finite IPs cannot strand their C, and similarly, an NP/QP would not be able to strand its DP layer. (On Spec and obligatory pied-piping, see also <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>.)</p>
<p>A related question of obvious significance is whether A-movement can pied-pipe non-nominal projections, such as VP and various clausal functional projections, by their DP specifier. A case in point would be, for instance, if instead of the subject DP being moved from its VP-internal base position to Spec of IP, as in an English-type SVO language, the same feature-checking and EPP requirement driving the movement of the DP could be satisfied, at least in some languages, by preposing the whole VP/<i>v</i>P or other clausal projection whose Spec position the relevant DP occupies. Notice that being (extended) projections of V, these categories would be less likely to block feature-inheritance from a DP in Spec by their head-projection than nominal projections. (Percolation of non-operator features from the complement would be excluded under (47), just like percolation of operator-features is.) A concrete test case of the above kind from English would be, for instance, the raising construction in (87a, b), where the (bare) IP complement of the raising predicate has a DP in its Spec position. The question is: can this DP pied-pipe the IP, instead of being extracted from it?</p>
<p>(87)&ensp;<object id="tu62" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu62_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;The students to enjoy the lecture&rsqb; are likely &lsqb;<i>t</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The students are likely &lsqb;<i>t</i> to enjoy the lecture&rsqb;. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Pied-piping of IP under A-movement turns out to be clearly impossible in the case of (87). The reason for this again appears to lie in the nature of the category moved (see (87a)). In this case it is a defective IP &ndash; i.e., one without a full set of phi-features &ndash; in terms of <link rid="b28">Chomsky (2000</link>). Such IPs, occurring in raising and ECM constructions, are known not to exhibit phonetic autonomy like, e.g., CPs or verb phrases do; specifically, they are unable to move or occur as elliptical answers on their own (e.g., *<i>it&apos;s</i> &lsqb;t <i>to enjoy the lecture</i>&rsqb; <i>that John seems</i>). While English, at least in the above type of case, does not exhibit the relevant pied-piping option, empirical work on a variety of languages has uncovered putative motivation for assuming pied-piping of VPs and various clausal functional projections by their specifiers under A-movements (see, e.g., <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi 2000</link> for relevant analyses and references).</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss22" level="1">
<heading id="h21" level="1">5&ensp;LF-movements and pied-piping</heading>
<p>Within the GB model of UG, it was assumed that the same operation Move &alpha; involved in mapping D-structures to S-structures also applies to S-structures, and derives from S-structures another level of syntactic representations, namely, LF. These post-S-structure applications of Move &alpha; became known as LF-movements, and were also referred to as covert movements, since they had no phonological effects, due to the architecture of the grammar (the T-model). Within such a model, the null hypothesis seems to be that all properties of LF-movement, including in particular the options of pied-piping, will be parallel to those found in the case of overt (i.e., pre-S-structure) movement, apart from any possible properties of overt movement that are imposed by phonological (PF) requirements.</p>
<p>The existence of pied-piping by LF-movements was thus taken for granted in the GB framework. The first actual empirical issue involving pied-piping and LF-movement arose in connection with the assumed LF-movement account of <i>wh</i>-in-situ constructions in languages such as Chinese and Japanese, and also of multiple <i>wh</i>-questions in English-type languages. Specifically, a problem for the expected parallelism between overt and LF-movement operations appeared to exist in relation to the application of Subjacency (<link rid="b65">Huang 1982a</link>). It was observed that in-situ (non-D-linked) <i>wh</i>-elements, assumed to undergo covert <i>wh</i>-movement, actually permitted certain island violations, and this raised the possibility that LF-movement was not subject to Subjacency. In an attempt to show that LF-<i>wh</i>-movement, too, obeys Subjacency, as one would expect, based on the null hypothesis, an interesting type of proposal was made independently in work by Choe and by Nishigauchi (published as <link rid="b22">Choe 1987</link> and <link rid="b23">Nishigauchi 1990</link>); the analysis was further elaborated by <link rid="b24">Pesetsky (1987a</link>). The proposal was based on the hypothesis of large-scale pied-piping by the LF-<i>wh</i>-movement involved, and it claimed that the suspected island violations are only apparent, since although the <i>wh</i>-element itself occurs within an island, such as a complex NP or an adjunct, what actually moves at LF is the island itself, in other words, the complex NP or the adjunct gets pied-piped. This movement, unlike extraction of the <i>wh</i>-in-situ element itself, would not violate Subjacency. Both Choe and Nishigauchi provided the type of evidence illustrated in (88), involving the felicity of answers to <i>wh</i>-questions, in support of their claim (example (88) is adapted from <link rid="b24">Pesetsky 1987a</link>: 113):</p>
<p>(88)&ensp;<object id="tu63" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu63_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Q:</entry>
<entry>Mary-wa &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>John-ni</entry>
<entry>nani-o</entry>
<entry>ageta&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hito-ni&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>atta-no?</entry>
<entry>Japanese</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>Mary-Top</entry>
<entry>John-Dat</entry>
<entry>what-Acc</entry>
<entry>gave</entry>
<entry>man-Dat</entry>
<entry>met-Q</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;What did Mary meet the man who gave to John?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">A1: */??</entry>
<entry>Konpyuutaa</entry>
<entry>desu.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>computer</entry>
<entry>Cop</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">&lsquo;It&apos;s a computer.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">A2: &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Konpyuutaa-o</entry>
<entry>ageta&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>hito-ni&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>desu.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>computer-Acc</entry>
<entry>gave</entry>
<entry>man</entry>
<entry>Cop</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col5">&lsquo;It&apos;s the man who gave a computer (to him).&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As shown in (88), only the whole complex NP can be a felicitous answer to the in-situ <i>wh</i>-question. These types of facts are taken to show that the pied-piping of the island by the <i>wh</i>-in-situ element is the only possible derivation in the prima facie problematic cases. Hence, the apparent discrepancy between overt and LF movements with respect to the application of Subjacency would be eliminated. It must be noted here that the above covert pied-piping proposal fails to account for the fact that a certain subset of <i>wh</i>-elements, in particular non-referential adjuncts such as &lsquo;why&rsquo; (reason) and &lsquo;how&rsquo; (manner), are unable to take wide scope out of islands in such <i>wh</i>-in-situ languages as well (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related>).</p>
<p>Apart from several empirical problems involved in the proposed evidence, such as those pointed out, e.g., in <link rid="b25">Fiengo et al. (1988</link>), the above account is undesirable from the point of view of the assumptions it makes about LF-pied-piping itself. Crucially, notice that, based on what is known about overt pied-piping, the same <i>wh</i>-in-situ structures that in the above proposal are assumed to undergo LF-pied-piping would obviously not be able to undergo pied-piping by overt <i>wh</i>-movement. Under accounts of overt pied-piping based on variants of a reasonably restrictive and empirically motivated feature percolation or inheritance mechanism (reviewed in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>), the relevant &lsqb;&plus;<i>wh</i>&rsqb; feature would clearly not be able to percolate to the complex NP in cases like (88), and, consequently, pied-piping would be impossible. This problem is best shown by the contrasts in English between overt <i>wh</i>-movement and <i>wh</i>-in-situ (alleged to involve LF-<i>wh</i>-movement) in the case of various islands, such as in (89a, b):</p>
<p>(89)&ensp;<object id="tu64" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu64_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;The man &lsqb;who bought what&rsqb;&rsqb; did Mary know?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Who knew &lsqb;the man &lsqb;who bought what&rsqb;&rsqb;? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>LF-pied-piping by <i>wh</i>-in-situ, then, as formulated in the Choe&ndash;Nishigauchi&ndash;Pesetsky analysis, seems to resolve the non-uniformity of overt and covert movement with respect to Subjacency only at the cost of introducing another non-uniformity between overt and covert movements, namely, one with respect to the application of pied-piping. This is a serious problem since there is no plausible reason why covert movement should permit &lsquo;heavier&rsquo; pied-piping than overt movement. Notice that if any needs of PF (relevant for the output of overt but not covert movement) have any impact on pied-piping options at all, these would presumably go in exactly the opposite direction; they would potentially force pied-piping rather than prevent it, e.g., in case the moved element was too &lsquo;small&rsquo; to be pronouncable, such as a feature or a bound morpheme (on such effects of PF, see <link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link>, discussed in <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>).</p>
<p>Some problems with this LF-pied-piping proposal from the point of view of interpretation were noted by <link rid="b66">von Stechow (1996</link>) (see also <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related>). Von Stechow&apos;s objections may be resolved under a conception of reconstruction involving the copy theory of movement, combined with appropriate deletion conventions, of the kind suggested in <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>). However, it is important to note at this point that in spite of the inadequacies of this particular account for <i>wh</i>-in-situ and Subjacency, the general idea behind the proposal, namely, LF-pied-piping providing the account for what appear to be various potential island violations, is arguably on the right track. This kind of account, in a slightly amended form, in fact received some striking confirmation in the domain of the LF-movement of negative phrases in French, studied in <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>). In this work on French sentence negation, LF-pied-piping was shown not only to exist but to obey the familiar configurational requirements attributed to the restrictive feature-percolation mechanism underlying overt pied-piping.</p>
<p>After establishing that French negative phrases (such as <i>personne</i>) undergo LF-movement to Spec of NegP (not just chain formation with the head of NegP), <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>) proceed to explore cases where <i>personne</i> occurs within some larger phrase that can be shown (based on overt <i>wh</i>-movement) to constitute an island for extraction. The pattern of grammaticality they find is that the negative element <i>personne</i> gives well-formed negative sentences in some of these cases, but results in ungrammaticality in another subset of the cases. The mixed pattern suggests first of all that Subjacency is relevant for the LF-movement of negative phrases, and more importantly, that contrary to assumptions of the proposal for <i>wh</i>-in-situ reviewed above, LF-pied-piping cannot apply freely, making all island effects disappear; rather, only certain kinds of configurations can result in LF-pied-piping.</p>
<p>The crucial claim made by Moritz and Valois on the basis of a variety of arguments is that the particular cases where an island can be pied-piped by <i>personne</i>, and thus a Subjacency violation by LF-raising to Spec of NegP can be avoided, are precisely the cases where <i>personne</i> contained in the larger phrase (i.e., in the extraction island) is able to move (covertly) to the highest Spec position of that phrase. Consider, for instance, the contrast between (90) and (91), representing one type of evidence used by Moritz and Valois.</p>
<p>(90)&ensp;<object id="tu65" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu65_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*l&rsquo;homme</entry>
<entry>dont<sub>i</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Lise</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>vu &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>sa (<i>agent</i>)</entry>
<entry>photo t<sub>i</sub> (<i>theme</i>)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry></entry>
<entry>the-man</entry>
<entry>of-whom</entry>
<entry>Lise</entry>
<entry>has</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
<entry>his</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col7">&lsquo;the man of whom Lise saw his picture&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Lise</entry>
<entry>n&rsquo;a</entry>
<entry>vu &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>sa (<i>agent</i>)</entry>
<entry>photo</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry><i>personne</i> (<i>theme</i>)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry></entry>
<entry>Lise</entry>
<entry>Neg-has</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
<entry>his</entry>
<entry>picture</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>nobody</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Lise did not see his picture of anybody.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col6" nameend="col8">(Adapted from <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>, (49b) and (50b)))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(91)&ensp;<object id="tu66" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu66_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*De</entry>
<entry>qui<sub>i</sub>
</entry>
<entry>Louise</entry>
<entry>est-elle</entry>
<entry>partie &lsqb;<sub>PP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>avec &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>l&rsquo;amie t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry></entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>whom</entry>
<entry>Louise</entry>
<entry>is-she</entry>
<entry>left</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>the-friend</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Whose friend did Louise leave with?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Louise</entry>
<entry>n&rsquo;est</entry>
<entry>partie &lsqb;<sub>PP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>avec &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub>
</entry>
<entry>l&rsquo;amie</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry><i>personne</i>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>Louise</entry>
<entry>Neg-is</entry>
<entry>left</entry>
<entry>with</entry>
<entry>the-friend</entry>
<entry>of</entry>
<entry>nobody</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col8">&lsquo;Louise did not leave with anybody&apos;s friend.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry namest="col6" nameend="col8">(Adapted from <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>, (58a, b)))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The (a) sentences demonstrate the impossibility of extraction from the DP in (90) and the PP in (91). Given this, the crucial evidence regarding LF-pied-piping is provided by the contrast between the negative sentences (90b) and (91b), both of which exhibit <i>personne</i> in a position prohibiting extraction. Apparently, the island effect in (91) can be voided via LF-pied-piping by <i>personne</i> in (91b); since the sentence is well-formed, a &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb; phrase must have moved covertly to the Spec of NegP to license the negative head. In contrast, sentence (90b) is ungrammatical, indicating that no movement of a &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb; phrase to the Spec of NegP could take place in it. Hence it must be the case that in (90b), not only extraction but crucially, also LF-pied-piping of the whole DP by <i>personne</i> is blocked. This fact about examples like (90b) is related by Moritz and Valois to a constraint widely observed in studies of extraction out of DP in Romance; it limits which argument of an N may move to the Spec of DP, and hence get extracted from DP. Crucially, it has the effect that when a noun phrase has both an agent and a theme, only the agent is able to move to the Spec position of the DP, and possibly get extracted further (this effect is shown overtly by the ungrammatical (90a)). The important point of the above argument is then that the impossibility of LF-piped-piping by <i>personne</i> (a theme) in (90b) and the contrast with the possibility of LF-pied-piping by <i>personne</i> in (91b) would follow if the LF-pied-piping option were dependent on the ability of <i>personne</i> to move to the Spec position of the phrase to be pied-piped (in our cases, the phrase constituting an island for it); in other words, the evidence suggests that <i>personne</i> can pied-pipe the DP by LF-movement only if it comes to occupy the Spec of DP position. Notice that this finding of <link rid="b5">Moritz and Valois (1994</link>) falls in place immediately in light of the two major conclusions we reached earlier on the basis of overt pied-piping: namely, (a) that pied-piping is possible only as a result of the &lsquo;pied-piped&rsquo; phrase acquiring the feature that drives the particular movement (in the above case &lsqb;&plus;Neg&rsqb;), and (b) that the feature-percolation mechanism is limited to Spec&ndash;Head agreement and to projection from the head of a phrase to the maximal projection (see (47) in <link rid="ss15">section 4.2</link>). Thus, Moritz and Valois&apos;s analysis seems to strongly support the assumption that, beyond Move &alpha; itself being uniform before and after S-structure/Spell Out, so are the mechanisms that regulate the possibility of pied-piping.</p>
<p>Within some versions of the MP, introducing feature movement to replace the traditional GB conception of Move &alpha;, and principles of derivational economy to limit movements strictly to operations necessary to ensure convergence, the very existence of covert phrasal movement was called into question. In particular, <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>) proposed that movement of any material beyond just the formal features themselves is an instance of pied-piping (referred to as &ldquo;generalized pied-piping&rdquo;) and furthermore, according to an economy condition postulated, it can take place only when forced by needs of the PF interface, i.e., when the output without it would be &lsquo;unpronounceable&rsquo;. (On this conception of pied-piping, see also <link rid="ss23">section 6</link>.) Under this strong hypothesis, all covert movements would necessarily be pure feature movements; only overt movements could be phrasal. In the context of this prediction, the evaluation of empirical evidence apparently pointing to the existence of covert phrasal movement, i.e., to the possibility of pied-piping under LF movement, becomes even more important than it was in earlier frameworks.</p>
<p>A particularly important kind of evidence in favor of LF-pied-piping is provided by the phenomenon of antecedent-contained deletion (ACD). The case of ACD constructions, exemplified in (92), is of special interest because the evidence it provides is very different in nature from the more common kind discussed above. In the above types, LF-pied-piping was inferred based on the observed bypassing of particular island effects. However, in the case of ACD, the evidence for LF-pied-piping involves interpretability, namely the resolution of VP anaphora.</p>
<p>(92) John &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> met &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> everyone that I did &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.<br/>(Interpreted as <i>John met everyone that I met</i> t.)</p>
<p>The essence of the argument from ACD is based on the fact that the elided VP in cases like (92) needs a linguistic antecedent in order to get interpreted, but its antecedent is the matrix VP that the elided VP is contained in. Thus, in the surface representation given in (92) there is no way to assign an interpretation to this null VP, since the process of VP-anaphora interpretation &ndash; the copying of the antecedent (the matrix VP) into the null VP &ndash; would reintroduce the VP gap itself, resulting in an infinite regress. This problem of regress can be eliminated, however, if there is some independently motivated process removing the elided VP from within the larger VP before the application of the interpretive (copying) procedure of VP-ellipsis. As was originally proposed by <link rid="b26">May (1985</link>), and elaborated further, for instance, in <link rid="b67">Larson and May (1990</link>), <link rid="b68">Fiengo and May (1994</link>), and <link rid="b69">Fox (1999</link>), precisely such an independently motivated process is QR, applying to the quantified head of the relative clause containing the elided VP. Thus if QR can move not only the quantifier, or the quantificational feature, but can pied-pipe the whole complex noun phrase, including the relative clause with the elided VP in it, to a position outside of the VP that contained it, then ACD inter-pretation would automatically become unproblematic. The LF-representation provided by QR under the assumption that it can involve pied-piping is given in (93).</p>
<p>(93) &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> everyone<sub>i</sub> that I did &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb; &lsqb;John &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> met <i>t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>This covert pied-piping would leave behind a VP of the form &lsqb;<i>met t</i>&rsqb; which could now constitute an appropriate antecedent to be copied into the VP gap and provide the proper interpretation for the ACD construction in (92) (on the compatibility of this account with the copy theory of movement in the MP, see <link rid="b69">Fox 1999</link>):</p>
<p>(94) &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> everyone<sub>i</sub> that I &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> <i>met t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb; &lsqb;John &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> <i>met t</i><sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>
<link rid="b36">Hornstein (1995</link>) proposes a Case-driven, rather than a quantifier-driven, view of the movement involved, but this account, too, relies on the assumption of covert pied-piping &ndash; specifically, on pied-piping under covert A-movement. (For proposals using overt movements in the account of ACD, see <link rid="b70">Baltin 1987</link> and <link rid="b35">Kayne 2000</link>: ch. 13.)</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss23" level="1">
<heading id="h22" level="1">6&ensp;The Minimalist Program and further current directions</heading>
<p>As reflected in the discussion of the above sections, the status of pied-piping in the theory has undergone substantial changes since its introduction in the late 1960s until current times, in accord with the evolution of the model of UG in general, and with the shifts in the conception of movement operations in particular. Here we will consider briefly the way pied-piping is conceived in current syntactic theorizing and sketch the role it plays and the issues it raises in <link rid="b6 b28">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c, 2000</link>) MP framework and other varieties of contemporary MP-related research.</p>
<subsection id="ss24" level="2">
<heading id="h23" level="2">6.1&ensp;Feature movement, economy, and generalized pied-piping</heading>
<p>From the perspective of the GB framework, the major issue regarding pied-piping was to determine when it has the option to take place and when it is impossible. This in turn was due to the underlying assumption that, just like movement itself, pied-piping has no cost, and that therefore its application does not need to be (though of course may be) forced by some particular structural or other circumstance. In sharp contrast to this, <link rid="b6">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) MP conception of pied-piping is based on the view of movement operations as involving, ideally, movement of no more than just the formal features of lexical items needed for the checking of corresponding uninterpretable features on some functional head. As pointed out already in <link rid="ss22">section 5</link>, the need for feature checking itself could not drive movement of any extra material beyond the feature itself. In the spirit of the economy of derivation adopted in the MP framework, this is taken to imply that movement of any lexical material, i.e., any pied-piping of material by the attracted or moved feature, referred to by Chomsky as generalized pied-piping, will be possible only to the extent that it is required for the convergence of the derivation at one of the interfaces. Furthermore, given that the most obvious problem with displacing isolated features seemed to be &lsquo;unpronouncability&rsquo; &ndash; namely the lack of proper interpretation at the PF interface &ndash; <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>: 262&ndash;263) suggested a stronger version of the above hypothesis, according to which it is only PF needs, such as morphological and phonological properties determining PF convergence, that can induce (generalized) pied-piping. On this conception, pied-piping is viewed as a repair strategy imposed on the computational system by factors external to the system itself.</p>
<p>This PF-based hypothesis works adequately in some cases, as exemplified by the way <i>wh</i>-feature attraction applies to a <i>wh</i>-phrase like <i>whose book</i> (where <i>who</i> is assumed to be in the Spec of DP and &rsquo;<i>s</i> is a possessive D, heading the DP). The attracted <i>wh</i>-feature cannot raise by itself since it would result in a crash at PF. So at least the whole lexical item <i>who</i> must be pied-piped; but in the present case, this would leave behind &rsquo;<i>s book</i>, a form that would also cause a crash at PF; furthermore, <i>whose</i> (at least in English) cannot raise either, since being made up of the Spec of DP (<i>who</i>) and the head D (&rsquo;<i>s</i>) it is a non-constituent, i.e., it is not a syntactic object at all, so it cannot be affected by a movement operation. Consequently, the smallest element that can legitimately be raised by Attract/Move &lsqb;wh&rsqb; according to <link rid="b6">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) hypothesis is predicted to be the phrase <i>whose book.</i> It would furthermore be predicted that unless justified by additional PF needs, this would also be the maximal phrase that gets pied-piped; thus, e.g., phrases like <i>read whose book</i> and <i>an article about whose book</i> cannot get pied-piped under <i>wh</i>-feature movement.</p>
<p>Although the PF convergence hypothesis correctly derives pied-piping and, moreover, also the Left Branch Condition effect in the present case, it obviously faces some serious conceptual and empirical challenges. On the conceptual side, the proposed economy condition involving the PF interface means that the determination of how much material is pied-piped each time when Attract applies to some feature in a derivation would involve significant look-ahead, a property known to result in sharply increased computational complexity. However, it is unlikely that such complexity is indeed inherent in overt movements, which manifest no corresponding special difficulty in production and processing (on the elimination of similar computational complexity with respect to Procrastinate and &lsquo;strong&rsquo; features, see <link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link>: 228). One obvious empirical challenge for a purely PF-convergence induced view of pied-piping would be the apparent optionality of some cases of pied-piping, i.e., its alternation with extraction. This is the case, for instance, in <i>wh</i>-phrases in the Spec of DP in Russian-type languages, which permit Left Branch Condition violations, or in the case of Hungarian DPs with dative-marked possessors in the top Spec position (analyzed in <link rid="b16">Szabolcsi 1983</link>). It is unclear how the larger phrases would be able to get pied-piped in such cases without violating the economy principle of carrying only the minimal amount of material sufficient for PF convergence.</p>
<p>These problems would not arise in the same way under <link rid="b28">Chomsky&apos;s (2000</link>) version of the MP since it gives up the view of overt movement as generalized pied-piping, treating it as a &lsquo;repair strategy&rsquo; for (pre-Spell Out) feature movement. It reanalyzes feature movement as long-distance agreement via the operation Agree and separates the case of overt movements from this feature-checking process in a way that makes overt movement essentially independent of the need of eliminating uninterpretable features. Instead, all overt movements are viewed as satisfying a further requirement imposed by particular functional heads to have a specifier projected (similarly to early versions of the EPP). Under this view the movement of overt material, namely, of a phrase, would no longer be a case of pied-piping induced by PF convergence. However, the empirical problem of how &lsquo;big&rsquo; the moved phrase can be, i.e., what constituent can be legitimately moved to satisfy these &lsquo;EPP&rsquo; requirements, is still a major issue.</p>
<p>It might be possible to deal with the problems of PF-convergence-induced pied-piping while maintaining the assumptions of feature movement and the economy principle of &lsquo;carry as little as possible&rsquo; in some form. This involves trying to attribute the existence of phrasal movements not exclusively to the needs of PF convergence, but at least in part to the interaction of the above economy principle, requiring movement of the minimal element, with a major independently motivated economy principle of <link rid="b6">Chomsky (1995c</link>: 297) built into the Attract operation. The latter condition requires Attract to target the closest feature that can enter into a checking relation with a feature of the attracting head (exemplified, e.g., in Superiority effects). Given that a feature (say, &lsqb;<i>wh</i>&rsqb;) occurring, for instance, on a morpheme in the Spec of a Spec of DP, such as in &lsqb;<i>whose friend&apos;s mother</i>&rsqb;, would be further away (under an appropriate definition of &lsquo;closeness&rsquo;) from the <i>wh</i>-attracting C-head of the clause than the whole large DP itself, the condition &lsquo;closest&rsquo; on Attract would force it to target the large DP, rather than the <i>wh</i>-morpheme <i>who</i>. This assumes that the <i>wh</i>-feature was present not only within the Spec of the Spec of the DP, but &ndash; due to feature percolation (motivated earlier) &ndash; also on the large DP itself. Such a proposal would have the further advantage of being able to maintain the desirable empirical results of the earlier feature-percolation based accounts of pied-piping with respect to the possible phrase-internal positions of pied-pipers, as discussed in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>. In a framework permitting feature-movement, this proposal would of course still need to avoid movement of just the bare <i>wh</i>-feature that percolated to the large DP in the case under discussion, and induce raising of that whole DP instead. But this would follow as before; bare feature movement prior to Spell Out would be excluded by the assumption that features displaced from their lexical item cause a PF-crash (<link rid="b6">Chomsky 1995c</link>). This type of conception of phrasal movement is explored in <link rid="b71">Pesetsky (2000</link>), where the option of phrasal vs. feature or morpheme movement is seen as moving the closest bearer vs. the smallest bearer of the relevant feature, both being considered ways of satisfying derivational economy.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss25" level="2">
<heading id="h24" level="2">6.2&ensp;Phrasal movement vs. head movement, large-scale pied-piping, and the elimination of feature movement</heading>
<p>The empirical issue of correctly accounting for how big a constituent bearing the relevant feature ends up moving can be &ndash; in other words, what constituent gets pied-piped by the minimal element needed for feature-checking &ndash; arises independently of whether the theory postulates feature movement per se and whether one assumes an economy-based preference for moving the smallest element possible (as <link rid="b6">Chomsky&apos;s 1995c</link> version of the MP did). Notice, for instance, that given the well-motivated feature-percolation mechanism underlying pied-piping, the problem of determining the choice between moving a head and moving the whole phrase (both bearing the same features) may arise in any framework in which movement is driven by feature-checking, even in one stipulating that features cannot move, i.e., that movements apply only to categories (as under Move &alpha; of the GB framework).</p>
<p>Notice that in GB theory this problem did not seem to arise. In that framework, movements were stipulated to involve requirements of individual Spec positions vs. requirements of particular heads, e.g., in the case of the <i>Wh</i>-Criterion, or the affix triggering V-to-I. This property, in conjunction with the structure preservation hypothesis (<link rid="b2">Emonds 1976</link>; <link rid="b18">Chomsky 1986a</link>), fully determined which movement will be phrasal movement and which will be head movement. Under the MP checking theory, however, this is no longer true, since the feature in need of checking (attracting to itself an element with a matching feature) always occurs on a functional head; specifiers as such are designated to play a role only in the more recent, EPP-based version of overt movement suggested in <link rid="b28">Chomsky (2000</link>) (see <link rid="ss24">section 6.1</link>).</p>
<p>Empirically, the issue of head vs. phrasal movement calls for further investigation. Yet, based on the range of cases studied, it appears that feature-checking, if it induces overt movement at all, induces pied-piping of a phrase rather than just the head (for evidence see, e.g., <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi&apos;s 2000</link> study of verb-raising structures). This may in turn follow automatically if head movement is in fact not an option in the computational system at all, only at PF (a hypothesis suggested recently on the basis of a variety of independent considerations for instance by <link rid="b28 b72">Chomsky 2000, Boeckx and Stjepanovi&#x0107; 2001</link> and others). If so, head movement could provide no alternative to feature-checking via phrasal movement.</p>
<p>Yet, a similar issue of whether or not a larger constituent XP gets pied-piped in the case of a phrase YP occurring in the Spec of XP remains an empirical problem, as it was for the previous hypotheses. The Spec position has been seen to be a position potentially permitting pied-piping of the phrase (given the Spec&ndash;Head agreement based feature percolation or inheritance mechanism). The question of when this option is taken and when the element in Spec extracts rather than pied-pipes the larger phrase would seem <i>a priori</i> to be subject to variation both within and across languages. In fact it is precisely this choice between extraction from Spec and pied-piping of the whole phrase by Spec provided by UG that is claimed in <link rid="b10">Koopman and Szabolcsi (2000</link>) to provide the basis for cross-linguistic as well as language-internal variation observed in the cases they studied.</p>
<p>An alternative, more challenging, hypothesis regarding pied-piping options is proposed in work by <link rid="b9 b7">Koopman (1996, 1997</link>). In exact opposition to <link rid="b6">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) economy principle minimizing the amount of pied-piped material, the hypothesis developed in this direction of research, conceptually inspired by Kayne&apos;s Antisymmetry framework, is that massive large-scale pied-piping is in fact the core operation by which derivation proceeds. This line of research makes use of no economy principles and stipulates no feature movement; instead it argues that large-scale pied-piping of different projections by feature-driven &lsquo;licensing&rsquo; movements within the functional layers of lexical categories is common, and, possibly, is the only option permitted by UG. Although these may be harder to detect than &lsquo;smaller&rsquo;, e.g. DP or PP, pied-piping, they can be argued for on empirical grounds, such as various agreement phenomena (for references, see <link rid="b9">Koopman 1996</link>). The reason given for why the alleged cases of large-scale heavy pied-piping escaped notice is that in structures with multi-layered functional projections above each lexical head (forming an extended projection in <link rid="b32">Grimshaw&apos;s 1991</link> terminology) the movement of large constituents (e.g., various clausal projections) to nearby Spec positions is hard to overtly detect, especially when the head of the phrase it lands in is null. In fact, <link rid="b7">Koopman (1997</link>) suggests that contrary to standard assumptions (see above), extraction from Spec is prohibited, and what appears to be extraction from Spec is actually pied-piping of the whole phrase that happens to be a remnant, containing overt material only corresponding to its Spec. Thus, the multiplicity of a universal set of functional categories generated above each lexical head assumed in current versions of the MP, in conjunction with the extensive use of remnant movement assumed in the above line of research, give a rather different picture of the pied-piping issue than previous theories did. Instead of a limited, relatively insignificant, property of movements, pied-piping in such a framework of assumptions is a major syntactic device that is a concomitant, essentially, of all movement. What forces such large-scale pied-piping is less clear; it obviously is not an economy condition that serves to maximize pied-piping. It appears that extensive heavy pied-piping is induced in the above version of the theory by directly eliminating potential alternatives from UG, for instance, by stipulating that bare feature-movements and extraction from Spec position do not exist.</p>
<p>In view of the emerging diverse hypotheses and research sketched above, what seems clear at this point is that pied-piping will be an important focus of attention and empirical investigation in the coming years of work in syntactic theory.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss26" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h25" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference id="b17" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Abney</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Steven<x> </x>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The English Noun Phrase in its Sentential Aspect. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>MIT</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b70" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baltin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Do Antecedent-Contained Deletions Exist?</title><x> </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>18</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">279</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">295</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Banfield</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ann</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1973">1973</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Stylistic Transformations in <i>Paradise Lost</i>. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Wisconsin</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b59" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Beghelli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Filippo</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Tim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stowell</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Distributivity and Negation: The Syntax of <i>Each</i> and <i>Every</i>
</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Ways of Scopetaking</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolcsi</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">71</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">107</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b72" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Boeckx</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Cedric</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Sandra</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stjepanovi&#x0107;</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2001">2001</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Head-ing Toward PF</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>32</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">345</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">355</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b48" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Botwinik-Rotem</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Irena</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2004">2004</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Category P: Features, Projections and Interpretation. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Tel Aviv University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Brame</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Head Selector Theory of Lexical Specifications and the Nonexistence of Coarse Categories</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Analysis</title><x> </x><volume>10</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">321</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">325</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bresnan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976c</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Form and Functioning of Transformations</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">3</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">40</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b61" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Brody</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Remarks on the Order of Elements in the Hungarian Focus Field</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Structures and Arguments: Approaches to Hungarian 3</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Istv&aacute;n</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kenesei</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">95</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">121</page><x>. </x><address>Szeged</address><x>: </x><publisher>Joseph Attila University.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Choe</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jae-Woong</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">LF Movement and Pied-Piping</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>18</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">348</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">353</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1964">1964a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Current Issues in Linguistic Theory</title><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1965">1965</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Aspects of the Theory of Syntax</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Lectures on Government and Binding</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Barriers</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Minimalist Program</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Minimalist Inquiries: The Framework</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Step by Step: Essays on Minimalist Syntax in Honor of Howard Lasnik</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Roger</forenames><x> </x><surname>Martin</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>David</forenames><x> </x><surname>Michaels</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Juan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Uriagereka</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">89</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">155</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b45" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cinque</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Guglielmo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Theory of Relative Clauses and Markedness</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">247</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">294</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b54" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cole</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Peter</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Imbabura Quechua</title><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>North-Holland.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Culicover</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Peter</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Syntactic Nuts: Hard Cases, Syntactic Theory, and Language Acquisition</title><x>. </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b55" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Echepare</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ricardo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Two Types of Focus in Basque</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Fifteenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Brian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Agbayani</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Sze-Wing</forenames><x> </x><surname>Tang</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">113</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">127</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A Transformational Approach to English Syntax: Root, Structure-Preserving and Local Transformations</title><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b44" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1979">1979</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Appositive Relatives Have No Properties</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>10</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">211</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">243</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Emonds</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A Unified Theory of Syntactic Categories</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b68" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fiengo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Indices and Identity</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fiengo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert,<x> </x>C<x>.</x>-T</forenames>
</name><x>. </x><name type="author">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>Huang</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Howard</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lasnik</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Tanya</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reinhart</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntax of <i>Wh</i>-in-Situ</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Seventh West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hagit</forenames><x> </x><surname>Borer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">81</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">98</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b69" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Economy and Semantic Interpretation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b56" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grewendorf</surname><x>, </x><forenames>G&uuml;nther</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Relativs&auml;tze im Deutschen: Die Rattenf&auml;ngerkonstruktion</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistische Berichte</title><x> </x><volume>195</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">409</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">434</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grimshaw</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Argument Structure</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grimshaw</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Extended Projections. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Brandeis University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pied-Piping and the Matching Parameter</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">41</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">58</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grosu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alexander</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Three Studies in Locality and Case</title><x>. </x><address>London</address><x>: </x><publisher>Routledge.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b64" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haegeman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Liliane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Negation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b58" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haegeman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Liliane</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Raffaella</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zanuttini</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Negative Heads and the NEG Criterion</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>8</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">233</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">251</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b46" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hendrick</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Randall</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Construing Relative Pronouns</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Analysis</title><x> </x><volume>9</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">205</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">224</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hornstein</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Norbert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Logical Form: From GB to Minimalism</title><x>. </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Blackwell.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b60" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Horvath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Julia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Focus in the Theory of Grammar and the Syntax of Hungarian</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Horvath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Julia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Multiple <i>Wh</i>-Phrases and the <i>Wh</i>-Scope-Marker Strategy in Hungarian Interrogatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Acta Linguistica Hungarica</title><x> </x><volume>45</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">31</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">60</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b62" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Horvath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Julia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Interfaces vs. the Computational System in the Syntax of Focus</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Interface Strategies</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hans</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bennis</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Martin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Everaert</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">183</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">206</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holland Academic Graphics.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b65" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Huang</surname><x>, </x><forenames>C.-T<x>. </x>James</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Logical Relations in Chinese and the Theory of Grammar. PhD dissertation, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ishihara</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Roberta</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Clausal Pied Piping: A Problem for GB</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">397</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">418</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Connectedness and Binary Branching</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Antisymmetry of Syntax</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Parameters and Universals</title><x>. </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b63" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kiss</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Katalin<x> </x>&Eacute;<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Logical Structure and Syntactic Structure</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Logical Structure and Linguistic Structure: Cross-Linguistic Perspectives</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>C.-T<x>. </x>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>Huang</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">111</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">147</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Koopman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hilda</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Spec&ndash;Head Configuration</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Syntax at Sunset</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Edward</forenames><x> </x><surname>Garrett</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Felicia</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lee</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">37</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">64</page><x>. </x><address>Los Angeles</address><x>: </x><publisher>UCLA.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Koopman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hilda</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Heavy Pied-Piping. Handout, Jena Workshop on Pied-Piping</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b50" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Koopman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hilda</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Specifiers and Heads</title><x>. </x><address>London</address><x>: </x><publisher>Routledge.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b52" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Koopman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hilda</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Dominique</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sportiche</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Variables and the Bijection Principle</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">139</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">160</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Koopman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hilda</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolcsi</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Verbal Complexes</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kratzer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Angelika</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Severing the External Argument from Its Verb</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Phrase Structure and the Lexicon</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Johan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rooryck</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Laurie</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zaring</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">109</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">137</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b67" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Larson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Antecedent Containment or Vacuous Movement: A Reply to Baltin</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>21</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">103</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">122</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lasnik</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Howard</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Tim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stowell</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Weakest Crossover</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>22</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">687</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">720</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>May</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Logical Form: Its Structure and Derivation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Moritz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luc</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Daniel</forenames><x> </x><surname>Valois</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pied-Piping and Specifier&ndash;Head Agreement</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>25</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">667</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">707</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Nanni</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Debbie</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Justine</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stillings</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Three Remarks on Pied Piping</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>9</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">310</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">318</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Nishigauchi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Taisuke</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Quantification in the Theory of Grammar</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b11" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Nkemnji</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Heavy Pied-Piping in Nweh. PhD dissertation, UCLA</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b53" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ortiz de Urbina</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jon</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Operator Feature Percolation and Clausal Pied Piping</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">MIT Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>13</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">193</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">208</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pearson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Matthew</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Two Types of OV Languages</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Derivation of OV and VO</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Svenonius</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">327</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">363</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pesetsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">
<i>Wh</i>-in-Situ: Movement and Unselective Binding</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Representation of (In)definiteness</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Alice<x> </x>ter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Meulen</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">98</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">129</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b71" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pesetsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Phrasal Movement and Its Kin</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Anaphora and Semantic Interpretation</title><x>. </x><address>London/Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Croom Helm/University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b49" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reflexivity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>24</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">595</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">652</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b51" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A Case Study in Syntactic Markedness: The Binding Nature of Prepositional Phrases<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Pied-Piped Infinitives in German Relative Clauses</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Studies in German Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jindrich</forenames><x> </x><surname>Toman</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">165</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">192</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Another Note on Clausal Pied-Piping</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Paths Towards Universal Grammar: Studies in Honor of Richard S<x>. </x>Kayne</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Guglielmo</forenames><x> </x><surname>Cinque</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Koster</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jean-Yves</forenames><x> </x><surname>Pollock</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Luigi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rizzi</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Raffaella</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zanuttini</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">331</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">342</page><x>. </x><address>Washington, DC</address><x>: </x><publisher>Georgetown University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b57" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991b</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Residual Verb Second and the <i>Wh</i>-Criterion. Technical Reports in Formal and Computational Linguistics 2</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Geneva</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ross</surname><x>, </x><forenames>John<x> </x>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Infinite Syntax!</title><x> </x><address>Norwood, NJ</address><x>: </x><publisher>Ablex.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b47" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Safir</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Kenneth</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Relative Clauses in a Theory of Binding and Levels</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">663</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">690</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Sketch of a Reductionist Approach to Syntactic Variation and Dependencies</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Evolution and Revolution in Syntactic Theory</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>H&eacute;ctor</forenames><x> </x><surname>Campos</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Paula</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kempchinsky</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">356</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">398</page><x>. </x><address>Washington</address><x>: </x><publisher>Georgetown University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b66" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Stechow</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Arnim<x> </x>von</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Against LF Pied-Piping</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>4</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">57</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">110</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Szabolcsi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anna</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Possessor that Ran Away from Home</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">89</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">102</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Webelhuth</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Principles and Parameters of Syntactic Saturation</title><x>. </x><address>Oxford/New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
