<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="74"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 74 - Unexpected Wide-Scope Phenomena.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">175</page>
<page type="last">228</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="1"/>
<count type="table" count="76"/>
<count type="formula" count="0"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="84"/>
<count type="page" count="54"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20051201"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 74&ensp;Ruys: Unexpected Wide-Scope Phenomena</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 74&ensp;Ruys: Unexpected Wide-Scope Phenomena</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">74&ensp;Unexpected Wide-Scope Phenomena</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>E. G.</forenames><x> </x><surname>RUYS</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>
<p>Introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>Specificity: a binary ambiguity?</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.1</number>
<p>A brief note on ambiguity</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>The scope of indefinites and QR</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Island-escaping scope</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Against &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo;</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Intermediate readings</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>VP ellipsis</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Distribution and scope</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>ACD and specificity</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusions</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>Intermediate readings</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>One solution: choice functions</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>6&ensp;</number>
<p>Do specific NPs support existential entailments?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>7&ensp;</number>
<p>How to create a specific NP</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>8&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusion: outline and summary</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1&ensp;Introduction</heading>
<p>It has long been known that quantificational expressions in natural language do not all have the same scope properties. While the scope of some expressions is closely related to their observable, &lsquo;surface&rsquo; position in syntactic structure, other expressions display a remarkable degree of freedom with respect to the relative scope that may obtain between them and other expressions in the structure. Compare (1) and (2):</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Some girl watched every movie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Some girl will be happy if every movie is shown.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(2)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every girl watched some movie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every girl will be happy if some movie is shown.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(1a) is ambiguous: it can be read as involving a girl who has seen all the movies, but is also judged true when each movie was seen by a different girl; the latter reading may be described by saying that <i>every movie</i> takes wide scope relative to <i>some girl</i>. (1b), on the other hand, does not allow wide scope for <i>every movie</i> relative to <i>some girl</i>; its truth requires that there be (at least) one indefatigable girl who will be happy if all the movies are shown. Thus, while the scope of <i>every movie</i> is not exactly fixed at its observable position &ndash; witness the ambiguity of (1a) &ndash; neither is it completely free. When <i>every movie</i> is embedded in an <i>if</i>-clause, as in (1b), it cannot take scope over another expression that is not so embedded. See <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 16 - Conditionals.xml" type="file">chapters 16</externallink></related>, <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 53 - Quantifier Scope Ambiguities.xml" type="file">chapter 53</externallink></related>, and <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">64</externallink></related>. The restriction observed in (1b) does not, however, apply to all NPs, as we find in (2), where the positions of the two NP types are reversed. The indefinite NP <i>some movie</i> can escape the scope of <i>every girl</i> not only in (2a), but also in (2b), regardless of the <i>if</i>-clause. Thus, (2b) can be understood as stating that there is a particular movie, such that every girl will be happy if it is shown.</p>
<p>This chapter focuses on the scope properties of NPs such as <i>some movie</i> in (2b), which, following tradition, we will refer to as being <i>specific</i> on the intended reading.<link rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup></link> <link rid="ss3">Section 2</link> provides a little historical background, and introduces two opposing views that underlie much of the literature on the subject. <link rid="ss5">Section 3</link> describes the properties that make the scope of indefinites exceptional in several respects. <link rid="ss13">Section 4</link> discusses the issue of &lsquo;intermediate island-escaping scope&rsquo;, which has featured prominently in the literature since <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>). <link rid="ss14">Section 5</link> goes into some detail in describing a fairly recent approach, which holds that a semantic choice function mechanism is to be held responsible for the exceptional wide-scope readings found with specific NPs; <link rid="ss15">section 6</link> discusses one prominent problem that seems to attend this approach. <link rid="ss16">Section 7</link> discusses some of the, mostly tentative, work that has been devoted to delineating the class of indefinite NPs that show exceptional wide scope. A more detailed outline and summary is given as <link rid="ss17">section 8</link>.</p>
<p>Our aims are highly descriptive throughout. We will refrain from attempting to summarize the wide variety of (mainly semantic) theories that have been proposed in explanation of the specificity phenomenon. We will merely attempt to establish the reality of the phenomenon, describe some of its attendant properties and preconditions, and delineate the prerequisites for a successful theory of specificity as they emerge from recent research.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss3" level="1">
<heading id="h2" level="1">2 Specificity: a binary ambiguity?</heading>
<p>This section introduces the specificity phenomenon. It provides some historical background, and along the way it presents some of the basic observations, and describes two prominent approaches to the analysis of specificity. The first approach says that indefinite NPs show an inherent binary ambiguity: they may be interpreted as quantificational expressions (non-specific) or as something else (specific). The second approach holds that indefinites are always quantificational expressions, and that the specific vs. non-specific ambiguity is a scope ambiguity.</p>
<p>By way of introduction to the binary ambiguity approach to specificity, consider the following examples adapted from <link rid="b2">Karttunen (1968</link>) (see also <link rid="b3">Baker 1966</link> for the observation regarding (4b)):</p>
<p>(3)&ensp;Mary has <i>a car</i>. <i>It</i> is blue.</p>
<p>(4)&ensp;<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Mary doesn&apos;t have <i>a car</i>. <i>It</i> is blue.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*John wants to catch <i>a fish</i>. You can see <i>it</i> from here.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*All the boys in this town are in love with <i>a girl in this town</i>. <i>She</i> is very pretty.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (3), the pronoun <i>it</i> can be felicitously used to refer to a car owned by Mary. This option is due to the appearance of the indefinite <i>a car</i> in the first sentence of the discourse, which, Karttunen claimed, introduces a discourse referent that the pronoun refers to. The pronouns in (4), on the other hand, cannot be so used. For instance, <i>it</i> in (4a) cannot be taken to refer to the car that Mary doesn&apos;t have. The generalization that apparently governs these facts is that in (4), the indefinite NPs are embedded in the scope of some other expression (<i>not</i>, <i>want</i>, <i>all the boys in this town</i>); this prevents the introduction of a discourse referent.</p>
<p>In many cases, however, some slight adjustment in the example will allow discourse anaphora even in the structures of (4):</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Mary doesn&apos;t own <i>a car she drives</i>. She rents <i>it</i> instead.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>John wants to catch <i>a fish he spotted today</i>. You can see <i>it</i> from here.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>All the boys in this town are in love with <i>a redheaded gogo-dancer who works at the Moonlight Inn</i>. <i>She</i> is very pretty.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Apparently, the indefinites in (5) do manage to introduce a discourse referent, despite the presence of a higher scoped element. <link rid="b2">Karttunen&apos;s (1968</link>) description of these facts stated that indefinites are ambiguous between a specific and non-specific reading. He took this binary ambiguity to reside in the interpretation of the indefinite itself. The non-specific ones in (4), which do not introduce a discourse referent from a scopally embedded position, are interpreted as existentially quantified expressions; the specific ones in (5), which introduce a discourse referent even from a scopally embedded position, function semantically as name-like referential expressions.<link rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup></link> This description provides no answer to the question why the non-specific readings are strongly favored in (4), whereas slight lexical and structural variations bring out the specific readings in (5) (a question that still goes unresolved; in fact, speakers generally allow a specific reading, and discourse anaphora, in (4) as well, albeit less readily than in (5); see <link rid="ss16">section 7</link>). The proposed quantificational/referential ambiguity does, however, point toward an explanation for the different discourse anaphora options along the following lines.</p>
<p>If the indefinites in (3) and (4) are associated with existential quantifiers, then we expect them to be sensitive to the presence of other scopal expressions in the structure. From a more modern DRT perspective, the sentences in (3) and (4) might then be roughly represented (<link rid="b4">Heim 1982</link>-style) as in (6) and (7):</p>
<p>(6)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>T</sub> &exist;x &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> car(x) &and; Mary has x&rsqb;. &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> x is blue&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>(7)&ensp;<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup> &lsqb;<sub>T</sub> &exist; &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> NEG &exist;x &lsqb;car(x) &and; Mary has x&rsqb;&rsqb;. &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> x is blue&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup> &lsqb;<sub>T</sub> &exist; &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> John wants &lsqb;&exist;x &lsqb;fish(x) &and; PRO catch x&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;. &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> You can see x from here&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup> &lsqb;<sub>T</sub> &exist; &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> &forall;x &lsqb;boy(x) &rarr; &exist;y &lsqb;girl(y) &and; x loves y&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;. &lsqb;<sub>S</sub> y is very pretty&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Here, consecutive sentences are thought of as being attached to a single T(ext) node. Discourse anaphora can come about when an existential quantifier takes scope at T level, binding a variable in one sentence, and subsequently binding a pronoun, translated as the same variable, in the next sentence. Thus, the indefinite in (3), even if it is non-specific and interpreted through existential quantification as in (6), may antecede the pronoun because the existential quantification in question takes place at Text level, and this quantifier takes scope over the second sentence and binds the pronoun. The non-specific indefinites in (4), on the other hand, are associated with a lower existential quantifier in scope, which does not scope over, and hence does not bind, the pronoun; even if there is a Text-level (default) existential quantifier, it binds nothing in the first sentence and cannot relate the pronoun in the second sentence to the indefinite.</p>
<p>If, furthermore, the specific indefinites in (5) are indeed &lsquo;name-like&rsquo; expressions, as Karttunen claimed, then we expect them to be insensitive to scope effects and to license discourse anaphora from any position, just like proper names. For instance, (5a) is expected to bear a close semantic resemblance to (8):</p>
<p>(8)&ensp;Mary doesn&apos;t own <i>Fido</i>. She is looking after <i>him</i> for the weekend.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b2">Karttunen&apos;s (1968</link>) view of specific indefinites exemplifies an approach to specificity that plays an important role in the literature to this day &ndash; namely, that the phenomenon derives from a binary ambiguity residing in the indefinite NP itself: an indefinite may be interpreted through a quantificational or a referential mechanism.<link rid="fn3">
<sup>3</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Around the same time, work by <link rid="b5">Heringer (1969</link>) and <link rid="b6">Fodor (1970</link>) on the interpretation of specific and non-specific indefinites in opaque contexts provided evidence against this view, and in favor of the view that indefinites are invariably quantificational expressions, involved in scope ambiguities. Fodor discussed several different effects that show up the ambiguity that obtains when an indefinite is embedded in an intensional context. First, such contexts block existential entailments:</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry> &plus; John has a car &rArr; there is a car.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&minus; John wants to marry a witch &rArr; there is a witch.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&plus; John wants to marry a witch he met last week &rArr; there is a witch John met last week.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When an indefinite is not embedded, the proposition it occurs in is judged to allow the entailment that the noun-set of the indefinite is not empty, as indicated in (9a). When the indefinite is embedded in an opaque context, a <i>de re</i>/<i>de dicto</i> ambiguity arises. The <i>de re</i> reading, prominent in (9c), says that there is a particular witch that John wants to marry; this reading entails that there is such a witch. The <i>de dicto</i> reading, favored in (9b), can be paraphrased as saying that John wants to marry any witch at all, a wish he may well entertain even if there exist no witches; hence, the entailment does not hold. Similar entailment observations can be made with respect to the other embedding contexts illustrated in (4) and (5) above.<link rid="fn4">
<sup>4</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Another ambiguity obtaining in opaque contexts relates to whether or not the description in the indefinite may be replaced by any extensionally equivalent description without changing the truth-conditions of the sentence. Such substitution is valid when the indefinite is not embedded, as the intuited validity of the inference in (10) illustrates:</p>
<p>(10)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Mary employs an Italian man.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>All Italian men drive a moped.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&plus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary employs a man who drives a moped.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When the indefinite is embedded in an opaque context, however, an ambiguity arises. On the <i>de dicto</i> reading, which is more prominent in (11), the inference is not valid; on the <i>de re</i> reading, which is more prominent in (12), it is:</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Mary wants to marry an Italian man.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>All Italian men drive a moped.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&minus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary wants to marry a man who drives a moped.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Mary wants to marry an Italian man she met in Venice the other day.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>All Italian men drive a moped.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&plus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary wants to marry a man who drives a moped.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These ambiguities are traditionally described by assuming that indefinites are interpreted as existential quantifiers, which may take narrow or wide scope relative to the intensional verb (see, e.g., <link rid="b7">Bach 1968</link>: 107, but also <link rid="b8">Quine 1956</link>). The narrow-scope reading corresponds to the <i>de dicto</i> reading; the wide-scope reading to the <i>de re</i> reading. (13) illustrates this:<link rid="fn5">
<sup>5</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">John wants to marry a witch.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>John wants &lsqb;&exist;x &lsqb;witch(x) &and; PRO marry x&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;witch(x) &and; John wants &lsqb;PRO marry x&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (13b), the existential quantifier takes wide scope relative to <i>want</i> (so that the sentence is about a particular individual (witch), and existential entailment is valid), and so does the description <i>witch</i> (so that that particular individual is asserted to be a witch in the world in which the sentence as a whole is evaluated, or &lsquo;according to the speaker&rsquo; &ndash; hence, substitution <i>salva veritate</i> is allowed). In (13a), both quantifier and description take narrow scope; hence the sentence is not about a particular individual, and both the existence of such an individual and the description <i>witch</i> need only hold in those worlds that conform to John&apos;s wishes; the description is not the speaker&apos;s responsibility, it is John who wants to marry any individual &lsquo;under the description of&rsquo; her being a witch. (13b) logically allows the existential entailment and the substitution; (13a) does not.</p>
<p>(13) exemplifies a view on specific indefinites that opposes <link rid="b2">Karttunen&apos;s (1968</link>) proposal. There is no binary ambiguity in the indefinite; rather, the indefinite is always interpreted with an existential quantifier. The observed ambiguities reflect the various scope positions available for the quantifier. Indeed, <link rid="b9">Karttunen (1971a</link>) adopted this view and argued that it explains the discourse anaphora facts in (3&ndash;5) as well: the specific indefinites in (5) are existential quantifiers that escape the scope of the other operators, and therefore allow discourse anaphora just like the indefinite in (3) (cf. (6)). Much of the literature on specificity since then has revolved around the pros and cons of these two opposing views.</p>
<p>Fodor presented several observations that argue against a binary referential/quantificational ambiguity. One such observation is that the analysis in (13) is not fine-grained enough. There is no strict correlation between the existential entailment and substitution effects; with an effort, we can observe a four-way ambiguity according to these two parameters. (14) approximates the two additional readings for (13), where the scope of the existential quantifier and the scope of the description do not coincide:</p>
<p>(14)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">John wants to marry a witch.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup> witch(x) &and; John wants &lsqb;&exist;x &and; PRO marry x&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><sup>??</sup> &exist;x John wants &lsqb;witch(x) &and; PRO marry x&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Some context can help to bring out the intended readings. Suppose, first, John wants to marry any old lady wearing a pointed hat who flies a broomstick, but believes these are called &lsquo;airline-hostesses&rsquo;. Then we can truthfully utter (14); but the description <i>witch</i> is the speaker&apos;s responsibility (John&apos;s desires do not relate to that description) whereas there is not one particular such individual that John wants to marry &ndash; something like (14a) seems to be called for. Suppose, next, that John hallucinates the existence of several witches, and wants to marry a particular one among them. (14) is again true, but this time scope relations are reversed: John&apos;s desire is particularized to an individual (<i>de re</i>: wide-scope existential), but the description <i>witch</i> is not the speaker&apos;s responsibility; we end up with something like (14b).</p>
<p>These two additional readings for indefinites have received relatively little attention in the literature; partly, no doubt, because the readings are more elusive than those in (13), partly because their analysis is so problematic. We will henceforth ignore them &ndash; the reader is referred to <link rid="b10">Farkas (1997</link>) for an analysis that teases apart the scope of the restriction and the quantifier in a way that seems promising; see also <link rid="b11">Abbott (1993</link>) for an insightful discussion. The observed four-way ambiguity does, however, indicate that a simple binary ambiguity of indefinite NPs does not provide sufficient descriptive latitude.<link rid="fn6">
<sup>6</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Another observation by Fodor, and one which allows of analysis by more conventional means, also argues against a simple &plusmn; specific ambiguity. When more than one intensional verb c-commands an indefinite, more than two readings, corresponding to more potential scopal positions for the quantifier, are observed (the same observation, relating to definite NPs as well, is made in <link rid="b9">Karttunen 1971a</link>; <link rid="b12">Jackendoff 1972</link>: 281; <link rid="b13">Kripke 1979</link>; the oldest version of this argument that I am aware of is due to <link rid="b7">Bach 1968</link>: 107). Consider (15) (from Kripke):</p>
<p>(15)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Hoover charged that the Berrigans plotted to kidnap a high American official</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;but he said they couldn&apos;t decide which one (to kidnap).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;but he didn&apos;t know which one (they plotted to kidnap).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;guess which one (he charged they plotted to kidnap).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Hoover charged (the Berrigans plotted (&exist;x &lsqb;Hi.Am.Off.(x) &and; PRO kidnap x&rsqb;)).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b&prime;.</entry>
<entry>Hoover charged (&exist;x &lsqb;Hi.Am.Off.(x) &and; the Berrigans plotted (PRO kidnap x)&rsqb;).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c&prime;.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;Hi.Am.Off.(x) &and; Hoover charged (the Berrigans plotted (PRO kidnap x))&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(15) allows three readings, brought out by the three sluices in (15a&ndash;c), and corresponding to three scope positions for the existential quantifier associated with <i>a high American official</i> as indicated in the primed formulae. An analysis of specificity which holds that indefinites show a binary ambiguity between a referential reading, and a reading as an existential quantifier that is interpreted in its position in overt syntax, fails, in particular because it cannot account for the &lsquo;intermediate scope&rsquo; brought out by (15b). Here, <i>a high American official</i> is not referential (Hoover&apos;s charge is not about a particular individual, and there need not even exist any American officials for this reading to be felicitous and true). But if the indefinite is quantificational, the position of the quantifier here does not coincide with the surface position of the indefinite. Hence, it must be assumed that an indefinite may be interpreted by means of an existential quantifier that may be dislocated with respect to the indefinite&apos;s surface position. But if that much is assumed, the wide-scope reading (15c) and the other specific readings discussed above follow automatically, and no motivation for assuming a referential reading in addition to the quantificational reading of indefinites seemed to remain. What did remain, of course, was the question of how to account for the fact that an indefinite can be so freely associated with different scope positions.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss4" level="2">
<heading id="h3" level="2">2.1 A brief note on ambiguity</heading>
<p>Before we can turn to this question, there is a potentially confounding issue that needs to be addressed. We have so far assumed that the examples under discussion are truly ambiguous, not merely vague. This is an analytical assumption that is sometimes difficult to justify. Consider (16):</p>
<p>(16)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Every girl saw some movie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&forall;x &lsqb;girl(x) &rarr; &exist;y &lsqb;movie(y) &and; saw(x,y)&rsqb;&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;y &lsqb;movie(y) &and; &forall;x &lsqb;girl(x) &rarr; saw(x,y)&rsqb;&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When we claim <i>some movie</i> in (16) can be specific or non-specific relative to <i>every girl</i>, we attribute to the sentence two different readings that can, for instance, be represented as in (16a) and (16b). However, as the two alleged readings are not logically independent, this might well be unnecessary. (16b) entails (16a), so that the situations in which (16b) comes out as true are just a subset of the situations in which (16a) is also true. We judge (16) true when some particular movie is seen by every girl, but to explain this we need not assume that (16) can <i>mean</i> that there is some movie that was seen by every girl, as (16b) states; if (16) just means (16a), we expect the same judgment.<link rid="fn7">
<sup>7</sup></link> We might conclude that (16) is ambiguous if we found we could confidently judge it <i>false</i> when every girl saw some movie, but a different one &ndash; that would indicate we had &lsquo;chosen&rsquo; reading (16b). But readings that render a sentence false are usually, for pragmatic reasons, difficult to detect when a reading that renders it true, as (16a) would in this situation, is also available. For these reasons, it is wise to concentrate on examples where the two purported readings are logically independent, and one is not just a special case of the other:</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;Every girl but one saw some movie.</p>
<p>We judge (17) true when every girl saw <i>Brazil</i>, but every girl but one saw <i>2001</i> &ndash; a narrow-scope construal of <i>some movie</i> does not allow that, but a wide-scope construal does. Below, we will be careful to point out the logical independence of the readings that we attribute to our examples.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss5" level="1">
<heading id="h4" level="1">3 The scope of indefinites and QR</heading>
<p>Assume that the ambiguity of structures containing indefinite NPs reflects not some inherent binary ambiguity, but the different scope positions that may be taken by some (existential) quantifier involved in the interpretation of the indefinite, as suggested by the multiple ambiguity of (15). Then what explains this variation in scope? An obvious answer, and one that will function as a straw-man theory from here on, is that the indefinite itself denotes an existential quantifier, and that the indefinite is subject to a general scope-shifting rule. Such rules have been proposed to be operative in semantics (e.g., <link rid="b14">Cooper&apos;s 1983</link> storage, which &lsquo;separates&rsquo; a QNP&apos;s denotation from the denotation of the structure it is contained in, and then recombines the two; see <link rid="b15">Abusch 1994</link> for a similar approach geared specifically to indefinites) and in syntax as well &ndash; notably, Quantifier Raising (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 53 - Quantifier Scope Ambiguities.xml" type="file">chapter 53</externallink></related>). The literature provides considerable evidence that this approach to specificity will not work. The present section reviews the evidence; we will concentrate mainly on the feasibility of explaining specificity as an effect of syntactic movement.</p>
<subsection id="ss6" level="2">
<heading id="h5" level="2">3.1&ensp;Island-escaping scope</heading>
<p>Consider once more a simple example:</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Almost every girl saw a movie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> Almost every girl<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> a movie<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> t<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> saw t<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> A movie<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> almost every girl<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> t<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> saw t<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Supposing that QR associates (18) with the two LFs (18a) and (18b) (and perhaps more), familiar techniques yield the wide-scope and narrow-scope (specific and non-specific) readings for <i>a movie</i>, in the same way they derive the ambiguity of (1a) when QR applies to <i>every movie</i>.</p>
<p>There exist, however, strong indications, put forward most forcefully by <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>), that treating indefinites on a par with other, especially universally quantified NPs in this manner is undesirable. Their scope properties are very different. First and foremost, while QR as it applies to such NPs as <i>every movie</i> is subject to a wide array of familiar constraints on movement, and may even be essentially clause-bounded, the scope of indefinites seems, at least superficially, to be insensitive to such constraints. Consider (19) (cf. <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag 1982</link>):</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>If a relative of mine dies, I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>IF a relative of mine dies THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>A relative of mine x &lsqb;IF x dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&minus;(19b) &rArr; I have relatives.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>e.</entry>
<entry>&plus;(19c) &rArr; I have relatives.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>f.</entry>
<entry>IF a relative of mine dies THEN I will inherit a fortune. (19b)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>John is a relative of mine.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&plus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>IF John dies THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>g.</entry>
<entry>A relative of mine x &lsqb;IF x dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;. (19c)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>John is a relative of mine.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&minus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>IF John dies THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Sentence (19a) is ambiguous between a narrow-scope and wide-scope reading for <i>a relative of mine</i>; the two readings are paraphrased schematically in (19b) and (19c). According to the first, I will inherit a fortune if any one of my relatives dies; according to the latter, I will become rich if one particular relative of mine dies. Neither supposed reading, furthermore, entails the other, so that no problems of the type described in <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link> arise. First, (19c) entails that I have at least one relative (see (19e)), whereas (19b) does not. So (19b) does not entail (19c), as it would then share all entailments of (19c). Second, in combination with the premise that John is a relative of mine, (19b) allows the conclusion that I will inherit if John dies (see (19f)). (19c) does not allow this reasoning; John may just not be the particular relative whose death will put me in clover. So (19c) does not entail (19b), or it would also allow the conclusion about John.</p>
<p>Since we judge the sentence true even if my indigent uncle John will not leave me a fortune, we need in particular to posit the wide-scope reading (19c); the narrow-scope reading (19b) is false in that situation. Under the QR hypothesis, obtaining the wide-scope reading involves extracting the indefinite from the <i>if</i>-clause:</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<sup>??</sup>&lsqb;A relative of mine<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;&lsqb;if t<sub>i</sub> dies&rsqb; &lsqb;I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>However, this type of movement is generally disallowed as an Adjunct Condition violation; e.g., <i>wh</i>-expressions cannot be extracted from an <i>if</i>-clause (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">chapter 64</externallink></related>). And indeed, a universally quantified NP undergoing QR cannot escape this, or any other extraction island (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 53 - Quantifier Scope Ambiguities.xml" type="file">chapter 53</externallink></related>):</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">If every woman gave birth to John, then he has a nice mother.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&plus; IF every woman gave birth to John THEN he has a nice mother.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&minus; every woman x &lsqb;IF x gave birth to John THEN he has a nice mother&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(21), adapted from <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>), can only be understood in the pragmatically odd way paraphrased in (21a): if John has as many mothers as there are women, then he has a nice mother. This is the reading that corresponds to narrow scope of <i>every woman</i> inside the <i>if</i>-clause. Pragmatics thus pushes us toward a, much less odd, wide-scope reading (21b): whoever John&apos;s mother, she would be a nice mother. The fact that this reading is nevertheless unavailable shows very clearly that <i>every woman</i> cannot be QRed out of the extraction island. This observation constitutes a major obstacle to semantic treatments of quantifier scope such as Cooper storage; it is equally problematic for a QR treatment of the scope of the indefinite in (19).</p>
<p>Other Ross islands (<link rid="b17">Ross 1986</link>; and see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">chapter 64</externallink></related>) provide similar examples:</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Mary dates every man who has met a producer I know.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&forall;x &lsqb;&lsqb;man(x) &and; &exist;y &lsqb;producer_I_know(y) &and; x met y&rsqb;&rsqb; &rarr; Mary dates x&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;y &lsqb;producer_I_know(y) &and; &forall;x &lsqb;&lsqb;man(x) &and; x met y&rsqb; &rarr; Mary dates x&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&minus; (22b) &rArr; I know a producer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>e.</entry>
<entry>&plus; (22c) &rArr; I know a producer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">f.</entry>
<entry>(22b)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John is a producer I know.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&plus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>Mary dates every man who has met John.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>g.</entry>
<entry>(22c)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>John is a producer I know.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&minus;________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>Mary dates every man who has met John.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(22) is ambiguous between a narrow- and wide-scope reading for <i>a producer I know</i>, shown in (22b) and (22c). As before, neither reading entails the other.<link rid="fn8">
<sup>8</sup></link> (22d) and (22e) show that the narrow-scope reading does not entail the wide-scope reading, and, more significantly, (22f) and (22g) show that the wide-scope reading is not a special case of the narrow-scope reading. We can judge (22) true even if John is a producer I know, but Mary does not date every man who knows John. Hence, the wide-scope reading is well-motivated; but deriving it through QR would involve a Complex Noun Phrase Constraint (CNPC) violation. Compare (23):</p>
<p>(23)&ensp;Mary dates a man who has met every producer I know.</p>
<p>(23) is not ambiguous, and only allows narrow scope for <i>every producer I know</i>, as we expect from the syntactic movement properties of QR.</p>
<p>These examples provide similar evidence from other extraction islands:</p>
<p>(24)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Mary denied that <i>a theory of mine</i> was correct.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Mary denied that <i>every theory of mine</i> was correct.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Almost every expert admired John&apos;s picture of <i>a statue in Washington</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Someone admired John&apos;s picture of <i>every statue in Washington</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Almost every expert admired <i>an article of mine</i> and nominated me for a Pulitzer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Some expert admired <i>every article of mine</i> and nominated me for a Pulitzer.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In each of the (a)-cases, the indefinite can take wide scope even though it occupies a position from which overt movement, as well as QR in the (b)-cases, is disallowed. Movement in (24) would cross a non-bridge verb (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 10 - Bridge Phenomena.xml" type="file">chapters 10</externallink></related> and <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">64</externallink></related>); in (25) it would violate the Specificity Condition (see <link rid="b18">Davies and Dubinsky 2003</link> for recent discussion and references); in (26) it would violate the Coordinate Structure Constraint (see, e.g., <link rid="b19">Fox 1999</link> and references cited there).</p>
<p>In conclusion, it seems unlikely that the same rule can be held responsible for the scope options of both indefinites and other types of quantificational NPs. Furthermore, any syntactic movement rule seems an inappropriate device for describing the scope of indefinites, as one would need to exempt such a rule from all normal constraints on movement. On the other hand, semantic devices for lifting an indefinite NP denotation out of its context would need to be prevented from applying to other quantificational NPs as well.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, let us continue to assume that indefinite NPs unambiguously denote (existential) quantifiers, and let us now assume also, for the sake of argument, that for the purpose of scope assignment they can be dislocated from their observable position by some unrestricted mechanism which is somehow insensitive to the usual scope and movement islands &ndash; say, &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo;. This describes the observations in the present section. The following section presents arguments to the effect that these, already highly questionable, assumptions are still not sufficient to describe all scope properties of specific indefinites.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss7" level="2">
<heading id="h6" level="2">3.2 Against &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo;</heading>
<p>This section takes as its point of departure a straw-man &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; theory of specificity: indefinite NPs unambiguously denote quantifiers, which may be assigned wide scope regardless of the usual island constraints on movement and scope taking. Several types of observations argue against this approach: it both overgenerates and undergenerates readings. <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) pointed out that on the island-free QR approach, one expects indefinites to be able to scope out of islands without necessarily having the widest scope in the structure; they claimed this is not the case (<link rid="ss8">section 3.2.1</link>). Fodor and Sag argued further that if indefinites are always quantifiers, they disregard not only island conditions, but also conditions on free variables in VP-deletion contexts (<link rid="ss9">section 3.2.2</link>). <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>) pointed out that if indefinites freely take wide scope, one naturally expects plural indefinites to freely take wide, distributive scope as well; he claimed this is not the case (<link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link>).</p>
<subsection id="ss8" level="3">
<heading id="h7" level="3">3.2.1&ensp;Intermediate readings</heading>
<p>Having established the point made above in <link rid="ss6">section 3.1</link>, <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) presented an empirical argument against an &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; hypothesis. Consider (27):</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Every professor overheard &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> the rumor &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> that a student of mine had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&plus;</entry>
<entry>Every professor x &lsqb;x overheard the rumor &lsqb;that a student of mine y &lsqb;y had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&minus;</entry>
<entry>Every professor x &lsqb;a student of mine y &lsqb;x overheard the rumor that &lsqb;y had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&plus;</entry>
<entry>A student of mine y &lsqb;every professor x &lsqb;x overheard the rumor that &lsqb;y had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The indefinite <i>a student of mine</i> is embedded in an extraction island (the complex NP <i>the rumor that .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</i>&nbsp;); this NP itself is c-commanded by yet a higher quantifier, the matrix subject <i>every professor</i>. If the scope of indefinites were indeed unbounded, one would expect <i>a student of mine</i> to be able to remain within the complex NP that contains it in overt syntax (as in 27a), or to leave the complex NP and land below the matrix subject (27b), or to take widest scope (27c). Fodor and Sag claimed that just the (b)-reading is unavailable. The unavailability of such &lsquo;intermediate island-escaping readings&rsquo; for specific indefinites seems virtually impossible to describe with any &lsquo;free-scope&rsquo; mechanism: if the indefinite is able to move all the way up to a position outside the scope of the matrix subject, then surely it should be able to move less far, and land outside the complex NP but below the matrix subject. Therefore, Fodor and Sag returned to the hypothesis, rejected by <link rid="b6">Fodor (1970</link>) and others, that specificity is due to a binary ambiguity in the indefinite NP itself. An indefinite can be a quantifier, in which case it may undergo local QR but not leave an island: (27a). Or it can be a referential expression, in which case it is insensitive to all scope effects and yields a reading nearly equivalent to (27c).<link rid="fn9">
<sup>9</sup></link> (27b) is not derived: in order to derive the intermediate island-escaping reading, the indefinite would have to be neither referential (or the student could not vary with every professor), nor a regular quantificational NP subject to conditions on movement.<link rid="fn10">
<sup>10</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Fodor and Sag&apos;s elegant demonstration has been the subject of considerable debate in the literature. Many counter-examples to the supposed impossibility of island-escaping intermediate readings have been put forward; we will turn to these in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss9" level="3">
<heading id="h8" level="3">3.2.2&ensp;VP ellipsis</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) presented one more imaginative argument in favor of a binary, quantificational/referential ambiguity in indefinites, based on a generalization from <link rid="b21">Sag (1980</link>) and <link rid="b22">Williams (1977</link>) concerning VP-deletion examples such as the following ((28a) from Fodor and Sag, (28b) from <link rid="b23">May 1985</link>, (28c) from <link rid="b24">Fiengo and May 1994</link>):</p>
<p>(28)&ensp;<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Someone &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> loves <i>everyone</i>&rsqb;. Chris knows that someone does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Some student &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admires <i>every professor</i>&rsqb;, but John doesn&apos;t &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Some student &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> hit <i>everyone</i>&rsqb;, and Max did &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;, too.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The observation is that the italicized direct object may not scope over the subject in this context, in which VP1 functions as antecedent for the elided VP2. The Sag/Williams generalization was (roughly) that a VP containing a free variable may not function as antecedent for an elided VP.<link rid="fn11">
<sup>11</sup></link> This explains the observation: for the italicized NP to scope over the subject, it must move out of VP1, thereafter binding a variable in VP1; VP1 then contains a variable that is free in VP1; hence VP1 can no longer function as antecedent for VP2.</p>
<p>Now consider (29) ((29b) is from <link rid="b25">Fox 1995b</link>):</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Sandy thinks that every student in our class &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> plays chess better than <i>a guy I beat this morning</i>&rsqb;. Chris thinks that every student does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Exactly half the boys &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admire <i>a certain professor</i>&rsqb;, and Mary does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;A certain professor x &lsqb;exactly half the boys &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admire x&rsqb;&rsqb;, and a certain professor x &lsqb;Mary does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> admire x&rsqb;&rsqb; too. </p>
<p>In (29), the italicized indefinite in VP1 may be interpreted outside the scope of the quantificational subject. For instance, (29b) may involve one particular professor whom exactly half the boys admire. This cannot be due to a quantificational reading of the indefinite, as that would involve a variable free in the antecedent VP1 &ndash; this is illustrated for (29b) in (30).<link rid="fn12">
<sup>12</sup></link> Hence, indefinites must possess some other means of creating the impression of a wide-scope construal. This is the referential reading of indefinites.</p>
<p>Fodor and Sag&apos;s assumptions do allow for a potential escape from this conclusion, but its correctness depends on subtle and undecided intuitions. The Sag/Williams generalization comes with an exception clause: a VP containing a free variable may antecede an elided VP, provided that the same quantifier instance binds both variables. This is exemplified in (31) (<link rid="b22">Williams 1977</link>: (85)):</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>John saw everyone before Mary did &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> e&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Everyone x &lsqb;John &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> saw x&rsqb; before Mary &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> saw x&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>One of the readings of (31a) is given in (31b): here each of the antecedent and elided VPs contains a free variable, but both variables are bound (outside VP) by the same instance of <i>everyone</i>. Given this option, the indefinite in (29) might be interpreted through wide-scope quantification, provided that the quantifier takes scope over both conjuncts, and binds two variables Across-the-Board, as illustrated in (32) for (29b):</p>
<p>(32)&ensp;A certain professor x &lsqb;&lsqb;exactly half the boys &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admire x&rsqb;&rsqb;, and &lsqb;Mary does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> admire x&rsqb; too&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>However, unlike the proscribed structure (30), the ATB structure (32) is associated with a maximal-scope reading by which the <i>same</i> professor is admired by exactly half the boys and by Mary. <link rid="b25">Fox (1995b</link>: fn. 44) reports that speakers&rsquo; intuitions are unclear on whether this is indeed the only available reading. It is not clear to me from their discussion which of the two wide-scope readings Fodor and Sag perceived to be available; but their treatment of indefinites is such that the two instances of the indefinite may have different referents, suggesting that they would not be satisfied with a restriction to (32).<link rid="fn13">
<sup>13</sup></link> It is possible also that Fodor and Sag did not envisage the option that a quantifier might take cross-sentential scope, as an ATB analysis of their example, (29a) above, would require. Under DRT and related dynamic approaches to semantics, however, the option of cross-sentential quantification cannot be ruled out. So, a quantificational approach to the wide scope of indefinites is still conceivable; but the cross-sentential case (29a) does rule out a description in terms of syntactic movement.<link rid="fn14">
<sup>14</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Quite apart from the possible ATB analysis of (29), the Sag/Williams generalization that Fodor and Sag rely on has itself not remained unchallenged. <link rid="b26">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1982</link>) presented examples such as (33) that contradict it ((33b) and (33c) from <link rid="b25">Fox 1995b</link>; (33d) from <link rid="b24">Fiengo and May 1994</link>):</p>
<p>(33)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A Canadian flag was &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> hanging in front of <i>each window</i>&rsqb;, and an American one was &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>One guard is &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> standing in front of <i>every building</i>&rsqb;, and one policeman is &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Some boy &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admires <i>every teacher</i>&rsqb; and some girl does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Some student &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> hit <i>everyone</i>&rsqb;, and some professor did &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;, too.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Further counter-examples are due to <link rid="b27 b28">Lappin (1992, 1993</link>) ((34a) cited from <link rid="b25">Fox 1995b</link>; (34b) cited from <link rid="b24">Fiengo and May 1994</link>):</p>
<p>(34)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>At least one MP &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> attended <i>every committee meeting</i>&rsqb;, and Bill did &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;, too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>A guide &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> accompanies <i>every tour of the Eiffel Tower</i>&rsqb;, and Jeanne does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;, too.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In each of these examples, the italicized NP may take wide scope. Furthermore, the examples in (35) are incompatible with an Across-the-Board analysis as considered in (32) ((35a) from Hirschb&uuml;hler; (35b) from Fiengo and May; (35c) from Fox):</p>
<p>(35)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A Canadian flag was &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> hanging in front of <i>most windows</i>&rsqb;, and an American one was &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>A Canadian flag was &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> hanging in front of <i>many windows</i>&rsqb;, and an American flag was &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;, too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>A guard is &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> standing in front of <i>many buildings</i>&rsqb;, and a policeman is &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>For instance, no building needs to have both a guard and a policeman standing in front of it for the wide-scope reading of (35c) to be true. So the Williams/Sag generalization requires modification. <link rid="b25">Fox (1995b</link>) suggests that the correct generalization is this: the inverted scope order is allowed in the antecedent structure just in case inverting the order in the elided structure will also have some semantic effect; if not, economy forbids QR in the elided structure, and then the parallelism requirement on deletion forbids QR in the antecedent structure as well. QR is disallowed in, say, (28b) because whether <i>every professor</i> takes wide or narrow scope relative to <i>John</i> makes no semantic difference. In (33) and (35) the right-hand conjunct has a quantified subject; crossing it will have a semantic effect, hence we obtain a wide-scope reading for the objects in the both conjuncts. If this is the correct generalization,<link rid="fn15">
<sup>15</sup></link> then the specific reading of <i>a certain professor</i> in (29b) still argues against a QR explanation of specificity. But if we manage to derive a quantificational wide-scope interpretation for the indefinite by some mechanism, other than QR, that is insensitive to this type of economy, then economy is not violated here and we may still avoid a referential/quantificational ambiguity. See the references cited above for further discussion.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss10" level="3">
<heading id="h9" level="3">3.2.3&ensp;Distribution and scope</heading>
<p>So far, we have considered only singular number indefinites. When we take plural indefinites into account, an additional problem arises for an &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; approach to specific indefinites, as pointed out in <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>). Consider first (36):</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Three relatives of mine wore a tie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lgr;P &lsqb;&verbar;<b>relative_of_mine&prime;</b> &cap; P&verbar; &ge; 3&rsqb; (&lgr;x<sub>i</sub> &exist;y&lsqb;<b>tie&prime;</b>(y) &and; <b>wear&prime;</b>(y)(x<sub>i</sub>)&rsqb;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The natural interpretation of (36a) is a &lsquo;distributive&rsquo; (as oppposed to &lsquo;collective&rsquo;) one: my three relatives did not together wear one and the same tie, but each his own. How this distributive reading for <i>three relatives of mine</i> is achieved depends, among other things, on the semantic treatment of plurals. We obtain the distributive effect for free with the simplest Generalized Quantifier (GQ) interpretation of the subject, as in (36b).<link rid="fn16">
<sup>16</sup></link> Alternatively, if the subject basically denotes a plural individual (see, e.g., <link rid="b29">Link 1983</link>), a distributivity operator needs to be applied in order to obtain this reading.<link rid="fn17">
<sup>17</sup></link> In any case, whatever the analysis, we observe that <i>three relatives of mine</i> must be granted a distributive interpretation.</p>
<p>Keeping this simple observation in mind, consider (37):<link rid="fn18">
<sup>18</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>If three relatives of mine die, I will inherit a house.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;three relatives of mine<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;&lsqb;if t<sub>i</sub> die&rsqb; I will inherit a house&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lgr;P &lsqb;&verbar;<b>relative_of_mine&prime;</b> &cap; P&verbar; &ge; 3&rsqb; (&lgr;x<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;IF x<sub>i</sub> dies THEN I will inherit a house&rsqb;).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;X &lsqb;X &sube; <b>relative_of_mine&prime;</b> &and; &verbar;X&verbar; &equals; 3 &and; &lsqb;IF X die THEN I will inherit a house&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Suppose, as before, that NPs such as <i>three relatives of mine</i> may undergo island-free QR. Then we derive the LF (37b), and we expect the interpretation represented in (37c). That is, we expect <i>three relatives of mine</i> to allow a distributive reading with scope over the <i>if</i>-clause, which says that there are three relatives of mine such that, if <i>any one</i> of them dies, I inherit a house. But this reading is not available. That is not to say that plural NPs such as <i>three relatives</i> cannot be specific. There is a reading on which <i>three relatives of mine</i> escapes the <i>if</i>-clause, but only the one roughly stated in (37d): there are three relatives of mine, such that if they <i>all</i> die, I inherit a house. In other words, while existential quantification over (sets of) relatives of mine can take scope outside the extraction island (so that we find the entailment properties illustrated for (19c) above), the distributivity that the NP normally allows cannot scope over the island.<link rid="fn19">
<sup>19</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Consider some examples from <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>) that illustrate this further:</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&num;Every artist who was born in <i>three cities</i> became famous.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&num;If <i>three women</i> gave birth to John then he has a nice mother.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>To begin with, (38a) has an odd narrow-scope reading for <i>three cities</i>, which attributes fame to every artist with a triple birthplace. The sentence also has the (equally odd) specific reading that there is a set of three cities, such that every artist born in all three of them became famous. The wide-scope distributive reading (there are three cities x, such that every artist born in x became famous) would not share this oddity; hence we would expect it to be highly prominent if it were available. As we find (38a) to be odd, the wide-scope distributive reading must be impossible; similar observations apply to (38b). (39) provides further evidence ((39a) from <link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>):</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>John overheard the rumor that some friends of mine had been called before the dean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I met a man who wore three neckties with red polka dots.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Exactly one house that some friends of mine built made it through the quake (so their business has lost its credibility).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(39a) allows an island-escaping specific reading for the plural indefinite, but it is necessarily about one single rumor. (39b) is not ambiguous (the wide-scope non-distributive reading and the narrow-scope reading happen to be equivalent here) and entails the existence of a man wearing three neckties &ndash; if the indefinite could both take wide scope (as we know it can) <i>and</i> distribute, the sentence should allow for different men wearing each of those ties.<link rid="fn20">
<sup>20</sup></link>
</p>
<p>It follows from these observations that positing a simple-minded &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; predicts readings that are in fact not available. If a plural indefinite can be lifted out of an island, as illustrated in LF (37b), then how do we prevent the interpretation (37c), assuming that the NP denotes a simple GQ? And if we take the more sophisticated view that indefinites start out with a collective interpretation, then how do we prevent the usual mechanisms for deriving distributivity from applying once the NP is outside the island?</p>
<p>One option that springs to mind is that, perhaps, &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; may apply only to collectively interpreted NPs to begin with &ndash; but this maneuver is easily blocked:<link rid="fn21">
<sup>21</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">If three workers on our staff have a baby soon, we will have to face some hard organizational problems.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist;X &lsqb;X &sube; <b>workers&prime;</b> &and; &verbar;X&verbar; &equals; 3 &and; &lsqb;IF &forall;x &isin; X (x has a baby) THEN we face problems&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;X &lsqb;X &sube; <b>workers&prime;</b> &and; &verbar;X&verbar; &equals; 3 &and; &forall;x &isin; X &lsqb;IF (x has a baby) THEN we face problems&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(40) allows a specific reading for <i>three workers on our staff</i> (without distribution over the <i>if</i>-clause), but on this reading each worker may still have her own baby. Schematically: although (40b) is not allowed (wide-scope existential, wide-scope distribution), (40a) is (wide-scope existential, narrow-scope distribution). There is distributivity associated with specific NPs, but it is island-restricted.</p>
<p>So far, we have looked at plural specific NPs in islands, and observed that they may not scope and distribute over those islands. We conclude that an &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; analysis of specificity faces severe problems. But a similar point can be made on the basis of much simpler examples (<link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>). If it were really the case that indefinite NPs undergo QR so easily, and with such greater freedom than other quantifiers do as the initial specificity data seem to suggest, then we certainly expect them to take wide scope with supreme ease when <i>no</i> islands intervene. And indeed, an indefinite in object position, as in (18), effortlessly escapes the scope of a quantifier in subject position. But when the specific object-NP is plural, we find that it allows a distributive reading with wide scope <i>over</i> the subject only with great difficulty, if at all. Consider (41):</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Two boys read three books.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;three books<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;two boys read t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lgr;P &lsqb;&verbar;<b>books</b>&prime; &cap; P&verbar; &ge; 3&rsqb; (&lgr;x<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;two boys read x<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given the supposed exceptional wide-scope propensity of indefinites, we would expect LF (41a) with the interpretation (41b) to be most readily available. This is not the case. The boys may not vary with the books: for (41) to be judged true it is not sufficient that each of three books was read by a different set of two boys, or it is only marginally so. Evidence has been available since at least the mid-1970s, and consensus growing since the early 1990s, that weak plural NPs take inverse wide scope in this sense much less easily than strong quantificational NPs such as <i>every friend of mine</i> (cf. <link rid="b30">Ioup 1975b</link>; <link rid="b31">Verkuyl 1988</link>;<link rid="fn22">
<sup>22</sup></link> <link rid="b32">Liu 1990</link>; <link rid="b20 b33">Ruys 1992, 1997</link>; <link rid="b34 b35">Beghelli 1993, 1995</link>; <link rid="b36">Kamp and Reyle 1993</link>; and references cited there). Consider also a structure of inverse linking, in which strong quantifiers preferably take inverse scope (<link rid="b37">May 1977</link>):</p>
<p>42<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="11">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Een</entry>
<entry>paar</entry>
<entry>mensen</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>iedere</entry>
<entry>stad</entry>
<entry>hadden</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>luchtballon</entry>
<entry>gezien.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>few</entry>
<entry>people</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>every</entry>
<entry>city</entry>
<entry>had</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>hot-air balloon</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Een</entry>
<entry>paar</entry>
<entry>mensen</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>drie</entry>
<entry>steden</entry>
<entry>hadden</entry>
<entry>de</entry>
<entry>luchtballon</entry>
<entry>gezien.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>few</entry>
<entry>people</entry>
<entry>in</entry>
<entry>three</entry>
<entry>cities</entry>
<entry>had</entry>
<entry>the</entry>
<entry>hot-air balloon</entry>
<entry>seen</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">Two pictures of every senator were on sale at the gift shop.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col11">Two pictures of three senators were on sale at the gift shop.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In Dutch, (42b), unlike (42a), is interpreted as making a statement about a few people each of whom were in three cities. Similarly, (42d) is about two &lsquo;three-senator pictures&rsquo;, not (or only marginally) about three times two &lsquo;single-senator pictures&rsquo;, in contrast with (42c), which easily allows wide scope for <i>every senator</i>. Consider finally (43):</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;<object id="tu35" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu35_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Everyone believed that three friends of mine had been called before the dean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>A professor believed that three friends of mine had been called before the dean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Three friends of mine<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;a professor believed that t<sub>i</sub> had been called before the dean&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl> </insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>If the wide-scope, specific reading of <i>three friends of mine</i> relative to <i>believed and everyone</i> in (43a) were due to non-clause-bounded QR, we would equally expect (43b) to have the LF (43c). But the evidence is against this, as <i>three friends of mine</i> cannot take wide distributive scope over <i>a professor</i>.</p>
<p>We seem to be faced with a contradiction. When we look at one set of data, such as presented in <link rid="ss6">section 3.1</link>, which show island-escaping specificity, we want to allow indefinites unlimited, &lsquo;island-free&rsquo; QR. But to explain the absence of wide-scope distributive readings for indefinites outside islands, and even locally, we want to prevent indefinites from undergoing QR altogether. There are several ways of resolving the contradiction.</p>
<p>One option is to give up the assumption that specificity is due to wide-scope quantification, and to follow <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) in returning to a referential/quantificational ambiguity in indefinites. Apparent wide scope is then due to the referentiality option, and we can, without contradiction, attempt to explain the limited distributive scope of indefinites in terms of limited QR. This option is discussed in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>.</p>
<p>Another option is to describe the interpretation of indefinite NPs in terms of one mechanism for existential quantification over plural or singular individuals, and a separate mechanism for distributivity. We must then ensure that existential quantification can take unlimited scope, while the domain of application of the distributivity operator is kept very local. If we pursue this option, an approach that manages to assign an indefinite its wide existential scope without displacing the indefinite itself is preferred, as the in-situ distributive properties of the indefinite are then likely to follow automatically. We will discuss such an approach in <link rid="ss14">section 5</link>. In contrast, an approach that does, through syntactic movement or some other means, displace the indefinite in order to derive its existential scope must define and motivate some way of separating the distributive mechanism from the indefinite and ensure that <i>it</i> does not acquire unbounded scope. To appreciate some of the difficulties such an approach would have to overcome, note that it must, all the same, allow distributive readings for plural weak NPs that are displaced in overt syntax through A-movement or A-bar-movement, as in (44) and (45a), and even wide-scope distributive readings in certain examples that appear to be due to QR, as in (45b) (from <link rid="b38">Reinhart 1997</link>):</p>
<p>(44)&ensp;<object id="tu36" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu36_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Fifty US senators appear to at least one supreme court judge to have violated the constitution.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Three languages are spoken by over a billion people.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(45)&ensp;<object id="tu37" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu37_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which men did some woman love?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>A guard is standing in front of two buildings.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>For instance, (44b), where <i>three languages</i> c-commands <i>over a billion people</i> only after A-movement, allows wide distributive scope for <i>three languages</i>: it is true if each of three languages is spoken by a different set of over a billion people. (45a) can be answered by providing a set of men each of whom was loved by a different woman.</p>
<p>We want to mention briefly another popular account of structures containing specific indefinites (as in (18), (41), etc.) which avoids island-free QR and diagnoses them as instances of branching quantification (see, e.g., <link rid="b32">Liu 1990</link>; <link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>), as illustrated for (41) in (46):</p>
<p>(46)&ensp;Two boys read three books.</p>
<p><object id="fu1" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_74_fu1.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu1_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object></p>
<p>The usual interpretation for branching quantification structures such as (46a) is that the value for a quantifier on one branch does not vary with the value for quantifiers on other branches.<link rid="fn23">
<sup>23</sup></link> So, <i>three books</i> in (46a) is not in the scope of <i>two boys</i> (wide &lsquo;existential&rsquo; scope for <i>three books</i>), but neither is <i>two boys</i> in the scope of <i>three books</i> (no &lsquo;distributive&rsquo; wide scope for <i>three books</i>) &ndash; this seems to be exactly what we need.<link rid="fn24">
<sup>24</sup></link> The crucial problem, of course, is how to (compositionally) derive (a denotation equivalent to) (46a) given the syntactic structure of the sentence. Another problem is that a quantifier on one branch cannot bind a variable in the restrictive clause of a quantifier on another branch, which is what we would need if we wanted to use a branching quantification structure to represent the specific reading of a quantifier A relative to B when A is contained in B. So the representational mechanism does not work in cases such as (42b) and (42d) (&lsquo;inverse linking&rsquo;), or for island-escaping examples such as (19) and (20).</p>
<p>A syntactic description of specificity might, however, build on the &lsquo;branching quantification&rsquo; insight by attempting to encode &lsquo;branching&rsquo; relations among quantifiers in syntactic representations. Now, the desired type of &lsquo;upward branching&rsquo; cannot be directly encoded in tree structures (in any sensible syntactic representation of (46), either <i>two boys</i> c-commands <i>three books</i> or vice versa). So to implement this idea, syntactic representations must be enriched with a diacritic mechanism with which the relative scopal dependence or independence of any two quantifiers (or other scoped expressions) can be encoded.<link rid="fn25">
<sup>25</sup></link> This is not an attractive prospect, unless considerable independent evidence for such a diacritic mechanism can be adduced. Furthermore, the problem of compositional interpretation of such &lsquo;scope-marked&rsquo; syntactic representations is not at all straightforward.</p>
<p>In conclusion, an analysis that assigns wide scope to indefinites by raising them to a scope position across an unlimited distance (be it a syntactic &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; or an unrestricted semantic storage mechanism) is not the optimal description (let alone explanation) of specificity effects. Such an analysis is likely to predict unattested wide-scope distributive readings for indefinites, unless special precautions are taken to prevent this. An analysis that does not predict such distributive readings is to be preferred.<link rid="fn26">
<sup>26</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="2">
<heading id="h10" level="2">3.3 ACD and specificity</heading>
<p>We might look for syntactic clues to determine whether the island-escaping scope of indefinites is due to syntactic movement, but we don&apos;t expect to find much evidence either way. QR does not, for instance, appear to feed Binding Theory in general (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 54 - Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope.xml" type="file">chapter 54</externallink></related>). One small piece of evidence, however, comes from Antecedent Contained Deletion. If ACD resolution is generally due to QR (see, e.g., <link rid="b23">May 1985</link>; <link rid="b39">Fox 1995a</link>; <link rid="b40">Kennedy 1997a</link>), then a syntactic &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; hypothesis would lead us to expect wide-scope indefinites to license unlimited ACD.<link rid="fn27">
<sup>27</sup></link> We cannot look directly at island-escaping specificity, though:</p>
<p>(47)&ensp;<object id="tu38" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu38_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Mary &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> dates every man who knows a producer OP Sue does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> a producer OP Sue does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> Mary &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> dates every man who knows t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;IP &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> a producer OP<sub>j</sub> Sue does &lsqb;<sub>VP2&prime;</sub> date every man who knows t<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> Mary &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> dates every man who knows t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>*There is a producer x such that Sue dates every man who knows x, and such that Mary dates every man who knows x.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(47a) does not allow VP1 to antecede the empty VP2: the reading given in (47c), paraphrased in (47d), is not available. But this does not in itself entail that LF (47b) is not derived. If it were, matrix ACD resolution should still be out because the relation between the relative pronoun OP and the trace inside the copied VP, VP2&prime;, violates the CNPC in (47c). Consider, however, (48), from <link rid="b40">Kennedy (1997a</link>):</p>
<p>(48)&ensp;John &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> believed that Bill &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> had seen a certain film that I did &lsqb;<sub>VP3</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>(48), according to Kennedy, has a <i>de re</i> reading with <i>a certain film that I did</i> specific relative to <i>believed</i>, but even on this matrix-scope reading, only VP2 may antecede the empty VP. Wide-scope specific readings apparently do not feed ACD resolution. This accords with our observation in <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link> that if indefinites undergo QR, QR must be (very) local.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="2">
<heading id="h11" level="2">3.4 Conclusions</heading>
<p>In this section, we have investigated the option of analyzing the specific/non-specific ambiguity as a scope ambiguity. Several conclusions may be drawn from this section. First, if the scope of indefinites is to be determined in syntax, it cannot be through a rule of movement; that hypothetical rule would exhibit such extraordinary properties as to render its characterization as a syntactic movement rule vacuous. As a corollary, nothing can be learned about QR by observing the scope of singular indefinite NPs, as in <i>everyone loves someone</i>. Second, if specificity is a scope phenomenon, and not due to a referential reading on indefinites, then the mechanism responsible for the scope of indefinites cannot be just the same one that also assigns scope to other quantificational NPs. QR is not a viable option; neither is a semantic storage mechanism that applies to all quantifier types. Third, if specificity is due to scope, not referentiality, then the mechanism that determines the scope of indefinites, be it syntactic or semantic, must distinguish two scope properties: free existential scope and scopally restricted distribution. This is likely to be easier when the indefinite itself is not displaced. Again, QR is not indicated, and neither is semantic storage. In section 5, we discuss one theory on the scope of indefinites that satisfies these requirements.</p>
<p>Several other issues have arisen that require further discussion. As we observe that not only singular indefinites but also plurals allow specific readings, we want to delineate the exact class of NPs that come with this property. Until we turn to that task in <link rid="ss16">section 7</link>, we will simply speak of &lsquo;indefinite NPs&rsquo; as the relevant class. More urgently, we want to ascertain whether Fodor and Sag&apos;s &lsquo;intermediate reading&rsquo; argument indeed provides conclusive evidence for a binary ambiguity in the indefinite, and against the scope ambiguity approach. This is the subject of the next section.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss13" level="1">
<heading id="h12" level="1">4 Intermediate readings</heading>
<p>In <link rid="ss8">section 3.2.1</link> above we outlined <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag&apos;s (1982</link>) claim that a specific indefinite cannot take island-escaping intermediate existential scope: <i>a student of mine</i> cannot scope above <i>the rumor</i> but below <i>every professor</i> in (27). If true, this implies that an indefinite does itself not denote an (existential) quantifier that is somehow interpreted at an arbitrary distance from its surface position. We subscribe to this conclusion. But there is a stronger implication. Specificity cannot involve quantification at all, unless one can define some quantificational mechanism that can take island-escaping maximal scope, but not island-escaping non-maximal scope. As they see no non-stipulative way of accomplishing this, Fodor and Sag return to the binary ambiguity position: indefinites are interpreted either through local quantification, or as referential expressions. Must we adopt this conclusion as well? This section outlines the case against it.</p>
<p>The weak point in Fodor and Sag&apos;s claim is that it involves subtle intuitions on complex examples containing at least three scope elements: the indefinite; the scope island from which it escapes; and the higher scoped expression below which the indefinite may or may not remain. Even before Fodor and Sag&apos;s paper had appeared in <i>Linguistics and Philosophy</i> in 1982, counter-examples to their generalization had been presented. The following is from <link rid="b41">Farkas (1981</link>):</p>
<p>(49) Each student has to come up with &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> three arguments which show that <i>some condition proposed by Chomsky</i> is wrong&rsqb;.</p>
<p>It is fairly easy to obtain an intermediate scope reading for the italicized NP, saying that each student has some (different) condition assigned to her, and must come up with three arguments regarding that particular condition. Unfortunately, as pointed out by <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>), the wide-scope reading of the italicized NP relative to the complex NP entails the narrow-scope reading, so that we may just be considering a special case of the narrow-scope reading here, not a separate reading (cf. <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link>).<link rid="fn28">
<sup>28</sup></link> But this is easily fixed:</p>
<p>(50)&ensp;<object id="tu39" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu39_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Each student has to come up with &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> exactly three arguments which show that <i>some condition proposed by Chomsky</i> is wrong&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Each student x &lsqb;some Chomsky-condition y &lsqb;x has to come up with exactly three arguments which show that y is wrong&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>There is a fairly strong intuition that (50) has the reading schematized in (50a). If so, this is a reading that cannot be attributed to QR, for reasons outlined in the previous section, or to a referential reading of the indefinite, as the choice of problem varies with each student. It now appears that intermediate island-escaping readings <i>are</i> possible, so that Fodor and Sag&apos;s argument collapses.</p>
<p>Many other authors have taken up Fodor and Sag&apos;s challenge and constructed examples which display intermediate readings; see, e.g., <link rid="b42">Partee and Rooth (1983</link>), <link rid="b43">King (1988</link>), <link rid="b44">Ludlow and Neale (1991</link>), <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>), <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>), and <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) for elaborate discussion of Fodor and Sag. We shall not go into all the details or discuss all the examples. We will present a few representative cases and consider ways of making the relevant intuitions more secure. Below are some more simple cases, from <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>) and <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>):</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;<object id="tu40" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu40_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every gambler will be surprised if one horse wins.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Most linguists have looked at every analysis that solves some problem.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In both cases, the narrow-scope reading runs counter to our knowledge of the world; in (51b), the maximal-scope reading does so as well. This favors the intermediate-scope reading, which is felt to be available.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>) investigates several ways of rendering intermediate readings more easily detectable by suppressing the other two readings. The wide-scope reading can be eliminated by placing a pronoun bound by the higher quantifier inside the indefinite ((52b) is from Abusch):</p>
<p>(52)&ensp;<object id="tu41" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu41_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every professor<sub>i</sub> will rejoice if <i>a student of his</i><sub>i</sub> cheats on the exam.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every professor<sub>i</sub> rewarded every student who read <i>a book he</i><sub>i</sub> <i>had recommended</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In these examples, only two potential scope positions for the indefinite are left (given that we choose a bound reading for the pronoun) &ndash; the intermediate reading thereby becomes more prominent. Combining this with a mechanism that strengthens the specific reading (although such mechanisms are hard to find and ill-understood, as we will see later (<link rid="ss16">section 7</link>)), we obtain examples where the intermediate reading is strongly favored:</p>
<p>(53)&ensp;<object id="tu42" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu42_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every professor<sub>i</sub> will rejoice if <i>a certain student of his</i><sub>i</sub> cheats on the exam.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every professor<sub>i</sub> rewarded every student who read <i>a particular book he</i><sub>i</sub> <i>had recommended</i>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Another method for isolating intermediate readings employed in <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>) requires some introduction. Recall from <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> <link rid="b2">Karttunen&apos;s (1968</link>) observation that an indefinite structurally embedded below a scope-taking expression may nonetheless introduce a discourse referent if it is interpreted specifically. Island-escaping specificity licenses discourse anaphora as well:</p>
<p>(54)&ensp;<object id="tu43" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu43_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>If <i>a relative of mine</i> dies, I will inherit a fortune. <i>He</i> got lucky on the derivatives market.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Mary dates every man who has met <i>a producer I know</i>. She wants to talk about <i>him</i> all the time.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We may use this property to influence the scope of an indefinite, provided that we control for two exceptions to Karttunen&apos;s generalization. First, a <i>plural</i> pronoun may be used to pick up the collection of all verifying values for an indefinite in the scope of a quantifier: in (55a), <i>they</i> may be taken to refer to all the girls the boys brought to the party.<link rid="fn29">
<sup>29</sup></link> Second, when the pronoun is in the scope of a quantifier as well, it may have a functional reading relating it to the indefinite narrow-scope antecedent (cf. note 2); see (55b). (For work on such issues see <link rid="b36 b45">Kamp and Reyle 1993, Chierchia 1995a</link>, and references cited there; see also <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 9 - Binding Theory.xml" type="file">chapter 9</externallink></related>.)</p>
<p>(55)&ensp;<object id="tu44" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu44_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every boy brought <i>a girl</i> to the party. But <i>they</i>/*<i>she</i> got bored quickly.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every boy brought <i>a girl</i> to the party. And every boy took <i>her</i> home as well.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given this background, we can use donkey anaphora structures to elicit wide-scope readings. The principle is illustrated in (56):</p>
<p>(56)&ensp;<object id="tu45" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu45_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>He often reads a book about linguistics.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Anyone who often reads <i>a book about linguistics</i>&rsqb; understands <i>it</i> well.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Anyone who often reads <i>a book about linguistics</i>&rsqb; understands <i>them</i> well.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Anyone who often reads <i>a book about linguistics</i>&rsqb; usually understands <i>it</i> well.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The ambiguity of (56a) shows that in structures such as this, the indefinite <i>a book about linguistics</i> may take wide or narrow scope relative to the adverbial <i>often</i>. Next, when we embed the structure in such a way that the indefinite becomes the antecedent for a donkey anaphor, we observe the same effects that occur with discourse anaphora, only one &lsquo;scope level&rsquo; down. A singular indefinite may antecede a singular donkey anaphor provided that the indefinite is not scopally embedded, except of course relative to the universal quantifier which also takes scope over the pronoun. In other words, the indefinite must occur in the immediate scope of the &lsquo;unselective binder&rsquo; <i>anyone</i>.<link rid="fn30">
<sup>30</sup></link> Thus, there is only a wide-scope reading relative to the adverbial for the indefinite in (56b). If we want to achieve narrow scope for the indefinite, we must either use a plural pronoun, as in (56c), cf. (55a), or use a similar adverbial to take scope over the pronoun, as in (56d), cf. (55b).</p>
<p>By placing the donkey antecedent in a scope island, we can now force an island-escaping intermediate-scope reading:</p>
<p>(57)&ensp;<object id="tu46" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu46_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every critic who reviews each and every book that <i>some author</i> writes quickly grows sick of <i>him</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every country whose security is threatened if <i>a building</i> is attacked by terrorists protects <i>it</i> well.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Whenever Beatrix overhears the rumor that <i>some politician</i> is corrupt, <i>the poor slob</i> loses his job.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We observe that the pronouns in (57) can function as donkey anaphors, with their antecedents taking intermediate island-escaping scope. In (57a), for instance, <i>some author</i> cannot be referential, since it is in the scope of <i>every</i>, but it must scope outside the embedded complex NP or it could not antecede a singular donkey pronoun. (57c) is interesting in that it allows an intermediate reading even though its structure mirrors that of Fodor and Sag&apos;s example (27). See <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>: 213ff.) for examples with other island and donkey anaphora types; see also <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>: 93).</p>
<p>There may be yet another, more theory-internal argument for the existence of intermediate island-escaping specificity. Recall from <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link> that the mechanism responsible for specificity does not yield distributive wide-scope readings. Consequently, distributive wide scope must be the effect of some other scope mechanism, e.g., (island-bound) QR. We found that in most structures, including simple SVO configurations such as (46), plural indefinites take distributive inverse wide scope with great difficulty, if at all. That would entail that (almost) any structure is a QR-island for indefinites; in particular, one might suppose that such NPs are never subject to QR. If so, any scope position that does not match the indefinite&apos;s syntactic surface position is &lsquo;island-escaping&rsquo; and must be due to the specificity mechanism. And any such scope taking would falsify Fodor and Sag&apos;s claim if it were non-maximal. Consider (58) (cf. <link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>):</p>
<p>(58)&ensp;<object id="tu47" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu47_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Elke professor vindt dat iedere student <i>een bepaalde theorie</i> moet aanhangen.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Every professor believes that every student should support a certain theory.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>It seems that every senator will accept <i>a proposal endorsed by Ronald Reagan</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>When every professor really likes <i>a student</i>, she is usually a genius.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Dutch (58a) supports a reading paraphrasable as &lsquo;for every professor there is a theory he believes every student should support&rsquo;. This reading cannot be due to QR, since a plural indefinite in the position of <i>een bepaalde theorie</i> could not even distribute over an indefinite in the position of <i>iedere student</i>, let alone take matrix scope. But if it is a case of specificity, specificity cannot be due to referentiality. Similarly, the indefinite in (58b) can be specific relative to <i>every senator</i> but in the scope of <i>seems</i> at the same time; (58c) is an example of this type in a donkey anaphora context, as above. If this line of reasoning is valid, we could conceivably even recycle one of the original arguments against a binary, referential/quantificational ambiguity of indefinites, namely the intermediate reading in examples such as (15).</p>
<p>When we accept the findings reported in this section, Fodor and Sag&apos;s main argument for a binary referential/quantificational ambiguity in indefinites no longer holds. Instead, we have again a version of the argument <i>against</i> such a binary ambiguity, such as resulted from the work of <link rid="b6">Fodor (1970</link>) and others, as discussed in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link>. Since intermediate-scope readings sometimes arise, as in (15), we need to assume a quantificational mechanism whose scope need not reflect the surface position of the indefinite. Since intermediate island-escaping scope readings sometimes obtain, as we now find, we need to assume that this quantificational mechanism is insensitive to scope islands. Hence, there is no need to assume a referential interpretation of indefinites as well, since the &lsquo;maximal-scope&rsquo; readings that would result from that also follow from the required quantificational mechanism. The next section describes one quantificational mechanism that serves our purposes.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss14" level="1">
<heading id="h13" level="1">5 One solution: choice functions</heading>
<p>We find ourselves with the following desiderata for a theory of specificity. It must specify a quantificational mechanism that is involved in the interpretation of indefinites, which can take any scope without being sensitive to scope islands, and which allows no distributive specific readings. Several quantificational mechanisms for indefinites have been proposed that meet these requirements to some degree (see, e.g., <link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>; <link rid="b15">Abusch 1994</link>; <link rid="b10">Farkas 1997</link>; <link rid="b46">Kratzer 1998</link>). It would not serve the purposes of our discussion to consider them all and compare their relative merits; empirical differences falling within the purview of this chapter are slight and not always essential. We will outline one treatment of the scope of indefinites, which was proposed by Tanya <link rid="b38">Reinhart in (1997</link>) and earlier work, and refined and developed further in <link rid="b47 b16">Winter (1997, 1998</link>).</p>
<p>We concluded in <link rid="ss12">section 3.4</link> that a description of the scope of indefinites is more likely to meet the empirical requirements if it does not involve movement, especially syntactic movement, of the indefinite itself. This entails that we must assume that the quantifier whose scope determines the existential import of the indefinite is not part of the interpretation of the indefinite itself; e.g., <i>some</i> does not denote the existential quantifier. The obvious alternative is to make use of the mechanism of default existential closure familiar from DRT (<link rid="b48">Kamp 1981a</link>; <link rid="b4">Heim 1982</link>; <link rid="b36">Kamp and Reyle 1993</link>). But it is well known (see, e.g., <link rid="b4">Heim 1982</link>) that existential quantification over individuals will not work for our purposes, as (19), repeated as (59), shows:</p>
<p>(59)&ensp;<object id="tu48" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu48_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">If a relative of mine dies, I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist; x IF relative_of_mine(x) &and; die(x) THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>DRT holds that the indefinite <i>a relative of mine</i> is interpreted as an open sentence relative_of_mine(x); default existential closure binds the variable. If we now allow a default quantifier at matrix level to bind that variable in (59a), we have matrix scope but not the correct meaning, as the descriptive content of the indefinite is still interpreted inside the <i>if</i>-clause. (59a) does not state there is a relative of mine with such-and-such property, but that there is an individual such that <i>if</i> he is a relative of mine, I inherit. This comes out true if there exists any individual who is not a relative of mine. The reason is that we can then pick as a value for <i>x</i> any individual not a relative of mine; this will render the antecedent clause false; hence the implication should be judged true. We want to solve this problem without extracting the indefinite from the <i>if</i>-clause. Reinhart&apos;s solution to this puzzle, which occurs also when we want to interpret <i>wh</i>-expressions in situ (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related>), was to use default existential quantification over choice function variables instead.</p>
<p>We will use the provisional definition of choice function, CF, in (60):</p>
<p>(60)&ensp;CF &equals;<sub>df</sub> &lgr;f<sub>&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,e&gt;</sub> &forall;P<sub>&lt;e,t&gt;</sub> &lsqb;P&ne;&Oslash; &rarr; P(f(P))&rsqb;</p>
<p>A choice function is a function which, when applied to a non-empty set, yields as its value a member of this set (we will discuss the empty set case in <link rid="ss15">section 6</link>). Reinhart assumed that the free variable that DRT postulates in the interpretation of an indefinite is not of type e (individual) but of the type of CF. This free function variable takes the set denoted by the descriptive content of the indefinite as its argument; the resulting individual is the denotational value of the indefinite DP. The function variable is bound through default existential closure. For example, (61a) is interpreted as (61b):</p>
<p>(61)&ensp;<object id="tu49" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu49_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A woman entered the room.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(woman) entered the room&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(61b) paraphrases as: &lsquo;there is some manner of choosing, such that the woman chosen in that manner entered the room&rsquo;; in other words: &lsquo;some woman entered the room&rsquo;. Given these assumptions, (59) now comes out correctly, as shown in (62):</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;<object id="tu50" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu50_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>IF &exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(relative_of_mine) dies&rsqb; THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(relative_of_mine) dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p><i>A relative of mine</i> is interpreted, in situ, as f(relative_of_mine); default existential closure states that there is a CF <i>f</i> with the indicated property. If closure applies immediately, as in (62a), we get just the narrow-scope reading for the indefinite. We obtain specificity of the indefinite relative to the <i>if</i>-clause when default existential closure takes place outside this clause, as in (62b). (62b) paraphrases as &lsquo;there is a way of choosing an individual from a set, such that if the person we choose from my relatives in that way dies, then I inherit a fortune&rsquo;. This does not fail in the way (59a) did, as it cannot be rendered trivially true by picking some individual that is not a relative of mine. Supposing that I have relatives, <i>f</i>, being a CF, is guaranteed to pick a relative of mine when applied to relative_of_mine. (62b) then comes down to the statement that there is a relative of mine that we can pick, such that if he dies, I will inherit.</p>
<p>To see that this analysis has the required properties, we want to look again at the entailment properties of (59) that we discussed in <link rid="ss6">section 3.1</link> (see reading (19c)). We will ignore the existential entailment property until <link rid="ss15">section 6</link>, and concentrate on the weakening effect of wide scope in this context: the reasoning in (63) should not be valid:</p>
<p>(63)&ensp;<object id="tu51" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu51_source"> <tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(relative_of_mine) dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;. (&equals; (62b))</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John is a relative of mine.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&minus; ________________________</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IF John dies THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This reasoning is indeed not valid; if there is <i>some</i> way of choosing a relative of mine that renders the implication true, that does not entail that choosing <i>any</i> relative, such as John, will render the implication true.</p>
<p>Other observed properties of specific indefinites also follow. As existential closure is not directed by syntax and may take place wherever a quantifier can bind the CF variable, intermediate readings are generated &ndash; we have decided in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link> that this is desirable. This is illustrated in (64) (from <link rid="b16">Winter 1998</link>: ch.3, (89)):</p>
<p>(64)&ensp;<object id="tu52" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu52_source"> <tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Every country&apos;s security will be threatened if some building is attacked by terrorists.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every country x IF &exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(building) is attacked by terrorists&rsqb; THEN x&prime;s security will be threatened.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every country x &exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(building) is attacked by terrorists THEN x&prime;s security will be threatened&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; &lsqb;every country x IF f(building) is attacked by terrorists THEN x&prime;s security will be threatened&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(64b) gives the intermediate reading: it allows a different choice (of building) to be made for every country.</p>
<p>As for specificity in VP-deletion contexts, the CF hypothesis conforms to our conclusion in <link rid="ss9">section 3.2.2</link> that this construction militates against a QR treatment of wide-scope indefinites, but not against a quantificational treatment per se. As no syntactic movement is involved in existential closure, an account of the restrictions on wide-scope quantification in VP-deletion antecedents in terms of economy constraints on syntactic movement will not affect the scope of indefinites, as pointed out by <link rid="b25">Fox (1995b</link>). We derive wide scope for <i>a certain professor</i> in (29b), repeated as (65), as indicated in (65a):</p>
<p>(65)&ensp;<object id="tu53" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu53_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Exactly half the boys &lsqb;<sub>VP1</sub> admire <i>a certain professor</i>&rsqb;, and Mary does &lsqb;<sub>VP2</sub> e&rsqb; too.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; Exactly half the boys admire f(professor)&rsqb; AND &exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; Mary admires f(professor)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; &lsqb;Exactly half the boys admire f(professor) AND Mary admires f(professor)&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>A potentially troubling situation would arise if it turned out that only the maximal-scope Across-the-Board reading (65b) is available. We would then need to rule out (65a), by returning, e.g., to the Sag/Williams ban on free variables in elided VPs, which allows only (65b).<link rid="fn31">
<sup>31</sup></link> But this would leave us without an account of the examples in (33&ndash;35) and other problems: see <link rid="ss9">section 3.2.2</link> and references cited.</p>
<p>An important advantage of the CF hypothesis is that it explains the observations reported in <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link> above, as pointed out by <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) and <link rid="b47 b16">Winter (1997, 1998</link>). Indefinites may have unlimited existential scope, but the <i>distributive</i> scope of a plural indefinite is quite limited. Consider again example (37a), repeated as (66):</p>
<p>(66)&ensp;<object id="tu54" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu54_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">If three relatives of mine die, I will inherit a house.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(three relatives of mine) die THEN I will inherit a house&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The observation was that <i>three relatives of mine</i> may scope, <i>qua</i> existential import, outside the <i>if</i>-clause, but may not be understood with distributive wide scope over the <i>if</i>-clause. This follows automatically from the CF mechanism, which yields the specific reading of (66) given in (66a). The reason is that the descriptive content of the indefinite, and in particular the cardinality information (<i>three</i>) associated with it, remains inside the <i>if</i>-clause. Taking wide scope over the <i>if</i>-clause is only the existential quantifier over CFs; no plurality is available there with respect to which distribution might take place.</p>
<p>For the CF mechanism to work with plural indefinites, we need to assume that these do not (always) denote generalized quantifiers. Instead, <i>three relatives of mine</i> must denote a set of plural individuals. Taking plural individuals to be sets, <i>three relatives of mine</i> then denotes the set of all sets that contain three relatives of mine; the CF <i>f</i> chooses one such set.<link rid="fn32">
<sup>32</sup></link> (66a) then paraphrases as &lsquo;there is a way of choosing, such that if the three relatives of mine chosen in that way die, I inherit a house&rsquo;. This gives us the required wide-scope reading.</p>
<p>Still, as with any similar approach to the semantics of plurals, we must account for the fact that plural indefinites can be interpreted distributively in a local domain, as in <i>three relatives of mine wore a tie</i> ((36) above). <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) leaves open the option that indefinites are ambiguous and that in such examples <i>three relatives of mine</i> denotes a (distributive) generalized quantifier (with local scope), local distributivity in (66a) being due to a lexical property of the predicate <i>die</i>. But this is not sufficient, in view of our example (40), repeated as (67):</p>
<p>(67)&ensp;If three workers on our staff have a baby soon, we will have to face some hard organizational problems.</p>
<p>On the intended reading, <i>three workers on our staff</i> in (67) is specific, hence not a generalized quantifier, but must take distributive wide scope relative to <i>a baby</i>. Therefore, we need to postulate a device that allows a distributive reading for the plural individual chosen by the CF. Given such a distributivity operator, we need not assume that indefinites ever denote in any other way than through the CF mechanism (see <link rid="b47 b16">Winter 1997, 1998</link>). More importantly, while the indefinite itself may move, covertly or overtly, within a local domain, and shift the scope of the distributivity operator in that way (see (44), (45)), there is no obvious way we can apply one in (66a) so as to derive island-escaping distributivity.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the advantage gained by adopting the CF approach lies in its explanatory value, not just in its descriptive adequacy. We can see why this is so by comparing the present hypothesis with that put forward by <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>). Abusch proposes a semantic storage mechanism which may &lsquo;lift&rsquo; an indefinite (a description applied to a free variable, as in DRT, and the associated cardinality information) out of islands. At any level, an existential closure rule may &lsquo;reattach&rsquo; the indefinite and bind its free variable. The variable that gets bound with wide scope may range over plural individuals, and a distributivity operator is assumed that may apply to such a variable and pick out its members. Abusch especially stipulates that the distributivity operator may be syntactically deep-generated anywhere, so as to derive island-escaping distributivity (which she felt was possible; cf. note 20) without movement. It does not appear too problematic to adopt the reverse stipulation and allow the distributivity operator to be generated only close to the indefinite&apos;s syntactic position. This would lead to a system that is empirically hard to distinguish from the CF system. However, this merely demonstrates that Abusch&apos;s approach to indefinites does not <i>predict</i> that wide-scope distributivity is impossible; the basic approach allows one to shift the predictions in any desired direction. The CF approach, on the other hand, predicts that there will be no wide-scope distribution, as the numeral and descriptive content information never leave the island and are not available for any wide-scope distributivity operator one might wish to employ. The system would require significant stipulative modification in order for it to make the wrong prediction in this respect.</p>
<p>The CF Hypothesis performs well with regard to the properties of specific indefinites mentioned so far. There is, furthermore, accumulating independent evidence that NL semantics makes use of the CF mechanism. For instance, <link rid="b49">Reinhart (1992</link>) has argued that <i>wh</i>-in-situ is likewise interpreted through existential quantification over CFs, and <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) argues they can be profitably employed in the description of sluicing (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 60 - Sluicing.xml" type="file">chapter 60</externallink></related>); <link rid="b33">Ruys (1997</link>) suggests that quantification over CFs might be used to resolve some of the semantic problems associated with the Move-Spec/Move-F analysis of Quantifier Raising proposed in <link rid="b50">Chomsky (1995c</link>) (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 53 - Quantifier Scope Ambiguities.xml" type="file">chapter 53</externallink></related>) (see also Von <link rid="b51">Heusinger 1999</link>).</p>
<p>Not all properties of specific indefinites are easily treated in terms of CFs, however. Consider the complex issue of specificity in intensional contexts, exemplified by (68) (see <link rid="ss3">section 2</link>):</p>
<p>(68)&ensp;<object id="tu55" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu55_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">John wants to marry a waitress.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; <b>want&prime;</b>(<b>John&prime;</b>, ^(<b>marry&prime;</b>(<b>John&prime;</b>, f(<b>waitress&prime;</b>))))&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In order to obtain the <i>de re</i> reading of (68), by which there is a particular individual, who <i>is</i> a waitress (&lsquo;according to the speaker&rsquo;), and who John wants to marry, we want to assign wide scope not only to the existential quantifier, but also to the description <i>waitress</i>. But so far, the best we can obtain is (68a), where <i>waitress</i> is interpreted inside the intensional context. <link rid="b49">Reinhart (1992</link>), in the context of a CF treatment of <i>wh</i>-in-situ, proposed that the CF apply to the intension of the description of the indefinite. We may assume, for instance, the definition of intensional choice function in (69a), and represent the desired reading of (68) as (69b):</p>
<p>(69)&ensp;<object id="tu56" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu56_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>ICF &equals;<sub>df</sub> &lgr;f<sub>&lt;&lt;s,&lt;e,t&gt;&gt;,e&gt;</sub> &forall;<i>P</i><sub>&lt;s,&lt;e,t&gt;&gt;</sub> &lsqb;<sup>V</sup><i>P&ne;&Oslash;</i> &rarr; <sup>V</sup><i>P</i>(f(<i>P</i>))&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;ICF(f) &and; <b>want&prime;</b>(<b>John&prime;</b>, ^(<b>marry&prime;</b>(<b>John&prime;</b>, f(^<b>waitress&prime;</b>))))&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>By (69b), <i>f</i> applies to the property <b>^waitress&prime;</b> and, by the definition of ICF, assigns it to an individual who is a member of the extension of <b>waitress&prime;</b> in the world of evaluation of the matrix sentence; John is said to want to marry that individual. The definition (69a) seems to work fine for this relatively simple case, but is difficult to maintain when we consider the possibility that the set of waitresses is empty (see next section). Also, we already observed in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> (see the discussion concerning (14)) that the issue of intensionality is considerably more complicated than this mechanism can handle. There are, furthermore, indications that &lsquo;wide-scope&rsquo; readings of the descriptive content of, e.g., universally quantified noun phrases are also possible in certain contexts; see, e.g., <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>) and <link rid="b10">Farkas (1997</link>) ((70) from Abusch):</p>
<p>(70)&ensp;Things would be different if every senator had grown up to be a rancher instead.</p>
<p>This is not the place, and I am not qualified, to discuss these issues further.</p>
<p>Another question that requires further research is how CFs relate to anaphora. We noted in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> that specific indefinites introduce discourse referents; we saw in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link> that specific indefinites may function as antecedents in donkey anaphora contexts, as discussed in <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>) and <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>). Consider again (71) (cf. (57a)):</p>
<p>(71)&ensp;Every critic who reviews each book that <i>some author</i> writes quickly grows sick of <i>him</i>.</p>
<p>Given that <i>some author</i> must be specific here relative to <i>each book that</i> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, we need to allow the value chosen by a CF to antecede the pronoun. A naive solution might be to assume that the relevant CF variable is unselectively bound by <i>every</i>, and that <i>him</i> is interpreted as f(some author). But it is unclear how this should be achieved; also, the solution is subject to the proportion problem.<link rid="fn33">
<sup>33</sup></link> <link rid="b15">Abusch&apos;s (1994</link>) theory provides a more straightforward solution for these examples; since the mechanism she proposes can lift a restricted individual variable up to the highest universal quantifier, that quantifier can unselectively bind the variable and the pronoun can also be interpreted as that bound variable. But the proportion problem occurs here as well.</p>
<p>The next section takes a detailed look at one further complication that attends the CF hypothesis: the case of the empty restriction set.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss15" level="1">
<heading id="h14" level="1">6 Do specific NPs support existential entailments?</heading>
<p>In <link rid="ss6">section 3.1</link> we first considered such examples as (19) (repeated as (72)):</p>
<p>(72)&ensp;<object id="tu57" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu57_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">If a relative of mine dies, I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>IF &exist;x &lsqb;relative_of_mine(x) &and; x dies&rsqb; THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;relative_of_mine(x) &and; IF x dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>IF &exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(relative_of_mine) dies&rsqb; THEN I will inherit a fortune.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(relative_of_mine) dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We observed that (72) has two readings, corresponding to two scope positions for the indefinite; we presented them schematically as in (72a) and (72b). In the previous section we discussed the CF Hypothesis, which attributes to (72) the two readings in (72c) and (72d). Unfortunately, the CF Hypothesis only partly accounts for the observations that initially led us to assume the readings (72a, b).</p>
<p>The truth conditions given by (72b) are weaker, in one sense, than those of (72a), which allowed us to construct a model where (72b) is true and (72a) false: uncle John dies, and I do not inherit. Since we judged (72) true in such a model, we concluded that a wide-scope reading such as (72b) must be assumed to exist. The wide-scope reading we now derive with the CF mechanism, (72d), is not directly equivalent to (72b), but it is sufficiently similar to (72b) in that it has the required property of being true in the given model.</p>
<p>We also noted that, in another sense, (72b) has stronger truth-conditions than (72a): (72b) entails that I have relatives, (72a) does not. We had already come across a similar observation in <link rid="ss3">section 2</link> (see (9)): wide-scope, specific indefinites have traditionally been taken to enable existential entailments (but see note 5). This does not, however, follow from the CF treatment (72d). In this section, we will consider whether this deviation from tradition is justified.</p>
<p>To see why the entailment fails, consider first this simple example:</p>
<p>(73)&ensp;<object id="tu58" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu58_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">A unicorn appeared.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>(73) &amp;rrArr; There exists a unicorn.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;<b>unicorn&prime;</b>(x) &and; <b>appeared&prime;</b>(x)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; <b>appeared&prime;</b>(f(<b>unicorn&prime;</b>))&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(<b>unicorn&prime;</b>)(<b>appeared&prime;</b>)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The indefinite <i>a unicorn</i> in (73) has wide scope (trivially). The sentence is judged to support the entailment stated in (73a). This is accounted for if the indefinite is interpreted as in (73b) &ndash; call this the Existential Hypothesis.</p>
<p>The entailment intuition is not accounted for if the indefinite is interpreted as in (73c). As <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) and <link rid="b47">Winter (1997</link>) point out, the basic definition of CF in (60) states that for every non-empty set X, a CF f applied to X yields a member of X. It imposes no restriction on the value of f(X) when X is empty. Hence, when there are no unicorns, (73c) comes out as true if anything appeared at all. But (73) is solidly judged false when there are no unicorns, as the Existential Hypothesis predicts. In order to remedy this, Reinhart and Winter revise the definition so that, when a CF is applied to the empty set, the value will be something that gives falsehood for every predicate. <link rid="b47">Winter&apos;s (1997</link>) revised definition is as follows:</p>
<p>(74)&ensp;CF &equals;<sub>df</sub> &lgr;f<sub>&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,t&gt;&gt;</sub> <b>.</b> f(&Oslash;<sub>&lt;e,t&gt;</sub>) &equals; &Oslash;<sub>&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,t&gt;</sub> &and; &forall;P<sub>&lt;e,t&gt;</sub>&lsqb;P&ne;&Oslash; &rarr; &exist; x&lsqb;P(x) &and; f(P) &equals; &lgr;R<sub>&lt;e,t&gt;</sub>R(x)&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>We adopt this definition from now on. By this definition, a CF applied to a non-empty set yields the Generalized Quantifier corresponding to some member of the set, but applied to the empty set it yields the empty GQ, which is false of every predicate. This means that the CF reading of <i>a unicorn</i> in (73) now results in (73d), and comes out as false when there are no unicorns, as desired. Call this the CF Hypothesis.</p>
<p>For simplex examples such as (73) the CF Hypothesis, thus refined, yields the same existential entailments as the Existential Hypothesis. This does not hold, however, of such complex examples as (72), predicted to have the specific reading (72d). When the argument set of a CF is empty, its value is the empty GQ, which takes a predicate and yields False. But in (72d), the further embedding of this falsehood is such that the sentence as a whole comes out True. Hence, the CF Hypothesis, unlike the Existential Hypothesis, predicts that the specific reading of this sentence is true when I have no relatives.</p>
<p>We are faced with an empirical question. When they adopt the CF Hypothesis, <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) and <link rid="b47">Winter (1997</link>) predict that an indefinite on its specific reading does not support an existential entailment in contexts such as (72), or in other downward-entailing contexts such as below a single negation, or in the restriction of a universal quantifier. <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>) and the &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; straw-man theory of <link rid="ss7">section 3.2</link> do predict such entailments, by implementing the more traditional Existential Hypothesis illustrated in (72b).<link rid="fn34">
<sup>34</sup></link> Which is the correct prediction? It turns out that this question is difficult to answer.</p>
<p>The contexts mentioned so far do not decide the issue. Rather than considering (72) directly, we can show this more easily by looking at the simpler case of an indefinite embedded under a single negation:</p>
<p>(75)&ensp;<object id="tu59" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu59_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">It is not the case that a unicorn appeared.</entry>
<entry><b>unicorn&prime;</b>&nbsp;&equals;&nbsp;&empty;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>NOT &exist;x &lsqb;<b>unicorn&prime;</b>(x) &and; <b>appear&prime;</b>(x)&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>TRUE</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;<b>unicorn&prime;</b>(x) &and; NOT <b>appear&prime;</b>(x)&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>FALSE</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>NOT &exist;f&lsqb;CF(f) &and; f( <b>unicorn&prime;</b>)(<b>appear&prime;</b>)&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>TRUE</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f&lsqb;CF(f) &and; NOT f(<b>unicorn&prime;</b>)(<b>appear&prime;</b>)&rsqb;</entry>
<entry>TRUE</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Ignoring for the moment the option of applying QR to <i>a unicorn</i>, the Existential and CF Hypotheses predict the readings in (75a, b) and (75c, d) respectively. Only the wide-scope readings are different. The CF Hypothesis derives the wide-scope reading (75d), which is true in a model without unicorns (if <b>unicorn&prime;</b> is empty, the subclause is false, hence (75d) as a whole true). The Existential Hypothesis gives the wide-scope reading (75b), which is false in such a model. But it is hard to evaluate this prediction, as the Existential Hypothesis still predicts that we may judge the sentence true in a model without unicorns &ndash; namely, on the basis of the narrow-scope reading (75a). In fact, if we take the truth-conditions of an ambiguous sentence to be simply defined as the truth-conditions of the disjunction of its readings, then both hypotheses are indistinguishable, since (75a) &or; (75b) is equivalent to (75c) &or; (75d).</p>
<p>There is one way in which we might conceivably distinguish the two hypotheses with regard to (75). Suppose the intuited truth-conditions for an ambiguous sentence need not be just the truth-conditions of the disjunction of its readings. Suppose instead that speakers have the ability to &lsquo;choose&rsquo; one reading as the interpretation of a sentence, ignoring any other readings. Then by the CF Hypothesis, we still cannot judge (75) false in a model without unicorns, on any of its readings. But by the Existential Hypothesis we should be able to judge the sentence false in a model without unicorns, on the basis of its wide-scope reading (75b). If we were now to find that speakers do not succeed in judging (75) false in the relevant model, this would count as evidence against the Existential Hypothesis. Unfortunately, the evidence would be far from conclusive. Even if we attribute to speakers an ability to &lsquo;choose&rsquo; readings, which is questionable in itself, the Existential Hypothesis still does not predict that the &lsquo;false&rsquo; reading will be easy to discern. On the contrary, as already pointed out in <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link>, even on the Existential Hypothesis we expect such a &lsquo;false&rsquo; judgment to be difficult to secure, since it is in competition with a reading that renders the sentence true in the given model (narrow-scope (75a)), and a reading that renders the sentence true is likely to be much more prominent.</p>
<p>We may nonetheless look for ways of rendering the relevant intuitions more secure. Both <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>) and <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) provide examples which, they claim, support the CF hypothesis. Reinhart presents the following paradigm:</p>
<p>(76)&ensp;<object id="tu60" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu60_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The organizers did not invite two American kings to the party.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>There are two American kings that the organizers did not invite to the party.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>The organizers did not invite two American linguists to the party.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(76a) is a simple variation on (75): given the non-existence of American kings, the CF Hypothesis predicts that (76a) is true on either reading; the Existential Hypothesis predicts that we might judge it false by &lsquo;choosing&rsquo; its wide-scope reading. But, Reinhart notes, (76a) is most easily judged as true. We agree on the judgment, but we do not believe it is significant as an argument against the Existential Hypothesis. Reinhart points out that (76a) contrasts with (76b), where the &lsquo;false&rsquo; reading (predicted by both hypotheses) is much more easily obtained. But (76a) and (76b) are not a clean minimal pair. The reason we expect a &lsquo;false&rsquo; reading to be hard to obtain in (76a), even on the Existential Hypothesis, is that it is in competition with a true reading. We expect the &lsquo;false&rsquo; reading to be completely apparent in (76b), since (76b) is not ambiguous and the false reading is the only one. The contrast between (76a) and (76c) does little more to disprove the Existential Hypothesis. Reinhart points out that it is easier to judge (76c) true in a model where two specific American linguists were not invited, but others were, than it is to judge (76a) false in a model without American kings, although both these judgments would follow from the same mechanism (taking the indefinite as specific) on the Existential Hypothesis. However, even if we can &lsquo;choose&rsquo; readings, we do not expect readings that are false in a given model to be as easily accessed as ones that are true. As a matter of Gricean cooperativeness, we will lean toward the true reading.<link rid="fn35">
<sup>35</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The logical equivalencies observed in relation to (75) also obtain in the other contexts we have mentioned (an indefinite in the antecedent clause of an implication, i.e., (72), or in the restriction of a universal quantifier). For instance, (72a) &or; (72b) is equivalent to (72c) &or; (72d), so that the distinction between our two hypotheses is obscured here, as well. Furthermore, as discussed at length in <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) and especially <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>), such contexts present additional difficulties. In models where our two hypotheses differ (the restriction on the indefinite denotes the empty set), the CF Hypothesis predicts such sentences, on either reading, to be <i>trivially</i> true by rendering the antecedent clause of an implication false; such judgments are notoriously hard, which confounds the issue. We might, however, be able to avoid this particular problem. Instead of regular <i>if</i>-clauses, we might consider counterfactuals. Instead of <i>every</i>, we might consider other left monotone decreasing determiners:</p>
<p>(77)&ensp;There were no real Americans who liked <i>a devoutly communist friend of mine</i>.</p>
<p>This example has the same logical properties as (75), but is a real example in that we no longer need to ignore QR in order to make the point, as the indefinite is safely embedded in an island. The Existential Hypothesis predicts that we may judge (77) false (but also true) if I have no communist friends; on the CF Hypothesis, (77) can only be judged true. However, even on this example I have not been able to obtain secure judgments.</p>
<p>I see two possible ways out of the present quandary, both of which require further research. We may look for configurations where the logical equivalencies observed in the examples above do not hold. Such structures exist, but quickly become too complex to process. Another option is to use some means of forcing a specific reading on the indefinite and thus remove the ambiguity that obscures the distinction between the two hypotheses. Again, this is not easy, as reliable specificity-inducing measures are scarce (see also next section).<link rid="fn36">
<sup>36</sup></link> We will conclude this section by looking at specificity in intensional contexts, which provides potential evidence of both types. Consider first (78), discussed by <link rid="b47">Winter (1997</link>):</p>
<p>(78)&ensp;<object id="tu61" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu61_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">John believes that some cat snored.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&exist;x &lsqb;<b>cat&prime;</b>(x) &and; <b>believe&prime;</b>(^&lsqb;<b>snore&prime;</b>(x)&rsqb;)(<b>john&prime;</b>)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;ICF(f) &and; <b>believe&prime;</b>(^&lsqb;f(^<b>cat&prime;</b>)(<b>snore&prime;</b>)&rsqb;)(<b>john&prime;</b>)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>ICF &equals;<sub>df</sub> &lgr;f<sub>&lt;&lt;s,&lt;e,t&gt;&gt;,&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,t&gt;&gt;</sub> . &forall;<i>P</i><sub>&lt;s,&lt;e,t&gt;&gt;</sub> &lsqb;(<sup>V</sup><i>P</i>&equals;&Oslash; &rarr; f(<i>P</i>)&equals;&Oslash;<sub>&lt;&lt;e,t&gt;,t&gt;</sub>) &and; (<sup>V</sup><i>P</i>&ne;&Oslash; &rarr; &exist;x&lsqb;<sup>V</sup><i>P</i>(x) &and; f(<i>P</i>) &equals; &lgr; R<sub>&lt;e,t&gt;</sub>R(x)&rsqb;)&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>John believes that there are cats which are not cats.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When considering these examples, we first need to adapt the ICF definition (69a) to the empty set case, along the lines of (74) above. The revised ICF is defined in (78c).<link rid="fn37">
<sup>37</sup></link> We obtain the wide-scope reading (78b): <i>f</i> applies to the property ^<b>cat&prime;</b> and assigns it the GQ corresponding to some member of the extension of <b>cat&prime;</b> in the world of evaluation of the matrix sentence; if that extension is the empty set, <i>f</i> yields the empty GQ. By the Existential Hypothesis, we obtain (78a). Again, (78a) entails there are cats; (78b) does not. Rather, when evaluated in a model without cats, (78b) attributes to John the belief that <b>snore&prime;</b> is a member of the empty GQ, a necessarily false proposition. In other words, in such a feline-free model, (78) should be on a par with (78d). This does not seem correct, but, as Winter states, the result is difficult to evaluate. However, we may be able to improve on the example.</p>
<p>In intensional contexts, there exist familiar ways of forcing wide or narrow scope. Consider Spanish (79), from <link rid="b52">Klein (1974</link>):</p>
<p>(79)&ensp;<object id="tu62" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu62_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Busco a un gu&iacute;a que habla<sub>IND</sub>/hable<sub>SUB</sub> quechua.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;I&apos;m looking for a guide who speak(s) Quechua.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>When an NP has a relative clause in the subjunctive mood, the NP must take narrow scope relative to the intensional operator that licenses the subjunctive; with <i>hable</i>, (79) means I&apos;m looking for any such guide, not a particular one. Unfortunately, in many Romance languages, the reverse is not true: indicative mood does not force the wide-scope reading we are looking for (see especially <link rid="b53">Farkas 1982</link>). In Catalan, however, it sometimes does (see <link rid="b54">Quer 1998</link> and references cited there):</p>
<p>(80)&ensp;<object id="tu63" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu63_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="10">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Vull</entry>
<entry>que</entry>
<entry>un</entry>
<entry>llibre</entry>
<entry>que</entry>
<entry>m&rsquo;agrada<sub>IND</sub>
</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
<entry>m&rsquo;agradi<sub>SUB</sub>
</entry>
<entry>el</entry>
<entry>convenci.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>I-want</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>book</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>me-pleases</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
<entry>me-please</entry>
<entry>him</entry>
<entry>convinces</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col10">&lsquo;I want a book that pleases me to convince him.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>With indicative, (80) is not ambiguous and has only a <i>de re</i> reading for the embedded subject. When there are in fact no books that please me, the sentence with indicative is solidly judged false, as the Existential Hypothesis predicts. We may improve the example further as in (81):</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu64" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu64_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="15">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="9" colname="col9" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="10" colname="col10" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="11" colname="col11" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="12" colname="col12" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="13" colname="col13" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="14" colname="col14" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="15" colname="col15" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>&Eacute;s</entry>
<entry>impossible</entry>
<entry>que</entry>
<entry>una</entry>
<entry>noia</entry>
<entry>francesa</entry>
<entry>que</entry>
<entry>jo</entry>
<entry>conec<sub>IND</sub>
</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
<entry>conegui<sub>SUB</sub>
</entry>
<entry>faci</entry>
<entry>una</entry>
<entry>cosa</entry>
<entry>aix&iacute;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Is</entry>
<entry>impossible</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>girl</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
<entry>that</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>know</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
<entry>know</entry>
<entry>do</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>thing</entry>
<entry>like-that</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col15">&lsquo;It is impossible that a French girl I know should do a thing like that.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Again, with the indicative, the sentence is judged false when I know no French girls. The CF Hypothesis, at least as implemented in (78c), clearly fails here. With the set of French girls I know empty &lsquo;in the real world&rsquo;, a wide-scope CF analysis has the embedded sentence denoting a necessarily false proposition, as explained above. The statement that such a proposition is &lsquo;impossible&rsquo; should be true, and quite natural, for instance in the context of a Semantics 101 class. Nevertheless, this reading is not obtained.<link rid="fn38">
<sup>38</sup></link>
</p>
<p>It should be clear that more research is required, on extensional CF and certainly on intensional CF, in order to determine whether the weakening of existential entailments of specific indefinites that the CF Hypothesis predicts can be upheld. At present, it does not appear that the CF approach can easily be falsified in this respect.<link rid="fn39">
<sup>39</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="1">
<heading id="h15" level="1">7 How to create a specific NP</heading>
<p>In this final section we return to more basic empirical concerns, and ask what are the factors that contribute to specificity. We will look at some properties of indefinites that favor or disfavor a specific reading, and we briefly examine <link rid="b46">Kratzer&apos;s (1998</link>) account of the conditions under which intermediate-scope readings arise.</p>
<p>The literature abounds with descriptions of types of indefinites, and contexts containing indefinites, that allegedly induce &lsquo;specificity&rsquo;. In many cases, as noted, the property so identified is not the wide-scope property under examination here, but some other supposed semantic property of the indefinite, e.g., some sort of &lsquo;D-linking&rsquo; (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 77 - Wh-in-Situ.xml" type="file">chapter 77</externallink></related>).<link rid="fn40">
<sup>40</sup></link> In many cases, authors simply state that a given indefinite in a given context is &lsquo;specific&rsquo; without detailing the semantic intuitions that lead them to this characterization, making it impossible to determine the relevance of the statement for any particular line of research, given the existing terminological confusion.<link rid="fn41">
<sup>41</sup></link> But such distractions apart, the crop of necessary and sufficient conditions for specificity still remains meager.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) provide a useful list of factors that help or hinder what they consider (see <link rid="ss6 ss7 ss13">sections 3.1, 3.2, 4</link>) a referential reading on indefinites &ndash; i.e., the reading that we have diagnosed as involving wide-scope quantification over CF. For instance, increasing the &lsquo;descriptive content&rsquo; of the indefinite (adding modifiers, adding relative clauses, especially appositive ones) contributes to this reading. The pragmatic rationale seems to be that a speaker who can provide such details apparently has a particular person in mind when using the indefinite; and, furthermore, that adding information to the indefinite that does not seem directly relevant to the truth of the intended assertion invites the inference that the information is added in order to single out a particular individual that verifies the assertion. It seems to me that these observations remain relevant, even though we do not adopt Fodor and Sag&apos;s contention that this individual the speaker has in mind is also, semantically, the referent of the indefinite; it still seems correct that wide-scope indefinites are often <i>used</i> in order to make a statement about a particular individual, who for some reason we cannot or would not identify more directly, e.g., by using a proper name. Nonetheless, what we describe here is only a tendency: indefinites endowed with considerable descriptive content, and even appositive relative clauses, may still be interpreted with narrow scope. Some reliable wide-scope-inducing modifiers I am aware of are positive polarity items &ndash; e.g., the Catalan indicative relative clauses cited in the previous section, or the German IV2 relative clause discussed by <link rid="b55">G&auml;rtner (2000</link>); unfortunately, none of these can be employed in a wide enough range of contexts for them to be a helpful tool in examining many of the empirical questions addressed in previous sections. Syntactic contexts that favor &lsquo;specific&rsquo; readings as intended here have also been widely discussed (see, e.g., <link rid="b56 b57">Kerstens 1975, Reuland 1988</link>, and <link rid="b58">Rullmann 1989</link> on Dutch VP-external subjects; <link rid="b56">Kerstens 1975</link>, de <link rid="b59">Hoop 1992</link>, and <link rid="b60">Diesing 1992b</link> on Germanic scrambling; see also <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 43 - Mittelfeld Phenomena (Scrambling in Germanic).xml" type="file">chapter 43</externallink></related>; and many references cited there) &ndash; but again, wide-scope readings are rarely the only readings available for indefinites in such contexts.<link rid="fn42">
<sup>42</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Measures for inducing narrow scope, although less useful for the kind of research reported here, are often somewhat more reliable. Indefinites containing bound variable pronouns take narrow scope relative to their binders (but see later in this section), as do indefinites containing polarity items, or subjunctive mood relative clauses, relative to their licensers. Bare plurals are rarely interpreted with wide scope, and neither are indefinites in predicative position (but see <link rid="b16">Winter 1998</link>), adverbial indefinite NPs, and certain indefinite pronominals (e.g., Dutch <i>wat</i> &lsquo;something&rsquo;). Other syntactic contexts disfavoring &lsquo;specificity&rsquo; typically include <i>there-</i>insertion sentences, but again this is only a tendency (see, e.g., <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag 1982</link>; De <link rid="b59">Hoop 1992</link>). In addition, the explanation of many of these tendencies remains obscure.</p>
<p>However, since the early 1990s, evidence has accumulated that one factor systematically determines whether an indefinite may be specific in our sense: the choice of determiner. <link rid="b32">Liu (1990</link>), <link rid="b34 b35">Beghelli (1993, 1995</link>), and <link rid="b61">Beghelli and Stowell (1997</link>) conducted research on the scope properties of different NP types, distinguished by determiner (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 71 - The Syntax of Quantified Phrases and Quantitative Clitics.xml" type="file">chapter 71</externallink></related>), which, although it was aimed at local (within-clause) scope phenomena, was relevant to our subject matter for the following reasons. We have found in <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link> that, in order to explain island-escaping, non-distributive wide scope (specificity), we need some interpretive mechanism that allows an indefinite to &lsquo;escape&rsquo; the scope of any higher operator, but without scoping (distributing) over that operator. The CF mechanism explained in the previous sections is such a mechanism. Now, even though we needed examples of island-escaping scope to motivate such a specificity mechanism, now that we know it exists, we must assume that it can operate in a local domain as well. Consider therefore an indefinite in object position, and its scope relative to the (local) subject. If the indefinite seems to escape the scope of the subject, this may reflect any of a number of mechanisms in operation: e.g., non-distributivity of the subject, local QR of the indefinite object, or specificity. Indeed, when we find that the &lsquo;non-narrow&rsquo; scope of the indefinite object in such a configuration can be described by the specificity mechanism (e.g., CF), then we should not look for another explanation, e.g., in terms of movement, as the specificity mechanism is needed independently to explain the phenomena in the previous sections (see note 24). More significant is the reverse situation: suppose we find that the indefinite object cannot escape the scope of the subject in a way that can be described by the specificity mechanism. Then we must conclude that the specificity (CF) mechanism cannot apply to this particular indefinite. Liu and Beghelli found several such cases:</p>
<p>(82)&ensp;<object id="tu65" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu65_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Fewer than five girls saw <i>more than five movies</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every girl saw <i>fewer than six movies</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; fewer than five girls x &lsqb;x saw f(more than five movies)&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; every girl x &lsqb;x saw f(fewer than six movies)&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In these examples, it is impossible for the object to escape the scope of the subject: there is no &lsquo;independent&rsquo; scope reading, in Liu&apos;s terms. For instance, (82a) does not have the reading that there was a particular set of more than five movies, such that fewer than five girls saw each of those movies; likewise, (82b) does not have a reading according to which there is a particular set of fewer than six movies, such that every girl saw those movies. Yet these are exactly the readings that would obtain if the specificity mechanism were to apply to the indefinite object; i.e., the readings that we do not find are exactly the readings given by wide-scope existential quantification over CF, as indicated in (82c) and (82d): a choice from the object is made independently of values of the subject, but the object does not show distributive scope over the subject.</p>
<p>Much more can be said about these examples. One point is that, apparently, a &lsquo;collective&rsquo; interpretation for the subject is impossible here, as well, since that would presumably lead to an interpretation very much like the interpretation we expect from specificity of the object (see especially <link rid="b62">Szabolsci 1997b</link> and <link rid="b16">Winter 1998</link> for discussion of what property of the subject is responsible for this). Furthermore, a wide-scope <i>distributive</i> reading for the indefinite object (which could not result from the specificity mechanism, see <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link>, but might conceivably result from QR of the object), is also missing. Beghelli and Beghelli and Stowell explain this by separating the (collective) indefinite from a syntactically fixed distributivity operator, and then allowing just the indefinite to move (Quantifier Raise) to a higher position. However, since such movement will never lead to island-escaping specific readings, so that some specificity mechanism that generates wide scope without movement is needed independently (as Beghelli confirms), it is unclear to me what purpose is served by assuming that these indefinites may move at LF at all (see <link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link>). The only readings we do find in (82) are wide-scope distributive readings for the subject, and possibly a &lsquo;cumulative&rsquo; reading for (82a).</p>
<p>For our purposes, the relevant observation is that specificity is not an option for the italicized indefinites in (82). The class of weak NP determiners that show this behavior, according to Liu and Beghelli, are all modified numerals, and all determiners that are not monotone increasing. In other words, specificity is reserved for simple monotone increasing weak determiners: <i>a</i>, <i>several</i>, <i>some</i>, <i>three</i>, etc.<link rid="fn43">
<sup>43</sup></link> These observations, based initially on local scope phenomena, are confirmed by the absence of island-escaping wide scope with other than simple increasing DETs:</p>
<p>(83)&ensp;<object id="tu66" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu66_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>If <i>fewer than three relatives of mine</i> die, I will inherit a house.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>If <i>more than three relatives of mine</i> die, I will inherit a house.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Neither (83a) nor (83b) has a specific reading for the italicized indefinite. The same observation was made independently in <link rid="b63">Corblin (1997</link>) for French:</p>
<p>(84)&ensp;<object id="tu67" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu67_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Chaque professeur a r&eacute;compens&eacute; &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> chacque &eacute;tudiant &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> qui a lu <i>un roman</i>&rsqb;&rsqb;. (Three readings)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&lsquo;Every professor has rewarded every student who has read a novel.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Chaque professeur a r&eacute;compens&eacute; &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> chacque &eacute;tudiant &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> qui a lu <i>au moins</i>/<i>au plus</i>/<i>exactement un roman</i>&rsqb;&rsqb;. (One reading)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>&lsquo;Every professor has rewarded every student who has read at least/at most/exactly one novel.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(84a) has three possible scope positions for <i>un roman</i> (including an island-escaping intermediate-scope reading; cf. <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>); the modified numerals in (84b) allow only a narrow-scope reading.</p>
<p>All monotone decreasing (and non-monotone) weak NP determiners are included here in the set of determiners that resist specific readings. That the specificity (CF) mechanism must not be allowed to apply to NPs with such determiners is also apparent from much simpler examples:</p>
<p>(85)&ensp;<object id="tu68" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu68_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Fewer than six boys arrived.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Exactly six boys arrived.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(fewer than six boys)(arrived)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; f(exactly six boys)(arrived)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The CF analyses for (85a, b) given in (85c, d) describe adjectival readings for <i>fewer than six</i> and <i>exactly six</i>. For instance, (85c) states there is some way of choosing fewer than six boys, such that those boys arrived; allowing that many other boys may also have arrived. Such monotone increasing readings for these determiners are not attested unless under very special circumstances. Hence, we know that these NPs do not allow CF readings; the same holds of other specificity mechanisms I am aware of.</p>
<p>Explaining the Liu/Beghelli bifurcation is another matter. <link rid="b61">Beghelli and Stowell (1997</link>) and <link rid="b62">Szabolcsi (1997b</link>) distinguish the two types of weak NPs in terms of morphosyntactic features as well as semantically. But this is hard to achieve other than by stipulation. <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) proposes a distinction on the basis of DP-internal syntax, inspired by <link rid="b64">Danon (1996</link>). Unmodified numerals may occupy the D head position, leaving the spec, DP position free for a covert CF variable, whereas modified numerals cannot, for obvious reasons, occupy D<sup>0</sup>; these are in Spec, DP. This approach requires further elaboration. For instance, a separate stipulation is needed to prevent a CF reading for unmodified monotone decreasing determiners (<i>no</i>, <i>few</i>). Furthermore, syntactic considerations indicate that modified numerals may occur more deeply embedded in DP; they may, e.g., be preceded by demonstratives, definite and universal determiners, and possessive phrases. More research on this topic is required, but the progress that has been made in identifying at least one necessary condition for specificity is promising.</p>
<p>Let us finally consider the conditions under which intermediate, island-escaping scope readings for indefinites may arise. Recall from <link rid="ss8">section 3.2.1</link> that <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) claimed that such a reading did not occur in (27), repeated as (86a): either <i>a student of mine</i> scopes inside the complex NP island, or it takes the widest possible scope. We subsequently argued in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link>, on the basis of many counter-examples from the literature, that intermediate readings out of islands do occur: (86b) is an example (from <link rid="b15">Abusch 1994</link>):</p>
<p>(86)&ensp;<object id="tu69" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu69_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every professor overheard &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> the rumor &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> that a student of mine had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every professor<sub>i</sub> rewarded &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> every student &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> who read some book he<sub>i</sub> had recommended&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As a consensus began to emerge in the literature that intermediate readings exist, little further attention was paid to Fodor and Sag&apos;s original intuition: that no such reading exists in (86a). Indeed, given the complexity of the structure and the competition of other available readings, it does not seem unreasonable to suppose that (86a) is assigned an intermediate reading as well, which just happens to be difficult to detect. We saw that in other examples special measures were often required to bring the intermediate reading to the fore.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b46">Kratzer (1998</link>) is an impressive and careful attempt to combine the best of both worlds. She takes Fodor and Sag&apos;s intuitions seriously, and develops a semantics for indefinites that is intended to explain the distinction between (86a) and (86b). This involves a return to an inherent binary ambiguity in indefinites, a sophisticated version of the referential/quantificational ambiguity postulated by Fodor and Sag and their predecessors and discussed at length in <link rid="ss3 ss5">sections 2 and 3</link>. Indefinites have one reading as a Generalized Quantifier, which yields the local-(narrow-)scope readings in (86). Alternatively, a CF variable may apply to an indefinite&apos;s description and pick a member of the set it denotes. But there is no free existential closure of CF variables, which would result in intermediate readings. Instead, the CF variable remains free and acquires its value from the context of utterance (just like a &lsquo;referential&rsquo; indefinite in Fodor and Sag&apos;s analysis). This results in a &lsquo;maximal-scope&rsquo; reading in (86a): the value of the indefinite is the particular individual picked from my students by the contextually given CF. The problem now lies in explaining how an intermediate reading arises in (86b).</p>
<p>Kratzer argues that the crucial difference between the two examples lies in the fact that the indefinite in (86b) contains a bound variable pronoun. We pointed out in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link> that this prevents a maximal-scope reading and thereby removes some of the competition for the intermediate reading. <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>) and <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>) made use of this device in order to make the intermediate reading more prominent. But it was not assumed that the intermediate reading is <i>caused</i> by the bound variable.<link rid="fn44">
<sup>44</sup></link> Kratzer starts out by investigating this option: that the bound pronoun is directly responsible for the occurrence of the intermediate reading. Consider a simpler example:</p>
<p>(87)&ensp;<object id="tu70" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu70_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every boy<sub>i</sub> read <i>a book he</i><sub>i</sub> <i>liked</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every boy x &lsqb;x read f(book x liked)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; every boy x &lsqb;x read f(book x liked)&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Every boy x &lsqb;x read f<sub>x</sub>(book x liked)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>If we attempt to assign the indefinite wide scope here, either by wide-scope existential closure of CF, as in (87c) or by leaving the CF variable free, as in (87b), the reading we obtain is, paradoxically, almost a narrow-scope reading. Since <i>f</i> chooses from a set that may be different for every boy, the choice of book may be different for every boy, as in a narrow-scope reading. This would hold in (86b) as well: a free CF variable applied to <i>some book he had recommended</i> may give a different value for every professor, resulting in a reading where the indefinite seems to remain in the scope of <i>every professor</i>.</p>
<p>But the reading obtained is not quite the narrow-scope reading. Supposing that two boys happen to like exactly the same books, (87b) and (87c) would say that those boys would read the same books, as <i>f</i> chooses from the same set (call this the case of accidentally identical sets). This is not what a narrow-scope reading gives us, and it is also, more significantly, not what (87a) means: (87a) cannot be false just because John and Bill like exactly the same books, but read a different choice from their common favorites. For the same reason, we do not quite obtain the intermediate-scope reading for (86b) in this way.</p>
<p>Kratzer&apos;s solution is to assume next that the CF variable itself is parameterized: (87a) may be interpreted as (87d), where <i>f</i> is a (contextually given) function from individuals to CFs. Since the (subscript) <i>x</i> on <i>f</i> may be bound by <i>every boy</i>, we may have a different CF for every boy, hence a different choice of book even if the set of books liked happens to be the same. Independent evidence for such a &lsquo;functional&rsquo; reading on indefinites comes from the semantics of <i>a certain</i> analyzed by <link rid="b65">Hintikka (1986</link>): Kratzer discusses (88):</p>
<p>(88)&ensp;<object id="tu71" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu71_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Each husband had forgotten a certain date &ndash; his wife&apos;s birthday.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every husband x &lsqb;x had forgotten f<sub>x</sub>(date)&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (88a), we may apparently interpret <i>a certain date</i> neither as a narrow-scope indefinite (for each husband any date at all), nor just as a wide-scope indefinite (one date, say September 14, for all husbands), but as a &lsquo;wife&apos;s birthday&rsquo; function which, for each husband, gives a function which picks one date from the set of dates, as in (88b).</p>
<p>This seems to solve the problem of accidentally identical sets: both in (87) and in (86b) the CF is parameterized in this manner, which leads to a &lsquo;narrow-scope reading&rsquo; relative to the binder of the parameterizing variable in the CF. The problem is that we have now lost our explanation for the distinction between (86a) and (86b). There is no relation between the presence of a bound pronoun in the indefinite, and the occurrence of a parameterized CF. Nothing prevents <i>every professor</i> in (86a) from binding a parameter on the CF as well. Kratzer&apos;s solution to this is more tentative. She suggests that &lsquo;functional readings&rsquo; for indefinites (with parameterized CF) are generally hard to obtain &ndash; an appropriate function must be salient in the context (such as a function from husbands to their wives&rsquo; birthdays in (88)). The reading seems easier to obtain in (86b) than in (86a) because the <i>un</i>parameterized CF reading already <i>almost</i> gives the same interpretation, the marginal case of accidentally identical sets apart.</p>
<p>Herein lies the weak point in Kratzer&apos;s analysis. For the explanation just given to go through, we must allow the unparameterized CF to be a freely available option in (86b) and (87). Indeed, given that parameterized, functional readings are assumed to be hard, we expect the unparameterized reading itself to be prominent in (86b) and (87). But this is not the case. We have seen this for (87), and it holds for (86b) as well: (86b) does not have a reading whereby for every professor there is some book he recommended, such that he rewarded all students who read it, with the proviso that two professors who happen to recommend the same books must also reward reading of the same book.</p>
<p>On the other hand, (87) presents a problem for any CF analysis of indefinites: the reading (87c) must not be allowed. The problem is discussed at length in <link rid="b66">Reniers (1997</link>)<link rid="fn45">
<sup>45</sup></link> and in <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>). Winter provides a solution very similar to Kratzer&apos;s, which is, furthermore, sensitive to the presence of a bound pronoun in the indefinite; I speculate that Winter&apos;s proposal might be employed to complete Kratzer&apos;s program.</p>
<p>Other problems for Kratzer&apos;s approach are more directly empirical. As pointed out by <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>), examples can be given of intermediate-scope readings for indefinites without bound pronouns, which do not seem to depend on a functional reading of the indefinite. Some examples can be found in <link rid="ss13">section 4</link> above; (89) is a variation on an example from <link rid="b15">Abusch (1994</link>):</p>
<p>(89) At most four committee members resisted my proposal that <i>a candidate</i> be turned down.</p>
<p>I feel (89) may be read with an intermediate-scope reading for <i>a candidate</i>, without its being understood that there is some relevant function from committee members to (choices from) candidates that they do not want to see turned down. One might further test Kratzer&apos;s predictions by constructing examples involving an indefinite escaping a scope island, while remaining inside the scope of some other operator, but one which does not bind a variable (e.g., negation). In spite of the problems mentioned, Kratzer&apos;s is an insightful suggestion, and it does not seem unreasonable to suppose that functional readings of indefinites may indeed account for many cases of apparent intermediate-scope readings.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss17" level="1">
<heading id="h16" level="1">8 Conclusion: outline and summary</heading>
<p>Examples such as (19):</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;If a relative of mine dies, I will inherit a fortune.</p>
<p>admit of a wide-scope (or &lsquo;specific&rsquo;) reading for the indefinite NP <i>a relative of mine</i>; it can be paraphrased as:</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;There is a relative of mine, such that: if (s)he dies, I will inherit a fortune.</p>
<p>Wide scope is not available for other types of NPs (e.g., <i>every relative of mine</i>) in this structure, nor is extraction from the <i>if</i>-clause (of, e.g., <i>wh</i>-expressions) possible in overt syntax. Thus, (19) shows &lsquo;island-escaping scope&rsquo; (<link rid="ss6">section 3.1</link>).</p>
<p>In order to describe island-escaping scope, one might postulate that indefinites can be extracted from the <i>if</i>-clause (through some semantic mechanism (storage) or through some exceptional form of syntactic movement): call this &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo;. But several observations argue against this (<link rid="ss7">section 3.2</link>).</p>
<p>If indefinites could be moved out of an island, one would naturally expect them to be able to move out of an island while still remaining in the scope of some other, yet higher scope-taking operator (<link rid="ss8">section 3.2.1</link>). So (27):</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;<object id="tu72" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu72_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Every professor overheard &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> the rumor &lsqb;<sub>CP</sub> that a student of mine had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every professor x &lsqb;a student of mine y &lsqb;x overheard the rumor that &lsqb;y had been called before the dean&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>would be expected to admit of the reading given in (27b): &lsquo;intermediate island-escaping scope&rsquo;. <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) claimed that it does not.</p>
<p>Wide-scope indefinites not only violate known movement and scope islands, they also appear to violate conditions on variable binding in VP-deletion contexts, so &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; still undergenerates readings (<link rid="ss9">section 3.2.2</link>).</p>
<p>If indefinites underwent unrestricted QR, then wide-scope <i>distributive</i> readings for plural indefinites would naturally be expected (<link rid="ss10">section 3.2.3</link>); (37a) would be expected to allow the reading paraphrased in (ii):</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;a.&ensp;If three relatives of mine die, I will inherit a house.</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;There are three relatives of mine, such that if any one of them dies, I will inherit a house.</p>
<p>But (<link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link>) this is not the case. In fact, a distributive wide-scope reading is (all but) impossible even for <i>three books</i> in (41),</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;Two boys read three books.</p>
<p>which suggests that these NPs do not freely undergo QR at all.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the &lsquo;island-free QR&rsquo; straw-man is falsified; the scope of indefinites is not determined through syntactic movement; in fact, the scope of indefinites is not determined through displacement, either syntactic or semantic, of the indefinite itself.</p>
<p>An alternative explanation of the apparent island-escaping wide-scope readings of indefinites was proposed by <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>): there is an inherent ambiguity in the indefinite itself. Either it denotes a quantifier, which may scope locally but may not escape islands. Or it functions as a referential, name-like expression; such expressions are insensitive to scope effects, creating the impression of a wide-scope quantifier: this accounts for the (now: apparent) island-escaping wide scope in (19), and is in accordance with the other scope properties observed above (excepting perhaps (41)).</p>
<p>However (<link rid="ss13">section 4</link>), it has since become apparent that intermediate island-escaping scope readings do exist. (51b) admits of the reading in (iii):</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;b.&ensp;Most linguists have looked at every analysis that solves some problem.</p>
<p>(iii)&ensp;For most linguists there is some problem x such that they have looked at every analysis that solves x.</p>
<p>This argues against the Fodor and Sag approach: the indefinite on its referential reading cannot be interpreted in the scope of any higher operator; the indefinite on its quantificational reading should not escape islands.</p>
<p>An alternative analysis due to <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) (<link rid="ss14">section 5</link>) says that indefinites do not have a referential reading and cannot be extracted from islands. Instead they may be interpreted in situ as open formulae containing a free variable that may be bound by an existential quantifier anywhere in the structure; when the indefinite is in an island, and its variable is bound from outside the island, &lsquo;island-escaping scope&rsquo; results. In order to obtain the correct semantics, the variable must be of the choice function (CF) type: a choice function is a function which, when applied to a set, picks out a member of this set. For (19), this gives the island-escaping wide-scope reading (62b), which is paraphrased in (iv):</p>
<p>(19) If a relative of mine dies, I will inherit a fortune.</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;b.&ensp;&exist;f &lsqb;CF(f) &and; IF f(relative_of_mine) dies THEN I will inherit a fortune&rsqb;.</p>
<p>(iv)&ensp;There is a way of choosing an individual from a set, such that if the person we choose from my relatives in that way dies, then I inherit a fortune.</p>
<p>The CF approach correctly predicts that intermediate island-escaping scope is possible, and that island-escaping distributive wide scope is not.</p>
<p>It has traditionally been assumed that wide-scope indefinites support existential entailments. For instance, the wide-scope reading for <i>a relative of mine</i> in (19) has been taken to entail that I have at least one relative. The CF approach, however, predicts that this is not always the case; for instance, (62b) for (19) does not entail that I have relatives. <link rid="ss15">Section 6</link> takes a close look at the relevant intuitions and concludes that the CF approach cannot easily be falsified; it may well be that wide-scope indefinites do not always support existential entailments.</p>
<p>
<link rid="ss16">Section 7</link> looks into the conditions on (island-escaping) wide-scope readings for indefinites. There are many ill-understood factors that help or hinder these readings; there appears to be at least one cross-linguistically constant and reliable necessary condition: the indefinite must have a simplex, monotone increasing determiner. Thus, there is no wide-scope reading in (83):</p>
<p>(83)&ensp;<object id="tu73" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu73_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>If <i>fewer than three relatives of mine</i> die, I will inherit a house.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>If <i>more than three relatives of mine</i> die, I will inherit a house. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This section also returns to intermediate island-escaping scope, and looks at <link rid="b46">Kratzer&apos;s (1998</link>) investigation of the factors that make these readings possible.</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss18" level="1">
<heading id="h17" level="1">NOTES</heading>
<p>I would like to thank Sarah Kennelly, Josep Quer, Yoad Winter, and two referees for helpful comments and suggestions.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>A note on this terminology: the label &lsquo;specific&rsquo; has been attached to indefinite (as well as definite) NPs for widely different reasons, and on the basis of widely different observations &ndash; whether those observations will all permit of one unified analysis is highly questionable. We use it here as a non-theoretical term in the sense of, e.g., <link rid="b9">Karttunen (1971a</link>), <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>): an indefinite or weak NP is specific relative to a given operator (that c-commands it in overt syntax) if it is not interpreted in the scope of that operator, under some reasonable analysis.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn2">
<number>2&ensp;</number>Karttunen did not fail to observe that even non-specific indefinites may introduce discourse referents, albeit short-term ones that quickly &lsquo;decay&rsquo;. Thus, the scopally embedded indefinites in (i) allow for discourse anaphoric pronouns, provided the pronouns are embedded in a similar way (see further (54&ndash;56) below):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu74" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu74_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You must write <i>a letter</i> to your parents. <i>It</i> has to be sent by airmail.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Harvey courts <i>a girl</i> at every convention. <i>She</i> always comes to the banquet with him.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn3">
<number>3&ensp;</number>To avoid the terminological confusion that hindsight may bring, the reader should note that &lsquo;quantificational&rsquo; is used here in the uncomplicated sense of &lsquo;involving a quantifier&rsquo; (namely, the existential quantifier &exist; (or, notationally, the eng-operator)). We are not concerned yet with such niceties as the &lsquo;quantificational&rsquo; (as opposed to &lsquo;cardinal&rsquo;) use of weak determiners (<link rid="b67">Milsark 1974</link>), or with &lsquo;essentially quantificational&rsquo; NPs in the sense of non-intersective and necessarily distributive NPs (see <link rid="b62">Szabolcsi 1997b</link> and references cited there). Likewise, the &lsquo;referential&rsquo; reading in Karttunen&apos;s work was thought of as simply being brought about by translating the indefinite as an individual constant, just like a proper name.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn4">
<number>4&ensp;</number>There may be grounds for doubting the validity of the existential entailment intuition for (9c) and similar examples. We discuss this issue in <link rid="ss15">section 6</link>.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn5">
<number>5&ensp;</number>To be slightly more historically accurate: for reasons having to do with such cases as (14) below, Fodor proposed a novel operator instead of the existential quantifier employed here &ndash; one which does not allow existential entailment but merely captures the &lsquo;individuating&rsquo; effect of the <i>de re</i> reading. The existential entailment does, however, appear to be real in many cases.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn6">
<number>6&ensp;</number>Example (70) below may indicate, furthermore, that the problem is not restricted to indefinites.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn7">
<number>7&ensp;</number>For an analysis of this issue and an overview of its role in the literature, see <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>: 7&ndash;15).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn8">
<number>8&ensp;</number>Despite mistaken claims to the contrary in the literature; see <link rid="b68">Cooper (1979</link>) and <link rid="b41">Farkas (1981</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn9">
<number>9&ensp;</number>Nearly, but not quite, as pointed out also by <link rid="b11">Abbott (1993</link>). The referential reading is obtained in <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>) by enriching the model with a context that includes a value for &ldquo;the individual the speaker has in mind&rdquo;; a specific indefinite refers to this individual. This implies that the specific reading of, say, (19a) could be falsified in case uncle Winston&apos;s death would make me rich, but I had my penniless aunt Sue in mind when I uttered (19a). This subtle prediction is difficult to verify, if only because the non-specific, narrow-scope reading is also false in that situation.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn10">
<number>10&ensp;</number>Recall that intermediate readings are possible for examples like (15), a fact that was originally put forward as an argument against a simple binary ambiguity analysis of specificity. But (15) does not falsify Fodor and Sag&apos;s position, which allows island-obeying Quantifier Raising in addition to the inherent binary ambiguity. Since <i>a high American official</i> in (15) is not embedded in an extraction island, the intermediate reading (15b) can be derived by Quantifier Raising the indefinite on its quantificational reading to the intermediate position. We will attempt to revive the argument from (15) in <link rid="ss3">section 4</link>.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn11">
<number>11&ensp;</number>.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;unless the copy of that variable in the elided VP is bound by the same quantifier (see below).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn12">
<number>12&ensp;</number>(30) assumes a &lsquo;deletion under LF identity&rsquo; approach to VP ellipsis, as in <link rid="b21">Sag (1980</link>) and <link rid="b25">Fox (1995b</link>); under <link rid="b22">Williams&apos;s (1977</link>) copying of LF theory, VP2 in (30) would contain an unbound variable.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn13">
<number>13&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b24">Fiengo and May (1994</link>: 232, fn. 34) likewise report on <i>every student hit someone, and every professor did, too</i> that it &ldquo;permits a reading in which the existential has broad scope, but under which different people were hit.&rdquo;</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn14">
<number>14&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b26">Hirschb&uuml;hler (1982</link>), however, speculates that a sequence of sentences might constitute a single conjoined structure, allowing syntactic scope taking across sentence boundaries.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn15">
<number>15&ensp;</number>The right-hand conjuncts in (34) do not have a quantificational subject; Fox argues that QR is licensed here because it results in inverse scope relative to a covert quantifier over events and a generic quantifier, respectively. The reported intuitions on (28a) and (28c), however, remain unaccounted for.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn16">
<number>16&ensp;</number>For an introduction to Generalized Quantifier theory, see, e.g., <link rid="b69">Gamut (1991</link>), <link rid="b70">Keenan (1996</link>). (36b) paraphrases as: &lsquo;Among the sets whose intersection with the set of my relatives contains three elements, is the set of individuals wearing a tie.&rsquo; This is equivalent to:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;&exist;X &lsqb;X &sube; <b>relative_of_mine&prime;</b> &and; &verbar;X&verbar; &equals; 3 &and; &forall;x &isin; X &exist;y&lsqb;<b>tie&prime;</b>(y) &and; <b>wear&prime;</b>(y)(x)&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn17">
<number>17&ensp;</number>For an introduction to plurality, see <link rid="b71">Landman (1996</link>) and references cited there.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn18">
<number>18&ensp;</number>(37a) is used here for simplicity&apos;s sake but may be susceptible to the objection that (taking <i>If</i> as material implication) (37c) entails (37d), creating a problem of the type hinted at in <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link> (see also <link rid="b16">Winter 1998</link>: 95ff.). The problem does not arise with the examples given below. ((37) is not from <link rid="b20">Ruys 1992</link> but from <link rid="b72">Ruys 1995</link>; however, it was deleted from the published version of that manuscript due to space limitations.) For those unfamiliar with Generalized Quantifiers: (37c) is equivalent to:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;&exist;X &lsqb;X &sube; <b>relative_of_mine&prime;</b> &and; &verbar;X&verbar; &equals; 3 &and; &forall;x &isin; X &lsqb;IF x dies THEN I will inherit a house&rsqb;&rsqb;.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn19">
<number>19&ensp;</number>This description of the problem in terms of &lsquo;existential scope&rsquo; and &lsquo;scope of distributivity&rsquo; follows the detailed discussion of specificity and its interaction with distributivity/collectivity effects in <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn20">
<number>20&ensp;</number>I know of one example in the literature that has been claimed to show island-escaping distributive scope for a plural indefinite: <link rid="b15">Abusch&apos;s (1994</link>: (44)):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;Every critic who reviewed two books by Henry Miller panned them.</p>
<p>Abusch states that (i) can be read as conveying that there is a set of two books by Miller, such that for each book x from this set, whoever reviewed x, panned x. If this intuition is genuine, it undermines the argument being made here, but it is hard to see how one could derive a wide-scope distributive reading for (i) without predicting that (37&ndash;39) also have such a reading, which they clearly do not. If we must choose which intuition is genuine, I would hesitate to follow Abusch, for two reasons. First, the reading Abusch attributes to (i) is not logically independent from the reading that all agree on, the wide-scope non-distributive reading that there is a set of two books by Miller such that whoever reviewed both, panned both. The alleged distributive reading entails the non-distributive reading, and can therefore be explained away as a &lsquo;special case&rsquo; (see <link rid="ss4">section 2.1</link> above, and <link rid="b15">Abusch 1994</link>: 88ff.). Second, Abusch appears to feel that a wide-scope distributive reading is also possible when we replace <i>two books</i> in (i) with the strong quantifier <i>most books</i> &ndash; if so, this cannot be an effect of specificity and her dialect must allow real island-insensitive QR. See also <link rid="b47">Winter (1997</link>: fn. 21) for discussion of Abusch&apos;s claim.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn21">
<number>21&ensp;</number>This example represents joint work with Yoad Winter: see <link rid="b47 b16">Winter (1997, 1998</link>). That specific indefinites distribute locally was assumed also in <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>: 217) (but not demonstrated).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn22">
<number>22&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b73">Verkuyl (1999</link>: ch. 6) does allow inverse wide scope for <i>three books</i> in (41), albeit grudgingly.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn23">
<number>23&ensp;</number>For recent discussion of branching quantification see <link rid="b74">Beghelli et al. (1997</link>), as well as references cited there.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn24">
<number>24&ensp;</number>Hence, the interpretation of <i>three books</i> given in (46a) is often described as the &lsquo;branching&rsquo; or &lsquo;independent&rsquo; reading. The similarity with the island-escaping non-distributive readings in (37&ndash;40) above, however, is often ignored, although it is hard to see how an account of specificity that explains the island-escaping examples could fail to explain the &lsquo;independent&rsquo; reading (46a) as well. See also <link rid="ss16">section 7</link>.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn25">
<number>25&ensp;</number>This describes the approach advocated in <link rid="b20">Ruys (1992</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn26">
<number>26&ensp;</number>See <link rid="ss14">section 5</link> for further discussion, and comparison of possible solutions.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn27">
<number>27&ensp;</number>And if ACD resolution is due to Case-movement in general, that still would not necessarily exclude the possibility that in certain instances ACD can be resolved through QR. This might explain why we find a contrast between QNPs and referential NPs in contexts without Case-movement such as (i):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu75" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu75_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Mary stood near Susan, who Emily did &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> e&rsqb; as well.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Mary stood near everyone Emily did &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> e&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn28">
<number>28&ensp;</number>Actually, this is not quite true, since the structure really contains <i>four</i> scoped elements if we count the modal <i>has to</i>. Wide scope relative to this expression does not entail the narrow-scope reading. But taking advantage of this would again involve very subtle judgments.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn29">
<number>29&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b36">Kamp and Reyle&apos;s (1993</link>) &lsquo;abstraction&rsquo;.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn30">
<number>30&ensp;</number>Other types of intervening scope takers are disallowed as well. Thus, (ia) only has a <i>de re</i> reading for <i>a dog</i>. As in (56d), we need to repeat the modal to obtain a <i>de dicto</i> reading, as (ib) illustrates; see also <link rid="b75">Roberts (1987</link>):</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;<object id="tu76" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu76_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Every farmer who was looking for a dog found it.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Every farmer who was looking for a dog wanted it to be really big.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn31">
<number>31&ensp;</number>Fox suggests that the problem, if it exists, might be overcome by resorting to <link rid="b46">Kratzer&apos;s (1998</link>) CF account without existential closure, to be discussed in <link rid="ss16">section 7</link> below; but to the extent that Kratzer allows apparent intermediate-scope readings as an effect of functional readings on indefinites, she would also allow the intermediate reading (65a).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn32">
<number>32&ensp;</number>CF must then be of a higher type than stated in definition (60); we shall not discuss such technical details; the reader is referred to the publications by Reinhart and Winter cited above.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn33">
<number>33&ensp;</number>See Von <link rid="b51">Heusinger (1999</link>) for a dynamic choice function approach to indefinites.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn34">
<number>34&ensp;</number>Yet another hypothesis might be that specific indefinites carry existence presuppositions; this naturally fits, e.g., the referential approach to specific indefinites advocated by <link rid="b1">Fodor and Sag (1982</link>). We will not consider this option here; see <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>: 388ff.) for some discussion. Reinhart also considers a way of using partial choice functions in a three-valued logic that emulates the Existential Hypothesis; see also <link rid="b46">Kratzer (1998</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn35">
<number>35&ensp;</number>An additional complication attends Reinhart&apos;s discussion of (76a). Strictly, she makes the same prediction as the Existential Hypothesis: that (76a) has a false reading next to its true readings. In view of (45b), she assumes that indefinites may undergo QR. If <i>two American kings</i> in (76a) QRs across the negation, the CF analysis renders the sentence false. Thus, in order to explain her observation that it is difficult to judge (76a) false, she must attribute it either to a pragmatic preference for true readings, thereby vindicating the Existential Hypothesis, or to a dispreference for QR in this context, to be explained. A similar problem attends <link rid="b16">Winter (1998</link>: ch. 3, (128a)).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn36">
<number>36&ensp;</number>Many &lsquo;specificity markers&rsquo; discussed in the literature (e.g., overt Accusative Case in Turkish; see <link rid="b76">En&ccedil; 1991</link>) are either unrelated or only tangentially related to the &lsquo;specificity&rsquo; phenomenon under discussion here.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn37">
<number>37&ensp;</number>This is not precisely the definition given in <link rid="b47">Winter (1997</link>), which mistakenly lifts the embedded predicate (<b>snore&prime;</b>) out of the intensional context as well; the corrected version (78c) is due to Yoad Winter (p.c.).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn38">
<number>38&ensp;</number>Furthermore, the context (81) is a scope island for <i>tot</i> &lsquo;every&rsquo;, so this wide-scope reading should be the only reading on the CF Hypothesis. I am grateful to Josep Quer for help in constructing these examples.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn39">
<number>39&ensp;</number>See the references cited above, and <link rid="b77">Ruys (1999</link>), for further discussion.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn40">
<number>40&ensp;</number>See <link rid="b78">Abbott&apos;s (1995</link>) excellent review of <link rid="b76">En&ccedil; (1991</link>) for an illustration.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn41">
<number>41&ensp;</number>For instance, there is a considerable body of literature (much of it in the typological tradition, but also in the generative framework) on &lsquo;specificity markers&rsquo; in various languages: Persian <i>r&acirc;</i> is a famous example (see, e.g., <link rid="b79">Browne 1970</link>; <link rid="b80 b81">Karimi 1990, 1999</link>). Unfortunately, most of this work bears little relevance to our present concerns, for the reasons stated in the text. A recent exception is <link rid="b82">Matthewson&apos;s (1999</link>) description of St&rsquo;&aacute;t&rsquo;imcets: some indefinite determiners in this language force (island-escaping, non-distributive) wide scope; another indefinite determiner prevents it.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn42">
<number>42&ensp;</number>See also <link rid="b83">Ruys (2001</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn43">
<number>43&ensp;</number>For convenience, we will continue to call NPs with these determiners &lsquo;indefinites&rsquo;. See the references cited above, and also <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>), for discussion of other properties that set these determiners apart. Unfortunately, the generalization is not without exception; e.g., <i>exactly n</i> sometimes seems to allow a specific reading, as in <i>if exactly one relative of mine dies, I will inherit a house</i>.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn44">
<number>44&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b82">Matthewson (1999</link>), however, claims that in St&rsquo;&aacute;t&rsquo;imcets, certain indefinite determiners force a wide-scope reading, and allow an intermediate- (or narrow-)scope reading only when the NP contains a bound pronoun. Matthewson takes this as evidence that existential closure of CF in this language is always in the widest scope position, contra <link rid="b38">Reinhart (1997</link>) and <link rid="b47 b16">Winter (1997, 1998</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn45">
<number>45&ensp;</number>Reniers concludes from this and similar problems that the CF line must be abandoned.</span>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h18" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference id="b11" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Abbott</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Barbara</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Referentiality, Specificity, Strength, and Individual Concepts</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Twelfth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Erin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Duncan</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Donka</forenames><x> </x><surname>Farkas</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Philip</forenames><x> </x><surname>Spaelti</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">473</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">483</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b78" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Abbott</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Barbara</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Some Remarks on Specificity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>26</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">341</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">347</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Abusch</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dorit</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Scope of Indefinites</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">83</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">136</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bach</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Emmon</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1968">1968</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Nouns and Noun Phrases</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Universals in Linguistic Theory</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Emmon</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bach</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>Harms</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">90</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">112</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holt, Rinehart and Winston</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carl<x> </x>L<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1966">1966</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Definiteness and Indefiniteness in English. MA dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Illinois</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Beghelli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Filippo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Minimalist Approach to Quantifier Scope</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 23</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Amy<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schafer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">65</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">80</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Beghelli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Filippo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Phrase Structure of Quantifier Scope. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>UCLA</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b61" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Beghelli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Filippo</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Tim</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stowell</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Distributivity and Negation: The Syntax of <i>Each</i> and <i>Every</i>
</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Ways of Scope Taking</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolcsi</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">71</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">107</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b74" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Beghelli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Filippo</forenames>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Dorit</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ben-Shalom</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolsci</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Variation, Distributivity and the Illusion of Branching</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Ways of Scope Taking</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolsci</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">29</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">69</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b79" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Browne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>W.</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date><x>). </x><title type="document">More on Definiteness Markers: Interrogatives in Persian</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">359</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">363</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b45" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chierchia</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gennaro</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Dynamics of Meaning</title><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b50" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Minimalist Program</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b68" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cooper</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1979">1979</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Variable Binding and Relative Clauses</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Semantics and Pragmatics for Natural Languages</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Franz</forenames><x> </x><surname>Guenthner</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Siegfried<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schmidt</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">131</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">169</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cooper</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Quantification and Syntactic Theory</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b63" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Corblin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Francis</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Les Ind&eacute;finis: Variables et Quantificateurs</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Langue Fran&ccedil;aise</title><x> </x><volume>116</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">8</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">32</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b64" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Danon</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gabi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Syntax of Determiners in Hebrew. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Tel Aviv University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Davies</surname><x>, </x><forenames>William</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Stanley</forenames><x> </x><surname>Dubinsky</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2003">2003</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Extraction from NPs</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>21</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">37</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b60" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Diesing</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Molly</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Indefinites</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b76" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>En&ccedil;</surname><x>, </x><forenames>M&uuml;rvet</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Semantics of Specificity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>22</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">25</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Farkas</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Donka</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Quantifier Scope and Syntactic Islands</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Papers from the Seventeenth Regional Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Roberta</forenames><x> </x><surname>Hendrick</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Carrie</forenames><x> </x><surname>Masek</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Mary<x> </x>F<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Miller</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">59</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">66</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Chicago Linguistic Society.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b53" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Farkas</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Donka</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Intensionality and Romance Subjunctive Relatives. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Pennsylvania State University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Farkas</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Donka</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Evaluation Indices and Scope</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Ways of Scope Taking</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolcsi</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">183</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">215</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fiengo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Indices and Identity</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fodor</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Janet<x> </x>Dean</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Linguistic Description of Opaque Contexts. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge, MIT</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fodor</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Janet<x> </x>Dean</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ivan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sag</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Referential and Quantificational Indefinites</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>5</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">355</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">398</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Condition C Effects in ACD</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">MIT Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>27</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">105</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">119</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Economy and Scope</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">283</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">341</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Economy and Semantic Interpretation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b69" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Gamut</surname><x>, </x><forenames>L<x>. </x>T<x>. </x>F<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Logic, Language, and Meaning. Vol. 2: Intensional Logic and Logical Grammar</title><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b55" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>G&auml;rtner</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hans-Martin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Are there V2 Relative Clauses in German?</title><x> </x><title type="journal">Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>/</x><issue>2</issue><x>: </x><page type="first">97</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">141</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heim</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Irene</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Semantics of Definite and Indefinite Noun Phrases. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Amherst, University of Massachusetts</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heim</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Irene</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">E-Type Pronouns and Donkey Anaphora</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>13</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">137</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">177</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heringer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>James<x> </x>T<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1969">1969</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Indefinite Noun Phrases and Referential Opacity</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Papers from the Fifth Regional Meeting of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Alice</forenames><x> </x><surname>Davison</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Georgia</forenames><x> </x><surname>Green</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jerry</forenames><x> </x><surname>Morgan</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</namegroup><x>), </x><page type="first">89</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">97</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Chicago Linguistic Society.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b51" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heusinger</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Klaus<x> </x>von</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Reference of Indefinites</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Reference and Anaphoric Relations</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Klaus</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>von</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Heusinger</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Urs</forenames><x> </x><surname>Egli</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">247</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">265</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b65" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hintikka</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jaakko</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Semantics of <i>A Certain</i>
</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">331</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">336</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hirschb&uuml;hler</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">VP Deletion and Across-the-Board Quantifier Scope</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 12</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>Pustejovski</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sells</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">132</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">139</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b59" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hoop</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Helen<x> </x>de</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Case Configuration and Noun Phrase Interpretation. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Groningen University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ioup</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Georgette</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1975">1975b</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Treatment of Quantifier Scope in a Transformational Grammar. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>CUNY</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jackendoff</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ray</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1972">1972</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Semantic Interpretation in Generative Grammar</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b48" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kamp</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hans</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Theory of Truth and Semantic Representation</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Methods in the Study of Language</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jeroen</forenames><x> </x><surname>Groenendijk</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Theo</forenames><x> </x><surname>Janssen</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Martin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stokhof</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">277</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">322</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mathematisch Centrum.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kamp</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hans</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Uwe</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reyle</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="book">From Discourse to Logic</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b80" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Karimi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Simin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Obliqueness, Specificity and Discourse Functions: R&acirc; in Persian</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Analysis</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">139</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">191</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b81" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Karimi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Simin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Specificity Effect: Evidence from Persian</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>16</volume><x>/</x><issue>2</issue><x>: </x><page type="first">125</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">141</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Karttunen</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Lauri</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1968">1968</date><x>). </x><title type="document">What Do Referential Indices Refer To?</title><x> </x><miscellaneoustext>Unpublished manuscript, distributed by Indiana University Linguistics Club</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Karttunen</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Lauri</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1971">1971a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Discourse Referents</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Notes from the Linguistic Underground</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>McCawley</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">363</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">385</page><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b70" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Keenan</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edward</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Semantics of Determiners</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Handbook of Contemporary Semantic Theory</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Shalom</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lappin</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">41</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">63</page><x>. </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Blackwell.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kennedy</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Christopher</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Antecedent-Contained Deletion and the Syntax of Quantification</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>28</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">662</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">688</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b56" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kerstens</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Johan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1975">1975</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Over Afgeleide Structuur en de Interpretatie van Zinnen. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Amsterdam</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>King</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jeffrey<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Are Indefinite Descriptions Ambiguous?</title><x> </x><title type="journal">Philosophical Studies</title><x> </x><volume>53</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">417</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">440</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b52" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Klein</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Philip<x> </x>W<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Observations on the Semantics of Mood in Spanish. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Washington</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b46" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kratzer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Angelika</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Scope or Pseudoscope? Are there Wide-Scope Indefinites?</title>
<miscellaneoustext> In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Events and Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rothstein</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">163</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">196</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kripke</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Saul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1979">1979</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Speaker&apos;s Reference and Semantic Reference</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Contemporary Perspectives in the Philosophy of Language</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>French</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Theodore<x> </x>E<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Uehling</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Howard</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wettstein</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">6</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">27</page><x>. </x><address>Minneapolis</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Minnesota Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b71" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Landman</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Fred</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Plurality</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Handbook of Contemporary Semantic Theory</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Shalom</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lappin</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</namegroup><x> </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Blackwell.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lappin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Shalom</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Syntactic Basis of Ellipsis Resolution</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Stuttgart Ellipsis Workshop</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Stephen</forenames><x> </x><surname>Berman</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Arild</forenames><x> </x><surname>Hestvik</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.). </x><address>Stuttgart</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Stuttgart.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lappin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Shalom</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Ellipsis Resolution at S-Structure</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 23</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Amy<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schafer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">255</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">269</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Link</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Godehard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Logical Analysis of Plurals and Mass Terms: A Lattice-Theoretical Approach</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Meaning, Use, and Interpretation of Language</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Rainer</forenames><x> </x><surname>B&auml;uerle</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Christoph</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schwarze</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Arnim</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>von</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Stechow</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">302</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">323</page><x>. </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Liu</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Feng-Hsi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Scope Dependency in English and Chinese. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>UCLA</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b44" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ludlow</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Peter</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Stephen</forenames><x> </x><surname>Neale</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Indefinite Descriptions: In Defense of Russell</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">171</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">202</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b82" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Matthewson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Lisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Interpretation of Wide-Scope Indefinites</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">79</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">134</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>May</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Grammar of Quantification. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge</address><x>, </x><publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>May</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Logical Form: Its Structure and Derivation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b67" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Milsark</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gary</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Existential Sentences in English. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Partee</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Barbara<x> </x>H<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Mats</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rooth</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Generalized Conjunction and Type Ambiguity</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Meaning, Use and Interpretation of Language</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Rainer</forenames><x> </x><surname>B&auml;uerle</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Christoph</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schwarze</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Arnim</forenames><x> </x><surnameprefix>von</surnameprefix><x> </x><surname>Stechow</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">361</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">383</page><x>. </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b54" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Quer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Josep</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Mood at the Interface</title><x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Holland Academic Graphics.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Quine</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Willard<x> </x>V<x>. </x>O<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1956">1956</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Quantifiers and Propositional Attitudes</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>53</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">177</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">187</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b49" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">
<i>Wh-</i>in-Situ: An Apparent Paradox</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Eighth Amsterdam Colloquium</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Paul</forenames><x> </x><surname>Dekker</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Martin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Stokhof</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">483</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">492</page><x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>Institute for Logic, Language and Information</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Quantifier Scope: How Labour is Divided between QR and Choice Functions</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">335</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">397</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b66" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reniers</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Fabien</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). How to (S)cope with Indefinites. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Utrecht University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b57" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reuland</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Eric</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Indefinite Subjects</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 18</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>Blevins</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Julie</forenames><x> </x><surname>Carter</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">375</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">394</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b75" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Roberts</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Craige</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Modal Subordination, Anaphora and Distributivity. PhD dissertation, Amherst</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>University of Massachusetts</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b17" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ross</surname><x>, </x><forenames>John<x> </x>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Infinite Syntax!</title><x> </x><address>Norwood, NJ</address><x>: </x><publisher>Ablex.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b58" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rullmann</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hotze</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Indefinite Subjects in Dutch. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Amherst, University of Massachusetts</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruys</surname><x>, </x><forenames>E<x>. </x>G<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). The Scope of Indefinites. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Utrecht University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b72" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruys</surname><x>, </x><forenames>E<x>. </x>G<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). WCO as a Scope Phenomenon. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Utrecht University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruys</surname><x>, </x><forenames>E<x>. </x>G<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Quantifier Raising and Move-F</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">OTS Yearbook 1997</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Don</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Ted</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sanders</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">83</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">104</page><x>. </x><address>Utrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>OTS.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b77" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruys</surname><x>, </x><forenames>E<x>. </x>G<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Choice Functions and Existence</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>Paper presented at the Workshop on Weird Quantification</publisher><x>, </x><address>Utrecht University</address>
<x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>June 7</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b83" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruys</surname><x>, </x><forenames>E<x>. </x>G<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2001">2001</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Dutch Scrambling and the Strong&ndash;Weak Distinction</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>4</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">39</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">67</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sag</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ivan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1980">1980</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Deletion and Logical Form<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Garland.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b62" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Szabolsci</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anna</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Strategies for Scope Taking</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Ways of Scope Taking</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Szabolcsi</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">109</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">154</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Verkuyl</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Aspectual Asymmetry and Quantification</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Temporalsemantik: Beitr&auml;ge zur Linguistik der Zeitreferenz</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Veronika</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ehrich</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Heinz</forenames><x> </x><surname>Vater</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">220</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">259</page><x>. </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Max Niemeyer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b73" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Verkuyl</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Aspectual Issues: Studies on Time and Quantity</title><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Williams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edwin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Discourse and Logical Form</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>8</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">101</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">140</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b47" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Winter</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Yoad</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Choice Functions and the Scopal Semantics of Indefinites</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">399</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">467</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Winter</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Yoad</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Flexible Boolean Semantics: Coordination, Plurality and Scope in Natural Language. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Utrecht University</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
