<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="56"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 56 - The SE-Anaphor and its Role in Argument Realization.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">118</page>
<page type="last">179</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="3"/>
<count type="table" count="119"/>
<count type="formula" count="0"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="89"/>
<count type="page" count="62"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20050811"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 56&ensp;Dobrovie-Sorin: The SE-Anaphor</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 56&ensp;Dobrovie-Sorin: The SE-Anaphor</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">56 The SE-Anaphor and its Role in Argument Realization</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>CARMEN</forenames><x> </x><surname>DOBROVIE-SORIN</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>
<p>Introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>Types of SE</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Accusative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Inherent and inchoative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Middle and passive SE</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.1.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Reflexive-reciprocal SE</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Reflexive SE-verbs are not transitives</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Reflexive SE-verbs are not unaccusatives</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Reflexive SE and the Agent theta-role</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.3.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Reflexive SE-verbs are unergatives</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.1.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Unifying characterizations of accusative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Lexical accounts</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>2.1.4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>SE as an anaphor</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Dative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Nominative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.4&ensp;</number>
<p>When SE combines with unergatives</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>The passivization of unergatives</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Does SE combine with unaccusatives?</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.4.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Cross-linguistic variation: the passivization of unergatives and impersonal constructions</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>SE-verbs and the representation of Agentivity</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Suspension of the external theta-role: suppression or absorption?</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Control</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Passive SE absorbs the external theta-role in the lexicon</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Middle-passive SE absorbs the external theta-role in the syntax, via a chain with the Spec, IP position</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.5&ensp;</number>
<p>Middle-passive SE forms a chain with an A-position other than Spec, IP</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.6&ensp;</number>
<p>SE absorbs the external theta-role and dative Case</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.7&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusions</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>The distribution of SE in non-finite Italian clauses</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>
<link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) analysis: two types of nominative SE in Italian</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>SE with unergatives vs. SE with adjectives, analytic passives, or psych verbs</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>A passivizing nominative SE</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Theoretical problems with the &plusmn;arg(ument) distinction</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Empirical problems</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.1.4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Verbal agreement</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.1.4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The distribution of accusative clitics</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.1.4.3&ensp;</number>
<p><i>L&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i>, floating of <i>tutti</i>
</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.1.4.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Control</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>
<link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin&apos;s (1998</link>) analysis</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Nominative clitics and agreement features</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Middle-passive SE in control infinitivals</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.2.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Case</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.2.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>A semantic constraint on control</p>
</li>
<li level="4">
<number>4.2.2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Passive SE unergatives and the argument status of PRO</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>The interpretation of SE-verbs and the position of their subject</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.1&ensp;</number>
<p>French: the choice between the middle and the passive readings depends on the S-structure position of the overt argument</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.2&ensp;</number>
<p>European Portuguese</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>
<link rid="b3">Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s (1996</link>) generalization</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Middle SE</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.3&ensp;</number>
<p>A unifying analysis of European Portuguese and French</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s explanation</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>An alternative line of inquiry</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1&ensp;Introduction</heading>
<p>All Romance languages have a reflexive-reciprocal clitic (<i>se</i> in French, Spanish, and Romanian, and <i>si</i> in Italian, referred to as SE henceforth). In most Romance languages, Goal/Benefactive reflexives are formally indistinguishable from Theme/Patient reflexives. In Romanian, however, Goal/Benefactive reflexive clitics are overtly marked for dative Case (<i>&icirc;&#x015F;i</i><sub>Dat</sub> vs. <i>se</i><sub>Accus</sub>). Certain Romance languages &ndash; for example, Italian, Spanish, and Portuguese (but not French or Romanian) &ndash; also have a nominative/subject SE (best translated as &lsquo;one&rsquo; in English and &lsquo;on&rsquo; in French).</p>
<p>The terms &lsquo;accusative, dative, and nominative&rsquo; SE may seem somewhat surprising insofar as these three elements show no overt morphological distinctions (with the exception of Romanian dative SE). This terminology is nevertheless justified by the possibility of analyzing the three types of SE as differing with respect to abstract Case. Assuming that a given abstract Case can be assigned to only one element (or chain) inside the same syntactic domain, it is possible to infer the abstract Case of SE on the basis of the Cases of the other DPs with which SE co-occurs: thus, accusative SE may co-exist with nominative or dative DPs, but not with accusative DPs; nominative SE may co-exist with accusative DPs; etc. The abstract Case distinctions correlate with functional distinctions only partially: nominative SE can indeed be analyzed as an arbitrary subject clitic, but accusative SE cannot be said to be an object clitic, because (i) reflexives built with accusative SE do not behave as transitives (see <link rid="ss8">section 2.1.3.1</link>) and (ii) accusative SEs other than reflexives (inherent, inchoative, passive, or middle SE) cannot even be assumed to correspond to (suppressed) arguments. Finally, theta-role distinctions are also only partially helpful: we can indeed distinguish between accusative and dative reflexive-reciprocals in terms of theta-roles (Theme/Patient vs. Goal/Benefactive), but theta-roles are irrelevant for distinguishing between accusative and dative inherent SE-verbs.</p>
<p>Dative and nominative SE will occupy only very few pages of this chapter (see <link rid="ss15 ss16">sections 2.2 and 2.3</link>, respectively). Starting with <link rid="ss21">section 3</link>, we will focus on accusative SE, and more particularly on its middle and passive readings. How many accusative SEs are there? What is the common feature or structure that underlies its various readings (reflexive, passive, middle, inchoative, inherent)? Is it possible to propose a unifying analysis or should we postulate several homophonous types of accusative SE?</p>
<p>There are many phenomena regarding <i>se/si</i> in Romance that will be left aside: (i) the intricate detail of the placement of SE in French and Italian causatives and Italian restructuring environments; (ii) the various semantic constraints on the features of the implicit Agent in passive SE configurations; and (iii) long-distance bound reflexives in Italian.<link rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss3" level="1">
<heading id="h2" level="1">2&ensp;Types of SE</heading>
<p>The overview below is meant to illustrate the main contexts in which accusative, dative, and nominative SE can each be found.</p>
<subsection id="ss4" level="2">
<heading id="h3" level="2">2.1&ensp;Accusative SE</heading>
<p>According to some GB theorists of the 1980s, reflexive, middle, and passive SE are intrinsically distinct elements (<link rid="b4">Belletti 1982</link>; <link rid="b5">Grimshaw 1982</link>; <link rid="b6">Zubizarreta 1987</link>; <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>; among many others).<link rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup></link> This view cannot explain why these elements systematically exhibit the same morphological form across Romance languages.<link rid="fn3">
<sup>3</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Partial unification of the various readings of accusative SE goes back to <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>): inchoative, inherent, middle, and passive SEs are alike insofar as they can all be analyzed as markers of unaccusativity,<link rid="fn4">
<sup>4</sup></link> understood as a lexical operation that triggers the suspension of the external theta-role and of accusative Case.</p>
<p>Interesting evidence due to <link rid="b8">Kayne (1975</link>), <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>), and <link rid="b9">Pesetsky (1995</link>) suggests that the unaccusative analysis can be extended to reflexive SE. This hypothesis has been convincingly criticized by <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>), who argue instead that reflexive SE-verbs behave as unergatives.</p>
<subsection id="ss5" level="3">
<heading id="h4" level="3">2.1.1&ensp;Inherent and inchoative SE</heading>
<p>Inherent and inchoative SE-verbs are two subclasses of unaccusatives (overt Theme, no explicit or implicit Agent), which differ from each other by the absence vs. presence of transitive alternates: inchoatives have transitive alternates, whereas &lsquo;inherent SE-verbs&rsquo; do not; they are of necessity accompanied by SE, and are registered as such in the Lexicon:</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="3">a.</entry>
<entry><b>Inherent:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Marie s&rsquo;est &eacute;vanouie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE has fainted.<link rid="fn5">
<sup>5</sup></link>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary fainted.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry><b>Inchoative:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>La branche<sub>i</sub> s<sub>i</sub>&rsquo;est cass&eacute;e e<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the branch SE has broken</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The branch broke.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Building on earlier insights by <link rid="b11">Zribi-Hertz (1987</link>), <link rid="b12">Labelle (1992</link>) has established that French inchoatives built with SE (e.g., <i>s&rsquo;agrandir</i> &lsquo;to get bigger, to enlarge&rsquo;) behave as unaccusatives, whereas those inchoatives that cannot be constructed with SE (e.g., <i>cuire</i> &lsquo;to cook&rsquo;) qualify as unergatives. The distinction was clearly established on the basis of tests such as auxiliary selection, <i>il</i>-impersonals and <i>en</i>-extraction, embedded infinitival relatives, tough-constructions, adjectival passives, and participial constructions.</p>
<p>The question now arises as to what determines &ndash; for a given change-of-state verb &ndash; the choice between functioning as an unaccusative (in which case it is marked with SE) or as an unergative (in which case SE is precluded). Following <link rid="b13">Rothemberg (1974</link>), <link rid="b14">Bernard (1971</link>), <link rid="b15">Burston (1979</link>), and <link rid="b16">Forest (1988</link>), the answer proposed by Labelle is that the unergative form is used with predicates that express internally driven, autonomous natural processes<link rid="fn6">
<sup>6</sup></link> (<i>vieillir</i>, <i>maigrir</i>, <i>grandir</i>, <i>grossir</i>, <i>rougir</i>, <i>s&eacute;cher</i>, <i>p&acirc;lir</i>, <i>fondre</i>, <i>cuire</i>, <i>durcir</i>, <i>&eacute;clater</i> &lsquo;to grow old, thin, tall, fat, to go red in the face, to dry, to pale, to melt, to cook, to harden, to burst&rsquo;). The processes described by these verbs may be brought about by external causes expressed by complements introduced by <i>de</i>, but such causes only constitute the initial force that induces an internally caused process. Even if such external causes are mentioned, these verbs do not allow SE: <i>(*se) rougir de honte</i>, <i>(*se) fondre sous l&rsquo;effet de la chaleur</i> &lsquo;(*se) go red with shame, (*se) melt with the heat&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Many inchoative verbs &ndash; more precisely, those that may refer to natural processes as unfolding in an autonomous way (although not internally caused) &ndash; allow both constructions, with notable aspectual differences: <i>casser/se casser</i> &lsquo;break&rsquo;, <i>raffra&icirc;chir/se raffra&icirc;chir</i> &lsquo;cool off&rsquo;, <i>durcir/se durcir</i> &lsquo;harden&rsquo;. In the SE-construction, the object undergoing the change of state is projected to the object position, and consequently it is used as an event-measure in the sense of <link rid="b17">Tenny (1987</link>). Correlatively, SE-inchoatives focus on the final state of the entity undergoing the change, rather than on the unfolding of the process itself.<link rid="fn7">
<sup>7</sup></link> This characterization of the difference between unergative and unaccusative inchoatives constitutes a refinement of <link rid="b11">Zribi-Hertz&apos;s (1987</link>) claim that reflexive inchoatives are perfective or resultative. This generalization has been questioned by <link rid="b18">Lagae (1990</link>), who argues that the focus on the final state that indeed characterizes SE-inchoatives is not to be analyzed as perfectivity, although it does explain certain restrictions on the choice of tense or the incompatibility with certain aspectual markers, e.g., <i>mettre le vin &agrave; raffra&icirc;chir/*se raffra&icirc;chir</i> &lsquo;let the wine cool&rsquo;.</p>
<p>SE is obligatorily used whenever an external cause is implied. It is particularly striking that verbs built with causative prefixes such as <i>a</i>- or <i>en</i>-, or causative suffixes like -<i>ifier</i>- or -<i>iser</i>, require SE: <i>s&rsquo;all&eacute;ger</i> &lsquo;become lighter&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;agrandir</i> &lsquo;to grow bigger&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;ass&eacute;cher</i> &lsquo;to dry out&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;amaigrir</i> &lsquo;to become thinner&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;ab&ecirc;tir</i> &lsquo;become stupid&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;allourdir</i> &lsquo;to become heavier&rsquo;, <i>se diversifier</i> &lsquo;to diversify&rsquo;, <i>s&rsquo;humidifier</i> &lsquo;to become humid&rsquo;.</p>
<p>There exist some verbs which, although they are not morphologically complex, require SE in order to take the inchoative reading. According to Labelle, such verbs are to be classified as &ldquo;conceptually transitive,&rdquo; i.e., as requiring both their arguments to be projected, unless the external argument is absorbed by SE. A case in point is provided by the pair <i>briser/casser</i> &lsquo;break&rsquo;, which are near-synonyms, but differ regarding the use of SE: in the absence of SE, <i>casser</i> can be used both as a transitive and as an inchoative, whereas <i>briser</i> is of necessity transitive; its inchoative use requires SE. The existence of pairs of verbs such as <i>briser/casser</i> indicates that the choice between the unaccusative and unergative status may sometimes be idiosyncratic, unmotivated. This leads us to expect that the choice between SE-marking and unmarked forms for semantically close verbs may differ from one Romance language to another. Although detailed analyses exist for most Romance languages (see in particular <link rid="b19 b20">Folli 2002a, 2002b</link> and <link rid="b21">Masullo 1999</link> for Italian and Spanish, respectively), there is no comparative study of this domain of the grammar.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss6" level="3">
<heading id="h5" level="3">2.1.2&ensp;Middle and passive SE</heading>
<p>Middle SE and passive SE are alike regarding thematic structure (the overt DP is a Theme, and the Agent is either implicit or realized as an Adjunct <i>by</i>-phrase), but differ insofar as middles are interpreted generically, as ascribing a property to the subject DP, whereas passives refer to (particular or habitual) events:</p>
<p>(2)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="3">a.</entry>
<entry><b>Middle:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Le grec<sub>i</sub> se<sub>i</sub> traduit e<sub>i</sub> facilement.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the Greek SE translates easily</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Greek translates easily.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry><b>Eventive passive:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Il<sub>j</sub> s<sub>i</sub>&rsquo;est traduit trois romans<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE has translated three novels</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Three novels were translated.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">c.</entry>
<entry><b>Habitual passive:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Les pommes se mangent en hiver.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>apples SE eat during winter</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Apples are eaten during winter.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Much of the literature devoted to SE has focused on various issues relating to the analysis of middle and passive SE: (i) the syntactic representation of the implicit Agent; (ii) the distribution of middle and passive SE in Italian non-finite clauses; and (iii) the correlation between the position of the subject and the reading of SE-verbs. <link rid="ss21 ss29 ss45">Sections 3, 4, and 5</link> below are devoted to these issues respectively.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss7" level="3">
<heading id="h6" level="3">2.1.3&ensp;Reflexive-reciprocal SE</heading>
<p>(3a&ndash;b) illustrate the reflexive and reciprocal uses of SE-verbs:</p>
<p>(3)&ensp;<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Jean<sub>i</sub> se<sub>i</sub> lave e<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE washes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John washes himself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Jean et Marie se disputent souvent.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John and Mary SE quarrel frequently</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Insofar as they alternate with object clitics, reflexive and reciprocal SEs seem to have pronominal status; hence <link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1975</link>) rule of SE-placement, which leaves behind a trace of SE in an A-position. Kayne clearly showed, however, that SE-placement differs from Cl(itic)-placement (the rule that moves pronominal clitics from an A-position to a clitic position; see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 13 - Clitic Climbing.xml" type="file">chapter 13</externallink></related>) in crucial ways. Further evidence going in the same direction led <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 42) to the conclusion that reflexive SE is ambiguous between an object clitic and a marker of unaccusativity (&ldquo;affix&lsqb;es&rsqb; with no other syntactic function than marking the lack of theta-role assignment to the subject position&rdquo;).<link rid="fn8">
<sup>8</sup></link> The same view was adopted in <link rid="b22">Bouchard (1984</link>), <link rid="b23">Marantz (1984</link>), <link rid="b24">Grimshaw (1990</link>), and <link rid="b9">Pesetsky (1995</link>), but <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>) have convincingly argued against analyzing reflexive SE-verbs as unaccusatives and have proposed instead that they behave as unergatives.</p>
<subsection id="ss8" level="4">
<heading id="h7" level="4">2.1.3.1&ensp;Reflexive SE-verbs are not transitives</heading>
<p>The empirical evidence reviewed in this subsection was invoked by <link rid="b25">Burzio (1981</link>) and subsequently by most GB theorists in favor of the unaccusative analysis. On closer scrutiny, however, these are not arguments in favor of the putative unaccusative behavior of reflexive verbs. What the facts really show is that reflexive SE-verbs do not pattern with transitives, which means that reflexive SE is not an object clitic.</p>
<p>Clear evidence against the pronominal status of SE is provided by French causatives. Pronominal clitics cannot attach to a verb embedded under causative <i>faire</i>, whereas this position is accessible to SE:</p>
<p>(4)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*La crainte du scandale l&rsquo;a fait <i>la</i> tuer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the fear of scandal him-has made her kill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The fear of scandal made him kill her.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>La crainte du scandale l&rsquo;a fait <i>se</i> tuer.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the fear of scandal him-has made SE kill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The fear of scandal made him kill himself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Consider next the paradigm in (5a&ndash;f). According to a clear empirical generalization, the underlying subject of an infinitival clause embedded under a causative <i>faire</i> must be preceded by the preposition <i>&agrave;</i> in case a direct object is present, but lacks <i>&agrave;</i> with intransitive verbs (see (5a&ndash;c)). The example in (5d) shows that pronominal clitics behave on a par with object DPs (see (5c)), whereas the grammaticality of (5e), without <i>&agrave;</i>, and the ungrammaticality of (5f), where <i>&agrave;</i> is present, indicate that SE does not function as a direct object:</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Jean a fait manger Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John has made eat Mary</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John let Mary eat.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Jean a fait manger <b>&agrave;</b> Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c</entry>
<entry>Jean a fait manger la soupe <b>&agrave;</b> Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John has made eat the soup to Mary</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John let Mary eat the soup.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>Jean l<sub>i</sub>&rsquo;a fait manger e<sub>i</sub> <b>&agrave;</b> Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John it-has made eat to Mary</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John let it eat to Mary.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">e.</entry>
<entry>La crainte du scandale a fait <i>se</i> tuer la m&egrave;re du juge.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The fear of scandal has made SE kill the mother of the judge.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The fear of scandal made the mother of the judge kill herself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">f.</entry>
<entry>*La crainte du scandale a fait <i>se</i> tuer <b>&agrave;</b> la m&egrave;re du juge.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The fear of scandal has made SE kill <b>to</b>-the mother of the judge.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The two tests just discussed for French cannot be used in other Romance languages such as Romanian or Italian: Romanian does not have counterparts of <i>faire</i>-causatives, and in Italian, <i>fare</i>-causatives block the cliticization of SE on the embedded infinitival (<link rid="b7">Burzio 1986</link>):</p>
<p>(6)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Questo far&agrave; &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> pentirsi Giovanni&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>This will make John repentSI</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Maria ha fatto &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> accusarsi Piero&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary has made accuseSE Peter</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary has made Peter accuse himself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 410) attempts to correlate the contrast between Italian and French with the difference between free subject inversion and <i>il</i>-impersonals, but the issue remains open.<link rid="fn9">
<sup>9</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss9" level="4">
<heading id="h8" level="4">2.1.3.2&ensp;Reflexive SE-verbs are not unaccusatives</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b7">Burzio&apos;s (1986</link>) data reviewed above show that SE-reflexives do not behave as transitive verbs accompanied by object clitics. Although the data are compatible with both the unergative and the unaccusative analysis, Burzio favored the unaccusative hypothesis: reflexive SE would be an unaccusative marker that suspends the subject theta-role: SE-affixation to a transitive verb, e.g., <i>accuse</i>, would be a morphological process that gives rise to a corresponding verb, &lsquo;self-accuse&rsquo;, which is an unaccusative verb (1986: 415). <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>) argued conclusively against the unaccusative analysis of SE-reflexives. Under their view, SE-reflexives are unergatives.</p>
<p>Arguing in favor of the unaccusative analysis of reflexives, <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) observed that the object of transitives and the subject of unaccusatives (cf. <i>arrivare</i> as well as SE-marked unaccusatives) can be relativized via small-clause relativization, in contrast with the subject of unergatives and transitives:</p>
<p>(7)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>uno studente &lsqb;scPRO<sub>i</sub> invitato t<sub>i</sub> alla festa&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a student (who was) invited to the party</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>uno studente &lsqb;PRO<sub>i</sub> arrivato t<sub>i</sub> ieri sera&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a student (who had) arrived yesterday evening</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>L&rsquo;auto capovoltasi nell&rsquo;incidente era la Ferrari.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The car (which had) rolled over in the accident was the Ferrari.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>Un pilota accortosi dell&rsquo;incidente diede l&rsquo;allarme.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A driver (who had) become aware of the accident gave the warning.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(8)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*uno studente &lsqb;PRO telefonato ieri sera&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a student (who had) telephoned yesterday evening</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Un individuo accusatolo di aver assassinato il presidente fu creduto pazzo.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A guy (who had) accused him of having assassinated the president was thought (to be) crazy.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*un individuo accusato se stesso di aver assassinato il presidente</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a guy (who had) accused himself of having assassinated the president</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>SE<i>-</i>reflexives behave on a par with unaccusatives:</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;Un individuo accusatosi di aver assassinato il presidente fu creduto pazzo. A man (who had) accused himself of having assassinated the president was believed crazy.</p>
<p>Reinhart and Siloni observed, however, that not all reflexives are allowed to occur in Italian reduced relatives:</p>
<p>(10)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*L&rsquo;uomo lavatosi ieri &egrave; mio nonno.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>The man washed-SE yesterday is my grandfather.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Burzio himself brought up empirical evidence going against his own proposal; in particular, SE-reciprocals cannot appear in reduced relatives:</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;?Due amici incontratisi allo stadio non si vedevano d&rsquo;anni.</p>
<p>A second argument in favor of the unaccusativity of SE-reflexives is based on auxiliary selection: they select the auxiliary <i>be</i>, in contrast with both transitives and unergatives, which select <i>have</i>:</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Jean s&rsquo;est puni.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE-has punished</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Jean s&rsquo;est lav&eacute; le visage.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE-has washed his face</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>Il s&rsquo;est mang&eacute; 300 kg de viande.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>there SE-has eaten 300 kg of meat</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Reinhart and Siloni observe that auxiliary selection is not a decisive argument in favor of unaccusativity, since <i>be</i> is selected by transitive verbs taking a dative SE:<link rid="fn10">
<sup>10</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Marie s&rsquo;est envoy&eacute; une carte du Maroc.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE-has sent a postcard from Morocco</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Further evidence against the unaccusativity of SE-reflexives is related to the distribution of <i>en</i>. Thus, although reflexives (marginally) allow their subject DP to occupy the postverbal position (presumably the direct object position) in French <i>il</i>-impersonals, <i>en</i>-extraction is blocked by SE-reflexives, in contradistinction to SE-unaccusatives and SE-passives, which behave on a par with unmarked unaccusatives and copula passives:</p>
<p>(14)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Il s&rsquo;en est cass&eacute; beaucoup dans ce lave-vaisselle. (unaccusative)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>there SE of them has broken many in this dish-washer</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Il s&rsquo;en est lav&eacute; beaucoup dans ces douches publiques r&eacute;cemment. (OK passive; *refl.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>there SE of them has washed many in these public showers recently</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>?*Se ne sono incontratisi due.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE of them have met two.&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;(<link rid="b7">Burzio 1986</link>: 424) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Note that quite independent of the distribution of <i>en</i>, the context of <i>il-</i>impersonals does not constitute clear evidence in favor of the unaccusative analysis of SE-reflexives. As shown in (15a), <i>il</i>-impersonals are productive and perfectly grammatical with unaccusatives (be they marked with SE or unmarked) and with periphrastic as well as SE-marked passives (<link rid="b25 b7">Burzio 1981, 1986</link>; <link rid="b26 b27">Pollock 1981, 1983</link>), but examples of the type in (15b), built with SE-reflexives, are quite hard to find:</p>
<p>(15)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">Il s&rsquo;est mang&eacute; 20 kg de viande en deux jours. (passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">it SE ate 20 kg of meat in two days</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">?Il s&rsquo;est d&eacute;nonc&eacute; trois mille hommes ce mois-ci. (reflexive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE denounced 3,000 people this month</entry>
<entry>(<link rid="b8">Kayne 1975</link>: 381) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss10" level="4">
<heading id="h9" level="4">2.1.3.3&ensp;Reflexive SE and the Agent theta-role</heading>
<p>Under later implementations of the unaccusative analysis of reflexives, reflexive SE was assumed to absorb the external theta-role (see <link rid="b23">Marantz 1984</link>; <link rid="b28">Kayne 1988</link>; <link rid="b29">Gu&eacute;ron 1991</link>; <link rid="b9">Pesetsky 1995</link>; <link rid="b30">Sportiche 1998</link>), on a par with passive SE. In <link rid="ss21">section 3</link> below, we will show that the hypothesis that accusative SE absorbs the external theta-role is problematic for passive SE. Those problems transfer to reflexive SE.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="4">
<heading id="h10" level="4">2.1.3.4&ensp;Reflexive SE-verbs are unergatives</heading>
<p>We have so far reviewed the evidence against two possible analyses of SE-reflexives: they are neither transitives nor unaccusatives. <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>) propose instead that SE-reflexives are unergatives, obtained from their transitive alternates by an operation that identifies the two arguments of a two-place relation. In certain languages, e.g., Hebrew, this identification takes place in the lexicon, in which case it amounts to a lexical reduction operation that reduces a two-place relation to a property (<link rid="b31">Chierchia 1989</link>; <link rid="b32">Reinhart 1997</link>). In Romance languages, on the other hand, reflexivization relies on an identification operation that takes place at LF. Whereas lexical reduction is restricted to apply to co-arguments, LF-identification may apply to arguments of two distinct predicates, as in ECM constructions:</p>
<p>(16)&ensp;<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Jean se consid&egrave;re &lsqb;e intelligent&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE considers intelligent</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John considers himself (to be) intelligent.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Hebrew counterparts of this kind of example are ungrammatical, because Hebrew reflexivization can only resort to lexical reduction.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="3">
<heading id="h11" level="3">2.1.4&ensp;Unifying characterizations of accusative SE</heading>
<p>Beyond important differences, non-reflexive accusative SE-verbs (inherent SE-verbs, inchoatives, middles, and passives) can all be argued to be unaccusatives<link rid="fn11">
<sup>11</sup></link> insofar as the external role is suspended (i.e., not realized in the syntax), and the internal role is realized as a subject (in particular, it is assigned nominative Case).<link rid="fn12">
<sup>12</sup></link>
</p>
<p>In the preceding section we have concluded, following <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>), that the unaccusative analysis of SE-reflexives should be discarded. And yet a unifying analysis of reflexive and non-reflexive accusative SE-verbs is desirable, due to very clear cross-linguistic generalizations: (i) Romance languages all have both reflexive and non-reflexive accusative SE; and (ii) many languages other than Romance have a non-active voice that is used both for reflexives and for inchoatives and middle-passives.</p>
<subsection id="ss13" level="4">
<heading id="h12" level="4">2.1.4.1&ensp;Lexical accounts</heading>
<p>It is widely agreed that accusative SE does not function as an object clitic, but rather as a morphological marker that affects argument structure at the level of the lexicon. This general characterization is compatible with quite different lexical rules, e.g., Inchoativization, Reflexivization, or Middle Formation (<link rid="b5">Grimshaw 1982</link>). According to <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>), the SE-morphology appears when some derivational operation has taken place, be it reduction, saturation, or reflexivization (identification).<link rid="fn13">
<sup>13</sup></link>
</p>
<p>One may wonder why operations as distinct as lexical reduction (which itself comes in two flavors: reduction of the external or of the internal role, corresponding respectively to unaccusatives and reflexives), LF-identification, or saturation (postulated in the analysis of passives and middles by <link rid="b31">Chierchia 1989</link> and <link rid="b32">Reinhart 1997</link>) should be marked by one and the same morphological marker, SE.</p>
<p>Similar questions arise for other lexicalist analyses, in particular for <link rid="b33">Wehrli&apos;s (1986</link>) view that the unifying characteristic of SE is that it absorbs an argument. According to this author, the various instantiations of SE are obtained by combining two parameters: (i) which argument is absorbed; and (ii) whether the absorption operation is lexicalized or not:</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Inherent SE:</entry>
<entry>absorption of the internal argument; lexicalized</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Unaccusative SE:</entry>
<entry>absorption of the external argument; lexicalized</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Reflexive SE:</entry>
<entry>absorption of the internal argument; non-lexicalized</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Middle SE:</entry>
<entry>absorption of the external argument; non-lexicalized</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But why should one and the same element absorb either one of the two arguments, despite the fact that it is uniformly marked with accusative Case?</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss14" level="4">
<heading id="h13" level="4">2.1.4.2&ensp;SE as an anaphor</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b, 1998</link>) argues that the GB notion of anaphor (defined as an element that is subject to Principle A of Binding Theory) provides a unified characterization of the various types of accusative SE. According to a restricted theory of binding, only elements that occupy A-positions are subject to binding conditions. Under such a theory, binding conditions do not apply to clitics, but only to their traces. In particular, the anaphoric feature of SE, which is registered in the lexicon, is transferred to a designated A-position. A sentence containing SE will thus of necessity rely on the indexing configuration given in (18), where NP<sub>i</sub> and e<sub>i</sub> occupy respectively the subject and the object positions. The &lsquo;complete&rsquo; version of the representation in (18) is (18&prime;):</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;NP<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub>
</p>
<p>(18&prime;)&ensp;NP<sub>i</sub> SE<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub>
</p>
<p>The absence of SE in (18) is only meant to indicate that the S-structure position of SE is irrelevant for Binding Theory, although, of course, the position of SE is crucial for phenomena having to do with cliticization; e.g., clitic climbing in <i>faire</i>-causatives or restructuring environments, etc.</p>
<p>The assignment of indices in (18&ndash;18&prime;) characterizes reflexive as well as unaccusative uses of SE, which differ regarding thematic structure, as shown in (19a&ndash;b), or the fully developed representations in (19&prime;a&ndash;b):</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>(NP<sub>i</sub>) (e<sub>i</sub>)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>(NP<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub>) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(19&prime;)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>(NP<sub>i</sub>) (SE<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub>)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>(NP<sub>i</sub> SE<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub>) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The representation in (19b) differs from that in (19a) insofar as the two co-indexed argument positions belong to the same theta-chain. The two-chain configuration given in (19a) underlies SE-reflexives, which are characterized by an identification relation between the internal and the external arguments,<link rid="fn14">
<sup>14</sup></link> whereas the representation in (19b) underlies the non-reflexive uses of accusative SE-verbs (inherent, inchoative, middle, and passive SE-verbs),<link rid="fn15">
<sup>15</sup></link> which qualify as unaccusatives.<link rid="fn16">
<sup>16</sup></link>
</p>
<p>In sum, the possibility of similar and yet distinct syntactic configurations is the result of the modularity of GB theory. The common property of SE-constructions pertains to binding theory (SE is lexically marked as an anaphor, and as such it forces the binding/co-indexation relation that characterizes both (19a) and (19b)),<link rid="fn17">
<sup>17</sup></link> whereas their dissimilarities pertain to theta-theory: one and the same binding relation may form one or two theta-chains, depending on the lexical properties of the predicates.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b35">Postma (1995a</link>) shares with <link rid="b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b, 1998</link>) the hypothesis that the unifying property of all uses of accusative SE is its being an anaphor, but proposes a different analysis. Postma assumes that the Agent role is projected in the syntax and that the various readings of SE arise as a consequence of the way in which the theta-chain corresponding to the Agent role is identified with the Theme-chain (for further details of Postma&apos;s proposal see <link rid="ss26">section 3.5</link>. below). In <link rid="ss21">section 3</link> it will be argued that the Agent is not projected in the syntax of SE-verbs (other than reflexives), and in <link rid="ss45">section 5</link> it will be shown that agentive or non-agentive interpretations depend on the syntactic position in which the internal argument is realized.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss15" level="2">
<heading id="h14" level="2">2.2&ensp;Dative SE<link rid="fn18">
<roman><sup>18</sup>
</roman></link>
</heading>
<p>In most Romance languages, dative SE is homophonous with accusative SE (cf. French, Italian, Spanish, Portuguese):</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Marie se fait des robes.</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE makes dresses</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary makes dresses for herself.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Jean s&rsquo;est envoy&eacute; des cartes postales.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>John SE HAS sent postcards</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In Romanian, reflexive clitics show an overt case distinction: <i>se</i> for accusatives and <i>&icirc;</i>&#x015F;<i>i</i> for datives. The Romanian counterparts of the French examples in (20) are given in (21):</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Maria &icirc;&#x015F;i face rochii.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE<sub>Dat</sub> makes dresses</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Ion &#x015F;i-a trimis c&#x01CE;r tcedil i po&#x015F;tale. (<i>&#x015F;i</i> is the phonologically weak form of <i>&icirc;&#x015F;i</i>)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE<sub>Dat</sub>-has sent postcards</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b8">Kayne (1975</link>) observed that in French, dative SE cannot be bound by a derived subject, i.e., a subject that is the head of an NP-chain resulting from NP-movement (cf. passives and subject-raising configurations). <link rid="b36">Rizzi (1986b</link>) showed that the generalization also holds in Italian ((22) for &minus; passives, (23&ndash;24) for &minus; subject raising):</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Gianni<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> &egrave; stato affidato e<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SI HAS been entrusted</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John to-himself was entrusted.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*I nostri amici<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sono stati presentati e<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>our friends SI HAVE been introduced</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Our friends to-each-other were introduced.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(23)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Gianni<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sembra &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> non fare il suo dovere&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SI seems not (to) do his duty</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John to-himself seems not to do his duty.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Le due candidati<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> risultavano &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> poter vincere&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the two candidates SI appeared (to) be able (to) win</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The two candidates to-each-other appeared to be able to win.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(24)&ensp;<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Gianni<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sembra &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> intelligente&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SI seems intelligent</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John to-himself seems intelligent.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Loro<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> risultano &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> in regola con le tasse&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(they) SI appear in good order with taxes</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;They to-each-other appear in good order with the taxes.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Non-clitic anaphors such as <i>se stesso</i> or <i>l&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i> are not subject to this constraint:</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Gianni<sub>i</sub> &egrave; stato affidato a <b>se stessi<sub>i</sub>
</b>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>John HAS been entrusted to himself</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I nostri amicii sono stati presentati l&rsquo;uno all&rsquo;altro<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
</entry>
<entry>our friends HAVE been introduced to each other</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The restriction observed with passives and raising verbs also holds in adjectival constructions, as shown in the (b) examples below. The (a) examples, which contain the corresponding non-clitic anaphors, are grammatical:</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Gianni<sub>i</sub> &egrave; &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> affezionato a se stesso<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John is affectionate to himself</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Gianni<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> &egrave; &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> affezionato&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SI is affectionate</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Loro<sub>i</sub> sono simili &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> l&rsquo;uno all&rsquo;altro&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>they are similar to each other</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Loro<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sono &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> simili&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>they SI are similar</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(28)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Loro<sub>i</sub> sono &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> odiosi I&rsquo;uno all&rsquo;altro<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>they are hateful to each other</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Loro<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sono &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub> odiosi&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>they SI are hateful</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The observed parallelism between A-chain configurations (passives and subject raising) and adjectival constructions is expected under the GB analysis of adjectives, going back to <link rid="b37 b38">Couquaux (1979, 1981</link>): the copula verb <i>be</i> is assumed to take a small-clause complement headed by the adjective; the subject position of <i>be</i>, which is empty at D-structure (because <i>be</i> assigns no theta-role) is targeted by the NP-movement of the subject of the small clause.</p>
<p>Verbs that are semantically close to the adjectives in (26&ndash;28) do not trigger ungrammaticality, presumably because in this case the subject is not the head of an A-chain but instead is base-generated in its S-structure position:</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Loro<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> assomigliano e<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(they) SI resemble</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;They resemble each other.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Loro<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> fanno e<sub>i</sub> pena/tenerezza/simpatia.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(they) SI make pain/tenderness/liking</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;They make pain/tenderness/liking to-each-other.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b8">Kayne&apos;s (1975</link>) account of the phenomenon relied on an extrinsic ordering of the rules of passivization and reflexive cliticization: the former applies before the latter, and the observed ungrammaticality obtains because reflexivization requires SE to be co-indexed with a subject, a requirement that cannot be satisfied: the prior application of passivization has suspended the external theta-role, and the object-to-subject NP-movement has not yet applied.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b7">Burzio&apos;s (1986</link>: 397&ndash;399) explanation builds on the same idea, but differs in the technical implementation. The ungrammaticality of dative SE with derived subjects would be due to the fact that the co-indexation relation between SE and a subject in Spec, IP, which defines SE, cannot be satisfied at D-structure in the relevant configurations: within the model of grammar assumed by Burzio, passives and raising verbs are generated with an empty Spec, IP position.</p>
<p>Rizzi (1986) rejected Burzio&apos;s account on the grounds that it stipulates an idiosyncratic property of SE, that of requiring a co-indexation with a subject at all levels of representation (in particular at D-structure), and he proposed instead an explanation relying on a Chain Condition: the chain in (30), representing a dative SE bound by a subject heading an A-chain, is ill-formed because the NP-trace (resulting from the NP-movement of the subject) is unduly locally bound by SE:</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;*NP<sub>i</sub> SE<sub>i</sub> t<sub>NPi</sub>
</p>
<p>This solution raises both empirical and theoretical problems. Note first that configurations of the type in (30) are grammatical in English, where the intervening binder is a strong dative reflexive pronoun:</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Mary<sub>i</sub> seems &lsqb;to herself<sub>i</sub>&rsqb; t<sub>i</sub> to have done her duty.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>John<sub>i</sub> appeared &lsqb;to himself<sub>i</sub>&rsqb; t<sub>i</sub> to be capable of doing the job. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Within Rizzi&apos;s proposal one could account for the grammaticality of (31) by assuming that the reflexive pronoun, because it is embedded inside a PP, does not C-command the NP-trace, and thus does not count as a disturbing intervening binder. <link rid="b9">Pesetsky (1995</link>: 105) observes that C-command must be postulated in exactly the same configuration in order to account for Principle C violations:</p>
<p>(32)&ensp;*Mary<sub>j</sub> seems &lsqb;to him<sub>i</sub>&rsqb; t<sub>j</sub> to like John<sub>i</sub>.</p>
<p>A comparable problem is raised by Romanian, a language in which the dative clitic <i>&icirc;</i>&#x015F;<i>i</i> can be bound by derived subjects:<link rid="fn19">
<sup>19</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(33)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ion &#x015F;i Maria &#x015F;i-au fost prezenta tcedil i anul trecut.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John and Mary SE<sub>dat</sub>-have been presented year-the last</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John and Mary were presented to each other last year.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Ion &icirc;&#x015F;i e recunosc&#x01CE;tor numai lui.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE<sub>dat</sub> is grateful only to him(self)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Ion &#x015F;i Maria &#x015F;i-au devenit pur &#x015F;i simplu insuportabili.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John and Mary SE<sub>dat</sub>-have become purely and simply unbearable (to each other)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John and Mary have become purely and simply unbearable to each other.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Romanian clearly differs from French and Italian insofar as dative and accusative reflexive clitics are overtly distinguished by morphological Case: <i>&icirc;&#x015F;i</i> and <i>se</i> respectively. Given Rizzi&apos;s account, one would have to say that morphological Case-marking blocks C-command. This proposal faces the problem noted above for English, regarding Principle C violations:</p>
<p>(34)&ensp;<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Maria &icirc;i<sub>j</sub> para a-l<sub>j</sub> place pe Ion<sub>j</sub>.<link rid="fn20">
<sup>20</sup></link>
</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Mary<sub>i</sub> to-him<sub>j</sub> seems to &lsqb;e<sub>i</sub>&rsqb; him<sub>j</sub> like John<sub>j</sub>. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It should be noted that although Rizzi&apos;s (1986) Chain Condition has the flavor of <link rid="b39">Rizzi&apos;s (1990b</link>) Relativized Minimality Constraint, <link rid="b39">Rizzi (1990b</link>) does not attempt to restate it. The reason might be that the Chain Condition cannot be restated in terms of relativized minimality: SE is an A&prime;-antecedent, and as such it should not disturb the relation between an NP-trace and its antecedent, because the latter sits in an A-position.</p>
<p>Following a suggestion by Kayne, <link rid="b9">Pesetsky (1995</link>: 103&ndash;105) proposes an explanation based on a Marantz&ndash;Kayne type of analysis for SE (see <link rid="ss27">section 3.6</link>): SE would necessarily be an external argument, regardless of whether it gives rise to reflexive, passive, or middle interpretations, and regardless of its Case: nominative, accusative, and dative SEs all need to absorb the external theta-role. The ungrammaticality shown in (22&ndash;24) and (26b), (27b), and (28b) would then be due to the fact that there is no external theta-role available for absorption by SE, since passives, raising verbs, and <i>be</i> do not assign an external theta-role. This solution does not explain why a dative SE that bears <i>morphological</i> dative Case, as in Romanian, does not need to absorb the external theta-role.</p>
<p>The problems faced by Rizzi (1986) and later proposals do not arise within Burzio&apos;s account, the only defect of which seems to be that it stipulates that the co-indexation relation required by SE (by virtue of its being an anaphor) should hold at all levels of representation, in particular at D-structure. This proposal is also confronted by a theory-internal problem, due to the evolution of the generative model: in the various versions of Minimalism, the D-structure level of representation is eliminated. It seems possible to solve this problem, while at the same time giving a conceptual justification to Burzio&apos;s proposal, by slightly modifying it: the co-indexing requirement imposed by SE would hold in the lexicon rather than at D-structure. The reason why it should hold in this component of the grammar would simply be its lexical nature: on a par with accusative SE, dative SE would be a <i>lexical</i> affix (rather than a pronominal clitic; see <link rid="ss7">section 2.1.3</link>), which as such should satisfy its anaphoric feature in the lexicon itself. This requirement cannot be satisfied if we assume that passives, adjectives, and raising verbs do not have external arguments in the lexicon. Because strong pronominal anaphors such as <i>l&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i> or <i>se stessi</i> are pronominal anaphors rather than lexical affixes, they do not function as anaphors in the lexicon, but only in the syntax: hence, they can be bound by derived subjects, i.e., elements that fill the (Spec, IP) position at S-structure. Similarly, we may explain the Romanian data by assuming that reflexives that are overtly marked for dative Case function as pronominal clitics rather than lexical affixes, and therefore the binding conditions are to be satisfied in the syntax rather than in the lexicon.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="2">
<heading id="h15" level="2">2.3&ensp;Nominative SE</heading>
<p>Only certain pro-drop Romance languages &ndash; in particular Italian, Spanish, and Portuguese &ndash; have a nominative/subject SE:</p>
<p>(35)&ensp;<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Non si<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> &egrave; mai contenti.</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not SI is ever satisfied</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One is never satisfied.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Spesso si<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> &egrave; traditi dai falsi amici.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>frequently SI is betrayed by false friends</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One is frequently betrayed by false friends.&rsquo; (SI&plus;passive)</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>In questa universit&agrave; si<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> studia le materie letterarie.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in this university SI teaches the humanities</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>(Le materie letterarie) le si<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> studia in questa universit&agrave;.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(the humanities) them SI teaches in this university</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(The humanities) one teaches them in this university.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(35a&ndash;b) cannot involve an accusative SE because neither (the copula verb <i>be</i> &plus;) adjectives nor passives can assign accusative Case. In (35c), the verb does not agree with <i>le materie letterarie</i>; therefore this DP cannot be a postverbal subject, but must instead be analyzed as a direct object; since direct objects take accusative Case, SE itself cannot be accusative. In (35d), accusative Case is assigned to the object clitic <i>le</i>, and is thus unavailable for SE itself. The examples in (35a&ndash;d) are instead compatible with analyzing SE as an arbitrary subject clitic (marked with abstract nominative Case) comparable to arbitrary <i>on</i> &lsquo;one&rsquo; in French.</p>
<p>Romance scholars have frequently attempted to unify nominative and accusative SE (see, among others, <link rid="b40">Castelfranchi and Parisi 1976</link>; <link rid="b41">Manzini 1986b</link>; <link rid="b29">Gu&eacute;ron 1991</link>; Kayne (class lectures in the 1980s and 1990s)). According to <link rid="b41">Manzini (1986b</link>), what brings together all the occurrences of <i>si</i> is the fact that <i>si</i> is co-indexed with the subject NP. This suggested unification is, however, problematic, since the co-indexation convention notates here two distinct types of dependency relations. It is by virtue of being a subject clitic that nominative <i>si</i> is co-indexed with the subject position. Accusative <i>si</i>, on the other hand, is co-indexed with the subject not because it is a clitic, but rather because it is an anaphor. Since it notates two distinct types of dependency relations (a subject clitic chain and an A-chain, respectively), the co-indexation itself cannot be viewed as a common property of the two <i>si</i>s, which means that Manzini&apos;s unification attempt fails. According to Kayne (1986), the unifying property of all uses of SE is the fact that it absorbs the external role. As we will demonstrate in <link rid="ss21">section 3</link> below, the notion of &lsquo;absorption&rsquo; was used to refer to two irreconcilable operations:</p>
<listgroup id="l2" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>The external theta-role may be &lsquo;absorbed&rsquo; but nevertheless projected in the canonical syntactic position of subjects. This kind of absorption characterizes nominative clitics (and agreement morphemes in pro-drop languages), in particular nominative SE, but crucially not passivizing morphemes.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>The external theta-role may be &lsquo;suspended&rsquo;, i.e., not projected in the subject position; it remains present in argument-structure and may surface as an adjunct <i>by</i>-phrase. The suspension of the external role characterizes passivizing morphemes in general, and middle-passive SE in particular, but cannot be correct for nominative SE.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Note that a unified approach to accusative and nominative SEs would predict that these two types of SE necessarily co-occur cross-linguistically, but this prediction is incorrect. It is indeed clear that French does not have nominative SE. Moreover, <link rid="b42 b43 b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1987, 1994b, 1998</link>) has established that although it is a pro-drop language, Romanian lacks nominative SE.<link rid="fn21">
<sup>21</sup></link> Thus, the Romanian counterparts of the Italian examples in (35) are all ungrammatical:</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Nu <i>se</i> este niciodat&#x01CE; mul tcedil umit.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not SE is never satisfied</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One is never satisfied.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Adesea <i>se</i> este tr&#x01CE;dat de prieteni fal&#x015F;i.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>frequently SE is betrayed by false friends</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One is frequently betrayed by false friends.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*&Icirc;n aceast&#x01CE; universitate se pred&#x01CE; &#x015F;tiin tcedil ele umane.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in this university SE teaches the humanities</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*(Stiin tcedil ele umane) le se pred&#x01CE; &icirc;n aceast&#x01CE; universitate.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(the humanities) them SE teaches in this university</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The contrast between Spanish and Romanian illustrated in (37&ndash;38) constitutes further evidence in favor of the lack of nominative SE in Romanian. Since Spanish SE may be nominative, it may co-occur with a prepositional accusative. Since Romanian SE is of necessity accusative, it blocks the occurrence of a prepositional accusative:</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>En esta escuela se castiga a los alumnos.</entry>
<entry>Spanish</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">in this school SE punishes <i>a</i> the students</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;In this school they punish the students.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*&Icirc;n &#x015F;coala asta se pedepse&#x015F;te pe elevi.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">in this school SE punishes <i>PE</i> students</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;In this school they punish the students.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given that all Romance languages have accusative SE, but only some of them have nominative SE, we may assume, in line with <link rid="b4">Belletti (1982</link>), <link rid="b25 b7">Burzio (1981, 1986</link>), <link rid="b44">Zribi-Hertz (1982</link>), <link rid="b45">Hyams (1986</link>), <link rid="b6">Zubizarreta (1987</link>), and <link rid="b42 b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1994b, 1998</link>), that these two SEs are homophonous, but clearly distinct linguistic entities as different from each other as <i>man</i> &lsquo;one&rsquo; and <i>sich</i> in German or <i>on</i> &lsquo;one&rsquo; and <i>se</i> in French.</p>
<p>Although some empirical intricacies related to the distribution of SE in Italian infinitivals made <link rid="b7">Burzio (1982, 1986</link>) wrongly believe that middle-passive SE is a particular type of nominative SE (see sections 3.4 and 4 below), Burzio proposed clearly different analyses for accusative and nominative SE, which can still be maintained modulo technical restatements due to the evolution of the GB model itself. <link rid="b7">Burzio&apos;s (1986</link>) characterization of the distinction is stated in terms of the level at which SE is inserted: (the core cases of) accusative SEs are analyzed as lexical affixes marking unaccusativity, which absorb/suspend the external theta-role at the level of the lexicon and are base-generated directly in their S-structure position (this is true for simple predicates; in complex predicates, e.g., causatives and restructuring environments, one must allow for clitic climbing). Nominative SE, on the other hand, behaves as a pronominal clitic: it is subject to clitic movement, and functions as an argument, being assigned a theta-role via a clitic chain.</p>
<p>The homonymical treatment of nominative and accusative SEs is confronted with some potential problems: auxiliary selection, relative order with respect to object clitics, and negation seem to treat the two SEs alike. Although these problems have not yet received a satisfactory solution, they do not seem to affect the view that nominative SE and accusative middle-passive SE should be treated as homonyms rather than as instantiations of the same element. This does not mean that the homonymy itself is completely accidental. It is, indeed, known that nominative SE developed via a diachronic reanalysis from accusative SE. According to <link rid="b46">Naro (1976</link>), constructions of the type SE V NP, involving passive SE, came to be reanalyzed as an S-V-O sequence, with SE taken as a subject pronoun. This reanalysis took place in Italian, Spanish, and Portuguese, but not in French or Romanian. In sum, the existence vs. the absence of nominative SE is a parameter according to which Romance languages that have middle-passive SE vary: Italian, Spanish, and Portuguese have both nominative and accusative SE, whereas Romanian and French have only accusative SE. This variation is expected under the homonymical analysis of nominative and accusative SE, since the existence of particular pairs of homonyms is language-specific.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss17" level="2">
<heading id="h16" level="2">2.4&ensp;When SE combines with unergatives</heading>
<p>Italian (and Spanish or Portuguese) constructions of the type <i>si dorme</i> &lsquo;SE sleeps&rsquo;, in which SE combines with unergatives, rely on nominative SE, but their Romanian counterparts cannot be assigned this analysis, because Romanian does not have nominative SE (see <link rid="ss16">section 2.3</link> above):</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;<object id="tu35" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu35_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>si canta/si dorme .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;/si mangia</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">SE sings/SE sleeps/ .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;SE eats</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;one sings/one sleeps/ .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;one eats&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;<object id="tu36" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu36_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry><i>se</i> c&icirc;nt&#x01CE;/<i>se</i> doarme/<i>se</i> munce&#x015F;te/<i>se</i> m&#x01CE;n&icirc;nc&#x01CE;</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">SE sings/SE sleeps/SE works/SE eats</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to <link rid="b42 b34">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1994b</link>), examples such as (40) rely on a passivizing accusative SE, comparable to impersonal middle <i>sich</i> in German:<link rid="fn22">
<sup>22</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;<object id="tu37" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu37_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Es lebt sich angenehm hier.</entry>
<entry>German</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">it lives SICH in a pleasant way here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;Life is pleasant here.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<subsection id="ss18" level="3">
<heading id="h17" level="3">2.4.1&ensp;The passivization of unergatives</heading>
<p>The passive phenomenon is currently described as involving the suspension of the external theta-role and of accusative Case; correlatively, the internal argument is NP-moved from the object to the subject position (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 2 - Adjectival Passives.xml" type="file">chapter 2</externallink></related>). Because unergatives are currently viewed as being unable to subcategorize a direct object, <link rid="b23">Marantz (1984</link>), <link rid="b47">Baker (1988a</link>), and <link rid="b48">Sobin (1985</link>), among many others, were led to modify and parameterize the analysis of passivization. The core property of passives was relaxed, merely requiring the suspension of the external role (the precise technical stipulation differs from one author to the other, and is of no interest here). This analysis of impersonal passives, described as the spontaneous demotion of the Agent by <link rid="b49">Perlmutter (1978</link>), has become general across grammatical models. This kind of analysis stipulates two distinct rules of passivization: one for transitives and another one for unergatives. Moreover, no real understanding of the cross-linguistic variation shown by the passivization of unergatives was achieved: the impossibility of passivizing unergatives in certain languages is assumed to be due to the parameterization of either passive morphemes or unergatives, but no independent evidence can be adduced in favor of either one of these parameters.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b42 b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1994b, 1998</link>) proposed a different line of inquiry, based on the hypothesis that the passivization of unergatives relies on exactly the same rule as the passivization of transitives.<link rid="fn23">
<sup>23</sup></link> Under this view, the structure underlying the example in (42c), where <i>se</i> combines with an unergative, is exactly the same as that underlying (42a) and (42b), constructed with a transitive. This analysis relies on the hypothesis that unergatives may project a null cognate object:<link rid="fn24">
<sup>24</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(42)&ensp;<object id="tu38" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu38_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>S<sub>i</sub>-au m&icirc;ncat pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> ieri.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE<sub>i</sub>-HAVE-3<smallcapitals>rd plur</smallcapitals> eaten pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> yesterday</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;They were eaten yesterday.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry>S<sub>i</sub>-a m&icirc;ncat pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> bine ieri.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE<sub>i</sub>-HAS-3<smallcapitals>rd sing</smallcapitals> eaten pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> well here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it was eaten well yesterday</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;We/they ate well yesterday.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">c.</entry>
<entry>Se<sub>i</sub> doarme pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> bine aici.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE<sub>i</sub> sleeps-3<smallcapitals>rd sing</smallcapitals> pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> well here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it is slept well here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One sleeps well here.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to Dobrovie-Sorin&apos;s analysis, these examples rely on chains of the form <i>(pro</i>, <i>e)</i>, made up of a null subject (its exact position is not directly relevant here: one may assume either (Spec, VP) or (Spec, IP)) and of an empty category that occupies the direct object position; this chain is marked with the Theme role, assigned in the object position.<link rid="fn25">
<sup>25</sup></link> The only difference between (42a, b, and c) concerns the interpretation of this chain (referential, protoypical, and cognate objects respectively), which depends on the selectional properties of the verb.</p>
<p>This analysis of middle-passive unergatives seems to be facilitated by <link rid="b50">Hale and Keyser&apos;s (1993a</link>) hypothesis that unergatives are universally transitive in their lexical relational structure; that is, they are to be represented as being derived by the incorporation of cognate objects into light verbs. Note, however, that this view on the lexical representation of unergatives does not oblige us, and perhaps does not even authorize us, to assume that the traces of the incorporated cognate objects are projected in the syntax. According to <link rid="b42 b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1994b, 1998</link>), the presence of null cognate objects in the syntactic representation of passive unergatives is not induced by the lexical properties of unergatives (unergatives merely <i>allow</i> the presence of a direct object), but rather by the properties of <i>passive</i> configurations, and in particular by the properties of middle-passive SE. Note that this proposal does not entail that null prototypical and cognate objects are projected in the S-structure representation of <i>active</i> unergatives or intransitively used transitives.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="3">
<heading id="h18" level="3">2.4.2&ensp;Does SE combine with unaccusatives?</heading>
<p>According to a well-known generalization, unaccusative verbs cannot passivize.<link rid="fn26">
<sup>26</sup></link> Given this generalization, we expect examples such as (43) to be ungrammatical in Italian:</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;<object id="tu39" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu39_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Ritengo non essersi arrivati in sufficiente anticipo.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) believe not to HAVE-SE arrived sufficiently ahead of time</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Non essendosi morti in giovane et&agrave;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not HAVING-SE died young</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*Sembra essersi arrivati troppo tardi.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) seems to HAVE-SI arrived too late</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These examples are ungrammatical because SE can be neither nominative (because nominative SE is ruled out in Italian non-finite clauses; see <link rid="ss29">section 4</link> below) nor a passivizing accusative SE (because unaccusatives cannot passivize).</p>
<p>Quite surprisingly, however, the Romanian examples in (44) are grammatical:</p>
<p>(44)&ensp;<object id="tu40" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu40_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ieri s-a ajuns la timp.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>yesterday SE-has arrived in time</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Yesterday people arrived on time.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>La noi, se moare des din cauza cancerului &#x015F;i a bolilor cardiace.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>here/in our country SE dies frequently because of cancer and of cardiac diseases</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Here/in our country people die frequently from cancer and from cardiac diseases.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Nu se moare din at&icirc;ta.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not SE dies of that much</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One does not die from so little.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>In sal&#x01CE; se amu tcedil este la apari tcedil ia examinatorului.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in the classroom SE goes quiet when the examiner appears</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Everyone goes quiet when the examiner shows up in the classroom.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">e.</entry>
<entry>Se &icirc;nt&icirc;rzie zilnic.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE arrives late every day</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;People arrive/are late every day.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">f.</entry>
<entry>Dup&#x01CE; medicamentele astea, sigur se va &icirc;nvia!</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>after (having taken) medicines-the these, for sure SE will resurrect</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;People will surely be restored to life after having taken these drugs.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">g.</entry>
<entry>La temperatura de &minus;20 grade, se deger&#x01CE;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>at the temperature of &minus;20 degrees, SE freezes</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given this type of data, one might be led to conclude, contra Dobrovie-Sorin, that Romanian does have a nominative SE. The solution suggested by <link rid="b43 b34">Dobrovie-Sorin (1987, 1994b</link>) herself is that in Romanian, the distinction between unergatives and unaccusatives is not grammatically encoded. Indeed, most of the current tests of unaccusativity cannot be used in Romanian: this language does not use <i>be</i> as a perfect auxiliary (all verbs are built with <i>have</i>), and it has no counterpart of the French clitic <i>en</i> (Italian <i>ne</i>).</p>
<p>One may, however, wonder whether there is any limitation on the use of passive SE with verbs that are semantically close to unaccusatives. And indeed, there exist at least two types of impossibilities (Pan&#x01CE;-Dindelegan, p.c.). On the one hand, passive SE cannot apply to inherent reflexives. Thus, verbs such as <i>a se aglomera</i>, <i>a se atrofia</i>, <i>a se bifurca</i>, <i>a se bronza</i>, <i>a se caria</i>, <i>a se cicatriza</i>, <i>a se &icirc;nnora</i>, <i>a se &icirc;nvechi</i>, <i>a se &icirc;neca</i> &lsquo;to get crowded, to atrophy, to bifurcate, to get tanned, to get a cavity, to scar, to get cloudy, to get old, to drown&rsquo; cannot be used with an impersonal passive SE. Given that inherent reflexives are unaccusatives, they behave exactly as predicted by the hypothesis that unaccusatives cannot passivize.</p>
<p>The second limitation concerns the type of subject selected by the verb: a one-argument verb can be used with an impersonal passive SE only if it is construed as involving a human argument. Thus, examples such as <i>Vasul acosteaz&#x01CE;</i> &lsquo;The ship is coming ashore&rsquo;, <i>Mi- a amor</i> tcedil <i>it piciorul</i> &lsquo;My leg went numb&rsquo;, <i>Soarele apune</i> &lsquo;The sun is going down&rsquo;, <i>Luna asfin</i> tcedil <i>e</i>&#x015F;<i>te</i> &lsquo;The moon is going down&rsquo;, <i>Pomii au &icirc;nfrunzit/&icirc;nmugurit/&icirc;nflorit</i> &lsquo;The trees grew leaves/budded/flowered&rsquo;, <i>Veniturile cresc/descresc</i> &lsquo;The income increases/decreases&rsquo; cannot give rise to impersonal forms. Some of these verbs may combine with impersonal SE, as shown in (45). But crucially, the implicit suspended argument can only be interpreted as human:</p>
<p>(45)&ensp;<object id="tu41" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu41_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Dup&#x01CE; v&icirc;rsta de 60 de ani, se apune &icirc;ncet-&icirc;ncet!</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>after the age of 60, SE goes down slowly-slowly</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;People slowly fade after reaching the age of 60!&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>S-a acostat departe de aici.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has come ashore far from here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The landing was far from here.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>S-a amor tcedil it.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has come numb</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;People got numb.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>Se cre&#x015F;te f&#x01CE;r&#x01CE; griji.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE grows up without worries</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One grows up carefree.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Although the constraint regarding the human feature of the implicit suspended argument of SE-passives is not well understood (see Mendikoetxea 1999), its existence supports the hypothesis that SE-passivization cannot apply to genuine unaccusatives: the human feature of the external argument makes it easier for a given verb to be construed as unergative, thus allowing for passivization.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss20" level="3">
<heading id="h19" level="3">2.4.3&ensp;Cross-linguistic variation: the passivization of unergatives and impersonal constructions</heading>
<p>French clearly differs from Romanian in not allowing passive SE to combine with unergatives:<link rid="fn27">
<sup>27</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(46)&ensp;<object id="tu42" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu42_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Il se proc&eacute;dera &agrave; une enqu&ecirc;te.</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL SE will proceed to an inquiry</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;An inquiry will be started.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Il s&rsquo;aboutira &agrave; un compromis acceptable.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL SE will arrive at/reach an acceptable compromise</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;An acceptable compromise will be reached.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Il s&rsquo;est tir&eacute; sur les manifestants.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL SE-HAS shot at the demonstrators</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The demonstrators were shot at.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>*Il se lui a &eacute;t&eacute; demand&eacute;/sugg&eacute;r&eacute; de partir.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL him/her<sub>Dat</sub> SE-has asked/ordered/suggested to leave</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;He/she was asked/ordered/suggested to leave.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) explains the ungrammaticality of (46) by parameterizing the types of SE, and by assuming that the SE that is allowed to combine with unergatives (analyzed as an impersonal passivizing &plus;arg nominative SE by Cinque) does not exist in French. This kind of account is not available for <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>), who argues against the existence of a nominative &plus;arg SE (see <link rid="ss30">section 4.1</link> below) and assumes that unergatives may combine with an accusative middle-passive SE. Since such an element exists in French, we would expect examples such as (46) to be grammatical.</p>
<p>One may choose to parameterize unergatives, as proposed by Jaeggli (1986):</p>
<p>(47)&ensp;In certain languages (see German), but not in others (see French), unergatives assign structural Case.</p>
<p>The first problem with (47) is that it parameterizes a property that is currently assumed to be universal, namely the possibility for unergatives to assign structural Case.</p>
<p>Note furthermore that the parameter in (47) cannot account for a very clear empirical generalization: languages that (do not) admit <i>se V</i><sub><i>unerg</i>
</sub> also (do not) admit <i>se V</i><sub><i>trans</i>
</sub> with a null prototypical object. Thus, the contrast between the Romanian examples in (42) and the French examples in (46) is parallelled by the contrast in (48a&ndash;b), where the verb is transitive in both languages:</p>
<p>(48)&ensp;<object id="tu43" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu43_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Se<sub>i</sub> m&#x01CE;n&icirc;nc&#x01CE; pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> prea mult aici.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE<sub>i</sub> eats pro<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> too much here</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One eats too much here.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Il<sub>i</sub> se<sub>j</sub> mange e<sub>j</sub> trop ici.</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it<sub>i</sub> SE<sub>j</sub> eats e<sub>j</sub> too much here</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Another problem raised by the parameterization of unergatives is that it cannot account for the fact that in one and the same language, French for example, unergatives may be used with copula passives, although they cannot be used with middle-passive <i>se</i>. Note indeed that the examples in (46) become grammatical if instead of the middle-passive <i>se</i> we use the copula passive:</p>
<p>(49)&ensp;<object id="tu44" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu44_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Il sera proc&eacute;d&eacute; &agrave; une enqu&ecirc;te.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL will be proceeded to an inquiry</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;An inquiry will be undertaken.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Il sera abouti &agrave; un compromis acceptable.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL will be arrived at a compromise acceptable</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;An acceptable compromise will be reached.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Il a &eacute;t&eacute; tir&eacute; sur les manifestants.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL has been shot at the demonstrators</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The demonstrators were shot at.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>Il lui a &eacute;t&eacute; demand&eacute;/ordonn&eacute;/sugg&eacute;r&eacute; de partir.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL him<sub>Dat</sub> has been asked/ordered/suggested to leave</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;He was asked/ordered/suggested to leave.&rsquo;<link rid="fn28">
<sup>28</sup></link>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>If we tried to analyze the ungrammaticality of (46) as being due to some property of French unergatives, we would incorrectly expect the examples in (49) to be equally ungrammatical.</p>
<p>We are led to conclude that the cross-linguistic variation regarding the possibility or the impossibility of passivizing unergatives cannot be due to parameters bearing on either passivizing morphemes or unergatives. A possible line of investigation is to relate the possibility of passivizing unergatives to the syntactic properties of <i>il</i>-impersonals, by taking into account the constraints that bear on copula passives and on SE passives, respectively. Thus, SE is legitimate only if a binding relation can be established, but this requirement cannot be satisfied in (48b): the trace of SE and the expletive subject are contra-indexed; if these two elements are co-indexed, <i>il</i> no longer counts as an expletive, but rather as a referential pronoun, which conflicts with the selectional properties of unergatives: they select cognate objects. In sum, a violation of Principle A arises in French <i>il</i>-impersonals whenever SE combines with unergatives. Romanian impersonals, on the other hand, rely on free subject inversion, the syntactic properties of which make it possible for Principle A to be satisfied: in (48a), the trace of SE is A-bound by the null subject <i>pro</i>. Turning finally to the French examples in (49), constructed with a copula passive, they do not contain any lexical anaphor, and consequently Principle A is irrelevant.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss21" level="1">
<heading id="h20" level="1">3&ensp;SE-verbs and the representation of Agentivity</heading>
<subsection id="ss22" level="2">
<heading id="h21" level="2">3.1&ensp;Suspension of the external theta-role: suppression or absorption?</heading>
<p>Descriptively speaking, passive configurations can be characterized as follows: the internal argument of the corresponding active verb surfaces as a subject (it is either realized in the canonical subject position or else is part of an expletive&ndash;argument chain), and this necessarily correlates with the fact that the Agent role is not realized in the subject position. In somewhat more theoretical terms, passive &lsquo;morphemes&rsquo; (cf. the -<i>en</i> suffix or passive SE) can be assumed to suspend the Agent role and correlatively block the assignment of accusative Case. For this generalization, as well as for many other issues brought up below (the realization of external arguments, the relations between lexicon and syntax), see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 2 - Adjectival Passives.xml" type="file">chapter 2</externallink></related>.</p>
<p>One way of understanding the suspension of the external theta-role is to identify it with its suppression. It is indeed clear that in the case of inchoatives, middles, or adjectival passives, the Agent role manifests no &lsquo;syntactic activity&rsquo; (see <link rid="ss23">section 3.2</link> below), although middles (unlike inchoatives and adjectival passives) arguably involve some kind of implicit agentivity.</p>
<p>Verbal passives in general, and passive SE configurations in particular, differ from inchoatives, adjectival passives, and middles in exhibiting agentivity: tests such as Agent-oriented adverbs or control into purpose clauses have been recurrently invoked in favor of the hypothesis that in passive configurations, the Agent is not suppressed but, quite on the contrary, syntactically realized (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 34 - Implicit Arguments.xml" type="file">chapter 34</externallink></related>).</p>
<p>What is, then, the syntactic position occupied by the Agent in passives? By the very definition of passives given above, a &lsquo;suspended&rsquo; Agent is <i>not</i> projected onto the subject position. One possibility is to assume that the Agent of passives is realized as an overt or covert <i>by</i>-phrase (<link rid="b51">Chomsky 1965</link>; <link rid="b52">Wasow 1977</link>; Jaeggli 1986; &Aring;farli 1989; <link rid="b53">Schoorlemmer 1995</link>). Other authors believe that implicit Agents are realized as pro or PRO (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 34 - Implicit Arguments.xml" type="file">chapter 34</externallink></related>). Still other theorists propose that it is the passive morpheme itself that constitutes the syntactic realization of the Agent role (this assumption was made for passive SE by <link rid="b4">Belletti 1982</link> and for the past participle morpheme -<i>en</i> by <link rid="b54">Baker et al. 1989</link>).</p>
<p>In what follows, we will first review the empirical evidence adduced in favor of the hypothesis that passive SE absorbs the external role (<link rid="ss23">section 3.2</link>). The various implementations of this widely assumed hypothesis<link rid="fn29">
<sup>29</sup></link> will then be discussed and rejected (sections 3.3&ndash;3.6). The concluding remarks (<link rid="ss28">section 3.7</link>) will establish an essentially negative result: in passive configurations, the Agent is not projected onto a subject(-like) position; nor can passive SE itself be assumed to function as an external argument; tests such as control into adjunct clauses or Agent-oriented adverbs do not prove the existence of a syntactically realized Agent (<link rid="b55">Williams 1985</link>).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss23" level="2">
<heading id="h22" level="2">3.2&ensp;Control</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b4">Belletti (1982</link>) proposed that the external theta-role is <i>absorbed</i> rather than merely <i>suspended</i> by passive SE. Belletti believed that this hypothesis could explain why, in contradistinction to analytic passives (<i>be</i> &plus; past participle), passive SE is incompatible with a <i>by</i>-phrase (e.g., <i>Ce po&egrave;me s&rsquo;est lu hier pendant la f&ecirc;te (*par Marie)</i> &lsquo;This poem SE HAS read yesterday during the party (*by Mary)&rsquo;): because the Agent theta-role is realized as SE, it cannot surface as a <i>by</i>-phrase. Belletti&apos;s hypothesis was extended to analytic passives by <link rid="b54">Baker et al. (1989</link>), who assume that the Agent role is absorbed by the passive morpheme -<i>en</i>. Under this view, the different distribution of <i>by-</i>phrases in passive SE configurations as opposed to analytic passives can no longer be explained.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b4">Belletti (1982</link>) assumed Agent-absorption by SE not only for passive but also for middle SE, which also implies some kind of agentivity (in clear contrast with, e.g., inchoative SE). This unifying hypothesis conflicts with a clear split between the two constructions: certain types of adjunct clauses can be controlled by the implicit Agent of (analytic or SE-marked) passives, but not by that of middles (the latter are identifiable by the property reading):</p>
<p>(50)&ensp;<object id="tu45" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu45_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Les livres ont &eacute;t&eacute; vendus pour aider les pauvres.</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The books were sold in order to help the poor.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Les livres se vendent facilement pour aider les pauvres.<link rid="fn30">
<sup>30</sup></link>
</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The books &lsqb;SE&rsqb; sell easily in order to help the poor.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;<object id="tu46" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu46_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Questi appartamenti si vendono volutamente occupati.</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">these apartments SI sell deliberately occupied</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">&lsquo;These apartments are deliberately sold occupied.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">Quell&rsquo;uomo politico si pu&ograve; corrompere (facilmente) per dimostrare la propria influenza.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">that politician SI can bribe (easily) to show one&apos;s influence</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">&lsquo;That politician can be bribed (easily) in order to show one&apos;s influence.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">Il museo del campo si pu&ograve; visitare facilmente anche nudi.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">the camping museum SI can visit even naked</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col2" nameend="col3">&lsquo;The camping museum can be visited even naked.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(52)&ensp;<object id="tu47" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu47_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Questi appartamenti hanno il vantaggio di vendersi (*volutamente) occupati.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>these apartments have the advantage of to sell-SI (*deliberately) occupied</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;These apartments have the advantage of being sold (*deliberately) occupied.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Quell&rsquo;uomo politico ha il vantaggio di potersi corrompere facilmente (*per dimostrare la propria influenza).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>that politician has the advantage of to bribe-SI easily (*to show one&apos;s influence)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>Il museo del campo ha il vantaggio di potersi visitare facilmente (*anche nudi).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the camping museum has the advantage of to be allowed-SI to visit easily (*even naked)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The possibility of control is currently invoked in favor of the hypothesis that the Agent of passives is projected in the syntax. The passive morpheme -<i>en</i>, as well as passivizing SE (in contrast with middle SE), would instantiate syntactically projected Agents (see Jaeggli 1986; <link rid="b54">Baker et al. 1989</link>; <link rid="b56">Hoekstra and Roberts 1993b</link> for -<i>en</i>; and <link rid="b4">Belletti 1982a</link> and 
<link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link> for SE). This view has been convincingly criticized by <link rid="b57">Fellbaum and Zribi-Hertz (1989</link>), who argued that phenomena such as control into final clauses or the possibility of Agent-oriented adverbs do not depend on the syntactic realization of the external argument, but instead should be analyzed as being sensitive to the presence of semantically implicit Agents.<link rid="fn31">
<sup>31</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Important evidence against the projection of Agents in passive configurations comes from control verbs. The Spanish examples in (53) are grammatical (and so are their analogs in (85a&ndash;b)), because in Spanish and Italian, SE can be a nominative clitic which, like any other subject clitic, qualifies as a legitimate <i>syntactic</i> controller:</p>
<p>(53)&ensp;<object id="tu48" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu48_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>En ciertos estudios basados en fenomenos linguisticos, se ha intentado reformar la historia politica y social.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in certain essays based on linguistic phenomena, SE has tried to reconstruct the political and social history</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Se espera llegar al final del camino.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE hopes to arrive at the end of the road</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The ungrammaticality of the Romanian examples in (54) can be explained if we assume that (i) passive SE is not a legitimate syntactic controller and (ii) Romanian does not have nominative SE (see <link rid="ss16">section 2.3</link> above):<link rid="fn32">
<sup>32</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(54)&ensp;<object id="tu49" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu49_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*In unele studii s-a &icirc;ncercat a reface, pe baza unor fenomene lingvistice, istoria politic&#x01CE; &#x015F;i social&#x01CE;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in certain essays based on linguistic phenomena, SE-has tried to reconstruct the political and social history</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Se sper&#x01CE; a ajunge la cap&#x01CE;tul drumului.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE hopes to arrive at the end of the road.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*S-a &icirc;nceput a tcedil ine seama de nevoile tuturor.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has started to take into account everybody&apos;s needs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*S-a promis a respecta dispozi tcedil iile</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has promised to obey the instructions</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The different guises of agentivity described above can be summarized as follows:</p>
<p>(55)&ensp;<object id="tu50" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu50_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Verbal passives and middles (unlike adjectival passives and inchoatives) are semantically agentive (semantically imply an Agent-role).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Verbal passives (be they analytic or marked by SE), have a <i>syntactically active implicit agent</i> (control into purpose adjunct clauses, subject-oriented adverbs).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Middles (exhibiting the property reading) have a <i>syntactically inactive implicit agent</i> (their implicit Agent-role shows no syntactic activity). </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(56)&ensp;Neither analytic nor SE-marked passives can combine with control verbs (<i>try</i>, <i>start</i>, etc.), nor do they license a reflexive pronoun, in contradistinction to nominative SE.</p>
<p>Although <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) advocates a unifying analysis of SE, his proposal is in fact based on postulating two homonymical morphemes, marked with distinct Cases: nominative &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; SE, which absorbs the external theta-role, and accusative &lsqb;&minus;arg&rsqb; SE, which merely suspends it, respectively corresponding to passive and middle SE. This distinction would explain the contrast described in (55a) vs. (55b) and illustrated in (50a) vs (50b) and (51) vs. (52). The hypothesis that passive SE is a nominative clitic functioning as an argument cannot, however, account for the generalization in (56).<link rid="fn33">
<sup>33</sup></link> A more detailed discussion of Cinque&apos;s proposal can be found in <link rid="ss29">section 4</link> below.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss24" level="2">
<heading id="h23" level="2">3.3&ensp;Passive SE absorbs the external theta-role in the lexicon</heading>
<p>According to some authors, the absorption of the external theta-role by SE takes place in the lexicon, in which case middle-passive SE, although functioning as an Agent, bears no syntactic relation to the subject position. This type of lexical rule is, however, highly problematic. Standard lexical rules affect argument structure, by suppressing or adding a theta-role (cf. passivization and causativization, respectively), but cannot directly assign a given theta-role to a designated lexical item.<link rid="fn34">
<sup>34</sup></link> Theta-roles can be assigned to lexical items only indirectly: a given lexical item is assigned a grammatical function (due to the syntactic position it occupies or to the morphological or abstract Case that it is assigned), and linking rules (lexicon&ndash;syntax mapping rules) ensure the relation between grammatical functions (or syntactic positions) and theta-roles.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss25" level="2">
<heading id="h24" level="2">3.4&ensp;Middle-passive SE absorbs the external theta-role in the syntax, via a chain with the Spec, IP position</heading>
<p>Let us now examine those analyses that rely on the hypothesis that passive SE is a particular type of subject clitic, which takes its external role in the syntax, via a chain with a subject-related position (which, depending on the author, can be Spec, IP; Spec, VP; Spec, vP; or Spec, AgrP), onto which the external role is projected. The numerous implementations of this view vary depending on the Case-features attributed to SE (accusative, nominative, or even dative), the empirical motivation, and the types of accusative SE for which the absorption hypothesis is postulated (most authors assume this analysis for passive SE; certain authors extend it to middle SE).</p>
<p>According to <link rid="b25">Burzio (1981</link>), middle-passive SE is a particular type of nominative-subject SE, which forms a chain with the (Spec, IP) position. This analysis is confronted with a number of problems, among which is Case-assignment: if SE itself absorbs nominative Case, there is no Case left for the overt DP, corresponding to the externalized internal argument. In order to allow nominative Case on both <i>si</i> and the preverbal DP, <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 47) allows for overlapping chains (see also <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>), an undesirable assumption. In (57), the chain (<i>gli spaghetti</i>, <i>si</i>), needed for the transfer of nominative Case to <i>si</i>, overlaps with the chain (<i>gli spaghetti</i>, <i>t</i>), needed for theta-role transmission. Precisely because the two chains intersect in the (Spec, IP) position, nominative Case would be assigned to both chains:<link rid="fn35">
<sup>35</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(57)&ensp;<object id="tu51" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu51_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Gli spaghetti<sub>i</sub> si<sub>i</sub> sono gi&agrave; comprati t<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the spaghettis SI HAVE already bought</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The spaghettis have already been bought.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Quite clearly, the assumptions needed in order to allow both SE and the overt DP to take nominative Case (and correlatively be in a CHAIN with Spec, IP) do not belong to core GB theory, but are in fact distortions of GB theory that are merely meant to provide a technical solution for the problems raised by the Burzio&ndash;Cinque analysis.</p>
<p>A further, interrelated problem is that the trigger of NP-movement is lost: an affix marked with nominative Case does not absorb accusative Case, which therefore is available for the internal argument, thus voiding the need for NP-movement. Since Cinque wants to preserve the hypothesis that passivization correlates with NP-movement, he provides the following solution (1988: 558&ndash;559): the suspension of accusative Case is triggered, due to Burzio&apos;s generalization, by the fact that nominative SE suspends/withholds the external theta-role.<link rid="fn36">
<sup>36</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Another problem is that French (as well as Romanian) lacks nominative SE, and yet has passive and middle SE. This is unexpected within Burzio&apos;s assumption, according to which middle and passive SEs are particular instantiations of nominative SE.<link rid="fn37">
<sup>37</sup></link> <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 145&ndash;148) concludes his short discussion of French middle-passive SE by acknowledging that it does not show the standard properties of nominative SE; it would be a &ldquo;particular, unique&rdquo; manifestation of nominative SE. But then, precisely because Italian and French middle-passives behave on a par, Burzio is led to conclude that Italian has two distinct types of nominative SE: the canonical one, which qualifies as a well-behaved nominative clitic, and is absent in French, and a peculiar one, corresponding to middle-passive SE (in both French and Italian).</p>
<p>Burzio&apos;s problematic analysis was adopted, under <link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) revision,<link rid="fn38">
<sup>38</sup></link> by the vast majority of GB theorists. <link rid="b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b, 1998</link>) argued instead that middle and passive SEs are particular instantiations of accusative SE (see <link rid="ss29">section 4</link> below for alternative analyses of the data brought up by Burzio and Cinque). Here, we will briefly sketch an alternative account of the piece of data illustrated in (58), corresponding to <link rid="b7">Burzio&apos;s (1986</link>: 47, example (69)):</p>
<p>(58)&ensp;&lsqb;quei libri&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> si andranno .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;a comprare t<sub>i</sub>
</p>
<p>According to Burzio, examples of this kind rely on both object-preposing of <i>quei libri</i> and NP-movement (more precisely, subject raising) of <i>si</i>. Since the NP-movement of <i>si</i> can only apply to the subject clitic <i>si</i>, in contrast to accusative <i>si</i>, Burzio concludes that the <i>si</i> in (58) is a subject <i>si</i>. There is, however, no evidence in favor of the fact that in this example, <i>si</i> has undergone NP-movement. We may alternatively analyze this displacement as being due to Restructuring (<link rid="b58">Rizzi 1982a</link>), a configuration in which the object clitics generated on the embedded verb end up cliticized on the main verb:<link rid="fn39">
<sup>39</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(59)&ensp;Giovanni lo<sub>i</sub> va/viene a prendere t<sub>i</sub>.</p>
<p>In sum, the position of <i>si</i> in (58) is to be accounted for in the same way as the position of <i>lo</i> in (59), which is consistent with <i>si</i> being accusative rather than nominative.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss26" level="2">
<heading id="h25" level="2">3.5&ensp;Middle-passive SE forms a chain with an A-position other than Spec, IP</heading>
<p>The proliferation of syntactic positions that characterized late versions of GB theory made it technically possible for the external role of middle-passive verbs to be syntactically projected in positions other than Spec, IP. In their analysis of Dutch middles (which are not marked by a reflexive clitic) Hoekstra and <link rid="b56">Roberts (1993)</link> propose that the external role is absorbed by a null subject of type pro that occupies (Spec, VP), the VP-internal subject position (see <link rid="b59">Sportiche 1988</link> and many others). The advantage of this proposal, which was adapted to Romance middle-passive SE in the subsequent GB and Minimalist literature, would be that the (Spec, IP) position remains available for the Theme to raise to. Note, however, that we must assume that an agentive pro in (Spec, VP) can be bypassed by the Theme-DP on its way to (Spec, IP). This is a locality problem that arises for all versions of this analysis, which essentially postulate that passive SE configurations consist of two chains: the chain of the internal argument, obtained by NP-movement from the object position to (Spec, IP), would co-exist with the chain of the external argument. The exact shape of this second chain differs from one author to the other, varying with the technical changes of the model itself. According to <link rid="b35">Postma (1995</link>), SE heads the projection of AGRo,<link rid="fn40">
<sup>40</sup></link> and PRO sits in the Spec of this same projection and binds a trace in (Spec, VP):</p>
<p>(60)&ensp;<object id="fu1" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_56_fu1.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu1_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Postma assumes that this configuration underlies all uses of accusative SE, and he derives the different possible readings from differences in agreement relations: if agreement takes place in IP, we get the reflexive reading; if no agreement takes place, we get the passive reading. The reader is referred to the technical details of this quite complex analysis. Let us simply observe that any analysis that assumes that passives rely on two distinct theta-chains is confronted with the locality problem. Various technical solutions have been proposed, which remain unconvincing.</p>
<p>Minimalist implementations of the same basic analysis are led to stipulate that, unlike overt external arguments (see (61b)), null pronouns corresponding to the external argument (see (61a)) do not block the movement of the internal argument to the subject position (<link rid="b60">McGinnis 1998</link>):<link rid="fn41">
<sup>41</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(61)&ensp;<object id="tu52" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu52_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A good guide <i>pro</i> was recommended <i>t</i> by Susanna.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*A good guide <i>Susanna</i> was recommended <i>t</i>. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similarly, the movement of the internal argument would not be blocked by the trace of se in se-passives and se-reflexives (for which McGinnis adopts an unaccusative/passive analysis). The configuration postulated by McGinnis is essentially the same as Potsma&apos;s, with AGRoP having been replaced by a light verb projection, notated vP (<link rid="b61">Chomsky 1995c</link>: <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 4 - Adverb Classes and Adverb Placement.xml" type="file">chapter 4</externallink></related>). The replacement of AGRoP with vP triggers another technical difference: SE can no longer be assumed to head the projection, but may instead be assumed to be generated in the (Spec, vP) position, which in this model is the canonical position for external arguments:</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;<object id="tu53" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu53_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Pierre se frappe.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Pierre slaps himself in the face.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
<object id="fu2" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_56_fu2.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu2_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>
<object id="fu3" type="figure" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<file name="Graphics\chapter_56_fu3.jpg" type="jpg" id="fu3_source"/>
</objectsource>
</object>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>SE cliticizes to T&deg; as soon as this node is filled by the raised verb, and once SE has cliticized, the object is free to raise to Spec, IP. The fact that null pronouns (see (61a)) and clitic traces allow NP-movement to bypass them, in sharp contrast with overt DPs, is explained on the basis of the assumption that once an NP has cliticized to T, it is no longer accessible for movement to Spec-TP, so this NP and its trace don&apos;t count as interveners for Shortest Move.</p>
<p>A still different version of the hypothesis that the external theta-role is syntactically projected in middle-passive configurations can be found in <link rid="b62">Cardinaletti&apos;s (1990</link>) analysis of German middles. According to Cardinaletti, the <i>es</i> that shows up in <i>hier lebt sich es angenehm</i> absorbs the external theta-role. Note that unlike Italian <i>si</i>, German <i>sich</i> is uncontroversially an accusative clitic. Cardinaletti&apos;s analysis of German thus winds up postulating that an accusative middle-passivizing morpheme such as <i>sich</i> (i) does not absorb the external theta-role but (ii) does not suspend it either (since this theta-role would be linked to <i>es</i>).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss27" level="2">
<heading id="h26" level="2">3.6&ensp;SE absorbs the external theta-role and dative Case</heading>
<p>The locality problem discussed above is avoided by a technical implementation due to <link rid="b29">Gu&eacute;ron (1991</link>), who builds on <link rid="b28">Kayne&apos;s (1988</link>) suggestion that in all its uses, including reflexive SE and subject/nominative SE: (i) SE absorbs the external role; (ii) SE absorbs dative Case; (iii) SE binds/identifies an empty category in a VP-adjoined position.<link rid="fn42">
<sup>42</sup></link> Although this is not explicitly stated, the Kayne&ndash;Gu&eacute;ron analysis is meant to solve what was taken to be a severe problem for the analysis of middle-passive SE (and for that of reflexive SE, if the latter is analyzed as unaccusative): if the empty category in object position is the trace of SE, it cannot also be the trace left behind by the A-movement of the internal argument. Note, however, that this problem only arises if one assumes the pronominal analysis of SE, according to which SE necessarily binds a SE-trace in the object position. If instead we adopt Burzio&apos;s hypothesis that accusative SE, including middle-passive SE, is a morphological marker, which as such binds no trace, the object position may host the NP-trace of the object raised to the subject position.</p>
<p>The Kayne&ndash;Gu&eacute;ron proposal is confronted with several problems. To make the discussion concrete, consider examples such as (63):</p>
<p>(63)&ensp;<object id="tu54" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu54_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Les pommes se mangent en automne.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the apples SE eat in autumn</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One eats apples in autumn.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since by assumption SE is dative, it is unclear how it can absorb the external role, because this role is not linked to a VP-adjoined position, or to any kind of dative-related position. The answer could be that the external role is of the Experiencer-type. This is indeed compatible with dative-marking, but crucially not with the suspended external role of passives, which is agentive. Gu&eacute;ron suggests that this peculiarity is due to quirky Case, but no empirical evidence supporting this proposal is provided. It is furthermore unclear why a dative-marked reflexive should trigger the absorption of accusative case, which is a defining characteristic of passives.<link rid="fn43">
<sup>43</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss28" level="2">
<heading id="h27" level="2">3.7&ensp;Conclusions</heading>
<p>Although standard GB theory (<link rid="b63">Chomsky 1981</link>) was designed to block it, most GB analyses of passivization postulated the projection of the external role in subject-related positions by modifying those principles of GB that were meant to prevent it. But each of the particular implementations of this hypothesis is confronted with its own problems: passive SE cannot be analyzed as either a nominative clitic or a (possibly accusative) clitic associated with (Spec, IP); nor can we assume passive SE to be a pro occupying (Spec, VP) or the Spec position of some other functional projection.</p>
<p>This negative result calls for alternative analyses of the empirical evidence adduced in favor of the syntactic projection of the Agent in middle-passive SE constructions: (i) the intricate distribution of middle-passive SE in Italian non-finite clauses; (ii) the correlation between the (preverbal vs. postverbal) position of the subject DP and the meaning (generic/middle/stative vs. eventive passive) of SE-verbs (<link rid="b64">Ruwet 1972</link>; <link rid="b3">Raposo and Uriagereka 1996</link>). These two sets of data will be examined in sections 4 and <link rid="b2">5</link> below.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss29" level="1">
<heading id="h28" level="1">4.&ensp;The distribution of SE in non-finite Italian clauses</heading>
<p>Because passivizing SE is illegitimate in control configurations, <link rid="b25 b7">Burzio (1981, 1986</link>) and all the subsequent literature assumed that passivizing SE needs nominative Case, an assumption that creates theoretical and empirical problems (see <link rid="ss33 ss34">sections 4.1.3 and 4.1.4</link>). <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>) has provided new solutions to the peculiar distribution of passivizing SE in control infinitivals, based on the view that (i) passivizing SE carries accusative Case and (ii) nominative SE is banned from non-finite clauses (see <link rid="ss40">section 4.2.1</link>). The ungrammaticality of passive SE in control configurations is traced back to three distinct constraints (see <link rid="ss41">section 4.2.2</link>). Finally, it is argued that in Italian non-finite clauses, the SE that appears with unergatives is a passivizing accusative SE (see <link rid="ss17">section 2.4</link> above).</p>
<subsection id="ss30" level="2">
<heading id="h29" level="2">4.1&ensp;<link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) analysis: two types of nominative SE in Italian</heading>
<subsection id="ss31" level="3">
<heading id="h30" level="3">4.1.1&ensp;SE with unergatives vs. SE with adjectives, analytic passives, or psych verbs</heading>
<p>The contrast between (64) and (65) shows that the class of (presumably) nominative SEs splits in Italian infinitivals: the examples in (64), in which nominative SE combines with unaccusatives, analytic passives, and adjectival predicates, are ungrammatical, whereas the examples in (65), built with unergatives, are grammatical. The examples in this section are borrowed from <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>), but some of the glosses and the clustering of examples may be different:</p>
<p>(64)&ensp;<object id="tu55" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu55_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Ritengo non essersi arrivati in sufficiente anticipo. (SE &plus; unaccusatives in Aux-to-Comp)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) believe not (to) HAVE-SI arrived sufficiently ahead of time</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*non essendosi morti in giovane et&agrave;. (SE &plus; unaccusatives in Aux-to-Comp) not HAVING-SI died young</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*Sembra essersi arrivati troppo tardi. (SE &plus; unaccusatives in raising configurations) it seems (to) HAVE-SI arrived too late</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>e.</entry>
<entry>*Sembra non essersi benvenuti qui. (SE &plus; copula in raising configurations) it seems not (to) BE-SI welcome here</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>f.</entry>
<entry>*Sembra non essersi stati invitati da nessuno. (SE &plus; passive in raising configurations) it seems not HAVE-SI been invited by anybody</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(65)&ensp;<object id="tu56" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu56_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ritengo non essersi provveduto alle sue necessit&agrave; con la dovuta solerzia.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) believe not (to) HAVE-SI taken care of his needs with due zeal.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(I) believe his needs have not been taken care of with due zeal.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>non essendosi provveduto alle sue necessit&agrave; con la dovuta solerzia</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not HAVING-SI taken care of his needs with due zeal</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;his needs not having been taken care of with due zeal&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Sembra non essersi lavorato a sufficienza.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) seems not HAVE-SI worked sufficiently</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It seems that there was not enough work.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given this contrast, we may conclude that the SEs that show up in the two classes of examples are of different types. This solution is compatible with several options: we may believe that (i) the two SEs are nominative and accusative, respectively, or (ii) the two SEs are both nominative, but nevertheless distinct. Building on a suggestion by <link rid="b25 b7">Burzio (1981, 1986</link>), Cinque argues in favor of the second hypothesis, which seems to be supported by the fact that in (65), SE combines with unergatives, a context that was believed to be compatible with nominative SE, but not with accusative SE. This hypothesis seems to be further supported by the contrast between examples such as (65), illustrating Aux-to-Comp and subject-raising configurations, which are known to be compatible with nominative Case assignment, and examples of the type in (66), illustrating configurations relying on arbitrary PRO, in which nominative Case cannot be assigned:</p>
<p>(66)&ensp;<object id="tu57" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu57_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Sarebbe meglio lavorarsi un po&rsquo; di pi&ugrave;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better (to) work SI a bit more</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It would be better to be worked a bit more.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) and <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>), the contrast between (65) and (66) can be explained by assuming that the SE that combines with unergatives needs nominative Case: the examples in (65) are grammatical because SE can get nominative Case (Aux-to-Comp configurations allow nominative Case assignment in Italian infinitivals), whereas the example in (66) is ungrammatical because nominative Case is unavailable in controlled clauses.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss32" level="3">
<heading id="h31" level="3">4.1.2&ensp;A passivizing nominative SE</heading>
<p>The contrast between (65) and (66) is parallelled by the contrast between (67) and (68), which shows that passive SE is allowed in Aux-to-Comp and subject-raising contexts, but disallowed in control configurations:</p>
<p>(67)&ensp;<object id="tu58" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu58_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ritengo non essersi ancora scoperto il vero colpevole. <b>(Aux-to-Comp)</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsqb;I&rsqb; believe not to HAVE-SI yet discovered the true culprit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;I believe the true culprit has not yet been discovered.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>non essendosi ancora scoperto il vero colpevole <b>(Aux-to-Comp)</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not HAVING-SI yet discovered the true culprit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;the true culprit not having yet been discovered&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>Sembra non essersi ancora scoperto il vero colpevole. <b>(Subject raising)</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) seems not (to) HAVE-SI yet discovered the true culprit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It seems that the true culprit has not yet been discovered.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(68)&ensp;<object id="tu59" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu59_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
<b>Control configurations:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>*Sarebbe meglio scoprirsi il colpevole.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better (to) discover SI the culprit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It would be better for the culprit to be discovered.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Quei prigionieri<sub>i</sub> vorrebero &lsqb;PRO<sub>i</sub> essersi gi&agrave; liberati e<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>those prisoners would want have SI already released</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Those prisoners would want to have been already released.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Although passive SE is compatible with an analysis in terms of accusative SE, the contrast between (67) &ndash; where nominative case can be assigned &ndash; and (68) &ndash; where nominative Case cannot be assigned &ndash; was interpreted by <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) and <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) as indicating that passive SE needs nominative Case, on a par with the SE that combines with unergatives (see again examples (65) vs. (66)).</p>
<p>Let us now be more specific about the details of Cinque&apos;s analysis: (i) two distinct nominative SEs are postulated, which are distinguished by different choices for the feature &plusmn;arg(ument); (ii) the SE that combines with unergatives (see (65)) may be either &plus;arg or &minus;arg, whereas the SE that combines with the copula, passives, unaccusatives, etc. (see (64)) can only be marked as &minus;arg; (iii) &minus;arg SE is disallowed in those configurations in which no overt AGR morpheme is present (hence the ungrammaticality of (64)).</p>
<p>(69)&ensp;<object id="tu60" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu60_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
<b>
<link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988)</link> typology:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&minus;arg &lsqb;nom&rsqb; impersonal SE (SE &plus; copula, SE &plus; unaccusatives, SE &plus; passives, SE &plus; unergatives)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&plus;arg &lsqb;nom&rsqb; passivizing SE (SE &plus; transitives, SE &plus; unergatives)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&minus;arg &lsqb;acc&rsqb; &lsquo;pure&rsquo; passivizing SE (Middle SE) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss33" level="3">
<heading id="h32" level="3">4.1.3&ensp;Theoretical problems with the <roman>&plusmn;</roman>arg(ument) distinction</heading>
<p>As presented by Cinque himself, the &plusmn;arg distinction is an attempt to solve a theoretical problem, which had been previously noted by <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 45f.), <link rid="b4">Belletti (1982a</link>: fns. 21, 37, Appendix), and Manzini (1986), concerning examples such as (70):</p>
<p>(70)&ensp;<object id="tu61" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu61_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Si parte.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One leaves.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The verb <i>partire</i> &lsquo;to leave&rsquo; belongs to the unaccusative class, and as such assigns a theta-role to the &lsqb;NP, V&prime;&rsqb; position, and leaves &lsqb;Spec, IP&rsqb; with no theta-role. On the assumption that <i>si</i> is an argument subject clitic base-generated in Infl (or in some Infl-related clitic position) that can take its theta-role only from the Spec, IP position, examples such as (70) violate the Theta-Criterion at D-structure. Cinque solves this problem by assuming that the <i>si</i> that appears in (71) is not an argument (hence the feature &lsqb;&minus;arg&rsqb; that would characterize it). Compare an example such as (71):</p>
<p>(71)&ensp;<object id="tu62" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu62_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Si dorme.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;One sleeps.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since <i>dormire</i> &lsquo;to sleep&rsquo; assigns a theta-role to the Spec, IP position at D-structure, it may combine with a &plus;arg <i>si</i>. But note that under Cinque&apos;s analysis, <i>dormire</i> may also combine with a &minus;arg <i>si</i>, on a par with <i>partire</i>. In other words, <i>si dorme</i> is systematically ambiguous in Italian, depending on the nature of <i>si</i>, whereas <i>si parte</i> unambiguously relies on a &minus;arg nominative <i>si</i>.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>) observes that the theoretical problem invoked by Burzio, Belletti, Manzini, and Cinque in connection with <i>si</i> in fact extends to subject clitics in general. Should we then assume a systematic ambiguity for subject clitics in general (cf. in particular the subject clitics of Italian dialects), on a par with the ambiguity that Cinque assumes for <i>si</i>? More concretely, should we assume that subject clitics may be either &plus;arg or &minus;arg when they combine with transitives or unergatives, but only &minus;arg when they combine with unaccusatives?<link rid="fn44">
<sup>44</sup></link> Cinque does not go in this direction, and his implicit answer to the problem of subject clitics is that they should be assumed to be &minus;arg elements, regardless of the type of verb with which they combine. It is important to stress that Cinque&apos;s &minus;arg feature should not be interpreted as notating expletive clitics, as opposed to referential clitics, but rather as saying that nominative clitics (and clitics in general) fall outside the argument/non-argument distinction, which is relevant only for elements that occupy A-positions.</p>
<p>We are thus led to conclude that the &lsqb;&minus;arg&rsqb; feature need not be stipulated: it is the unmarked option for clitics in general; &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; nominative SE, on the other hand, is an element that does not fall under the general characterization of clitics. Cinque assumes &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; <i>si</i> to be related to an A-position that is assigned a theta-role at D-structure, but is filled with an expletive at S-structure. Such a discrepancy between the clitic and its trace, which is unprecedented for clitics, brings to mind the current characterization of passive morphemes in general and middle-passive <i>si</i> in particular: <i>si</i> absorbs (or rather suspends) the external theta-role, and as a consequence the subject position is occupied by an expletive. In sum, the &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; feature of <i>si</i>, which is found with no other clitic, can be viewed as a label for passive <i>si</i>. Since passive morphemes cannot be marked with nominative Case, we are led to conclude that Cinque&apos;s &plus;arg nominative SE is in reality a passivizing SE that absorbs accusative Case. The only genuine nominative SE is Cinque&apos;s &minus;arg nominative SE. We thus end up with only two basic distinct types of SE, accusative and nominative.<link rid="fn45">
<sup>45</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss34" level="3">
<heading id="h33" level="3">4.1.4&ensp;Empirical problems</heading>
<p>Cinque&apos;s proposal is also confronted by several empirical problems:</p>
<p>(72)&ensp;<object id="tu63" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu63_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The hypothesis that &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; nominative SE is a passivizer<link rid="fn46">
<sup>46</sup></link> is problematic, since the occurrence of a nominative clitic marked with the external theta-role is incompatible with the passivization phenomenon. To make them compatible, one would have to allow for the double assignment of nominative Case or for overlapping CHAINS, which are undesirable on general grounds (see <link rid="ss25">section 3.4</link>. above).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Passive SE-verbs agree with the overt DP, on a par with reflexives and other types of accusative SE-verbs. Compare &minus;arg &lsqb;nom&rsqb; SE, which triggers <i>lack</i> of agreement between the verb and the overt DP.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Passive SE cannot co-occur with an accusative-marked argument. This is expected if SE itself is &lsqb;acc&rsqb;, but not if it is &lsqb;nom&rsqb;. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In what follows, these problems will be illustrated with examples borrowed from <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) himself. Crucial for the analysis of the data is the contrast between SE-verbs in Italian finite and non-finite clauses: whereas a truly nominative SE can appear in Italian finite clauses (see <link rid="ss16">section 2.3</link> above), it is ungrammatical in Italian non-finite clauses. The contrast between Italian finite and non-finite clauses is parallelled by the contrast between Italian and Romanian finite SE-verbs. This is predicted by the hypothesis that Romanian does not have nominative SE.</p>
<subsection id="ss35" level="4">
<heading id="h34" level="4">4.1.4.1&ensp;Verbal agreement</heading>
<p>Because the overt DP of a middle-passive SE is a subject, it triggers agreement with the verb. With nominative SE instead, the verb is in the third person singular. In Italian infinitivals, verb agreement with the postverbal NP is obligatory (the agreement can only be checked here on the past participle, since in non-finite clauses the auxiliary verb is not inflected for number and person), which supports the analysis in terms of a middle-passive SE:</p>
<p>(73)&ensp;<object id="tu64" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu64_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Ritengo essersi venduto pochi automobili.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) esteem (to) have SI sold (sing.) few cars</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*?essendosi venduto pochi automobili</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>having SI sold (sing.) few cars</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(74)&ensp;<object id="tu65" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu65_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ritengo essersi venduti pochi automobili.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) esteem (to) have-SI sold (pl.) few cars</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;I esteem to have been sold (pl.) few cars.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry>essendosi venduti pochi automobili</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>having SI sold (pl.) few cars</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;having been sold (pl.) few cars&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(examples borrowed from <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>: (79&ndash;80))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As expected, the agreement pattern found in Italian non-finite <i>si</i> constructions also characterizes Romanian finite <i>si</i> constructions, because they can only rely on middle-passive <i>si</i>:</p>
<p>(75)&ensp;<object id="tu66" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu66_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*&Icirc;n aceast&#x01CE; universitate se pred&#x01CE; &#x015F;tiin tcedil ele umane.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in this university SE teaches (sing.) the humanities</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>&Icirc;n aceast&#x01CE; universitate se predau &#x015F;tiin tcedil ele umane.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in this university SE teach (plur.) the humanities</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;In this university are taught the humanities.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss36" level="4">
<heading id="h35" level="4">4.1.4.2&ensp;The distribution of accusative clitics</heading>
<p>Another piece of evidence showing that passive SE in Italian infinitivals is &lsqb;acc&rsqb; is provided by the distribution of accusative clitics. While &lsqb;nom&rsqb; impersonal SE is compatible with accusative clitics (see example (35d)), middle-passive SE is not:</p>
<p>(76)&ensp;<object id="tu67" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu67_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Ritengo esserlesi vendute ad un prezzo eccessivo.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) esteem (to) have-them-SI sold at an excessive price</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*essendolesi vendute ad un prezzo eccessivo</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>having-them-SI sold at an excessive price </entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(examples borrowed from <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>: (81&ndash;82))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The same type of ungrammaticality arises in Romanian finite clauses:</p>
<p>(77)&ensp;<object id="tu68" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu68_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*(&#x015F;tiin tcedil ele umane) le <i>se</i> pred&#x01CE; &icirc;n aceast&#x01CE; universitate</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(the humanities) them SE teach in this university</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss37" level="4">
<heading id="h36" level="4">4.1.4.3&ensp;<i>L&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro,</i> floating of <i>tutti</i>
</heading>
<p>Impersonal &lsqb;nom&rsqb; SE can serve as an antecedent for <i>l&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i>:</p>
<p>(78)&ensp;<object id="tu69" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu69_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Si era parlato l&rsquo;uno con l&rsquo;altro.</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SI had spoken with each other</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;We/they had spoken with each other.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>But <i>l&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i> is disallowed in Italian infinitivals (and in Romanian finite clauses):</p>
<p>(79)&ensp;<object id="tu70" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu70_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>(Io non c&rsquo;ero, ma) *deve/sembra essersi parlato l&rsquo;uno con l&rsquo;altro. Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(I wasn&apos;t there, but) (it) must/seems (to) have SI spoken with each other.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Ritenevo essersi parlato l&rsquo;uno con l&rsquo;altro.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;I deemed (to) have SI spoken with each other.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*non essendosi affatto parlato l&rsquo;uno con l&rsquo;altro</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;not having SI at all spoken with each other&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(80)&ensp;<object id="tu71" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu71_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*S-a vorbit unul cu altul.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;SI has spoken with each other.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The observed ungrammaticalities can be understood if we assume that in Italian infinitivals, the SE that combines with unergatives can only be a middle-passive accusative SE (just as in Romanian finite clauses; see (82) and <link rid="ss17">section 2.4</link> above), which induces a chain of the type (pro, e), which is assigned the theta-role corresponding to a cognate object. But cognate objects are not legitimate antecedents of <i>l&rsquo;uno l&rsquo;altro</i>, hence the ungrammaticality of (79a&ndash;c) in Italian and (80) in Romanian.</p>
<p>The same behavior is found with the quantifier <i>tutti</i>: it allows impersonal &lsqb;nom&rsqb; SE as an antecedent (see (81)) but not the &lsqb;acc&rsqb; passive SE, which occurs in Italian embedded infinitivals (see (82)) and in Romanian finite clauses (see (83)):</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu72" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu72_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Si &egrave; reagito a sproposito tutti.</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SI has reacted off the point all</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;We all reacted off the point.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(82)&ensp;<object id="tu73" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu73_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*?Sembra essersi reagito a sproposito tutti.</entry>
<entry>Italian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(It) seems (to) have SI reacted off the point all.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*?Ritiene essersi reagito a sproposito tutti.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(He) believes (to) have SI reacted off the point all.&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*?essendosi reagito a sproposito tutti</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Having SI reacted off the point all&rsquo;</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(83)&ensp;<object id="tu74" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu74_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*S-a reac tcedil ionat prost to tcedil;i.</entry>
<entry>Romanian</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;SE-has reacted badly all.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss38" level="4">
<heading id="h37" level="4">4.1.4.4&ensp;Control</heading>
<p>In Italian non-finite clauses, <i>si</i> cannot combine with control verbs:</p>
<p>(84)&ensp;<object id="tu75" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu75_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">*Ritengo non essersi promesso di ottemperare alle disposizioni.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;(I) believe not (to) HAVE-SI promised to obey the instructions.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This is still another context in which Italian non-finite clauses contrast with Italian finite clauses (85) and are parallel to Romanian finite clauses ((54), repeated here as (86)):</p>
<p>(85)&ensp;<object id="tu76" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu76_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>In certi studi basati su fenomeni linguistici, si &egrave; cercato di ricostruire la storia politica e sociale.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in certain essays based on linguistic phenomena, SE-has tried to reconstruct the political and social history</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Se espera llegar al final del camino.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE hopes to arrive at the end of the road</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>Si &egrave; cominciato a prendere in considerazione le esigenze di tutti.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has started to take into account everybody&apos;s needs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>Si &egrave; promesso di seguire le istruzioni.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has promised to obey the instructions</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(86)&ensp;<object id="tu77" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu77_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*In unele studii s-a &icirc;ncercat a reface, pe baza unor fenomene lingvistice, istoria politic&#x01CE; &#x015F;i social&#x01CE;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>In certain essays based on linguistic phenomena, SE-has tried to reconstruct the political and social history</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Se sper&#x01CE; a ajunge la cap&#x01CE;tul drumului.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE hopes to arrive at the end of the road</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*S-a &icirc;nceput a  tcedil;ine seama de nevoile tuturor.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has started to take into account everybody&apos;s needs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*S-a promis a respecta dispozi tcedil;iile</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has promised to obey the instructions</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The data in (84) are surprising under <link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) analysis relying on nominative SE, but expected if nominative SE is disallowed in Italian non-finite clauses; in examples such as (84), <i>si</i> can only be analyzed as a middle-passive accusative <i>si</i>, which is not a legitimate syntactic controller.<link rid="fn47">
<sup>47</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss39" level="2">
<heading id="h38" level="2">4.2&ensp;<link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin&apos;s (1998</link>) analysis</heading>
<subsection id="ss40" level="3">
<heading id="h39" level="3">4.2.1&ensp;Nominative clitics and agreement features</heading>
<p>According to <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>), Cinque&apos;s &plus;arg nominative SE is a passivizing accusative SE. Because passivization cannot apply to the copula, passives or unaccusatives, the examples in (64) cannot be analyzed as relying on a passivizing accusative SE, but could only rely on nominative SE (which is free to combine with any kind of verb). However, this possibility is itself ruled out, because nominative <i>si</i> is not allowed in Italian non-finite clauses, an impossibility that Dobrovie-Sorin attributes to the empirical generalization stated in (87):<link rid="fn48">
<sup>48</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(87)&ensp;Nominative clitics must be identified by overt subject agreement morphemes.<link rid="fn49">
<sup>49</sup></link>
</p>
<p>This generalization explains why examples of the type in (64) are ungrammatical. The examples in (65), on the other hand, are grammatical, because they can be analyzed as relying on a passivizing accusative SE (which can combine with unergatives; see <link rid="ss17">section 2.4</link> above).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss41" level="3">
<heading id="h40" level="3">4.2.2&ensp;Middle-passive SE in control infinitivals</heading>
<p>The main empirical data that led <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) and <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) to believe that passivizing SE needed nominative Case was the ban on passivizing SE in control configurations ((68), repeated here as (88&ndash;89), and (66), repeated here as (90)):</p>
<p>(88)&ensp;<object id="tu78" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu78_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Sarebbe meglio scoprirsi il colpevole.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better (to) discover SI the culprit</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It would be better for the culprit to be discovered.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(89)&ensp;<object id="tu79" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu79_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Quei prigionieri<sub>i</sub> vorrebero &lsqb;PRO<sub>i</sub> essersi gi&agrave; liberati e<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>those prisoners would want have SI already released</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Those prisoners would want to have been already released.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(90)&ensp;<object id="tu80" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu80_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Sarebbe meglio lavorarsi un po&rsquo; di pi&ugrave;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better (to) work SI a bit more</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It would be better to be worked a bit more.&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Following <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 44), <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) attributes the ungrammaticality of (88&ndash;90) to a violation of the Case filter: <i>si</i> requires nominative Case, which cannot be assigned in control configurations. Compare Aux-to-Comp contexts (see (67)), in which nominative Case can be assigned. This explanation is not available within <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin&apos;s (1998</link>) analysis, according to which the <i>si</i> in (88&ndash;90) is marked with accusative Case. Dobrovie-Sorin proposes that the ungrammaticality shown in (88&ndash;90) is due to three distinct constraints, none of which requires <i>si</i> itself to be marked with nominative Case.</p>
<subsection id="ss42" level="4">
<heading id="h41" level="4">4.2.2.1&ensp;Case</heading>
<p>Case assignment is relevant only in example (88): <i>il colpevole</i> is an overt DP, which as such needs Case. But nominative Case cannot be assigned in this type of Italian infinitivals; <i>il colpevole</i> cannot take accusative Case either, because it is <i>si</i> itself that needs accusative Case.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss43" level="4">
<heading id="h42" level="4">4.2.2.2&ensp;A semantic constraint on control</heading>
<p>Nominative Case is not needed in (89), since there is no lexical DP in the infinitival clause. Dobrovie-Sorin suggests that the relevant factor is a semantic constraint, which is in fact suggested by <link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) own observation that control is compatible with <i>si</i> if the property reading is forced:</p>
<p>(91)&ensp;<object id="tu81" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu81_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>La luce gialla ha il vantaggio di vedersi bene anche nella nebbia pi&ugrave; fitta.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the yellow light has the advantage of see SI well even in the thickest fog</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The yellow light has the advantage of being able to be seen even in the thickest fog.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="3">b.</entry>
<entry>Certe lingue hanno la propriet&agrave; di impararsi con pi&ugrave; facilit&agrave; di altre.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>certain languages have the property of acquire SI more easily than others.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Certain languages have the property of being more easily learnable than others.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(&equals; <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>: (187a&ndash;b))</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to Cinque, the examples in (91) are grammatical because the property reading relies on middle <i>si</i>, which is accusative. Compare the ungrammaticality of (89), constructed with an impersonal passive <i>si</i>, which according to Cinque requires nominative Case. Since there is, however, no conclusive evidence in favor of the Case distinction between passive and middle <i>si</i>, Dobrovie-Sorin assumes only one type of passivizing <i>si</i>, marked with accusative Case, which allows either an eventive passive or a middle reading, depending on the position of the overt DP-argument (see <link rid="ss45">section 5</link> below). Examples such as (89) are ungrammatical because the verb <i>volere</i> &lsquo;want&rsquo; requires the embedded clause to refer to a particular event, but the eventive passive reading of SE-verbs is blocked in controlled clauses. This constraint on the reading of SE-verbs is a particular case of a broader empirical generalization, to be examined in <link rid="ss45">section 5</link> below: the eventive passive reading is blocked if the subject DP sits in Spec, IP.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss44" level="4">
<heading id="h43" level="4">4.2.2.3&ensp;Passive SE unergatives and the argument status of PRO</heading>
<p>We are left with (90), repeated as (92a). Dobrovie-Sorin&apos;s explanation relies on the parallellism with (92b), the ungrammaticality of which is itself comparable to that of (93a&ndash;c) in English:</p>
<p>(92)&ensp;<object id="tu82" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu82_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>*Sarebbe meglio &lsqb;PRO<sub>i</sub> lavorarsi<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> un po&rsquo; di pi&ugrave;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better &lsqb;PRO<sub>i</sub> (to) work SI<sub>i</sub> e<sub>i</sub> a bit more&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Sarebbe meglio &lsqb;PRO piovere un po&rsquo; di pi&ugrave;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) would be better &lsqb;PRO (to) rain a bit more&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(93)&ensp;<object id="tu83" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu83_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*PRO to rain tomorrow would be a tragedy.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*PRO to arrive a man would be marvelous.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(cf. For there to arrive a man .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>*PRO being likely that.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, we didn&apos;t go.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(cf. It being likely that .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, we didn&apos;t go.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>PRO to arrive late would be an offense.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(cf. For us/you .&nbsp;.&nbsp;. to arrive late .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>According to <link rid="b63">Chomsky (1981</link>: 325&ndash;327) and Rizzi (1982), the ungrammaticality of (93a&ndash;c) is due to the generalization stated in (94):</p>
<p>(94)&ensp;&lsqb;A chain headed by&rsqb; arbitrary &lsqb;non-controlled&rsqb; PRO is necessarily an argument.</p>
<p>Examples (93a&ndash;c), as well as (92b), are ungrammatical because weather verbs and impersonal constructions must be constructed with quasi-argumental and expletive subjects, respectively, which conflicts with the argument status of PRO (see (94)). Compare the example in (93d), which is grammatical, because there PRO takes a fully referential reading.</p>
<p>This analyis also accounts for (92a): the (PRO, e) chain on which (92) relies counts as an argument, and this conflicts with the selectional requirements imposed by middle-passive unergatives (cognate objects are not fully referential arguments).</p>
<p>This account predicts the grammaticality of middle-passive <i>si</i> unergatives in Aux-to-Comp configurations (65a&ndash;b), repeated here as (95)):</p>
<p>(95)&ensp;<object id="tu84" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu84_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ritengo non essersi provveduto alle sue necessit&agrave; con la dovuta solerzia.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) believe not (to) HAVE-SI taken care of his needs with due zeal</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;(I) believe his needs have not been taken care of with due zeal.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>non essendosi provveduto alle sue necessit&agrave; con la dovuta solerzia</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>not HAVING-SI taken care of his needs with due zeal</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;his needs not having been taken care of with due zeal&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since nominative Case can be assigned here (by the Aux raised to Comp), these examples can be analyzed as relying on chains of the type (pro, e), which are not subject to the constraint in (94), and therefore can function as cognate objects, licensed by the quasi theta-role assigned by unergatives to their objects.</p>
<p>The distribution of SE unergatives is thus completely parallel to the distribution of weather verbs as described and analyzed by Rizzi (1982):</p>
<p>(96)&ensp;<object id="tu85" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu85_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Essendo piovuto per tutto il pomeriggio, non siamo usciti.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;Having rained for the whole afternoon, (we) didn&apos;t go out.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(97)&ensp;<object id="tu86" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu86_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Suppongo &lsqb;esser molto improbabile che Mario ci aiuti&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">&lsquo;(I) consider (it) (to) be very unlikely that Mario help us.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In sum, the fact that <i>si V</i><sub><i>unerg</i>
</sub> sequences are allowed in Aux-to-Comp contexts and disallowed in control configurations is not due to the fact that <i>si</i> needs nominative Case, but rather to the interpretive constraint in (94), which holds for PRO as opposed to <i>pro</i>.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss45" level="1">
<heading id="h44" level="1">5&ensp;The interpretation of SE-verbs and the position of their subject</heading>
<p>In this section we will examine a well-known constraint on the passive reading of SE: it can only obtain in those contexts in which the subject (corresponding to the underlying internal argument) occupies a VP-internal position; in case it occupies the canonical subject position, the passive reading is unavailable, the only possible interpretation being the middle reading. We will show that this generalization, established for French by <link rid="b65">St&eacute;fanini (1962</link>) and <link rid="b64">Ruwet (1972</link>), subsumes <link rid="b3">Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s (1996</link>) generalization regarding European Portuguese. We will, however, question Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s explanation, which was based on <link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) hypothesis that passive SE is a subject-like clitic.</p>
<subsection id="ss46" level="2">
<heading id="h45" level="2">5.1&ensp;French: the choice between the middle and the passive readings depends on the S-structure position of the overt argument</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b65">St&eacute;fanini (1962</link>) and <link rid="b64">Ruwet (1972</link>) have established that:</p>
<p>(98)&ensp;French SE-verbs with preverbal subjects allow the middle reading, but cannot take the eventive passive reading (see (99)),<link rid="fn50">
<sup>50</sup></link> which is allowed only in <i>il</i>-impersonals (see (100)).</p>
<p>(99)&ensp;<object id="tu87" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu87_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Ce livre s&rsquo;ach&egrave;te par correspondence.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this book SI buys by mail</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;This book can be bought by mail.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Ce livre s&rsquo;est achet&eacute; hier.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this book SI HAS bought yesterday</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;This book was bought yesterday.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Les prisonniers se lib&eacute;reront la semaine prochaine/le plus rapidement possible.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the prisoners SE will release next week/as soon as possible</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The prisoners will be released next week/as soon as possible.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(100)&ensp;<object id="tu88" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu88_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Il se boira beaucoup de vin ce soir.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE will drink a lot of wine this evening</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;A lot of wine will be drunk this evening.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Il s&rsquo;est bu beaucoup de whisky &agrave; la r&eacute;ception.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE HAS drunk much whisky at the reception</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;A lot of whisky was drunk at the reception.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The eventive meaning is indicated by the compatibility with temporal adverbials and the incompatibility with the manner adverbs characteristic of middles (<link rid="b66">Obenauer 1970</link>: 62):</p>
<p>(100)&ensp;<object id="tu89" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu89_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>* Il se reboise pas mal de terrains difficilement.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE reforests quite a number of grounds difficultly</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Quite a number of grounds are difficult to reforest.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since the postverbal DP of French <i>il</i>-impersonals occupies the object position, the French data can be summarized as follows:</p>
<p>(101)&ensp;<object id="tu90" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu90_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Subject DP in Spec, IP &rArr; middle and habitual passive readings of &lsqb;acc&rsqb; SE.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>subject DP in VP-internal position &rArr; eventive passive reading of &lsqb;acc&rsqb; SE. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss47" level="2">
<heading id="h46" level="2">5.2&ensp;European Portuguese</heading>
<subsection id="ss48" level="3">
<heading id="h47" level="3">5.2.1&ensp;<link rid="b3">Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s (1996</link>) generalization</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b3">Raposo and Uriagereka (1996</link>) established that in European Portuguese (eventive-)passive configurations, the preverbal subject is not in (Spec, IP), but instead occupies a left-peripheral position (Topic or Focus, depending on the inherent properties of the DP):<link rid="fn51">
<sup>51</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(102)&ensp;<object id="tu91" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu91_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub>DP&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>I&prime;</sub> se V .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb;&rsqb; &rArr; *passive SE.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub>DP&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>I&prime;</sub> se V .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&rsqb;&rsqb; &rArr; OK passive SE. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Inflected infinitivals provide evidence in favor of this analysis. Thus, both an analytic passive and a SE-passive may occur as inflected infinitives with the agreeing DP in the <i>post</i>verbal position (all the following examples are European Portuguese):</p>
<p>(103)&ensp;<object id="tu92" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu92_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Vai ser difficil &lsqb;<i>pro</i> serem aceites &lsqb;<b>os documentos</b>&rsqb;&rsqb;. (analytic passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>will be difficult to-be-3pl accepted the documents</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It will be difficult for the documents to be accepted.&rsquo; (SE-passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Vai ser difficil &lsqb;<i>pro</i> aceitarem-se &lsqb;<b>os documentos</b>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>will be difficult (to)-accept-3pl-SE the documents</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It will be difficult for the documents to be accepted.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>However, an eventive-passive SE, in contrast with analytic passives, is ungrammatical if the DP is in the <i>pre</i>verbal position:</p>
<p>(104)&ensp;<object id="tu93" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu93_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Vai ser difficil &lsqb;&lsqb;<b>os documentos</b>&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> serem aceites <i>t</i><sub><i>i</i>
</sub>&rsqb;. (analytic passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>will be difficult the documents to-be-3pl accepted</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It will be difficult for the documents to be accepted.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Vai ser difficil &lsqb;&lsqb;<b>os documentos</b>&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> aceitarem-se <i>t</i><sub><i>i</i>
</sub>&rsqb;. (SE-passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>will be difficult the documents SE-to-accept-3pl</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In embedded infinitivals, preverbal subjects can only occupy the Spec, IP position, since the Spec, Top position is not available there:</p>
<p>(105)&ensp;<object id="tu94" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu94_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>*Vai ser dificil &lsqb;&lsqb;<b>esses documentos</b>&rsqb;, os tribunais aceitarem(-nos) <i>ec</i>&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) will be difficult those documents, the courts (to) accept-3pl(-them)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It will be difficult those documents, for the courts to accept (them).&rsquo; </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since the Spec, IP position, blocks the eventive-passive reading of SE-verbs (by virtue of the generalization in (102a)), this reading is unavailable in (104b).</p>
<p>Another relevant context is Aux-to-Comp: the position immediately on the right of Aux is of necessity Spec, IP, which can be occupied by the subject of analytic passives, but not by the subject of SE passives:</p>
<p>(106)&ensp;<object id="tu95" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu95_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Eu penso &lsqb;terem<sub>j</sub>&lsqb;&lsqb;os presos&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> <i>t</i><sub><i>j</i>
</sub> sido fuzilados t<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;. (copula passive)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) think (to)-have-3pl the prisoners been shot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;I think the prisoners were shot.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Eu penso &lsqb;terem-se<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;&lsqb;os presos&rsqb;<sub><i>j</i>
</sub> <i>t</i><sub><i>j</i>
</sub> fuzilado <i>t</i><sub><i>j</i>
</sub>&rsqb;. (passive SE)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(I) think (to) have-3pl-SE the prisoners shot</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Raposo and Uriagereka furthermore show that in eventive SE passives, the Topic DP cannot bind a trace in (Spec, IP). The argument relies on the distribution of bare NPs. As is well known, in Romance pro-drop languages, bare NPs (BNPs) cannot occupy the preverbal subject position (Spec, IP):</p>
<p>(107)&ensp;<object id="tu96" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu96_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>O Nestor compra salsichas no talho Sanzot. (BNP in object position)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the Nestor buys sausages at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Nestor buys sausages at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Salsichas sao compradas no talho Sanzot. (BNP in Spec, IP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages are bought at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages are bought at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Salsichas custam caro no talho Sanzot. (BNP in Spec, IP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages cost expensive at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages are expensive at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Dislocated bare NPs are allowed only if they bind the object position (see (108a)). The ungrammaticality of (108b&ndash;c) indicates that the dislocated subjects (marked by the comma intonation) of analytic passives and of unergatives bind a trace in &lsqb;Spec, Infl&rsqb;, which is illegitimate:</p>
<p>(108)&ensp;<object id="tu97" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu97_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Salsichas, o Nestor compra <b>ec</b> no talho Sanzot. (trace in object position)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages, the Nestor buys at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages, Nestor buys at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>*Salsichas, <b>ec</b> sao compradas <i>t</i> no talho Sanzot. (intermediate trace in Spec, IP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages, are bought at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages, (they) are bought at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>*Salsichas, <b>ec</b> custam caro no talho Sanzot. (intermediate trace in Spec, IP)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages, cost expensive at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages, (they) are expensive at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The grammaticality of (109b) indicates that the dislocated subject of SE passives does not necessarily bind a trace in (Spec, IP), but may be directly coindexed with the object position:</p>
<p>(109)&ensp;<object id="tu98" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu98_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>Vendem-se salsichas no talho Sanzot. (BNP in obj position)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sell-3pl-SE sausages at-the butcher-shop Sanzot</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages are sold at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Salsichas, vendem-se <b>ec</b> no talho Sanzot.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>sausages, sell-3pl-SE at-the butcher-shop Sanzot.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Sausages, (they) are sold at the Sanzot butcher-shop.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Further evidence in favor of Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s generalization is provided by parasitic gaps (which we do not review here), and by the position of the subject DP relative to other left-peripheral DPs. The left periphery of European Portuguese contains at least three positions, as indicated in (110). Each one of these slots may, but need not, be instantiated:</p>
<p>(110)&ensp;&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub> <b>def DP</b> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>specFocP</sub> <b><i>wh</i>-phrases</b> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub> <b>canonical subject</b>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;</p>
<p>With the eventive-passive SE, the preverbal subject cannot occupy the Spec, IP position (see (111b)); it is either in &lsqb;Spec, Top&rsqb;, as in (111a), or in (Spec, Foc), as in (112), depending on whether it is a definite DP or a focused constituent (<i>wh</i>-phrase, emphatic operator):</p>
<p>(111)&ensp;<object id="tu99" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu99_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub>&lsqb;<b>Esses livros</b>&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> &lsqb;<sub>specFocP</sub>&lsqb;so numa loja&rsqb;<sub>k</sub> &lsqb;<sub>IP/I&prime;</sub> se vendem ec<sub>i</sub> ec<sub>k</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>those books only at-one store SE-sell-3pl</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Those books only at a (particular) store are sold.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;<sub>specFP</sub>&lsqb;So numa loja&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>&lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub> &lsqb;<b>esses livros</b>&rsqb;<sub>i</sub> se vendem ec<sub>i</sub> ec<sub>k</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>only at-on store those books SE-sell-3pl</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(112)&ensp;<object id="tu100" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu100_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub> A Maria, &lsqb;<sub>spec FP</sub> <b>&lsqb;quantos presentes&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>
</b> &lsqb;<sub>spec IP</sub> &lsqb;se deram ec<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>to-the Mary, how-many presents SE-gave-3pl</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;To Mary, how many presents were given?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub> A Maria, &lsqb;<sub>specFP</sub><b>&lsqb;muitos presentes&rsqb;<sub>i</sub>
</b> &lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub> &lsqb;se deram ec<sub>i</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>to-the Mary, many presents SE-gave-3pl</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;To Mary, many presents were given.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The example in (111c) shows that the subject of analytic passives can occupy Spec, IP:</p>
<p>(111)&ensp;<object id="tu101" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu101_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specFP</sub>So numa loja &lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub> <b>esses livros</b> sao vendidos&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>only at one store those books are sold (subject of copula passive SE in Spec, IP)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In sum, Raposo and Uriagereka provide clear evidence showing that the preverbal subject of eventive-passive SE does not sit in (Spec, IP), nor does it bind a trace in (Spec, IP). It sits in a left-peripheral position and entertains a direct relation with a VP-internal position. This behavior of passive SE contrasts with analytic passives, as well as with SE-reflexives.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss49" level="3">
<heading id="h48" level="3">5.2.2&ensp;Middle SE</heading>
<p>The behavior of middle SE was not examined by Raposo and Uriagereka. One may simply guess that middle SE contrasts with passive SE and behaves on a par with reflexives. By using the tests provided by Raposo and Uriagereka themselves, it can indeed be shown that middle SE allows its subject to sit in Spec, IP.</p>
<p>In contrast with eventive-passive SE, middle SE allows its subject to be in the preverbal position in inflected infinitivals, and this position can only be analyzed as being Spec, IP (compare example (104b)):</p>
<p>(113)&ensp;<object id="tu102" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu102_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>vai ser dificil esta luz ver-se de longe</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) will be difficult this light see(inflected)- SE from afar</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>vai ser dificil este lindo vestido lavar-se facilmente</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(it) will be difficult this beautiful dress wash-SE easily </entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(examples provided by Joao Costa, p.c.)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Note furthermore that the preverbal subject of middle SE may occur to the right of an extracted adjunct, in which case it can only sit in (Spec, IP). Middle SE thus patterns with reflexives and analytic passives and contrasts with eventive passive SE:</p>
<p>(114)&ensp;<object id="tu103" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu103_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTop</sub>Em que momento do espect&aacute;culo&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub>a luz&rsqb; se viu bem?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>at what moment of the show the light SE saw well</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Joao Costa, p.c.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTop</sub>Em que momento da opera&ccedil;ao&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub>os especialistas&rsqb; se consultaram?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>at what moment of the operation the specialists consulted each other</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&ne; at what moment of the operation the specialists were consulted</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Given the data just reviewed, Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s generalization should be revised as follows:</p>
<p>(115)&ensp;<object id="tu104" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu104_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
<b>Revision of Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s generalization:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specIP</sub>DP&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>I&prime;</sub> se V .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb; &rArr; OK middle, *eventive-passive</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<sub>specTopP</sub>DP&rsqb; &lsqb;<sub>IP</sub> &lsqb;<sub>I&prime;</sub> se V .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;&lsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb; &rArr; OK eventive passive</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss50" level="2">
<heading id="h49" level="2">5.3&ensp;A unifying analysis of European Portuguese and French</heading>
<p>The data in European Portuguese summarized in (115a&ndash;b) bring to mind Ruwet&apos;s generalization (see (101)):</p>
<p>(116)&ensp;Just as in French, a preverbal DP sitting in (Spec, IP) triggers the middle/generic reading of passive SE constructions. The eventive-passive reading is blocked.</p>
<p>Because European Portuguese is a pro-drop language, preverbal subjects do not necessarily sit in Spec, IP, but may be in Spec, Top or Spec, Focus instead. These positions do not induce the interpretive constraint characteristic of Spec, IP. We may thus conclude that French and European Portuguese illustrate two particular instantiations of one and the same constraint on passive SE configurations.</p>
<subsection id="ss51" level="3">
<heading id="h50" level="3">5.3.1&ensp;Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s explanation</heading>
<p>Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s explanation basically amounts to the idea that the Spec, IP position is made unavailable by the eventive-passive SE. Raposo and Uriagereka follow <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>) in assuming that the eventive-passive SE is marked as &plus;arg and is an &lsquo;&lsqb;NP, IP&rsqb;&rsquo; clitic, which as such fills &ndash; at some point in the derivation &ndash; the &lsqb;NP, IP&rsqb; position: SE goes to (Spec, v&prime;) and from there to (Spec, IP), thus rendering this position unavailable for the internal argument to raise to. This account is problematic insofar as it basically amounts to assuming that a passivizing morpheme, here SE, is a subject clitic (see sections 3.4 and 4 above).</p>
<p>The contrast between the middle and the eventive-passive reading is not explicitly brought up by Raposo and Uriagereka. Within their account, the behavior of middle SE can only be analyzed as being due to its inherent features: in contrast with passive SE, middle SE does not need to go to Spec, IP. Thus, in order to account for the contrast between passive and middle SE, Raposo and Uriagereka would have to postulate lexical homophony: passive SE and middle SE would be two inherently distinct elements, much as in <link rid="b1">Cinque (1988</link>).<link rid="fn52">
<sup>52</sup></link> The problem is that there is no evidence &ndash; other than the data we try to explain &ndash; in favor of a distinction between passive and middle SE. In particular, they both trigger &lsquo;agreement with the object&rsquo; (this is Raposo and Uriagereka&apos;s term, which in fact refers to the overt subject, corresponding to an underlying Theme), which is the criterion that Raposo and Uriagereka choose for distinguishing eventive-passive (their &lsquo;indefinite&rsquo;) SE from the &lsquo;impersonal&rsquo; (i.e., nominative) SE.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss52" level="3">
<heading id="h51" level="3">5.3.2&ensp;An alternative line of inquiry</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b67 b88">Dobrovie-Sorin (2004, forthcoming</link>) proposes an explanation based on the idea that the &lsquo;syntactic activity&rsquo; of the Agent (which is necessary for the passive reading to obtain) of SE-verbs is possible only if the internal argument occupies the object position. Under this view, the passive reading of accusative SE is blocked not because passive SE itself goes to Spec, IP, but rather because this position must remain empty in order for the Agent to be present at Logical Form.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss53" level="1">
<heading id="h52" level="1">NOTES</heading>
<p>
<span id="fn1">
<number>1&emsp;</number>To this day, <link rid="b8">Kayne (1975</link>) and <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) remain the best references on the problem stated in (i), both for the detail of the empirical description and for insights regarding the analysis. For (iii) the reader is referred to <link rid="b68">Giorgi (1991</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn2">
<number>2&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b6">Zubizarreta (1987</link>) and <link rid="b4">Belletti (1982</link>) distinguish reflexives from middle-passive SE: the latter, but not the former, would absorb the external theta-role. <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) analyzes middle-passive SE as a particular instantiation of subject/nominative SE. Cinque adopts this analysis for impersonal and habitual passive SE (<i>Dans cette maison, la Bible se lit tous les jours</i> &lsquo;In this house, the Bible SE reads every day&rsquo;), but departs from Burzio in assuming that the property interpretation of middles (<i>Ce livre se lit facilement</i> &lsquo;This book SE-reads easily&rsquo;) relies on accusative SE. Within Cinque&apos;s typology, impersonal passives (including habitual passives) rely on a nominative &plus;arg SE, whereas middles rely on an accusative &minus;arg SE.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn3">
<number>3&emsp;</number>The morphological identity shown by passives, anticausatives, and reflexives is widespread across unrelated language families, such as Indo-European, Uto-Aztecan, Athapaskan, Turkic, Ethiopian Semitic, and Dravidian (<link rid="b69 b70">Haspelmath 1987, 1990</link>; <link rid="b71">Kemmer 1993</link>; <link rid="b72">Geniu&scaron;en&#x0117; 1987</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn4">
<number>4&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b49">Perlmutter&apos;s (1978</link>) unaccusatives were called &lsquo;ergatives&rsquo; by <link rid="b25 b7">Burzio (1981, 1986</link>). Because it may cause confusion (by unduly bringing to mind &lsquo;ergative&rsquo; languages), this terminology will be avoided here.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn5">
<number>5&emsp;</number>In order to simplify the glosses, the verb <i>&ecirc;tre</i> &lsquo;be&rsquo; will be translated as <i>have</i> whenever it functions as a perfect auxiliary.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn6">
<number>6&emsp;</number>For the claim that unergatives and unaccusatives can be distinguished in terms of internal/external causation see also <link rid="b73">Levin and Rappaport (1995</link>), who attribute the main insight to <link rid="b74">Smith (1970</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn7">
<number>7&emsp;</number>Labelle further assumes that in SE-inchoatives the external role (the one to which is attributed &lsquo;responsibility&rsquo; for the change) is discharged by SE itself, which would be generated in the (Spec, VP) position, leaving the Spec, IP slot available for the externalization of the internal argument (1992: 395). This proposal, which suffers from the problems brought up in <link rid="ss21">section 3</link> below, is not crucial for Labelle&apos;s main proposal.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn8">
<number>8&emsp;</number>Crucial to Burzio&apos;s view is the idea that SE is not a pronoun, but rather an unaccusativity marker. The &lsquo;affixal&rsquo; nature of SE is less central: being an unaccusativity marker does not force a given element to be an affix (completely bound morpheme), but is compatible with it being a clitic (&lsquo;semi-bound&rsquo; morpheme, or &lsquo;syntactic affix&rsquo; in <link rid="b75">Anderson&apos;s 1992</link> terms), or a weak pronoun (cf. Dutch <i>zich</i>-anaphors). Conversely, affixes (e.g., agreement morphemes on the verb) may function as pronouns, by virtue of binding an empty category of type <i>pro.</i>
</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn9">
<number>9&emsp;</number>In Italian, the embedded verb may be interpreted as reflexive in the absence of SE:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu105" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu105_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">(i)</entry>
<entry>Questo far&agrave; &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub>pentire Giovanni&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this will make &lsqb;repent John&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;This will make John repent himself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Maria ha fatto &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub>accusare Piero&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary has made &lsqb;accuse Peter&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary made Peter accuse himself.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>The fact that SE cannot surface in Italian examples such as (i&ndash;ii) thus seems to be due not to a constraint on the compatibility between the syntactic operations underlying causatives and reflexives, but rather to a morphological constraint on SE-placement in Italian causatives. <link rid="b9">Pesetsky (1995</link>: 99&ndash;100) suggests that the disappearance of SE in Italian causatives and the disappearance of SE in nominalizations (in all Romance languages) are due to the same constraint. The generalization would be that the lexicalization of the &plus;reflexive feature is blocked by derivational morphemes. French and Spanish causatives, which allow reflexives, would have to be analyzed as syntactic causatives, whereas their Italian counterparts would be morphological causatives.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn10">
<number>10&emsp;</number>According to <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 140, 406), the verb <i>be</i> as a perfect-marker is triggered, in both French and Italian, by the co-indexation relation that holds between SE and the subject position. Because both accusative SE and dative SE are co-indexed with the subject position, <i>be</i> is used as a perfect marker in both cases. Note, however, that dative SE differs from accusative SE in not allowing agreement on the past participle, despite <i>be</i>-selection. With accusative SE, past participle agreement is <i>obligatory</i> (compare the optional agreement triggered by accusative clitics):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu106" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu106_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>Marie s&rsquo;est d&eacute;crite aux enfants.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE HAS described-femin. to the children</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Marie l&rsquo;a d&eacute;crite aux enfants.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary her has described-femin. to the children</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(iii)</entry>
<entry>Marie s&rsquo;est souvenu/*souvenue de Jean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE-HAS recalled-unmarked/*recalled-fem. of John</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(iv)</entry>
<entry>Marie s&rsquo;est dit/*dite qu&rsquo;elle n&rsquo;aimait plus Jean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE-HAS said-unmarked/*said-femin that she no longer loved John</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(v)</entry>
<entry>Marie s&rsquo;est maudite/*maudit d&rsquo;avoir laisser mourir Jean.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Mary SE-HAS blamed-unmarked/*blamed-femin. for having let die John</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>The dissociation between <i>be</i>-selection and past participle agreement is analyzed by Burzio as indicating that past participle agreement is not triggered by the co-indexation between SE and the subject, but rather by the presence of an NP-chain. Accusative SE relies on an NP-movement chain, but dative SE does not (<link rid="b7">Burzio 1986</link>: 406).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn11">
<number>11&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) shows that dative SE cannot be subsumed under the unaccusative analysis, but functions instead as an object clitic.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn12">
<number>12&emsp;</number>According to <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>), middle-passive SE is not an unaccusativity marker, but rather a particular type of subject clitic. Evidence against this view will be presented in sections 3.4 and 4 below.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn13">
<number>13&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b6">Zubizarreta&apos;s (1987</link>) proposal is a mixed lexicalist-syntactic approach, according to which SE is a verbal operator that is inserted either at L-R (the lexico-syntactic level of lexical representation, to be kept distinct from the lexico-semantic level, notated S-R) or at S-structure, which would result in middle and reflexive interpretations, respectively. Although Zubizarreta herself assimilates SE to A&prime;-operators, this hypothesis does not seem to play any role in her approach, and in fact her notion of &lsquo;verbal operator&rsquo; seems closer to that of voice-marker or argument-change marker.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn14">
<number>14&emsp;</number>Note that given the unergative analysis of SE-reflexives advocated by <link rid="b10">Reinhart and Siloni (2004</link>), the representations in (19a) and (19a&prime;) should be viewed as pertaining to a level of representation other than S-structure.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn15">
<number>15&emsp;</number>The particular choice that predicates make between (19a) and (19b) is a matter of lexical semantics: some verbs may take the option in (19a), others the one in (19b) and yet other verbs may allow either option (cf. <i>aimer</i> &lsquo;love&rsquo;, <i>casser</i> &lsquo;break&rsquo;, and <i>laver</i> &lsquo;wash&rsquo;, respectively).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn16">
<number>16&emsp;</number>Note that French <i>il</i>-impersonals do not rely on the chain configuration in (19b):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu107" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu107_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">(i)</entry>
<entry>Il<sub>j</sub> s<sub>i</sub>&rsquo;est traduit trois romans<sub>i</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IL SE HAS translated three novels</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Three novels were translated.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>
<link rid="b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b, 1998</link>) suggests that a chain of the type in (19b) is formed at LF, after expletive replacement (required by <link rid="b76">Chomsky&apos;s 1986a</link> Full Interpretation Principle) by the raised DP.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn17">
<number>17&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>) suggests that her characterization of SE can be restated in reflexivity terms (<link rid="b77">Reinhart and Reuland 1993</link>). SE can be assumed to be a reflexive marker if the definition of reflexive predicates is changed: a reflexive predicate would be one in which two argument <i>positions</i> (rather than two theta-roles) are co-indexed. This suggestion is, however, problematic, because the notions of reflexive marker and reflexive predicate are designed in such a way that they are distinct from &lsquo;simplex expression anaphors&rsquo; such as <i>zich</i>. Now, although SE differs from <i>zich</i> in being unable to be long-distance bound, it resembles <i>zich</i> insofar as both SE and <i>zich</i> can be markers of &lsquo;inherent reflexivity&rsquo; (in <link rid="b78">Everaert&apos;s 1986b</link> terms) or &lsquo;unaccusativity&rsquo;, unlike <i>zichself</i>. A careful rethinking of the properties of SE in terms of reflexivity theory remains to be developed.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn18">
<number>18&emsp;</number>We will leave aside the &lsquo;intensifying&rsquo; use of dative SE, which is found in colloquial Spanish:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu108" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu108_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)&ensp;</entry>
<entry>Juan se baila tangos, rumbas, chotis: lo que sea.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE dances tangos, rumbas, chotis: whatever there is</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Juan se escribe cien versos al dia.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE writes (one) hundred verses a day</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>This type of SE is subject to a syntactic constraint that also holds for benefactives: it can be used only if a direct object is present.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn19">
<number>19&emsp;</number>Note, however, that (the trace of) <i>&icirc;</i>&#x015F;<i>i</i> cannot be bound by the subject of raising verbs:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu109" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu109_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>Copiii t&#x01CE;i &icirc;&#x015F;i p&#x01CE;reau s&#x01CE; fie ferici tcedil;i.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>your children SE<sub>dat</sub> seemed that &lsqb;they&rsqb; be happy</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>?*Copiii t&#x01CE;i &icirc;&#x015F;i p&#x01CE;reau ferici tcedil;i.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>your children SE<sub>dat</sub> seemed happy</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>This ungrammaticality might be due to a different constraint: a reflexive dative and its antecedent must be co-arguments.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn20">
<number>20&emsp;</number>The Romanian data are somewhat complex, due to the use of prepositional accusatives and clitic doubling, which are both obligatory for proper names. These phenomena are irrelevant here.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn21">
<number>21&emsp;</number>The correlation between being a pro-drop language and having nominative SE was suggested by <link rid="b4">Belletti (1982</link>). This correlation holds for French but not for Romanian.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn22">
<number>22&emsp;</number>The German example in (41) has a generic reading, whereas the Romanian examples in (40) refer to particular events. Note, however, that the impossibility of particular time reference is not peculiar to the <i>sich</i> that combines with unergatives, but characterizes the passivizing use of <i>sich</i> in general:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu110" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu110_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>*Dieses Buch hat sich gestern gelesen.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this book HAS SICH yesterday read</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Dieses Buch liest sich angenehm.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>this book reads SICH with pleasure</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>
<span id="fn23">
<number>23&emsp;</number>A conceptually similar analysis can be found in <link rid="b49">Perlmutter (1978</link>), who argues against the spontaneous demotion of the Agent and proposes instead that impersonal passives rely on the advancement of a dummy, an operation that is the relational grammar counterpart of the NP-movement of a null object in GB theory.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn24">
<number>24&emsp;</number>Under this view, unergatives do not differ from transitives by their subcategorization properties (both types of verbs may, but are not obliged to, take a direct object), but only by their selectional requirements: unergatives select a cognate object, which as such need not be projected in the syntax, whereas transitives normally select fully referential objects, which must be syntactically realized; some transitives can be construed as having prototypical objects (e.g., <i>eat</i>, <i>drink</i>, <i>write</i>, etc.), which are not lexicalized; those transitives that do not allow for prototypical objects must lexicalize their object (e.g., <i>observe</i>, <i>consider</i>, <i>discover</i>, etc.). In sum, the borderline between unergatives and transitives is less clear cut than is usually assumed, which explains why this distinction is not grammaticalized in well-described languages (compare the <i>be</i>/<i>have</i> alternation that distinguishes unaccusatives on the one hand from transitives and unergatives on the other hand).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn25">
<number>25&emsp;</number>Dummy null cognate objects may be assumed to be assigned a quasi theta-role (see <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin 1998</link>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn26">
<number>26&emsp;</number>Depending on the particular definition of passivisation that one may adopt, the reason may be that (i) the &lsquo;absorption&rsquo; of accusative Case &ndash; which is imposed by passivisation &ndash; cannot apply vacuously (<link rid="b79">Jaeggli 1986a</link>) &ndash; in other words, passivisation cannot apply because there is no accusative Case to absorb; or (ii) unaccusatives have no external role, and passivization can apply only if there is an external role to be suspended.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn27">
<number>27&emsp;</number>Similar contrasts between Romanian and French arise regarding verbs that take idiomatic and sentential complements. The French examples in (iia&ndash;c) have the same glosses as the Romanian examples in (ia&ndash;c):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu111" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu111_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="8">(i)</entry>
<entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>S-a luat loc imediat.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has taken place immediately</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Place was taken immediately.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Li s-a dat ap&#x01CE; la moar&#x01CE;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>to-them SE-HAS given water to the mill</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;They were given favorable evidence.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>S-a spus/descoperit/declarat c&#x01CE; Ion e nebun.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has said/discovered/declared that John is crazy</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It was said/discovered/declared that John was crazy.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">(ii)</entry>
<entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Il s&rsquo;est pris place imm&eacute;diatement.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Il s&rsquo;est donn&eacute; de l&rsquo;eau &agrave; leur moulin.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*Il s&rsquo;est dit/d&eacute;couvert/d&eacute;clar&eacute; que Jean &eacute;tait irresponsable.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>For lack of space we restrict our attention to the contrast concerning unergatives. A detailed discussion of the other data can be found in <link rid="b34">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b</link>, <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 5 - Affectedness.xml" type="file">chapter 5</externallink></related>).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn28">
<number>28&emsp;</number>The reader may have noticed that the examples in (49) are constructed with unergatives that subcategorize a PrepP. With unergatives that do not subcategorize PrepPs, the passive is somewhat less acceptable (the presence of a modifier is obligatory):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu112" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu112_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>?Ensuite, il a &eacute;t&eacute; couru jusqu&rsquo;&agrave; la gare.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>then, IL was run to the station</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>?Mais, il a &eacute;t&eacute; dormi dans ce lit r&eacute;cemment.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>but, IL has been slept in this bed recently</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>For discussion see <link rid="b34">Dobrovie-Sorin (1994b</link>).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn29">
<number>29&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b80">Haider (1985b</link>), <link rid="b81">Haider and Rindler-Schjerve (1987</link>), and <link rid="b42 b34 b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1986, 1994b, 1998</link>) are isolated exceptions.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn30">
<number>30&emsp;</number>French SE-verbs are ambiguous between passive and middle readings. Adverbs such as <i>facilement</i> &lsquo;easily&rsquo; are only compatible with the middle reading, which in turn is incompatible with control into a final clause. If <i>facilement</i> is suppressed, the example becomes grammatical, but it loses the middle reading.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn31">
<number>31&emsp;</number>See also <link rid="b55">Williams (1985</link>) and <link rid="b82">Lasnik (1988</link>), who argue that the PRO subject of final clauses need not be controlled by a DP argument, but may be controlled by an event.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn32">
<number>32&emsp;</number>These examples become grammatical if the embedded verb undergoes SE-passivization:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu113" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu113_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="2">(i)</entry>
<entry>&Icirc;n unele studii s-a &icirc;ncercat a se reface istoria politic&#x01CE; &#x015F;i social&#x01CE;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>in certain essays SE has tried to SE reconstruct the political and social history.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;In certain essays it was tried for the political and social history to be reconstructed.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Se sper&#x01CE; a se ajunge la cap&#x01CE;tul drumului.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE hopes to SE arrive at the end of the road</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It is hoped that the end of the road will be arrived at.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">(iii)</entry>
<entry>S-a &icirc;nceput a se  tcedil;ine seama de nevoile tuturor.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has started to SE take into account everybody&apos;s needs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It was started that everybody&apos;s needs be taken care of.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">(iv)</entry>
<entry>S-a promis a se respecta dispozi tcedil;iile.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SE-has promised to SE obey the instructions</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It was promised that the instructions will be obeyed.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>As indicated by the glosses, both occurrences of SE are interpreted as SE-passives. No ungrammaticality arises, since the verb in the main clause does not function as a control verb: as for any passivized verb, its external argument is suspended and its only argument is the embedded clause itself. We may now wonder why a similar analysis is ruled out for the examples in (54): why is it not possible to analyze the SE in the main clause as an instance of passive SE? The answer is that the embedded verb is in the active form, and as such projects a null subject, which needs to be controlled, a requirement that cannot be satisfied because passive SE cannot function as a legitimate controller. Compare (i&ndash;iv), where the embedded clause contains a SE-passive: the external argument has been suspended, thus suspending the need for control.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn33">
<number>33&emsp;</number>Cinque tries to solve this problem by assuming that his &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; nominative SE binds a non-referential trace in Spec, IP, which as such is unable to function as a syntactic controller. This peculiarity of &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; nominative SE conflicts with the currently observed behavior of nominative clitics, which qualify as syntactic controllers. This is indeed what we find with Cinque&apos;s &minus;arg nominative SE, which according to Dobrovie-Sorin (1988) is the only truly nominative SE (see <link rid="ss29">section 4</link> below).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn34">
<number>34&emsp;</number>Pronominal clitics exist that are specified for a designated grammatical function (e.g., nominative, dative, or accusative), but not for a particular theta-role.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn35">
<number>35&emsp;</number>Adopting a suggestion by <link rid="b76">Chomsky (1986a</link>: 217), Cinque argues that the two chains in (57) are allowed to overlap because they belong to distinct types: one of them is a theta-chain, whereas the other is an expletive&ndash;argument pair. One can thus maintain the ban on overlapping theta-chains, while allowing overlapping CHAINs (this notion covers both expletive&ndash;argument pairs and theta-chains).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn36">
<number>36&emsp;</number>This proposal unduly identifies the absorption of the external theta-role by a nominative clitic &ndash; which is in fact a particular kind of syntactic realization of the external role, a process that <i>does not suspend</i> accusative Case &ndash; with the suspension of the external theta-role by a passivizing morpheme, which blocks the syntactic realization of the external role in the canonical subject position and correlates with the suspension of accusative Case. To make this point clear, consider nominative clitics or even agreeement morphemes. One may assume that they absorb/retain/withhold the external theta-role, but one must ensure that the (Spec, IP) position vacated by nominative clitics/agreement morphemes is <i>not</i> available for a DP that carries the Theme-role (correlatively, accusative Case <i>is</i> available). Otherwise, we would expect nominative clitics, as well as subject-agreement morphemes, to function (at least optionally, but maybe necessarily) as passivizing morphemes, which they do not. In sum, nominative clitics cannot be passivizers because they are syntactic realizations of the external role, which blocks the externalization (encoded as NP-movement in GB theory) of the internal role.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn37">
<number>37&emsp;</number>
<link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>: 144&ndash;148) himself observes that French middle-passive <i>se</i> contrasts with Italian nominative <i>si</i>: whereas the latter behaves as a pronominal subject clitic, the former behaves as a lexical affix (cf. inchoative and inherent SE), which as such cannot be affected by subject raising:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu114" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu114_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>*Il se semble construire beaucoup d&rsquo;immeubles.</entry>
<entry>French</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>it SE seems (to) build many buildings</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>
<span id="fn38">
<number>38&emsp;</number>A detailed review of <link rid="b1">Cinque&apos;s (1988</link>) analysis can be found in <link rid="b2">Dobrovie-Sorin (1998</link>). Let us simply mention here that Cinque differs from Burzio insofar as Cinque distinguishes between middle and passive SE, which would be marked as accusative and nominative, respectively.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn39">
<number>39&emsp;</number>Although <link rid="b7">Burzio (1986</link>) himself is of course fully aware of Restructuring phenomena, he does not subsume examples of <i>si</i>-raising under Restructuring.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn40">
<number>40&emsp;</number>Mendikoetxa and Battye (1990) assume that nominative and accusative SE head AGRsP and AGRoP, respectively. However, the Spec positions of these projections are not related to SE, since these authors assume that the external role is not absorbed, but merely suspended by SE.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn41">
<number>41&emsp;</number>The idea that passives involve a null pronoun in Spec, VP is not integral to McGinnis&apos;s work on reflexives. In fact, she discarded this idea in later work: <link rid="b60 b83">McGinnis (1998, 2004</link>) does not treat passives as involving a &lsquo;pro&rsquo; external argument.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn42">
<number>42&emsp;</number>The two authors differ regarding the nature of the empty category controlled/identified by SE (PRO for Kayne and pro for Gu&eacute;ron), as well as regarding the position of this empty category. Both Kayne and Gu&eacute;ron allow the empty category identified by SE to be VP-adjoined, but they disagree on a further possible position: according to Gu&eacute;ron, subject SE binds a pro in a right-hand-generated (Spec, IP) position, whereas Kayne assumes that SE may occupy (Spec, VP). Since for Kayne&apos;s views we can only rely on lectures of the 1980s and on a short (1986) abstract, we will concentrate here on the syntactic side of <link rid="b29">Gu&eacute;ron&apos;s (1991</link>) analysis, leaving aside its semantic part, which was not taken up in the subsequent literature on SE.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn43">
<number>43&emsp;</number>The fact that a dative-marked reflexive does not trigger passivization is clearly indicated by Romanian. Examples such as (i), which contain dative reflexives, can only be interpreted as containing goal or benefactive reflexive pronouns:</span>
</p>
<object id="tu115" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu115_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>Ion &icirc;&#x015F;i trimite c&#x01CE;r tcedil;i po&#x015F;tale.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>John SE<sub>Dat</sub> sends postcards</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>Conversely, a dative reflexive cannot appear in the Romanian counterparts of French examples of the type in (63):</p>
<object id="tu116" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu116_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Merele se m&#x01CE;n&icirc;nc&#x01CE; toamna.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>apples-the SE<sub>Accus</sub> eat in &lsqb;the&rsqb; autumn</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(iii)</entry>
<entry>*Merele &icirc;&#x015F;i m&#x01CE;n&icirc;nc&#x01CE; toamna.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>apples-the SE<sub>Dat</sub> eat in &lsqb;the&rsqb; the autumn</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>
<span id="fn44">
<number>44&emsp;</number>There seems to be no reason to believe that in an example such as (i), the Friulan subject clitic <i>al</i> is ambiguous (between the &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb; and the &lsqb;&minus;arg&rsqb; features), whereas in (ii&ndash;iii) it is non-ambiguous (being compatible only with the &lsqb;&minus;arg&rsqb; feature). The examples are due to <link rid="b84 b85">Poletto (1991, 1993</link>):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu117" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu117_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>Al duar.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;He sleeps.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>Al ven duman.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;He will come tomorrow.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(iii)</entry>
<entry>Al e staat vist.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;He has been seen.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>The only plausible analysis is that in all these examples <i>al</i> is a referential clitic. Compare (iv&ndash;vi), where <i>al</i> is quasi-argumental or expletive:</p>
<object id="tu118" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu118_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(iv)</entry>
<entry>Al pluof.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;It rains.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(v)</entry>
<entry>al par che . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;it seems that.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">(vi)</entry>
<entry>Al ven Toni.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;There will come Toni.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>It thus seems clear that Cinque&apos;s &lsqb;&plus;arg&rsqb;/&lsqb; &minus;arg&rsqb; distinction cannot be identified with the well-established distinction between referential and expletive subject clitics.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn45">
<number>45&emsp;</number>Given this analysis, Italian examples of the type <i>SE V</i><sub><i>unerg</i>
</sub> (see (71)) are indeed ambiguous, as suggested by Cinque himself, but the ambiguity is not one between two types of nominative SE but rather one between a nominative SE and a passivizing accusative SE.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn46">
<number>46&emsp;</number>Cinque&apos;s assumption that a nominative passive <i>si</i> exists can be traced back to <link rid="b7">Burzio&apos;s (1986</link>: 48)) proposal, to the effect that certain passive <i>si</i>s bear both accusative and nominative Case.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn47">
<number>47&emsp;</number>Regarding control into adjunct clauses, see <link rid="ss23">section 3.2</link> above.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn48">
<number>48&emsp;</number>Existing analyses of nominative clitics, bearing in particular on Italian dialects, do not provide any counter-example to this generalization, which has, however, not been derived as a consequence of theoretical principles.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn49">
<number>49&emsp;</number>That overt agreement morphology rather than finiteness is required by nominative SE is clear when one considers Portuguese: it is because this language has infinitivals inflected for AGR features that the Portuguese counterparts of the examples in (64) are grammatical (see <link rid="b1">Cinque 1988</link>: 531&ndash;533).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn50">
<number>50&emsp;</number>The generalization in (98) has to be qualified in view of some French examples due to <link rid="b44">Zribi-Hertz (1982</link>):</span>
</p>
<object id="tu119" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu119_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="11">(i)</entry>
<entry morerows="2">a.</entry>
<entry>La question s&rsquo;est discut&eacute;e hier dans la salle du conseil.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the issue SE HAS discussed yesterday in the council hall</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The issue was discussed yesterday in the council hall.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry>Le crime s&rsquo;est commis ce matin.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the crime SE HAS committed this morning</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The crime was committed this morning.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">c.</entry>
<entry>L&rsquo;op&eacute;ration s&rsquo;est effectu&eacute;e hier.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the operation SE HAS carried out yesterday</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The operation was carried out yesterday.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">d.</entry>
<entry>Le point s&rsquo;est soulev&eacute; hier &agrave; la r&eacute;union.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>the point SE HAS raised yesterday at the meeting</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;The point was raised yesterday at the meeting.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
<p>We will leave these exceptions aside.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn51">
<number>51&emsp;</number>Raposo and Uriagereka furthermore show that in order for the eventive passive reading to survive, the topicalized DP should not transit through Spec, IP.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn52">
<number>52&emsp;</number>Although Raposo and Uriagereka do not follow Cinque in characterizing passive SE as a nominative clitic, it is difficult to see how an &lsquo;&lsqb;NP, IP&rsqb;&rsquo; clitic, which &lsquo;must go to Spec, IP&rsquo;, could avoid being marked with nominative Case.</span>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss54" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h53" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>&Aring;farli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tor<x> </x>A<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Norwegian Passive Constructions<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b75" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Anderson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Stephen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="book">A-Morphous Morphology</title>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b47" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Incorporation: A Theory of Grammatical Function Changing</title>
<x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b54" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Kyle</forenames><x> </x><surname>Johnson</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Roberts</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive Arguments Raised</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">219&ndash;251</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Belletti</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Adriana</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Morphological Passive and Pro-Drop: The Impersonal Construction in Italian</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Linguistic Research</title><x> </x><volume>2/4</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1&ndash;34</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bernard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Georges</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1971">1971</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). La Transitivit&eacute; en Fran&ccedil;ais Contemporain</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>PhD dissertation, University of Rennes</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bouchard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Denis</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="book">On the Content of Empty Categories<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Burston</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jack<x> </x>L<x>.</x>
</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1979">1979</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Pronominal Verb Construction in French: An Argument Against the Fortuitous Homonimy Hypothesis</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Lingua</title><x> </x><volume>48</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">147&ndash;176</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Burzio</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Intransitive Verbs and Italian Auxiliaries</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>PhD dissertation, MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Burzio</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Italian Syntax: A Government-Binding Approach</title>
<x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b62" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cardinaletti</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anna</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Impersonal Constructions and Sentential Arguments in German</title>
<x>. </x><address>Padua</address><x>: </x><publisher>Unipress.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Castelfranchi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Cristiano</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Domenico</forenames><x> </x><surname>Parisi</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Towards One <i>Si</i>
</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Italian Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">83&ndash;121</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chierchia</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gennaro</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Anaphora and Attitudes De Se</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Semantics and Contextual Expression</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Renate</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bartsch</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Johan<x> </x>van</forenames><x> </x><surname>Benthem</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter<x> </x>van<x> </x>Emde</forenames><x> </x><surname>Boas</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">1&ndash;32</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b51" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1965">1965</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Aspects of the Theory of Syntax<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b63" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Lectures on Government and Binding<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b76" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Barriers</title>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b61" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Minimalist Program<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cinque</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Guglielmo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On <i>Si-</i>Constructions and the Theory of Arb</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>19</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">521&ndash;581</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Couquaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Daniel</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1979">1979</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Sur la Syntaxe des Phrases Pr&eacute;dicatives en Fran&ccedil;ais</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguisticae Investigationes</title><x> </x><volume>III/2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">245&ndash;284</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Couquaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Daniel</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">French Predication and Linguistic Theory</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Levels of Syntactic Representations</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Koster</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">143&ndash;184</page>
<x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Propos du Contraste entre le Passif Morphologique et <i>Se</i> Moyen dans les Tours Impersonnels</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguisticae Investigationes</title><x> </x><volume>X/2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">289&ndash;330</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">&Agrave; Propos de la Structure du Groupe Nominal en Roumain</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Rivista di Grammatica Generativa</title><x> </x><volume>12</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">123&ndash;152</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Romanian: Comparative Studies in Romance</title>
<x>. </x><address>Berlin/New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Impersonal <i>Se</i> Constructions in Romance and the Passivization of Unergatives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>29/3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">399&ndash;438</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Eventive and Generic/Predicational Readings of <i>Se</i>-Passives. GLOW abstract</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b67" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2004">2004</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Implicit Agentivity without Agents in the Syntax: A Crosslinguistic Analysis of SE-Verbs. Unpublished manuscript, University of Paris 7</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b88" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup>
<miscellaneoustext> (forthcoming)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<title type="document">Contraintes Syntaxiques sur l&rsquo;Agentivit&eacute; Implicite: L&rsquo;Interpr&eacute;tation des Verbes en SE dans les Langues Romanes</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="other">Actes du Colloque Repr&eacute;sentation du Sens, Montr&eacute;al, May 2003</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Ivan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Evrard</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</namegroup>
</reference>
<reference id="b78" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Everaert</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Reflexivization<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b57" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fellbaum</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Christiane</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Anne</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zribi-Hertz</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Middle Construction in French and English: A Comparative Study of its Syntax and Semantics</title>
<x>. </x><address>Bloomington</address><x>: </x><publisher>Indiana University Linguistics Club.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Folli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Raffaella</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Constructing Telicity in English and Italian</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>PhD dissertation, University of Oxford</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Folli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Raffaella</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Relation of Priority Between Causative and Inchoative Structures</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Romance Languages and Linguistics Theory, 1999</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Yves</forenames><x> </x><surname>D&rsquo;hulst</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Johan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rooryck</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Schroten</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">143&ndash;166</page>
<x>. </x><address>Amsterdam</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Forest</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">S&eacute;mantisme Ent&eacute;l&eacute;chique et Affinit&eacute; Descriptive: Pour une Reanalyse des Verbes Sym&eacute;triques ou Neutres du Fran&ccedil;ais</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Bulletin de la Soci&eacute;t&eacute; de Linguistique de Paris</title><x> </x><volume>83</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">87&ndash;148</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b72" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Geniu&scaron;en&#x0117;</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Emma</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Typology of Reflexives</title><x>. </x><address>Berlin</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b68" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Giorgi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alessandra</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Prepositions, Binding and Theta-Marking</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Long-Distance Anaphora</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Koster</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grimshaw</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Lexical Representation of Romance Reflexive Critics</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<title type="book">The Mental Representation of Grammatical Relations<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Joan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bresnan</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">87&ndash;148</page>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Grimshaw</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jane</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Argument Structure<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Gu&eacute;ron</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jacqueline</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Le Clitique SE et la Grammaire des Pronoms Ind&eacute;finis</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Grammaire G&eacute;n&eacute;rative et Syntaxe Compar&eacute;e</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jacqueline</forenames><x> </x><surname>Gu&eacute;ron</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jean-Yves</forenames><x> </x><surname>Pollock</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">191&ndash;213</page>
<x>. </x><address>Paris</address><x>: </x><publisher>Editions du CNRS.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b80" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haider</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hubert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">&Uuml;ber &lsquo;Sein&rsquo; und Nicht &lsquo;Sein&rsquo; zur Grammatik des Pronomens &lsquo;Sich&rsquo;</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Erkl&auml;rende Syntax des Deutschen</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Werner</forenames><x> </x><surname>Abraham</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">223&ndash;254</page>
<x>. </x><address>T&uuml;bingen</address><x>: </x><publisher>Narr.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b81" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haider</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hubert</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Rosita</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rindler-Schjerve</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Parameter of Auxiliary Selection</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>25</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1029&ndash;1055</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b50" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hale</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ken</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Samuel<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Keyser</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Argument Structure and the Lexical Expression of Syntactic Relations</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The View from Building 20: Essays in Linguistics in Honor of Sylvain Bromberger</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Ken</forenames><x> </x><surname>Hale</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Samuel<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Keyser</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">53&ndash;109</page>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b69" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haspelmath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Transitivity Alternations of the Anticausative Type</title><x>. </x><title type="other">Arbeitspapiere K&ouml;ln</title><x> </x><page type="first">5</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b70" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Haspelmath</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Grammaticization of Passive Morphology</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Studies in Language</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">25&ndash;71</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b56" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hoekstra</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Teun</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Roberts</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Middle Constructions in Dutch and English</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Knowledge and Language II: Lexical and Conceptual Structure</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Werner</forenames><x> </x><surname>Abraham</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">183&ndash;220</page>
<x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b45" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Hyams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Nina</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Language Acquisition and the Theory of Parameters<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b79" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jaeggli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Osvaldo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Passive</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">587&ndash;622</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1975">1975</date><x>). </x><title type="book">French Syntax: The Transformational Cycle</title>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name><x> (</x>
</namegroup>
<date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Romance <i>Se</i>/<i>Si</i>
</title><x>. </x><title type="other">GLOW Newsletter</title><x> </x><name type="author">
<surname>
</surname>
<forenames>20</forenames>
</name><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b71" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kemmer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Suzanne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Middle Voice</title>
<x>. </x><address>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</address><x>: </x><publisher>John Benjamins.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Labelle</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Marie</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Change of State and Valency</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Linguistics</title><x> </x><volume>28</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">375&ndash;414</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lagae</surname><x>, </x><forenames>V&eacute;ronique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Les Caract&eacute;ristiques Aspectuelles de la Construction R&eacute;flexive &lsquo;Ergative&rsquo;</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Travaux de Linguistique</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">23&ndash;42</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b82" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lasnik</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Howard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Subjects and the Th-Criterion</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">1&ndash;17</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b73" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Levin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Beth</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Malka<x> </x>Rappaport</forenames><x> </x><surname>Hovav</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Unaccusativity at the Syntax&ndash;Lexical Semantics Interface<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Manzini</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Maria<x> </x>Rita</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Italian Si</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Syntax of Pronominal Clitics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hagit</forenames><x> </x><surname>Borer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Marantz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Alec</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="book">On the Nature of Grammatical Relations<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Masullo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Pascual</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). La Interfaz L&eacute;xico-Sintaxis: Presencia y Ausencia del Cl&iacute;tico <i>Se</i> en Construcciones Inacusativas del Espa&ntilde;ol</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>Unpublished manuscript, Universidad Nacional del Comahue</publisher><x>, </x><address>Argentina</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b60" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McGinnis</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martha</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Locality in A-Movement</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>PhD dissertation, MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b83" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McGinnis</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Martha</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2004">2004</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Lethal Ambiguity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>35/1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">47&ndash;95</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Mendikoetxea</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Amaya</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Adrian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Battye</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Arb SE/SI in Transitive Contexts: A Comparative Study</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Rivista di Grammatica Generativa</title><x> </x><volume>15</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">161&ndash;195</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b46" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Naro</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anthony</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1976">1976</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Genesis of the Reflexive Impersonal in Portuguese: A Study in Syntactic Change as a Surface Phenomenon</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>52/4</volume>
<page type="first">
</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b66" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Obenauer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hans-Georg</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). La Construction Pronominale Passive en Fran&ccedil;ais Moderne</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>Masters dissertation, University of Paris 8</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b49" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Perlmutter</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1978">1978</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Impersonal Passives and the Unaccusative Hypothesis</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Fourth Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistics Society</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jeri<x> </x>J<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jaeger</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Anthony<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Woodbury</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Farrell</forenames><x> </x><surname>Ackerman, et al.</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Berkeley</address><x>: </x><publisher>Berkeley Linguistics Society.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pesetsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Zero Syntax: Experiencers and Cascades</title>
<x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b84" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Poletto</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Cecilia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Diachronic Development of Subject Clitics in North Eastern Italian Dialects</title><x>. </x><title type="other">University of Venice Working Papers in Linguistics</title><x> </x><page type="first">1&ndash;68</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b85" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Poletto</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Cecilia</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">La Sintassi del Soggetto nei Dialetti Italiani Settentrionali</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Quaderni Patavini di Linguistica</title><x> </x><volume>12</volume>
<page type="first">
</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pollock</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jean-Yves</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Case and Impersonal Constructions</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Levels of Syntactic Representation</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Jan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Koster</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.)</x><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pollock</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jean-Yves</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Accord, Cha&icirc;nes Impersonnelles et Variables</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguisticae Investigationes</title><x> </x><volume>VII/1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">131&ndash;183</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Postma</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Gert-Jan</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Zero Semantics: A Study on the Syntactic Conception of Quantificational Meaning</miscellaneoustext><x>. </x>
<publisher>PhD dissertation, University of Leiden</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Raposo</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Eduardo</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Juan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Uriagereka</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1996">1996</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Indefinite <i>Se</i>
</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">749&ndash;810</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Quantifier Scope: How Labour is Divided between QR and Choice Functions</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistics and Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>20</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">335&ndash;397</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b77" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reflexivity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>24</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">595&ndash;652</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Tal</forenames><x> </x><surname>Siloni</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2004">2004</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Against the Unaccusative Analysis of Reflexives</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Unaccusativity Puzzle</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Artemis</forenames><x> </x><surname>Alexiadou</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Elena</forenames><x> </x><surname>Anagnostopoulo</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Martin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Everaert</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">159&ndash;180</page>
<x>. </x><address>Oxford</address><x>: </x><publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b58" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> </x><namegroup type="editors">
<miscellaneoustext>(ed.)</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Issues in Italian Syntax<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Chain Formation</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Syntax of Pronominal Clitics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hagit</forenames><x> </x><surname>Borer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">65&ndash;95</page>
<x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Relativized Minimality<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rothemberg</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mira</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Les Verbes &agrave; la Fois Transitifs et Intransitifs en Fran&ccedil;ais Contemporain</title>
<x>. </x><address>Paris</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b64" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Ruwet</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Nicolas</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1972">1972</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Th&eacute;orie Syntaxique et Syntaxe du Fran&ccedil;ais<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Paris</address><x>: </x><publisher>Seuil.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b53" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Schoorlemmer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Maaike</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Participial Passive and Aspect in Russian. PhD dissertation, Utrecht, Research Institute for Language and Speech</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b74" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Smith</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carlota</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1970">1970</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Jespersen&apos;s &lsquo;Move and Change&rsquo; Class and Causative Verbs in English</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Linguistic and Literary Studies in Honor of Archibald A. Hill. Vol. 2: Descriptive Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Mohammed<x> </x>Ali</forenames><x> </x><surname>Jazayery</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Edgar<x> </x>C<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Plom&eacute;</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Werner</forenames><x> </x><surname>Winter</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">101&ndash;109</page>
<x>. </x><address>The Hague</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b48" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sobin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Nicolas</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Case Assignment in the Ukrainian Morphological Passive Construction</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>16</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">649&ndash;662</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b59" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Theory of Floating Quantifiers and its Corollaries for Constituent Structure</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>19</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">425&ndash;449</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Partitions and Atoms of Clause Structure: Subjects, Agreement, Case and Clitics</title>
<x>. </x><address>London/New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Routledge.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b65" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>St&eacute;fanini</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jean</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1962">1962</date><x>). </x><title type="book">La Voix Pronominale en Ancien et Moyen Fran&ccedil;ais</title>
<x>. </x><address>Aix-en-Provence</address><x>: </x><publisher>Ophrys.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b17" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Tenny</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carol</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Grammaticalizing Aspect and Affectedness. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Cambridge</address><x>, </x><publisher>MIT</publisher><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b52" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wasow</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Thomas</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1977">1977</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Transformations and the Lexicon</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Formal Syntax</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Culicover</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Thomas</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wasow</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Adrian</forenames><x> </x><surname>Akmajian</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">327&ndash;360</page>
<x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Wehrli</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Eric</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On Some Properties of French Clitic <i>Se</i>
</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">The Syntax of Pronominal Clitics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Hagit</forenames><x> </x><surname>Borer</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">263&ndash;283</page>
<x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b55" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Williams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edwin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="document">PRO and the Subject of NP</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">297&ndash;315</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b44" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zribi-Hertz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The &lsquo;Middle-<i>Se</i>&rsquo; Construction in French and its Status in the Triad Middle Voice&ndash;Passive&ndash;Reflexive</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Lingvisticae Investigationes</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">345&ndash;401</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b11" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zribi-Hertz</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anne</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="document">La r&eacute;flexivit&eacute; ergative en fran&ccedil;ais moderne</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Le Fran&ccedil;ais Moderne</title><x> </x><volume>55</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">23&ndash;54</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zubizarreta</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mar&iacute;a-Luisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1987">1987</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Levels of Representation in the Lexicon and in Syntax<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
