<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="bpg4-0.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE content PUBLIC "-//BLACKWELL PUBLISHING GROUP//DTD 4.0//EN" "bpg4-0.dtd" []>
<content dtdver="4.0">
<publisherinfo>
<publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher>
<address>Oxford, UK</address>
</publisherinfo>
<contentinfo type="book">
<contentcode>BCT</contentcode>
<titlegroup>
<title type="book">Blackwell Companion to Syntax</title>
</titlegroup>
<isbn>1405114851</isbn>
<copyright>&copy; 2006 by Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright>
</contentinfo>
<document sequence="1" type="primary_chapter" referencetype="harvard">
<header>
<documentinfo language="en">
<idgroup>
<documentid type="bpl" id="54"/>
</idgroup>
<relatedgroup>
<related relationship="self" type="primary_chapter">
<file name="chapter 54 - Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope.xml" type="xml"/>
</related>
</relatedgroup>
<date date="2005-11">November 2005</date>
<pagedetails>
<page type="first">35</page>
<page type="last">93</page>
</pagedetails>
<countgroup>
<count type="figure_total" count="0"/>
<count type="table" count="107"/>
<count type="formula" count="1"/>
<count type="reference_total" count="65"/>
<count type="page" count="59"/>
<count type="word" count="0"/>
</countgroup>
<trackinghistory>
<trackingdate type="created" date="20051125"/>
<trackingdate type="markedup" date="0000"/>
<trackingdate type="paginated" date="0000" by="Graphicraft"/>
</trackinghistory>
<tocheading>Original Articles</tocheading>
<runningheadgroup>
<runninghead type="title">
<i>Chapter 54&ensp;Sportiche: Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope</i>
</runninghead>
<runninghead type="author">
<i>Chapter 54&ensp;Sportiche: Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope</i>
</runninghead>
</runningheadgroup>
</documentinfo>
<titlegroup>
<title type="document">54&ensp;Reconstruction, Binding, and Scope</title>
</titlegroup>
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<forenames>DOMINIQUE</forenames><x> </x><surname>SPORTICHE</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
</header>
<section id="s1-1" type="body">
<subsection id="ss1" level="1">
<listgroup id="l1" type="1">
<li level="1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>
<p>Introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>An informal introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>A more systematic introduction</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>1.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Relevant principles</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>1.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Movement and pied-piping</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>2&ensp;</number>
<p>Basic reconstruction effects</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Pronominal binding</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Scope</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>DP&ndash;DP interactions</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>2.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>DP&ndash;predicate interactions</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.4&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition A</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.5&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition B</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>2.6&ensp;</number>
<p>Idioms and theta-roles</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>3&ensp;</number>
<p>Some basic generalizations</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction: where to?</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>No reconstruction into non-traces</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction into intermediate positions</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction and movement types</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>A-bar movement</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>A-movement</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Modalities of reconstruction</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Obligatoriness, optionality, or impossibility</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>3.3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Partial reconstruction vs. radical reconstruction</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>4&ensp;</number>
<p>Accounts</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition A</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Anywhere Principle</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.1.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Predicate&ndash;argument asymmetry</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Argument&ndash;adjunct distinction</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Anywhere Principle</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>4.2.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Predicate&ndash;argument asymmetry</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>4.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Scope</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>5&ensp;</number>
<p>Simultaneous reconstruction requirements</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C, Condition A, and pronominal binding</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Scope and Condition C</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.2.1&ensp;</number>
<p>The wide-scope reading</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.2.2&ensp;</number>
<p>The narrow-scope reading</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>5.3&ensp;</number>
<p>Predicate movement, scope, Condition C, and predicate-internal subjects</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.3.1&ensp;</number>
<p>Scope reconstruction and islands</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.3.2&ensp;</number>
<p>Definite descriptions, predicate-internal subjects, and partial reconstruction</p>
</li>
<li level="3">
<number>5.3.3&ensp;</number>
<p>What drives predicate reconstruction?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>6&ensp;</number>
<p>Conclusion</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss2" level="1">
<heading id="h1" level="1">1&ensp;Introduction</heading>
<subsection id="ss3" level="2">
<heading id="h2" level="2">1.1&ensp;An informal introduction</heading>
<p>Condition C of the Binding Theory, or some equivalent formulation, prohibits coreference between a non-pronoun (names, descriptions, etc.) and a pronoun under certain structural conditions. This prohibition is illustrated in the paradigm in (1) (underlined elements are supposed to corefer or to enter into a binding relationship):</p>
<p>(1)&ensp;<object id="tu1" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu1_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><u>John</u> said <u>he</u> was running for office.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He</u> said that <u>John</u> was running for office.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>The office that <u>John</u> is running for will make <u>him</u> influential.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>The office that <u>he</u> is running for will make <u>John</u> influential.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The pronoun may refer to the person designated by the name <i>John</i> in a, c, and d but not in b. This pattern shows that linear order is not at stake, or least not alone. The relevant notion involves c-command, leading to the informal formulation of Condition C in (2):</p>
<listgroup id="l2" type="1">
<li>
<number>(2)&ensp;</number>
<p><b>Condition C:</b>
</p>
<p>A pronoun cannot corefer with a non-pronoun that it c-commands.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Only in (1b) is this principle violated under the relevant reading. In this context, (3) is surprising:</p>
<p>(3)&ensp;<object id="tu2" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu2_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Whose examination of <u>John</u> did <u>he</u> fear?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He</u> feared Mary&apos;s examination of <u>John</u>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (3a), the pronoun does not c-command the <i>wh</i>-phrase, yet this sentence is deviant. This means that some modification of Condition C is needed.</p>
<p>A priori we may think that there are two distinct approaches to explaining this deviance: either modify the way Condition C is formulated, or keep it constant and modify how we define the kind of input that is used to evaluate whether it is satisfied or not. This is a subtle distinction. For the distinction to be real we must make sure that the two approaches are not mutually interchangeable. If we build into the formulation of Condition C a rule for evaluating the input that duplicates what we would do if we modify the input to Condition C without changing its formulation, the proposals are identical on these data and will have to be evaluated on something they truly do differently. This does not mean there is no issue, but the issue will not be relevant to the data we will look at, nor will it modify the logical structure of what ultimately needs to be said.</p>
<p>The second approach has always looked quite plausible, given that the deviance of (3a) seems related to the deviance of (3b): in both, the offending description is contained in the direct object of the verb <i>fear</i>, and the canonical<link rid="fn1">
<sup>1</sup></link> position of the direct object of <i>fear</i> is the postverbal position, a position c-commanded by the pronoun. If the direct object is treated as if it were in this canonical object position, we would have essentially manipulated the input to Condition C without reformulating it. Again, there are many different notations that can be used to construe this idea, and justifying which one should be used is a rather complex issue related to the choice of approaches discussed above, and not discussed here.<link rid="fn2">
<sup>2</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Since (3a) involves a movement dependency between the clause-initial <i>wh</i>-phrase and one argument of the verb &ndash; a non-controversial claim when properly understood &ndash; we will use one current notation for this dependency in terms of traces. Accordingly, it can be represented as a binding relationship between this preposed phrase and the direct object position of this verb:</p>
<p>(4)&ensp;&lsqb;Whose examination of <u>John</u>&rsqb;<sub>j</sub> did <u>he</u> fear t<sub>j</sub>?</p>
<p>with t<sub>j</sub> the trace of the <i>wh</i>-phrase. The pronoun <i>he</i> c-commands this trace t<sub>j</sub>. If we suppose that this preposed phrase is, for the purpose of Condition C, in its trace position t<sub>j</sub> or behaves as if it were in its trace position, the problem this sentence raises is accommodated, as it now has a structure similar to that of (3b).</p>
<p>Since the preposed phrase is moved, but behaves as if it had not, i.e., as if it were in the position it moved from, this process is, using the spatial movement metaphor, called reconstruction: the preposed phrase is reconstructed into its trace.</p>
<p>The kind of questions we will ask are: when does reconstruction take place? Is it always possible? Is it sometimes obligatory? Is it sensitive to the type of movement constructions involved? For example, we may ask of A-movement constructions whether they exhibit reconstruction effects at all (researchers are historically divided on this question) and, if they do, whether they do so in the same way as A-bar constructions.</p>
<p>These, however, are a small corner of a bigger problem. To provide a broader perspective, we note that the investigation of reconstruction effects is part of increasingly larger questions, which are important but will essentially be left unaddressed here.</p>
<p>We may first ask whether reconstruction effects function the same way in all movement constructions. Second, we may ask a set of more general descriptive questions. Reconstruction effects can be viewed as special cases of the more general category of connectivity effects. Connectivity effects are cases in which a phrase seems to behave as if it occupied a position different from its &lsquo;surface&rsquo; position, i.e., the position that it seems to be occupying in the spoken string. Such effects are found in a great variety of constructions, in particular constructions involving movement but also in constructions for which movement is not clearly or perhaps not plausibly involved.</p>
<p>As descriptive questions we can ask:</p>
<listgroup id="l3" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Under what conditions are connectivity effects found?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Are connectivity effects and reconstruction effects the same?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Are connectivity effects always and only found in movement constructions?</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Connectivity effects have been extensively investigated and there have been many proposals to achieve a principled understanding of their existence and their properties, with repercussions affecting core aspects of the architecture of syntactic theory. One type of construction in particular stands out as significant: (specificational) pseudocleft constructions. They exhibit connectivity effects and it is far from obvious that they involve movement (of the relevant kind). They may instead involve deletion or special interpretive rules. Recent work dealing with these questions includes <link rid="b1">Heycock and Kroch (1999</link>); <link rid="b2">Sharvit (1999</link>); <link rid="b3">Den Dikken et al. (2000</link>); and <link rid="b4">Schlenker (2003b</link>).</p>
<p>Finally, we ought to raise theoretical questions, i.e., questions of explanatory adequacy:</p>
<listgroup id="l4" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Why do we find the answers that we do to the descriptive questions?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>How is linguistic theory organized so that connectivity effects, or the relationship between connectivity and reconstruction, fall out from the very architecture of the theory?</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>For example, given the current state of the research, it may well be true that connectivity effects are found only in cases of movement (reconstruction effects) or deletion (under some kind of identity). If such is the case, the existence of connectivity is related to the presence of the &lsquo;connected&rsquo; phrases in positions other than where they overtly occur, at the right level of analysis. If it were otherwise, the existence of connectivity would appear more mysterious. Similarly, differences in reconstruction properties in A- and A-bar-movement constructions should follow directly from the differences between these movements, in much the same way as different projectiles (in a vacuum) follow different paths due to some difference in their initial velocity and nothing else.</p>
<p>Finally, before proceeding, it is worth noting that the data on reconstruction will mostly come from English, the language for which there is a systematic and deep and wide enough body of technical literature. The data are complex and non-uniform across speakers. The root of these dialectal differences is not understood. What will be presented here is what, in the author&apos;s judgment, the technical literature takes more or less to be the standard dialect. The text will contain scattered, non-systematic remarks about such variations (see <link rid="b5">Kuno 1997</link> and <link rid="b6">Safir 1999</link> for some discussion).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss4" level="2">
<heading id="h3" level="2">1.2&ensp;A more systematic introduction</heading>
<subsection id="ss5" level="3">
<heading id="h4" level="3">1.2.1&ensp;Relevant principles</heading>
<p>We define connectivity effects as cases in which a phrase superficially in a certain position P behaves as if it were in position Q.<link rid="fn3">
<sup>3</sup></link> In principle, such effects could arise and mostly do arise with respect to any principle appealing to the syntactic position of particular phrases (e.g., what it means to be interpreted as an argument of some predicate, to be inflected for a particular Case, or to show a certain kind of agreement morphology).</p>
<p>For the most part, we will focus on reconstruction or connectivity effects involving a few interpretive principles of binding and scope, that is, generalizations about structure-sensitive referential dependencies between phrases. The term &lsquo;reconstruction&rsquo; is customarily reserved for such cases of connectivity.</p>
<p>For each of these interpretive principles, we provide in (5) a rough approximation of its formulation below, sufficient to illustrate the problems relating to connectivity:</p>
<p>(5)&ensp;<object id="tu3" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu3_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="3">a.</entry>
<entry><b>Binding principles</b> (see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 9 - Binding Theory.xml" type="file">chapter 9</externallink></related>):</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Condition A: anaphors must have a local antecedent (more or less a c-commanding antecedent in the same clause no further than the first c-commanding subject).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Condition B: pronouns cannot have a local antecedent (more or less a c-commanding antecedent in the same clause).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>Condition C: pronouns cannot corefer with non-pronouns they c-command.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="2">b.</entry>
<entry><b>Scope principles:</b>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>If <i>X</i> superficially c-commands <i>Y</i>, <i>Y</i> can be interpreted in the scope of <i>X</i>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><i>X</i> and <i>Y</i> can outscope each other only if <i>X</i> and <i>Y</i> are clause mates.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry><b>Pronominal binding principle</b> (a principle of both binding and scope):</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>A pronoun can behave as a variable bound by <i>X</i> only if it can be interpreted in the scope of <i>X</i>. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As we have seen above in the case of Condition C, in order to understand reconstruction effects, and beyond, connectivity effects, we need to concurrently develop first how exactly Condition C should be formulated, and second what kind of manipulation (syntactic processes, rules of semantic interpretation, etc.) surface syntactic structures have to be subjected to in order to provide the right kind of input for the application of this principle.</p>
<p>The same questions arise for each of the principles above. This makes the potential complexity of the resulting system we will need to postulate increase exponentially. Thus it is conceivable that each properly formulated principle requires a different kind of manipulation of the strings we are studying. On the other hand, it is also conceivable that a unique input in conjunction with principles (not covertly encoding in their formulation any manipulation of the surface syntactic string) is sufficient. This would, for example, justify a level of Logical Form representations, that is, manipulated surface structures, which all the principles under consideration would take as input. Regardless of what the correct answer is, it is clear that it will have a fundamental bearing on the internal organization of syntactic theory and its interface with semantic theory.</p>
<p>We will now adopt a certain vocabulary to talk about syntactic dependencies, which is standard in the Principles and Parameters family of theoretical models and encodes various assumptions. It is important to keep in mind that this does not affect the essence of the limited data discussed here, but does affect the form in which they are presented.<link rid="fn4">
<sup>4</sup></link> One such assumption is the representation of predicate&ndash;argument relations as structurally local underlying relations modified by movement dependencies. Another is the representation of movement dependencies as trace-binding relations. Finally we talk about movement derivationally, mostly because standard vocabulary &ndash; invented with a derivational perspective in mind &ndash; sounds more intuitive this way.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss6" level="3">
<heading id="h5" level="3">1.2.2&ensp;Movement and pied-piping</heading>
<p>To talk meaningfully about connectivity and reconstruction, we need basic characterizations of movement and pied-piping. This is what this section provides.</p>
<p>Natural languages exhibit movement dependencies. The existence of such dependencies can be simply illustrated by the distributional differences between the DPs <i>the boy</i> and <i>which boy</i> in (6) and (7):</p>
<p>(6)&ensp;<object id="tu4" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu4_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Jones met <u>the boy</u>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Who met <u>the boy</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*<u>The boy</u> did Jones meet. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(7)<object id="tu5" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu5_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Jones met <u>which boy</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Who met <u>which boy</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry><u>Which boy</u> did Jones meet? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We want to say that regardless of the choice of determiner D in &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> D boy&rsqb;, this DP behaves as a direct object of <i>met</i> in the sense that whatever kind of semantic object this DP stands for, it is understood as bearing the same semantic relation &ndash; call it its thematic property &ndash; to the predicate <i>meet</i> in all these sentences. The fact that D &equals; <i>which</i> induces different distributional properties than D &equals; <i>the</i> means that these determiners have different licensing requirements. These licensing requirements &ndash; call them quantificational in the present case &ndash; sometimes force a <i>wh</i>-D (<i>which</i>), but not a definite D (<i>the</i>), to appear sentence-initially, as in (7c).</p>
<p>A minimal description of these observations could take the following form: a DP &ndash; say <i>which boy</i> &ndash; encodes two set of properties (to simplify say only two, even though it may be two among others): thematic properties and quantificational properties. Its thematic properties require it to be paired to some predicate (here, <i>meet</i>). Its quantificational properties require it to be paired with some quantificational position (i.e., to be assigned scope: here the clause-initial position). The movement dependency is the dependency between the quantificational position of this DP and the predicate.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, we use a standard notation to express this dependency, assuming as correct the consequences that this choice carries (even though almost everything discussed here could be recast in some alternative notation). In these terms, the thematic properties of the &lsquo;object&rsquo; DP in (7c) are expressed by the direct object position this DP occupies in underlying structure, or, to put it representationally, by the position of its most deeply embedded trace. Its quantificational properties are derived from the position it occupies in overt structure, i.e., by the position in which the DP is &lsquo;pronounced&rsquo;, namely &lsqb;spec, CP&rsqb;. The movement dependency is then a dependency between &lsqb;spec, CP&rsqb; and the direct object position. A fuller picture would take into account the fact that DPs need (and in many cases morphologically encode) Case. Current theories postulate that all DPs will also involve movement to a Case position to license their Case property.</p>
<p>In (8):</p>
<p>(8) <formula id="mu1" format="inline">
<file name="Graphics\chapter_54_mu1.gif" type="gif"/>
</formula>
</p>
<p>we get three positions (e<sub>0</sub>, e<sub>1</sub>, e<sub>2</sub>) where e<sub>0</sub> &equals; &lsqb;spec, CP&rsqb; is the quantificational position, e<sub>1</sub> &equals; &lsqb;spec, IP&rsqb; is the nominative position, and e<sub>2</sub> is the thematic position of the phrase &lsqb;which pictures&rsqb;. In this example, the <i>wh</i>-DPs must participate in a movement dependency between the thematic position and the quantificational position. What is remarkable is that the need for this movement is a property of the determiner <i>which</i>, not of the noun <i>pictures</i>. This is made clear by (6) and (7), which involve the same object noun, different determiners, and different movement possibilities. The fact that the noun <i>pictures</i> in (8) is pronounced at the front of the embedded clause is no doubt because (i) <i>which</i> needs to be linked to this clause-initial position, and (ii) <i>which</i> and <i>pictures</i> need to be closely associated. Generalizing on standard use, let us call this property pied-piping:<link rid="fn5">
<sup>5</sup></link> the NP <i>pictures</i> has pied-piped in the sense that it appears where it does, not by virtue of what it is intrinsically but rather because it must be closely associated with an element, <i>which</i>, which has this distributional requirement.</p>
<p>Now suppose that a moved XP (e.g., a DP linked to several positions) contains moved material sensitive to the position in which this DP occurs. For a given property, which one(s) of these positions is this sensitive material evaluated in? Because a given DP is only pronounced once but is associated with several positions (e.g., thematic, Case, quantificational, etc.), the overt position in which it appears is not necessarily the one in which it is evaluated. Answering these questions means answering the descriptive questions we listed about reconstruction.</p>
<p>More generally, suppose we have a phrase P linked by movement to several positions ordered from highest to lowest (e<sub>1</sub>, e<sub>2</sub>, .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, e<sub>n</sub>). By convention here (we only consider overt movement for the moment), this phrase is pronounced in position e<sub>1</sub>. If this phrase P contains material that appears to behave with respect to some principle (e.g., Binding Theoretic principles) in a position, say e<sub>n&minus;1</sub>, lower than that in which it is pronounced, we say that we are observing a &lsquo;reconstruction effect&rsquo;. We also say that the material &lsquo;reconstructs&rsquo; into e<sub>n&minus;1</sub>.<link rid="fn6">
<sup>6</sup></link> As mentioned earlier, the term &lsquo;reconstruction&rsquo; is customarily reserved for cases in which the principles in question are interpretive principles of binding and scope.</p>
<p>It is worth remarking that there is no reason to think that this is a scientifically well-founded decision: it may well be that the right approach treats in a uniform way reconstruction effects involving thematic roles (something that actually systematically takes place), morphological properties such as Case or Agreement, and every other reconstruction effect. Nevertheless it is reasonable to try to understand how reconstruction for scope and binding works before worrying about whether all reconstruction effects should be treated uniformly. In what follows, I will thus use the term &lsquo;reconstruction&rsquo; to mean reconstruction for scope and/or binding.</p>
<p>It is in this context that the following specific questions arise immediately:</p>
<listgroup id="l5" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>How does the reconstruction property arise?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>What properties does it have? Is it always possible? Is it sometimes obligatory?</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Do the possibilities of reconstruction depend on the overt distribution of P (i.e., on the position in which P is pronounced?</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>One question we may ask that we will not investigate in detail here is the following: when a phrase is moved, can we in principle find reconstruction effects with any part of this moved phrase? The answer seems to be mostly yes, with perhaps one exception: pied-piped material clearly shows reconstruction effects, but it is less clear whether, and perhaps unlikely that, the portion of the moved phrase that induces the movement is allowed to reconstruct. In the <i>wh</i>-movement example above, a negative answer would mean that the <i>wh</i>-determiner itself does not reconstruct. We will not discuss this question here.</p>
<p>We will restrict our discussion throughout to the reconstruction of pied-piped material in the sense of pied-piping adopted earlier. It should be noted that it is sometimes hard to tell what is the trigger for movement and what is pied-piped, e.g., in the case of topicalization of DPs and VPs, or in the case of A-movement. With this proviso, the reconstruction problem is nearly the mirror-image of the pied-piping problem: the pied-piping problem is the problem of how much bigger a phrase can move than seems strictly necessary, while the reconstruction problem asks how big a portion of a moved phrase can behave as if it had not moved.</p>
<p>The very existence of reconstruction effects may appear somewhat surprising: why should languages bother to move a phrase to some position, only to interpret a portion of this phrase in a position it has been moved from? This may be taken as a reason to reject a &lsquo;literal&rsquo; reconstruction mechanism process in favor of an alternative account without any &lsquo;moving back&rsquo;. But this would be an illusion, for there seems to be no account available at the moment &ndash; and perhaps in principle &ndash; which does not construe the relevant reconstructed readings differently from that gotten from a structure in which movement of the reconstructed portions would not have taken place at all. And this is precisely what needs to be explained, regardless of the notations used to do it.</p>
<p>By definition, pied-piped material is moved for reasons extrinsic to the movement trigger. It is thus not so surprising that this material might behave as if it had not moved. Perhaps what is really surprising is that pied-piping exists at all. So far as is presently known, it is an unexplained property of language.<link rid="fn7">
<sup>7</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss7" level="1">
<heading id="h6" level="1">2&ensp;Basic reconstruction effects</heading>
<p>We begin by illustrating reconstruction effects with each of the interpretive principles we are focusing on. In each case, the examples will show that a (portion of a) moved phrase behaves from the point of this principle as if it had not moved.</p>
<subsection id="ss8" level="2">
<heading id="h7" level="2">2.1&ensp;Pronominal binding</heading>
<p>Consider (9) (where the underlined quantifier is meant to bind the underlined pronoun):</p>
<p>(9)&ensp;<object id="tu6" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu6_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><u>No politician</u> ignores many of <u>his</u> collaborators.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Many of <u>his</u> collaborators ignores <u>no politician</u>?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(Note that (9b) shows a weak crossover effect.) The judgments are preserved under movement:</p>
<p>(10)&ensp;<object id="tu7" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu7_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Which of <u>his</u> collaborators does <u>no politician</u> ignore t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Intended answer: His main pollster.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Which of <u>his</u> collaborators t ignores <u>no politician</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Intended answer: His main pollster.) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The pronoun <i>his</i> can only be bound by the quantifier <i>no politician</i> if the trace of the <i>wh</i>-phrase containing it is c-commanded by this quantifier, i.e., if the condition on pronominal binding is satisfied if we treat the moved phrase as unmoved.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss9" level="2">
<heading id="h8" level="2">2.2&ensp;Scope</heading>
<p>Reconstruction effects for scope can be illustrated in a variety of ways. We illustrate cases of scopal interactions between two DPs, and cases of scopal interaction between a DP and a predicate.</p>
<subsection id="ss10" level="3">
<heading id="h9" level="3">2.2.1&ensp;DP&ndash;DP interactions</heading>
<p>DP&ndash;DP scopal reconstruction can be illustrated by such examples as (11):</p>
<p>(11)&ensp;Visit some girl, Bill says every boy did t.</p>
<p>Such a sentence may be interpreted with the DP <i>some girl</i> in the scope of the DP <i>every boy</i>, i.e., as meaning that Bill says that each boy visited a girl different from the one the other boys visited. If this were the interpreted form, we would not expect <i>every boy</i> to be able to outscope <i>some girl</i>, since these expressions are not clause mates. This is of course a reading that is available in the unmoved counterpart of this example:</p>
<p>(12)&ensp;Bill says every boy visited some girl.</p>
<p>Examples illustrating the same effect but involving <i>wh</i>-movement are given below. First consider (13):</p>
<p>(13)&ensp;<object id="tu8" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu8_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You convinced three friends of <u>a friend</u> that <u>every member</u> should co-opt Bill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>You convinced Bill that <u>every member</u> should co-opt three friends of <u>a friend</u>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Only in (13b) is it possible to understand the phrase <i>a friend</i> as being in the scope of <i>every member</i>. In other words, in (13b), Joe should co-opt a certain number of friends of a friend of Joe&apos;s, Mary should co-opt a certain number of friends of a friend of Mary&apos;s, etc. This reading is unavailable in (13a).</p>
<p>These judgments are preserved under <i>wh</i>-movement:</p>
<p>(14)&ensp;<object id="tu9" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu9_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many friends of <u>a friend</u> did you convince t that <u>every member</u> should co-opt you?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many friends of <u>a friend</u> did you convince Bill that <u>every member</u> should co-opt t? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Only in (14b), in which the trace t of the preposed <i>wh</i>-phrase is a clause mate of the quantifier <i>every member</i>, is it possible to understand the phrase <i>a friend</i> as being in the scope of <i>every member</i>. This is consistent with the idea that the pied-piped material in the preposed phrase can be interpreted as if it were in a position (it occupies overtly or in a position) it has been moved from.<link rid="fn8">
<sup>8</sup></link>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss11" level="3">
<heading id="h10" level="3">2.2.2&ensp;DP&ndash;predicate interactions</heading>
<p>Consider (15):</p>
<p>(15)&ensp;<object id="tu10" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu10_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many songs will you compose?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many songs will you perform? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Thinking for illustrative purposes of the meaning of the verb <i>compose</i> as <i>cause to be in existence</i>, and <i>perform</i> as <i>cause to be performed</i>, we can paraphrase (15a) by (16a), and (15b) by either (16b) or (16c):</p>
<p>(16)&ensp;<object id="tu11" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu11_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, you will cause there to be x many songs in existence?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, you will cause there to be x many songs performed?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, there are x many songs you will cause to be performed?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&equals; How many songs are there that you will perform?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The difference lies in the scope of the existential quantification rendered here by <i>there are</i> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;with respect to the expression <i>will cause</i>. The reading in (16c) is less natural in the case of (15a): we cannot assert the existence of a set of objects with certain properties if these objects do not yet exist (presuming that if the songs are not composed yet, they do not exist in the relevant sense). For ease of reference, let us call the readings in (16a) and (16b) the narrow-scope or narrow readings (since <i>there</i> has narrower scope than <i>will cause</i>). We will call the reading in (16c) the wide-scope or wide reading.</p>
<p>The crucial ingredient here is this: one cannot plausibly be asserting the existence of songs in (15a) because the preposed phrase is an argument of a verb of creation, namely <i>compose</i>. Thus, these two sentences behave like their unmoved counterparts in (17) and illustrate a reconstruction effect:</p>
<p>(17)&ensp;<object id="tu12" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu12_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You will compose three songs?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>You will perform three songs? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss12" level="2">
<heading id="h11" level="2">2.3&ensp;Condition C</heading>
<p>We have already illustrated Condition C effects in (3). We repeat these examples here as (18):</p>
<p>(18)&ensp;<object id="tu13" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu13_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Whose examination of <u>John</u> did <u>he</u> fear?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He</u> feared Mary&apos;s examination of <u>John</u>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(18b), without <i>wh</i>-movement, behaves like (18a), illustrating a reconstruction effect.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss13" level="2">
<heading id="h12" level="2">2.4&ensp;Condition A</heading>
<p>Reconstruction for Condition A of the Binding Theory can seemingly be illustrated by cases such as the following involving the reciprocal anaphor <i>each other</i>. Consider first the paradigm in (19) without <i>wh</i>-movement:</p>
<p>(19)&ensp;<object id="tu14" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu14_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*She reminded <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends that <u>they</u> saw Bill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><u>They</u> reminded <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends that she saw Bill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>She reminded Bill that they saw <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The pattern in (20) with <i>wh</i>-movement exactly mirrors this paradigm:</p>
<p>(20)&ensp;<object id="tu15" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu15_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Which of each other&apos;s friends did she remind <b>t</b> that they saw Bill?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which of each other&apos;s friends did they remind <b>t</b> that she saw Bill?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Which of each other&apos;s friends did she remind Bill that they saw <b>t</b>? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Unless some trace of the moved phrase is c-commanded by a potential antecedent, the sentence is ill-formed: these sentences behave from the point of view of anaphor binding as if movement had not taken place. However, the anaphor <i>each other</i> is a bound variable and thus falls under the principle of pronominal binding. As a result, we need to proceed differently to illustrate a pure Condition A reconstruction effect.</p>
<p>Either we illustrate a Condition A reconstruction effect with an anaphor that is not a bound variable, or we check that the locality condition that Condition A imposes on the antecedent anaphor relation must be satisfied under reconstruction. It turns out not to be straightforward to perform either of these tests in a simple way. It is possible that reflexives qualify as non-bound-variable anaphors in certain conditions (with non-quantificational antecedents), but showing that this is the case is at best complicated and perhaps not really possible. Checking the locality condition may be possible in cases involving intermediate traces (that we will discuss later, in <link rid="ss19">section 3.1.2</link>) but also involves complications. We thus leave this open at this point.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss14" level="2">
<heading id="h13" level="2">2.5&ensp;Condition B</heading>
<p>Showing that Condition B effects are found under reconstruction also requires some analysis. (21&ndash;2) show a case in which a pronoun shows disjoint reference effects in its original position and under movement (topicalization), i.e., under reconstruction:</p>
<p>(21)&ensp;<object id="tu16" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu16_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Mary says <u>he</u> saw <u>him</u>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><u>He</u> says Mary saw <u>him</u>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(22)&ensp;<object id="tu17" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu17_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*<u>Him</u>, Mary says <u>he</u> saw t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><u>Him</u>, <u>he</u> says Mary saw t. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Of course, we should make sure that (22a) is not independently excluded. It may be, if all traces of A-bar-moved DPs (e.g., Topicalized DPs) behave like descriptions with respect to Condition C (<i>wh</i>-traces are R-expressions subject to Condition C): t would have to be disjoint from <i>he</i> because of Condition C without reconstruction. The acceptability of (22b), however, suggests that the traces of preposed pronouns are not subject to Condition C. If they were, the object t of <i>saw</i> would have to be disjoint from <i>he</i> (a Condition C effect). We conclude that the parallelism between (21) and (22) does illustrate a reconstruction effect.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss15" level="2">
<heading id="h14" level="2">2.6&ensp;Idioms and theta-roles</heading>
<p>It is not customary to include the checking of predicate&ndash;argument relations in a discussion of reconstruction effects, even though predicate&ndash;argument relations (theta-role assignment) are interpretive relations. We have already seen in the case of verbs of creation that it is necessary to include such checking in the description of reconstruction effects. Once this is done, we can recast trace theory (in part) as encoding the fact that reconstruction for thematic role assignment systematically takes place.</p>
<p>For example, in (23):</p>
<p>(23)&ensp;<object id="tu18" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu18_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You think I like John.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>John, you think I like t. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>the presence of the trace t encodes the observation that from a thematic point of view, <i>John</i> in (23b) behaves exactly like <i>John</i> in (23a): this is a reconstruction effect. Although it is not fundamentally conceptually different from the general case, one special subcase of this is particularly useful, namely the case of (non-compositional) idiom chunks:</p>
<p>(24)&ensp;<object id="tu19" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu19_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>You think Mary <u>took</u> much <u>care</u> of Bill.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How much <u>care</u> do you think Mary <u>took</u> t of Bill? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Unlike what happens with a preposed name or description, a preposed idiom chunk receives no relevant interpretation independently of the rest of the idiom. As a consequence, it must be understood exactly as if it was reconstructed.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss16" level="1">
<heading id="h15" level="1">3&ensp;Some basic generalizations</heading>
<p>This section is a short overview of some basic generalizations regarding reconstruction in A-bar-movement cases, which form the basis of many discussions. They will be discussed in turn. We have seen that there are reconstruction effects with respect to every principle listed in (5). Recall that a reconstruction effect is an &lsquo;as if&rsquo; effect: a moved item I behaves as if it were in a different position Q from the position P in which it is &lsquo;pronounced&rsquo;.</p>
<p>The first generalization is that Q is a position from which I has moved, and no other position: reconstruction in movement cases is into traces, including intermediate traces, and nowhere else. The second generalization is that there are reconstruction effects in every type of phrasal movement: all varieties of A-bar-movement constructions and A-movement constructions (we leave aside non-phrasal movement cases).</p>
<subsection id="ss17" level="2">
<heading id="h16" level="2">3.1&ensp;Reconstruction: where to?</heading>
<subsection id="ss18" level="3">
<heading id="h17" level="3">3.1.1&ensp;No reconstruction into non-traces</heading>
<p>Naturally, it is not possible to prove that reconstruction is possible only into traces. However, individual examples can be (and have been) provided showing that other options are unavailable. We repeat below a few such examples, making the relevant point explicit.</p>
<p>Consider the contrasts in (25a), in which the pronoun <i>he</i> may or may not corefer with the phrase <i>the typical male viewer</i>:</p>
<p>(25)&ensp;<object id="tu20" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu20_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Whose characterization of him&rsqb; does the typical male viewer like t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of the typical male viewer&rsqb; does he like t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We construe this as indicating that the preposed phrase (<i>wh</i>-moved) is reconstructed in the t position. That it is the position of this trace that matters rather than the mere fact that some movement has taken place is demonstrated by the contrast in (26):</p>
<p>(26)&ensp;<object id="tu21" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu21_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which examiner of <u>a good student you know</u> did you tell <b>t</b> that <u>he</u> knew the dean?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Which examiner of <u>a good student you know</u> did <u>he</u> tell the dean that you knew <b>t</b>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*Which examiner of <u>a good student you know</u> did you tell the dean that <u>he</u> knew <b>t</b>? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It is only when the trace t of the preposed <i>wh</i>-phrase is c-commanded by the pronoun <i>he</i> that deviance ensues. Thus, it is the position from which movement originates that is important.</p>
<p>The same conclusion can be reached for other principles. We can illustrate it in the case of the reciprocal anaphor <i>each other</i>. (27) shows that unless some trace of the moved phrase is c-commanded by a potential antecedent, the sentence is ill-formed:</p>
<p>(27)&ensp;<object id="tu22" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu22_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Which of <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends did he remind <b>t</b> that <u>they</u> saw Bill?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which of <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends did <u>they</u> remind <b>t</b> that he saw Bill?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Which of <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends did he remind her that <u>they</u> saw <b>t</b>? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This shows again that we are dealing with a reconstruction effect and not the effect of some movement having taken place.</p>
<p>Similar examples can be constructed for pronominal binding ((10), repeated here as (28), where the underlined quantifier is meant to bind the underlined pronoun):</p>
<p>(28)&ensp;<object id="tu23" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu23_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Which of <u>his</u> collaborators does <u>no politician</u> ignore t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Intended answer: His main pollster.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>*Which of <u>his</u> collaborators t ignores <u>no politician</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>(Intended answer: His main pollster.) </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As seen earlier, the pronoun <i>his</i> can only be bound by the quantifier <i>no politician</i> if the trace of the <i>wh</i>-phrase containing it is c-commanded by this quantifier.</p>
<p>We can also illustrate this with respect to scopal interaction between quantifiers ((14), repeated here as (29)):</p>
<p>(29)&ensp;<object id="tu24" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu24_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many friends of <u>a friend</u> did you convince t that <u>every member</u> should co-opt you?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many friends of <u>a friend</u> did you convince Bill that <u>every member</u> should co-opt t? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As seen earlier, only in (29b) is it possible to understand the phrase <i>a friend</i> as being in the scope of <i>every member</i>. In (29b), Joe should co-opt a certain number of friends of a friend of Joe&apos;s, Mary should co-opt a certain number of friends of a friend of Mary&apos;s, etc. This reading is unavailable in (29a), and this is consistent with the idea that the pied-piped material in the preposed phrase can be interpreted in a position (it occupies overtly or in a position) it has been moved from.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss19" level="3">
<heading id="h18" level="3">3.1.2&ensp;Reconstruction into intermediate positions</heading>
<p>When a phrase is moved several times, reconstruction appears possible, at least in some cases, in any position the phrase has moved through: reconstruction is possible into any trace. Let us examine the logic of this situation. Consider the following structure, in which each element c-commands the next one:</p>
<p>(30)&ensp;P .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;A .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;t1 .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;B .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;t2</p>
<p>P is a phrase moved from t2 to the c-commanding t1 on the surface c-commanding position of P. To illustrate the existence of cases in which reconstruction is into t1, we need to look at cases in which the exact reconstructed position of a moved phrase matters. One option is to check Condition A, which imposes a locality requirement.<link rid="fn9">
<sup>9</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The reconstruction properties of pied-piped anaphors is exemplified in (31):</p>
<p>(31)&ensp;<object id="tu25" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu25_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of <u>each other you</u> think <u>they</u> said <u>we</u> liked.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of <u>each other</u> &lsqb;<u>you</u> think &lsqb;t1 <u>they</u> said &lsqb;t2 <u>we</u> liked t3&rsqb;&rsqb;&rsqb;. </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(31a) is ambiguous as to what the antecedent of the reciprocal anaphor is. Any underlined DP qualifies ((32): contrast this with (20)):</p>
<p>(32)&ensp;<object id="tu26" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu26_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of the others (of you) each of you thinks they said we liked t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of the others (of them) you think each of them said we liked t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of the others (of us) you think they said each of us liked t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This state of affairs finds a ready description, given the otherwise well-supported assumption that extraction out of a sequence of clauses proceeds by successively fronting the moving phrase to the beginning of each clause containing it until it finds its final landing spot. As a result, a more complete representation of (31a) is (31b). Optional reconstruction into traces can then put the moved phrase back into any intermediate t position, where it can select an appropriately local antecedent. If reconstruction in t1 or t2 were not available, neither <i>you</i> nor <i>they</i> would qualify as appropriately local antecedents. This is a reconstruction effect in &lsquo;intermediate&rsquo; traces. (Note that this paradigm also illustrates a reconstruction effect for Condition A.)</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss20" level="2">
<heading id="h19" level="2">3.2&ensp;Reconstruction and movement types</heading>
<p>We now briefly address the question of whether the possibility of reconstruction is sensitive to the type of movement involved. We will show that reconstruction effects seem to be found with all types of movement.</p>
<subsection id="ss21" level="3">
<heading id="h20" level="3">3.2.1&ensp;A-bar movement</heading>
<p>Reconstruction effects are not limited to direct <i>wh</i>-questions of DPs. We find the same Condition C effect as above in direct or indirect <i>wh</i>-questions or Topicalization of various phrases, such as PPs, APs, or VPs, or other types of A-bar movement of various phrases. This is illustrated in (33):</p>
<p>(33)&ensp;<object id="tu27" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu27_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder &lsqb;whose pictures of <u>a successful athlete</u>&rsqb; <u>he</u> reminded Bill that you saw t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*It is incredible &lsqb;how proud of <u>a successful athlete</u>&rsqb; Mary told <u>him</u> you were t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Next to <u>a good student&apos;s locker</u>&rsqb;, <u>she</u> always puts stickers t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Train <u>a successful athlete I know</u>&rsqb;, <u>he</u> says I should t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(34) exemplifies reconstruction effects with the anaphor <i>each other</i> in a variety of constructions:</p>
<p>(34)&ensp;<object id="tu28" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu28_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which of <u>each other</u>&apos;s comments <u>they</u>/*Sue reported t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which of <u>each other</u>&apos;s friends did <u>they</u>/*Bill remember t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*It is incredible &lsqb;how proud of <u>each other</u>&rsqb; Mary said <u>you</u> were t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Next to <u>each other</u>&apos;s starting blocks, <u>the athletes</u>/*she put lucky charms t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>And (35) does the same thing for bound pronouns:</p>
<p>(35)&ensp;<object id="tu29" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu29_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder whose comments about <u>him no one</u> reported t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Happy that <u>he</u> had to lie, <u>no one</u> thinks you are t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Against <u>his</u> own country, <u>no true patriot</u> will ever fight t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss22" level="3">
<heading id="h21" level="3">3.2.2A-movement </heading>
<p>We will now demonstrate that reconstruction effects are also found with A-movement. It should be noted that this is a more controversial conclusion. The reason is that reconstruction seems to fail in a variety of A-movement cases. Dealing in detail with this controversy is beyond the scope of this chapter. The preponderance of the evidence clearly supports the existence of reconstruction effects in A-movement constructions. Here, we will limit ourselves to presenting some clear cases of reconstruction effects, noting a couple of cases of reconstruction failures.</p>
<p>The basic problem is raised by the ambiguity of (36):</p>
<p>(36)&ensp;A Russian seems to have won the race.</p>
<p>(36) can have the two paraphrases in (37):</p>
<p>(37)&ensp;<object id="tu30" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu30_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>It seems that there is a Russian who won the race.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>There is a Russian who seems to have won the race.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (37a), existential quantification takes place inside the scope of the verb <i>seem</i>. In (37b), existential quantification outscopes the verb <i>seem</i>.</p>
<p>One standard account takes the following form:</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;The target sentence involves raising to subject, that is, it is associated with a pair of syntactic representations, roughly (38):</p>
<p>(38)&ensp;<object id="tu31" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu31_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>seems &lsqb;a Russian to have won the race&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>a Russian &lsqb;seems to have won the race&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>These two representations are technically described as respectively the underlying structure of the target sentence and the surface structure of the target sentence.</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;The relationship between these syntactic structures is movement: the difference between these two structures &ndash; the relative position of the constituent <i>a Russian</i> &ndash; is formalized as a movement rule or movement dependency, the effect of which is to express the non-redundant portions of these two structures. The constituent &lsqb;a Russian&rsqb; is raised from the position &lsquo;subject of the embedded clause&rsquo; to the position &lsquo;subject of the main clause&rsquo;; everything else remains the same. This movement, called &lsquo;raising to subject&rsquo;, belongs to the subcategory of A-movement.</p>
<p>(iii)&ensp;The scopal ambiguity arises from taking either of these representations as input to compute scope relations, the first one giving rise to (37a) or (37b), the second to (37b) only.</p>
<p>(iv)&ensp;Since the first interpretation is computed on the basis of the representation of the target sentence which does not surface, it looks like this interpretation is reached by exactly undoing movement: this is a reconstruction effect.</p>
<p>Many authors have argued that there is reconstruction under A-movement in this sense (e.g., <link rid="b7">Barss 1986</link>; <link rid="b8 b9">Sportiche 1997, 1999</link>; <link rid="b10">Romero 1997a</link>; <link rid="b11">Lebeaux 1998</link>; <link rid="b12">Fox 1999</link>). Some authors (e.g., <link rid="b13">May 1985</link>) have argued that these readings arise by a different mechanism than exact undoing of the movement (they invoke a mechanism of Q-lowering). These doubts are echoed by <link rid="b14">Zubizaretta (1982a</link>) and <link rid="b15">Lasnik (1998</link>) regarding whether there is reconstruction under A-movement. The form of their argumentation is as follows: if there is reconstruction, we expect it to be fully general. Whenever we have a raising-to-subject structure, we should expect all interpretations to be available that are computed on pre-movement structures. If some of these interpretations are not available, this suggests that reconstruction is not generally available.</p>
<p>One such case is attributed to Chomsky by Zubizarreta. It is based on the pair in (39&ndash;40):</p>
<p>(39)&ensp;Everyone is not listening.</p>
<p>(40)&ensp;Everyone seems not to be listening.</p>
<p>(39) allows a reading in which negation outscopes the universally quantified subject, yielding the meaning in (41):</p>
<p>(41)&ensp;It is not the case that everyone is listening.</p>
<p>Assuming reconstruction is available in (40), it should, from the relevant interpretive point of view, be treated as in (42):</p>
<p>(42)&ensp;It seems everyone is not listening.</p>
<p>and thus yield the interpretation in (43), which is not an available interpretation:</p>
<p>(43)&ensp;It seems that it is not the case that everyone is listening.</p>
<p>Lasnik argues for a similar conclusion based on the available readings for (44) (and other comparable examples):</p>
<p>(44)&ensp;Every building is 10 percent likely to collapse.</p>
<p>If reconstruction were available in such a case, it should behave as in (45):</p>
<p>(45)&ensp;It is 10 percent likely that every building will collapse.</p>
<p>But such a reading seems unavailable. What (44) says is that each building has a 10 percent probability of behaving a certain way. If there are two buildings in total, the probability that both collapse is 10 percent of 10 percent, that is, 1 percent, not 10 percent as (45) states. In other words, <i>every</i> cannot scope under <i>10 percent likely</i>: reconstruction seems impossible.</p>
<p>Although such cases raise serious problems which a theory of reconstruction must address, they do not seem to undermine the availability in principle of reconstruction in A-movement cases. First, note that the reading in (41) of (39) (and many other similar cases) looks like a straightforward case of reconstruction of A-movement from VP-internal subject position:</p>
<p>(46)&ensp;Everyone is not &lsqb;t listening&rsqb; &rarr; is not &lsqb;everyone listening&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Second, there are many other cases that <link rid="b7">Barss (1986</link>), <link rid="b8 b9">Sportiche (1997, 1999</link>), <link rid="b10">Romero (1997a</link>), <link rid="b11">Lebeaux (1998</link>), and <link rid="b16">Fox (2002</link>) provide suggesting reconstruction does take place. Cases involving complex scopal interactions can straightforwardly be computed on the basis of the pre-movement structures. Consider (47):</p>
<p>(47)&ensp;<object id="tu32" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu32_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A southerner is predicted to win every senate race.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>It is predicted that for every senate race, a (different) southerner will win it.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>For every senate race, there is a (different) southerner who is predicted to win it.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>For every senate race, it is predicted that there is a (different) southerner who will win it.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Three relevant scope-inducing elements are involved: the existential quantifier introduced by the singular indefinite subject <i>a southerner</i>, the universal quantifier <i>every</i>, and the verb <i>predict</i>. A priori this should yield six scopal readings, but the three in which <i>a southerner</i> outscopes <i>every senate race</i> are pragmatically odd (since they require the same southerner to win every senate race). The remaining three are listed in (47b, c, d). (47b) clearly is the most accessible and natural reading, and is also the most relevant for our present purposes. The readings paraphrased in (47b, c) correspond to readings in which the sentence expresses a summary of individual predictions, one for each senate race. Such readings seem difficult at best, perhaps entirely unavailable for this sentence (although pragmatically quite plausible): the sentence in (47a) most naturally reports a unique global prediction. This means that the only way that <i>every senate race</i> can outscope <i>a southerner</i> is if both of them are in the scope of the verb <i>predict</i>. These two observations indicate that one (perhaps the only) input for scope computation is (48a):</p>
<p>(48)&ensp;<object id="tu33" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu33_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>is predicted &lsqb;a southerner to win every senate race&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>a southerner will win every senate race</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As the prominent reading of (48b) shows, within a single clause, <i>every senate race</i> can then outscope <i>a southerner</i>.</p>
<p>Moreover, reconstruction effects can be illustrated with binding effects. Let us begin with Condition A, and consider the well-formed examples in (49):</p>
<p>(49)&ensp;<object id="tu34" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu34_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Pictures of each other seemed to the boys &lsqb;t to be fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Pictures of each other struck them as &lsqb;t rather fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>It seemed to each of the boys &lsqb;that pictures the other boys were fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>It struck each of them &lsqb;that pictures of the others were fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(49a, b) are well-formed with the readings indicated in (49c, d) respectively, even though the antecedent <i>them</i> of <i>each other</i> does not c-command it. Furthermore, the presence of an acceptable (plural) antecedent seems crucial to their acceptability. A similar reading with a discourse antecedent or a singular antecedent is unavailable. Thus, (50a, b) are deviant:<link rid="fn10">
<sup>10</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(50)&ensp;<object id="tu35" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu35_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Pictures of each other seemed (to him) &lsqb;t to be fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Pictures of each other struck him as &lsqb;t rather fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The interpretation of these facts is straightforward and indicates that reconstruction for binding is possible. Under reconstruction, sentences (49a, b) and (50a, b) are respectively treated from the point of view of binding as their underlying structures (in 51&ndash;52):</p>
<p>(51)&ensp;<object id="tu36" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu36_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>seemed to the boys &lsqb;pictures of each other to be fuzzy&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>struck them as &lsqb;pictures of each other rather fuzzy&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(52)&ensp;<object id="tu37" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu37_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*seemed (to him) &lsqb;pictures of each other to be fuzzy&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*struck him as &lsqb;pictures of each other rather fuzzy&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (51), the anaphors have a local enough c-commanding antecedent, while they do not in (52). The assumption that the experiencer <i>them/the boys</i> does c-command the subject of the embedded clause can be somewhat controlled by the unacceptability of (53):</p>
<p>(53)&ensp;*It seemed to <u>him</u> &lsqb;that <u>John</u> was sick&rsqb;.</p>
<p>which follows straightforwardly from a Condition C violation if this c-command relation holds. The assumption that the experiencer <i>them/the boys</i> does c-command material in the embedded infinitive can be controlled by the unacceptability of (54):</p>
<p>(54)&ensp;*Mary seemed to <u>him</u> &lsqb;t to like <u>John</u>&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Reconstruction effects with pronominal binding can also be directly illustrated. The well-formedness of (55):</p>
<p>(55)&ensp;<object id="tu38" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu38_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Pictures of his child seemed to everyone &lsqb;t to be good&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Such evaluations of his speech struck every child as &lsqb;t unfair&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>shows that A-movement can remove a c-commanding binder for a pronoun without creating a violation of the structural requirement for pronominal binding. This suggests that pronominal binding can be evaluated on the pre-movement (i.e., reconstructed) structures in (56):</p>
<p>(56)&ensp;<object id="tu39" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu39_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>seemed to everyone &lsqb;pictures of his child to be good&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>struck every child as &lsqb;such evaluations of his speech unfair&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We can control for this conclusion by first noting that close parallels to (56a) support the relevant interpretation (see (57)):</p>
<p>(57)&ensp;it seemed to everyone that pictures of his child were good</p>
<p>Second, we can check that in the absence of a position to reconstruct the raised subject in, the relevant reading is unavailable (due to the weak crossover effect: see (58)):</p>
<p>(58)&ensp;<object id="tu40" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu40_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*The new friend of <u>his</u> father painted every child.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Such teachers of <u>her</u> children call every mother.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similar reconstruction effects can also be illustrated for Condition C (cf. again <link rid="b8 b9">Sportiche 1997, 1999</link>; <link rid="b10">Romero 1997a</link>; <link rid="b12">Fox 1999</link>). We present one such type of example which will become relevant later.</p>
<p>First note that the French idioms in (59&ndash;60) can be somewhat marginally passivized as indicated:</p>
<p>(59)&ensp;<object id="tu41" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu41_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Jean a pris grand soin de Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;John took a lot of care of Mary.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin de Marie a &eacute;t&eacute; pris (par Jean).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*&lsquo;A lot of care of Mary was taken by John.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(60)&ensp;<object id="tu42" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu42_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Dans cette conversation, Jean a pris le parti de Marie trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;In this conversation, John took Mary&apos;s side three times.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>?Dans cette conversation, le parti de Marie a &eacute;t&eacute; pris trois fois (par Jean).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>?&lsquo;In this conversation, Mary&apos;s side was taken three times by John.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The idea is to use these idioms to design examples in which movement of an idiom chunk overtly removes a Condition C configuration. Their crucial feature is the passivizable object which can contain a name, and which can then be raised across a coreferential pronoun. We get (61&ndash;62):</p>
<p>(61)&ensp;<object id="tu43" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu43_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin de Marie me semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin d&rsquo;elle<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>k</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*Grand soin de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Good care of Mary/her seemed to me/her to have been taken.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(62)&ensp;<object id="tu44" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu44_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?Le parti de Marie me semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>?Son<sub>j</sub> parti lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>?Le parti de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>k</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*Le parti de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary&apos;s/her side seemed to me/her to have been taken three times.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(Passivization followed by) raising of the embedded direct object containing a name across a co-indexed pronoun systematically yields the deviant sentences (61d) and (62d), as compared to the benchmark, in which either the direct object contains a name but is raised across a non-co-indexed pronoun ((61a, b) or (62a, b)) or the direct object contains a pronoun ((61c) and (62c)).<link rid="fn11">
<sup>11</sup></link>
</p>
<p>We noted in <link rid="ss15">section 2.6</link> that idiom chunks had to reconstruct for the purpose of idiom interpretation. The effect of idiom reconstruction is to create a configuration violating Condition C. Since the sentences are deviant, they show that Condition C has access to structures reconstructed for the purpose of idiom interpretation.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss23" level="2">
<heading id="h22" level="2">3.3&ensp;Modalities of reconstruction</heading>
<p>Reconstruction seems to operate differently depending on the circumstances. In this section we briefly describe some observed possibilities before returning to some of them in later sections. First, we will illustrate the observation that reconstruction may appear to be obligatory, optional, or impossible. Second, we will briefly consider how much of a moved phrase can reconstruct.</p>
<subsection id="ss24" level="3">
<heading id="h23" level="3">3.3.1&ensp;Obligatoriness, optionality, or impossibility</heading>
<p>We will illustrate the following basic observations. First, in the simple and general case, reconstruction for Condition A is optional, while reconstruction for Condition C is obligatory. Consider again the cases of Condition C discussed previously. Imagine the context of asking questions about, or commenting to a person comparing and analyzing, various surveys of TV viewers. We find the following:</p>
<p>(63)&ensp;<object id="tu45" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu45_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> object to t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*The standard characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u>, <u>he</u> objects to t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It is not sufficient to say reconstruction is available; we must say it is obligatory. If the option of not reconstructing the (pied-piped portion of the) preposed phrase in its trace position were available, there would be a derivation without a Condition C violation and the sentences should be acceptable.</p>
<p>It is not the case, however, that reconstruction of pied-piped material is always obligatory. In some cases, it seems to be optional. Observe the contrast in (64):</p>
<p>(64)&ensp;<object id="tu46" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu46_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Whose survey describing <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This contrast is typically taken to reflect a complement&ndash;adjunct asymmetry (see <link rid="b17">Van Riemsdijk and Williams 1981</link>; <link rid="b18">Freidin 1986</link>; <link rid="b19 b20 b11">Lebeaux 1988b, 1991, 1998</link>). The offending description in (64a) is part of a pied-piped complement of the pied-piped head N of the <i>wh</i>-phrase, while it is part of the adjunct (the relative clause) to the pied-piped head N of the <i>wh</i>-phrase in (64b). We return to discussion of these facts in <link rid="ss31">section 4.2.1</link>.</p>
<p>In the case of Condition A, the optionality of reconstruction can easily be illustrated. We have seen that pied-piped phrases containing anaphors may reconstruct into any of their traces, but they need not reconstruct at all. Thus (65a) is well-formed with the interpretation given in (65b):</p>
<p>(65)&ensp;<object id="tu47" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu47_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry><u>They</u> wonder which pictures of <u>each other</u> I preferred t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Each of them wonders which pictures of the others I preferred.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>If reconstruction were required, we would expect this sentence to be deviant, since the only possible antecedent, <i>they</i>, for <i>each other</i> would be &lsquo;too far&rsquo;. This expectation is not met.</p>
<p>Second, sometimes reconstruction is impossible. We have already seen such cases in A-movement constructions. For example, (44), repeated here as (66), lacks a reading in which <i>10 percent likely</i> outscopes <i>every</i>:</p>
<p>(66)&ensp;Every building is 10 percent likely to collapse.</p>
<p>Other, superficially more complex cases of impossible reconstruction are illustrated in (67&ndash;68):</p>
<p>(67)&ensp;<object id="tu48" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu48_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Stand on every roof, a guard will.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>A guard will stand on every roof.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Every roof will have a different guard on it.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(68)&ensp;<object id="tu49" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu49_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Likely to win, nobody is.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Nobody is likely to win.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>It is likely that nobody will win. (&equals; In all likelihood, nobody will win.)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Nobody has the property of being likely to win.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(67a) should, under reconstruction of the preposed constituent, allow all the readings allowed by (67b), and in particular, the pragmatically most plausible reading paraphrased by (67c). Such a reading seems unavailable, perhaps suggesting that reconstruction of the preposed constituent is not possible. (68a) should, under reconstruction of the preposed constituent, allow all the readings allowed by (68b), and in particular, the reading paraphrased by (68c). Such a reading also seems unavailable, only the reading paraphrased by (68d) is available. This again may suggest that reconstruction of the preposed constituent is not possible.</p>
<p>We will not discuss any of these extremely interesting cases any further here. <link rid="b21">Sportiche (2003</link>) extensively discusses cases of the sort in (66). <link rid="b7">Barss (1986</link>), <link rid="b22">Sauerland (1999c</link>), and <link rid="b23">Sauerland and Elbourne (2002</link>) discuss the sorts in (67&ndash;68).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss25" level="3">
<heading id="h24" level="3">3.3.2&ensp;Partial reconstruction vs. radical reconstruction</heading>
<p>As we mentioned earlier in <link rid="ss6">section 1.2.2</link>, reconstruction typically is held to affect only pied-piped material. Whether or not this description is factually accurate depends on a fine analysis of movement triggers and targets. Superficially, however, it seems false.</p>
<p>First consider a <i>wh</i>-question already discussed in 2.2.1 ((14b), repeated here as (69); see also note 8).</p>
<p>(69)&ensp;How many friends of <u>a friend</u> did you convince Bill that <u>every member</u> should co-opt t?</p>
<p>There does not seem to be a reading in which the <i>wh</i>-operator <i>how many</i> reconstructs. Such a question would ask, for each member, the number of friends of a friend (of his) that you convinced Bill that this member should co-opt. The unavailability of such a reading is plausible given that <i>wh</i>-operators seem to be propositional operators, which in English<link rid="fn12">
<sup>12</sup></link> scope over the clause in front of which they are preposed. Thus it is quite plausible to assume that they cannot reconstruct.<link rid="fn13">
<sup>13</sup></link> Such examples may thus involve partial reconstruction.</p>
<p>There are cases for which it is harder to tell. For example, in cases of &lsquo;Topicalization&rsquo; such as (70):</p>
<p>(70)&ensp;A book, it is obvious everyone will buy.</p>
<p>the whole of the preposed element can be under the scope of <i>every</i>, suggesting total or so-called &lsquo;radical&rsquo; reconstruction. But we cannot really decide without knowing exactly what the movement trigger and targets are. In particular, when a constituent is topicalized, there are informational properties added to the sentence (being a topic or a focus, etc.). What would it mean for these properties to be reconstructed, and are they?</p>
<p>Finally, there are similar cases in A-movement constructions. The reading in which the subject scopes under the raising verb in (71a) seems undistinguishable from the interpretation that (71b) &ndash; without the movement &ndash; would receive:</p>
<p>(71)&ensp;<object id="tu50" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu50_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A southerner will win every senate race.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>is predicted &lsqb;a southerner to win every senate race&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Such cases are also said to involve radical reconstruction. We will not discuss these questions any further here. Some issues regarding A-movement are addressed in <link rid="b22">Sauerland (1999c</link>) and <link rid="b23">Sauerland and Elbourne (2002</link>).</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss26" level="1">
<heading id="h25" level="1">4&ensp;Accounts</heading>
<p>We now turn to discussions of the accounts that have been given of the reconstruction effects found with each principle, accompanied by some critical remarks. We will provide a discussion of each principle and its associated reconstructed effects in turn. In the next section, we will look at how all the various conclusions reached for each individual principle can be reconciled in a coherent whole.</p>
<p>We begin by outlining the essential ingredients of the theoretical constructions elaborated in the Principles and Parameters framework to account for the facts above, following more or less their historical development. Again, very little that will be discussed depends on the particular notation that we use; most of what we say could readily be translated into other notations. However, we need to be rather specific about this notation to do justice to some of the proposals that have been put forth within this framework.</p>
<p>We assume the following:</p>
<listgroup id="l6" type="i">
<li level="1">
<number>(i)&ensp;</number>
<p>There is a level of surface syntactic structures (surface trees or, in Minimalist terms, input to spell-out). These structures are derived from underlying syntactic structures by means of movement.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(ii)&ensp;</number>
<p>There is a level of underlying structures (underlying trees). These structures are defined as representing predicate argument relations as local syntactic relations.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(iii)&ensp;</number>
<p>Movement maps underlying trees onto surface trees (spell-out trees) by successive application. Movement dependencies are represented as trace-binding relations in surface syntactic structures.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>(iv)&ensp;</number>
<p>A surface structure tree can be manipulated by processes yielding its Logical Form (LF), which is the interface with non-grammatical systems of interpretation.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Note that conceptually, in such models, LF representations, which may (or may not) differ from underlying or surface representations, have their raison d&rsquo;&ecirc;tre in providing a transparent input for semantic interpretation. In effect, LFs &lsquo;are&rsquo; exhaustive representations of the structure-sensitive aspects of sentence meanings. Note also that there is a priori no assumption that LFs are different from underlying structures or surface (spelled-out) structures.</p>
<subsection id="ss27" level="2">
<heading id="h26" level="2">4.1&ensp;Condition A</heading>
<p>We begin with a discussion of reconstruction effects with respect to Condition A. Recall what we have established so far:</p>
<listgroup id="l7" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>There are reconstruction effects with respect to Condition A.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction for Condition A can be into any trace position of the moved phrase.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction is optional.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>How do we account for these properties?</p>
<subsection id="ss28" level="3">
<heading id="h27" level="3">4.1.1&ensp;Anywhere Principle</heading>
<p>All accounts essentially have the same structure: they simply allow a moved phrase containing an anaphor to be evaluated in any position that it is linked to by movement &ndash; its original position or any intermediate landing position. In the literature, several alternative proposals (P) are put forward to derive this result:</p>
<p><b>P1 Literal reconstruction:</b> Condition A applies at the output of a manipulated surface structure in which pied-piped material is literally in a position in which Condition A can be satisfied. Under such a proposal, (72a) would be first manipulated to yield the LF (72b). Condition A would be applied to this LP, yielding the interpretation in (72c) or ultimately (72d):</p>
<p>(72)&ensp;<object id="tu51" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu51_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which pictures of <u>each other they</u> remained fond of t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I wonder which <u>they</u> remained fond of pictures of <u>each other</u>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>I wonder for which x, <u>they</u> remained fond of x, pictures of <u>each other</u> (x).</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>I wonder for which x, each of them remained fond of x, pictures of the others (x).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p><b>P2 Modification of Condition A (<link rid="b7 b24">Barss 1986, 1988</link>):</b> The binding domain of an anaphor for Condition A is by definition computed from any position that the anaphor has occupied in the course of a derivation. Thus, in (72a), the local domain of the anaphor can be computed either from the position that <i>which pictures of each other</i> occupies at surface structure or from t.</p>
<p><b>P3 Condition A as an anywhere principle (<link rid="b25">Belletti and Rizzi 1988</link>):</b> Condition A can be satisfied in the course of a derivation. As long as an anaphor satisfies Condition A at any point in the course of derivation, Condition A is satisfied. Thus, (72a) is well-formed because Condition A is satisfied before <i>wh</i>-movement takes place.</p>
<p>P2 is stated in derivational terms while P3 is stated in representational terms (it can be seen as applying to a single level of representation). For our purposes, they are equivalent. The question, then, is whether we can distinguish P1 from P2/P3.</p>
<p>Consider, first, reciprocals. Recall that a reciprocal is a bound variable. As a result, it seems clear that given the shared conceptualization of LF, only P1 is acceptable for reciprocals. Indeed, since a reciprocal is a bound variable, to be interpreted as such it must be in the scope of &ndash; that is, be c-commanded by &ndash; its antecedent at LF (recall this is how LF is defined). This means literal reconstruction is required anyway for the LF of (72a). The other alternatives seem to become redundant.</p>
<p>It should be noted that current theoretical developments considerably narrow the difference between these two (or three) approaches. Indeed, under some recent models (Minimalist cyclic models), LF representations are constructed and interpreted cyclically from the bottom up. As a result, Condition A could reasonably be held to have to be checked at the end of each cycle, rather than only once at the end of the last cycle, giving the appearance of P2 or P3 under the guise of P1.</p>
<p>Turning now to reflexives, it is clear that this reasoning does not necessarily apply to them. Unlike reciprocals, a reflexive does not have to be analyzed as a bound variable. It can be thought of as a pronoun coreferential with (i.e., picking out the same referent as) its antecedent, whose selection obeys c-command and locality constraints. In other words, scope and the determination of an acceptable antecedent are perhaps divorced in the case of reflexives, and may thus provide a way to distinguish P1 from P2/P3 as they apply to reflexives. Indeed, if a phrase containing a reflexive is allowed to outscope the c-command position of the antecedent of the reflexive, P1 cannot be right, while P2/P3 may. We will leave this question open here (but see <link rid="b26">Cresti 1995</link> and <link rid="b27">Fox and Nissenbaum 2002</link> for some discussion).</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss29" level="3">
<heading id="h28" level="3">4.1.2&ensp;Predicate&ndash;argument asymmetry</heading>
<p>The statement that reconstruction for Condition A can be into any trace position of the moved phrase seem contradicted by the existence of the kind of case in (73&ndash;74), noted in <link rid="b28">Cinque (1984</link>) and <link rid="b7">Barss (1986</link>):</p>
<p>(73)&ensp;<object id="tu52" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu52_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;These pictures of each other&rsqb;, I think they liked t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Visit each other&apos;s parents&rsqb;, I think they will t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(74)&ensp;<object id="tu53" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu53_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>They think that &lsqb;these pictures of each other&rsqb;, I like t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*They think that &lsqb;visit each other&apos;s parents&rsqb;, I will t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (73), the preposed phrase may reconstruct, allowing <i>they</i> to antecede <i>each other</i>. (74a, b), however, diverge: (74a) allows <i>each other</i> to take <i>they</i> as antecedent, indicating that the domain for anaphor binding is the main clause. This is not sufficient, however, for (74b), which is deviant. This suggests that predicate movement (such as VP-preposing) differs from A-bar movement of DPs: predicate movement behaves as if reconstruction is always obligatory even when anaphors are involved: if the preposed predicate must be interpreted in the position t in (74b), its deviance is derived. This generalization seems corroborated by the behavior of AP preposing:</p>
<p>(75)&ensp;<object id="tu54" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu54_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>I wonder how fond of <u>each other&apos;s parents</u> (Bill thinks) <u>they</u> are t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>They</u> wonder how fond of <u>each other&apos;s parents</u> (Bill thinks) Sue is t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As (75b) illustrates, it is not possible to select <i>they</i> as antecedent, even though it would be in the local domain of the anaphor if it could compute its binding domain from the moved position. Furthermore, when there are intermediate traces, reconstruction must be all the way down:</p>
<p>(76)&ensp;<object id="tu55" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu55_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*I wonder how fond of <u>each other&apos;s parents they</u> think &lsqb;t Bill is t&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*Visit <u>each other&apos;s</u> parents, <u>you</u> think &lsqb;t <u>they</u> said &lsqb;t Mary and Bill did t&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Reconstruction into intermediate trace positions would wrongly allow <i>they</i> to be antecedent in (76a) and <i>you</i> or <i>they</i> in (76b).</p>
<p>Descriptively, the computation of the binding domain for Condition A of an anaphor pied-piped under predicate movement must take place from the lowest possible reconstructed position. Of course, a theory of reconstruction should be able to derive why predicate movement behaves differently from other types of movement. We postpone this discussion to <link rid="ss40">section 5.3</link>, until after we have discussed reconstruction effects for Condition C.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss30" level="2">
<heading id="h29" level="2">4.2&ensp;Condition C</heading>
<p>We now turn to a more detailed discussion of reconstruction effects with respect to Condition C. Summarizing the descriptive generalizations we have from <link rid="ss24">section 3.3.1</link>, we get:</p>
<listgroup id="l8" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction for Condition C is obligatory.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction for adjuncts is optional.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>We will begin by examining how the second generalization should be derived. Next we will survey some proposals regarding the first generalization and proceed to discuss cases in which it appears violated. We will then return to predicate&ndash;argument asymmetries discussed in the previous section and survey how these asymmetries should be handled.</p>
<subsection id="ss31" level="3">
<heading id="h30" level="3">4.2.1&ensp;Argument&ndash;adjunct distinction</heading>
<p>Recall what the argument&ndash;adjunct asymmetry is. It is based on the kind of contrast in (77a, b):</p>
<p>(77)&ensp;<object id="tu56" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu56_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;Whose survey describing <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As was said earlier, this contrast is typically taken to reflect a complement&ndash;adjunct asymmetry (see <link rid="b17">Van Riemsdijk and Williams 1981</link>; <link rid="b18">Freidin 1986</link>; <link rid="b19 b20 b11">Lebeaux 1988b, 1991, 1998</link>). The offending description in (77a) is part of a pied-piped complement of the pied-piped head N of the <i>wh</i>-phrase, while it is part of the adjunct (the relative clause) to the pied-piped head N of the <i>wh</i>-phrase in (77b).</p>
<p>(78) initially suggests that what is at stake in this difference is not only the degree of embedding of the offending descriptions within the preposed phrase, since they are more or less equally embedded:</p>
<p>(78)&ensp;<object id="tu57" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu57_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which pictures that you had given to <u>an actor you know</u> did <u>he</u> say you wanted back t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*How happy that you had met <u>an actor you knew</u> did <u>he</u> say you were t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In both cases, the offending description is embedded inside a pied-piped clause. When this pied-piped clause is a complement of the Adjective head of the <i>wh</i>-phrase, deviance results. This seems to strengthen the conclusion that we are dealing with a complement&ndash;adjunct asymmetry. We should note, however, that this assumption is controversial (see, for example, <link rid="b6">Safir 1999</link>; <link rid="b5">Kuno 1997</link>; <link rid="b15">Lasnik 1998</link>) and there seems to be some poorly understood speaker variation. In what follows, we will suppose that the relevant difference is indeed a complement&ndash;adjunct asymmetry and we will formulate the relevant generalizations in these terms.</p>
<p>At this point, the most mainstream idea concerning how to treat this asymmetry is the one put forward by <link rid="b19 b20">Lebeaux (1988b, 1991</link>). To resolve the apparent paradox caused by the difference between (77a) and (77b), Lebeaux suggests that unlike a complement to a phrase, an adjunct to a phrase &ndash; here the relative clause adjunct to the NP <i>survey</i> &ndash; can be inserted in a derivation after this phrase has moved (can be inserted acyclically).<link rid="fn14">
<sup>14</sup></link> Accordingly, the derivation of (77b) would have the stages in (79):</p>
<p>(79)&ensp;<object id="tu58" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu58_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Underlying structure:</entry>
<entry>He resents whose survey?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry><i>Wh</i>-movement:</entry>
<entry>Whose survey does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Adjunct insertion:</entry>
<entry>Whose survey &lsqb;describing <u>the typical male viewer</u>&rsqb; does <u>he</u> resent t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since reconstruction is, descriptively, a matter of accessing a pre-movement structure to evaluate interpretation, no Condition C can arise in such cases if such a derivation is possible. Hence the complement&ndash;adjunct asymmetry that we have been assuming holds in these reconstruction cases.</p>
<p>Granting the correctness of the putative adjunct&ndash;argument asymmetry and Lebeaux&apos;s basic idea, several questions arise, which we address in turn. The first is why adjuncts can be inserted in this fashion while complements cannot. One idea is that relations of predicate saturation and modification must be syntactically local. A predicate needs its complement locally to be properly saturated. This means that at LF, a predicate must have its complement locally. If reconstruction is nothing but access to pre-movement structures, complements must be inserted in underlying structures. A phrase also needs its modifier locally somewhere, but this can be satisfied anywhere, e.g., after the phrase has moved. Such an idea makes sense especially for representations that are interpreted, that is, LFs. Consider now the well-formed example in (80a):</p>
<p>(80)&ensp;<object id="tu59" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu59_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like &lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The head of the relative clause must reconstruct to allow <i>each other</i> to be properly and locally bound by <i>they</i>, but the relative must have been inserted late in order to avoid a Condition C violation between <i>John</i> and <i>he</i>. This means the interpreted form must be as in (80b); that is, the head of the relative clause must be present twice: once in the low position, because complements must reconstruct and because <i>each other</i> needs to be properly bound, and once high, so that the relative clause can modify it locally.</p>
<p>This is natural in the context of <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) proposal that traces are copies (to which we return in <link rid="ss38">section 5.2.1</link>): the second form is simply the LF representation of the first:</p>
<p>(81)&ensp;<object id="tu60" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu60_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like &lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This means that we could just as well state Lebeaux&apos;s idea representationally by stating that the only requirement should be that LFs satisfy the locality requirement necessary to interpret predicate&ndash;complement (more generally predicate&ndash;argument) and modifier&ndash;modifiee relations. In such a case, the derivation of these sentences (if there is one) would be (82):<link rid="fn15">
<sup>15</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(82)&ensp;<object id="tu61" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu61_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>John</u> likes&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>he</u> think they like &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other&rsqb; &lsqb;<strike>which <u>John</u> likes</strike>&rsqb;&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>with selective LF erasure of what need not be interpreted (here the lowest copy of the adjunct).</p>
<p>As a last remark on this topic, it should be noted that relative clauses raise particular problems. First, it is not entirely clear that relative clauses should be treated as adjuncts. <link rid="b30">Kayne (1994</link>), for example, argues that they should be treated as complements of Determiners. Second, there are cases which have been argued to involve raising of the head of the relative clause from inside the relative clause (cf. <link rid="b31">Vergnaud 1974</link>; <link rid="b30">Kayne 1994</link>). According to such proposals, the head of the relative must originate inside the relative clause. Consequently, the relative clause cannot be inserted as an instance of late adjunct insertion, which makes this derivational approach problematic. The representational equivalent does not face such a problem, however, as selective reconstruction (or partial copy erasure) is still viable.</p>
<p>A relevant case would be the well-formed sentence in (83):</p>
<p>(83)&ensp;Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other<sub>j</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>Jane</u> showed the boys<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u>she</u> think you like?</p>
<p>Since the reciprocal <i>each other</i>, as part of the head of the relative clause, is bound by the object inside the relative clause, this should be a case of a head having raised from inside the relative clause. Under a derivational approach &agrave; la Lebeaux/Chomsky, the lower copy should at least contain the head of the relative clause, hence the relative clause itself (since this head is only introduced inside the relative clause), incorrectly triggering a Condition C violation, as in (84a). Under a representional approach, no such problem arises: portion of traces can be selectively interpreted as in (84b):</p>
<p>(84)&ensp;<object id="tu62" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu62_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other<sub>j</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>Jane</u> showed the boys<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u><b>she</b>
</u> think you like &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other<sub>j</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u><b>Jane</b>
</u> showed the boys<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which &lsqb;&lsqb;pictures of each other<sub>j</sub>&rsqb; &lsqb;which <u>Jane</u> showed the boys<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;&rsqb; does <u><b>she</b>
</u> think you like &lsqb;pictures of each other<sub>j</sub>&rsqb;?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We leave these questions open and refer to <link rid="b32">Sportiche (2000</link>) for further discussion.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss32" level="3">
<heading id="h31" level="3">4.2.2&ensp;Anywhere Principle</heading>
<p>Ignoring the adjunct&ndash;argument asymmetries just discussed, the preliminary observations we have presented suggest that reconstruction is obligatory when it comes to Condition C effects. We first sharpen this observation by asking what happens when there are several traces. (85a, b) are illustrative:</p>
<p>(85)&ensp;<object id="tu63" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu63_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u> does <u>he</u> object to t1?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Whose characterization of <u>the typical male viewer</u> do you think t2 <u>he</u> object to t1?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(85b) is deviant.<link rid="fn16">
<sup>16</sup></link> If obligatory reconstruction could be done in the intermediate trace t2, no Condition C effect should arise, leaving this deviance unexplained. We conclude that with respect to Condition C, reconstruction is mandatory in the lowest trace, all the way down.</p>
<p>How should these observations be handled? There are basically two proposals:</p>
<listgroup id="l9" type="text">
<li level="1">
<number><b><b>P4:</b>
</b>&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C is an anywhere principle: it cannot be violated at any stage of a derivation.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number><b><b>P5:</b>
</b>&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C applies at LF and literal reconstruction is obligatory: the (pied-piped portion of the) moved phrase occurs in LF in the position of the most deeply embedded trace.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>P4 is put forward by <link rid="b19 b20 b11">Lebeaux (1988b, 1991, 1998</link>), while P5 is proposed by <link rid="b29">Chomsky (1995c</link>) and is defended in <link rid="b12">Fox (1999</link>) (but perhaps undermined by <link rid="b16">Fox 2002</link> and by <link rid="b33">Fox and Nissenbaum 1999</link>, as we will see below).</p>
<p>Comparing P4 and P5, it is easy to see that P5 is conceptually preferable: why should Condition C, a principle of interpretation, apply anywhere else but at LF? This is one of the reasons Chomsky provides for his view.<link rid="fn17">
<sup>17</sup></link> However, just as we have discussed in connection with Condition A, this argument loses some force in a model in which bits of LF are incrementally and cyclically calculated. P4 could, in such a model, be seen as applying at the output of each cycle. P5 could too, so that the differences between them would be much diminished, but it could also apply as originally intended by Chomsky (i.e., as last cyclic in a cyclic model).</p>
<p>Still, the proposals would not be identical. Are there grounds on which to decide whether P4 can be an anywhere Principle as Lebeaux defines it? Note that P4 is stronger than P5: P5 applies to a subset of cases that P4 applies to. The way to decide, then, is to find cases falling under P4 but not under P5 and see whether they are deviant or not: P4 predicts a positive answer, P5 a negative one. What we need to find are sentences in which a pre-movement structure violates Condition C, but the post-movement structure does not. P4 predicts them to be deviant, P5 does not.</p>
<p>One class of cases is discussed by <link rid="b34">May and Fiengo (1994</link>) and <link rid="b12 b16">Fox (1999, 2002</link>), and involves Antecedent Contained Deletion (ACD). Examples are in (86):</p>
<p>(86)&ensp;<object id="tu64" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu64_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*If the pollsters showed <u>him</u> the characterizations of the typical male viewer . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>If the pollsters showed <u>him</u> the surveys <u>the typical male viewer</u> would want them to . . .</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;<u>the typical male viewer</u> would want them to ___ &rsqb;<sub>j</sub> the pollsters <i>showed <u>him</u> t</i><sub><i>j</i>
</sub>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(86a), a Condition C effect, shows that the pronoun <i>him</i> c-commands the second object <i>the characterizations of the typical male viewer</i>. Despite this c-command relationship, (86b) is fine. The basic reasoning proposed is the following (see the references cited for more detail): the antecedent of the missing VP in (86b) is the VP containing the relative clause. Replacing the missing VP with its antecedent would lead to infinite regress (as it still contains the missing VP). To resolve this paradox, movement of the relative to a position outside of the VP must be available as in (86c), providing a non-paradoxical antecedent (in italics) for the missing VP. As a side-effect, this movement removes <i>the typical male viewer</i> from the c-command domain of the pronoun <i>him</i>. The fact that the sentence is fine suggests that Condition C is checked only after this movement has taken place.</p>
<p>However, according to <link rid="b16">Fox (2002</link>) and <link rid="b33">Fox and Nissenbaum (1999</link>), this last set of examples could be derived without the relative clause being c-commanded by the pronoun at any level &ndash; roughly speaking, the relative clause is merged into the tree as extraposed. Such analyses crucially rely on the adjunct&ndash;argument asymmetry (perhaps analyzed as late adjunct insertion &ndash; see <link rid="ss31">section 4.2.1</link>). Under such analyses, these examples, which involve the relative clauses as adjuncts, become irrelevant to the present point. A discussion of this proposal is important to decide the significance of examples such as (86a) and (86b), but this is beyond the scope of this chapter.<link rid="fn18">
<sup>18</sup></link>
</p>
<p>There are cases, however, which seem more difficult to reconcile with P4. Consider the following examples involving A-movement, such as (87a) with (87b) as pre-movement structure:</p>
<p>(87)&ensp;<object id="tu65" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu65_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>This picture of <u>John</u> seems to <u>him</u> &lsqb; t to be fuzzy&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>seems to <u>him</u> &lsqb;this picture of <u>John</u> to be fuzzy&rsqb;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Since this sentence is well-formed, it suggests that Condition C is not checked before movement, as the pre-movement structure in (87b) would otherwise violate Condition C. <link rid="b20 b11">Lebeaux (1991, 1998</link>), who wants to preserve Condition C as an Anywhere Principle, suggests a different theory of underlying structure to get around this problem, namely that in underlying structure, all NPs are empty slots which are allowed to be filled only after A-movement has taken place. Accordingly the underlying structure for (87a) would be:</p>
<p>(88)&ensp;seems to <u>him</u> &lsqb;&lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> this &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> e&rsqb; of &lsqb;<sub>DP</sub> D &lsqb;<sub>NP</sub> e&rsqb;&rsqb; to be fuzzy&rsqb;</p>
<p>In this structure, it must be assumed that Names such as NPs are NPs (a non-trivial assumption) with a silent Determiner, annotated as D here. At this point, this DP would not qualify as a name or an R-expression and thus not fall under Condition C. Insertion of <i>John</i> would take place after raising to subject yielding (87a).</p>
<p>There are several problems with such an approach. One problem is that it is unclear exactly what the principles guiding the form of underlying structures are any more. Another is the fact mentioned earlier involving idiom chunks (which is actually a fact about scope). Recall that if an idiom chunk is (passivized and) raised, we get Condition C effects ((61&ndash;62), repeated here as (89&ndash;90)):</p>
<p>(89)&ensp;<object id="tu66" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu66_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin de Marie me semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin d&rsquo;elle<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>?Grand soin de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>k</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*Grand soin de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Good care of Mary/her seemed to me/her to have been taken.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(90)&ensp;<object id="tu67" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu67_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?Le parti de Marie me semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>?Son<sub>j</sub> parti lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>?Le parti de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>k</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">d.</entry>
<entry>*Le parti de Marie<sub>j</sub> lui<sub>j</sub> semble avoir &eacute;t&eacute; pris t trois fois.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;Mary&apos;s/her side seemed to me/her to have been taken three times.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>To get a Condition C effect, the name must be c-commanded by the pronoun either in underlying structure or at LF. If the former, a reason must be found as to why an NP object of an idiom chunk must be inserted in underlying structure. If the latter, we must suppose that we reconstruct into the trace position material that was never there in the first place. (What then is the reconstruction process?)</p>
<p>Similar conclusions can be reached by looking at cases (cf. <link rid="b8 b9">Sportiche 1997, 1999</link>; <link rid="b10">Romero 1997a</link>; <link rid="b12">Fox 1999</link>) in which a raised subject containing a name is understood as under the scope of the raising verb. <link rid="b12">Fox (1999</link>), provides the following example, again going in the same direction:</p>
<p>(91)&ensp;*For these issues to be clarified, many more new papers about Quine<sub>j</sub>&apos;s philosophy seem to him<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;t to be needed&rsqb;.</p>
<p>Fox&apos;s reported judgment is as indicated. This sentence is constructed so as to strongly favor a reading in which the existence of these new papers is not asserted. In other words, it strongly favors a reading in which the subject is interpreted as reconstructed in the scope of the verb <i>seem</i>, i.e., as corresponding to the underlying representation in (92):</p>
<p>(92)&ensp;seem to him<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;to be needed many more new papers about Quine<sub>j</sub>&apos;s philosophy&rsqb;</p>
<p>Its status ensues from the Condition C violation that is incurred.</p>
<p>As a control, note that coreference per se is not problematic. (93), with the pronoun and the name swapped, is fine:</p>
<p>(93)&ensp;Many more new papers about his philosophy seem to Quine<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;t to be needed&rsqb;.</p>
<p>All these are cases in which movement removes an offending configuration for Condition C, and thus they argue against the idea that Condition C is an Anywhere Principle.</p>
<p>We conclude that Condition C applies at LF and does not apply to underlying structures.<link rid="fn19">
<sup>19</sup></link> This is not compatible with P4, but it is with P5 and thus favors the latter (under either construal: cyclic or last cyclic). It is less clear at this point whether P5 is correct in stating that Condition C only applies at LF rather than, say, to surface representations as well (if they are different). In a Minimalist model such as <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>), given the results above, LF would indeed be the only option.</p>
<p>Assuming the correctness of P5 raises further problems. If the mapping from (what roughly corresponds to) surface representations to LF is not trivial, it remains to be explained why, in general, such mapping operations (<i>wh</i>-in-situ interpretation, quantifier raising &ndash; apart perhaps from the ACD cases discussed earlier) never bleed Condition C. For example:</p>
<p>(94)&ensp;<object id="tu68" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu68_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>A different person compared her to every picture of Jane.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Who told him about which picture of Bill?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (94a), <i>every picture of Jane</i> can outscope <i>a different person</i>, but this interpretive operation (quantifier raising to a position higher than the subject) cannot remove the Condition C violation incurred if <i>her</i> and <i>Jane</i> are coreferential. In (94b), if <i>wh</i>-movement preposes <i>which picture of Bill</i> to &lsqb;spec, CP&rsqb;, there will not be a Condition C violation at LF.</p>
<p>One option is to assume that there are no &lsquo;covert&rsquo; operations (cf. <link rid="b35">Williams 1986</link>; <link rid="b36">Brody 1995b</link>); another is to assume that Condition C applies to &lsquo;surface-like&rsquo; structures. In <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) Minimalist framework, the second option is unavailable and the first is not considered. This is why, talking about <i>wh</i>-in situ interpretation, Chomsky suggests that such mapping operations move only the quantifier and not the whole DP (just the D without the NP), here yielding (95), which still violates Condition C:</p>
<p>(95)&ensp;which &lsqb;who told him about t picture of Bill&rsqb;</p>
<p>Chomsky&apos;s copy theory of traces could be construed differently to handle this general observation. Adopting for expository purposes <link rid="b16">Fox&apos;s (2002</link>) construal of such copies as definite descriptions and assuming phrasal covert movement, the LF of (94a) would roughly be (96):</p>
<p>(96)&ensp;for every picture of Jane &lsqb;a different person compared her to this picture of Jane&rsqb;</p>
<p>New problems of course now arise: if traces are copies, or if movement is limited to Ds, what happens in the cases of ACD discussed above? We refer to <link rid="b12 b16">Fox (1999, 2002</link>) and <link rid="b33">Fox and Nissenbaum (1999</link>) for further discussion.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss33" level="3">
<heading id="h32" level="3">4.2.3&ensp;Predicate&ndash;argument asymmetry</heading>
<p>Unlike argument preposing, predicate preposing does not seem to increase the set of possible antecedents for a pied-pied anaphor. This contrast is illustrated in (97):</p>
<p>(97)&ensp;<object id="tu69" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu69_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>They think that &lsqb;these pictures of each other&rsqb;, John likes t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*They think that &lsqb;visit each other&apos;s parents&rsqb;, John will t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>How should this contrast be handled?</p>
<p>One class of proposals (<link rid="b37">Williams 1980</link>; <link rid="b7 b24">Barss 1986, 1988</link>; <link rid="b38">Huang 1993</link>; and in part <link rid="b39">Reinhart and Reuland 1993</link>) require (using different devices) that nothing other than the subject of a predicate can bind an anaphor inside this predicate from outside this predicate: either the anaphor is bound internally to the predicate phrase, or it is bound by the subject of this predicate. Clearly all such proposals will be able to exclude (97b), since the only antecedent it would allow for the reciprocal would be <i>John.</i> However, most will be insufficient in general to extend to cases not involving anaphors. For example, <link rid="b7">Barss (1986</link>) and <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) note the ill-formedness of the type of example in (98):</p>
<p>(98)&ensp;<object id="tu70" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu70_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Bribe <u>a Nobel Prize winner</u>&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, <u>he</u> did t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Bribe <u>a Nobel Prize winner</u>&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, <u>he</u> says you<sub>j</sub> did t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The relevant factor here is that coreference between <i>he</i> and <i>a Nobel Prize winner</i> is excluded. One option for handling these facts would be to adopt <link rid="b20">Lebeaux&apos;s (1991</link>) proposal that Condition C is an Anywhere Principle and cannot be violated at any stage of the derivation. However, we have seen that this option is not tenable. Furthermore, it would not generalize to the anaphor cases.</p>
<p>In effect what is needed to handle all of these cases ((97) and (98)) is some reason why reconstruction of preposed predicates to their lowest trace is required. If such is the case, examples (97b) and (98b) would respectively receive the LFs in (99):</p>
<p>(99)&ensp;<object id="tu71" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu71_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*They think that <strike>&lsqb;visit each other&apos;s parents&rsqb;</strike>, John will &lsqb;visit each other&apos;s parents&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;Bribe a Nobel Prize Winner&rsqb;, <u>he</u> says you did.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>whose ill-formed status follows immediately. This is exactly what <link rid="b7">Barss (1986</link>) proposes. The question is now why it should be true that reconstruction of predicates is required.</p>
<p>There are two proposals in the literature. The first is an elaboration of <link rid="b38">Huang (1993</link>) due to <link rid="b41">Takano (1995</link>), which we will detail below. The second is due to <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>), who argues that predicates must always reconstruct for scope reasons. If we accept that predicates must (at least under normal circumstances) take narrow scope &ndash; and <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) provides strong supporting evidence for this claim &ndash; we derive the reconstruction properties of preposed predicates. We only have an explanation, however, if we can derive the idea that predicates must have narrow scope. Otherwise, we simply have a sophisticated stipulation of the result that we want with as many stipulated properties (&equals; predicates must have narrow scope) as results (&equals; they must reconstruct). In other words, granting that predicates must always reconstruct for scope reasons, the question is why.</p>
<p>If the semantic properties of predicates somehow precluded them from being interpreted with wide scope, we would have such an explanation, but there do not seem to be reasons why failure to reconstruct a predicate should lead to semantic ill-formedness. Thus a priori there is nothing wrong with representation of the meaning of (100a) as (100b) with wide scope of the predicate:</p>
<p>(100)&ensp;<object id="tu72" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu72_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>John will sleep.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>There is a property P of sleeping, will (P (John)). (assuming verbs range over properties or relations)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<link rid="b38">Huang&apos;s (1993</link>) proposal seems to be successfully extendable to all such cases, and with some explanatory power, because it seems independently plausible given general assumptions about phrase structure. Regarding anaphors, Huang suggests the preposing of predicates actually always preposes a constituent containing the subject of this predicate. As a result, the domain within which the anaphor must be bound is no larger than this preposed constituent itself.</p>
<p>The details of this proposal are as follows: first, the subject of a predicate is always generated internally to the projection of this predicate as specifier of this projection (this is the so-called Predicate Internal Subject Hypothesis, justified on independent grounds). In underlying structure, the subject of a verb V (or an adjective A) is always the specifier of the corresponding VP (or AP). If this subject shows up elsewhere, it has been moved. For example, (101a) has the surface structure indicated in (101b):</p>
<p>(101)&ensp;<object id="tu73" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu73_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>John will see Mary.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>John<sub>j</sub> will &lsqb;<sub>VP</sub> t<sub>j</sub> &lsqb;see Mary&rsqb;&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The structure of the example involving VP-preposing now looks as in (102):</p>
<p>(102)&ensp;<object id="tu74" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu74_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Visit each other&apos;s friends, you think they said &lsqb;Bill and Mary&rsqb;<sub>j</sub> will t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Visit each other&apos;s friends&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, you think they said &lsqb;Bill and Mary&rsqb;<sub>j</sub> will t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The trace t<sub>j</sub> closes off the domain within which <i>each other</i> can look for an antecedent and thus can be the only antecedent available. Since this trace is the trace of <i>Bill and Mary</i>, <i>Bill and Mary</i> is the only allowed antecedent. One appealing aspect of this proposal is that under these assumptions about phrase structure, pied-piping of the subject trace follows from the general properties of phrasal movement: the subject trace is within the minimal phrasal constituent containing the predicate and thus must move along with it; the minimal movable projection of a predicate always contains the (trace of the) subject of this predicate.</p>
<p>Of course, this proposal covers (98a) but not (98b), repeated &ndash; with traces &ndash; as (103):</p>
<p>(103)&ensp;<object id="tu75" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu75_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Bribe <u>a Nobel Prize winner</u>&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, <u>he</u><sub>j</sub> did t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Bribe <u>a Nobel Prize winner</u>&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, <u>he</u><sub>m</sub> says you<sub>j</sub> did t<sub>k</sub>.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As we saw earlier, (98b) would also be straightforwardly handled as a Condition C effect if the VP were forced to literally reconstruct: the description <i>a Nobel Prize winner</i> would be c-commanded by the coreferential pronoun <i>he</i>, thus triggering a Condition C effect.</p>
<p>If we modify Huang&apos;s proposal and suppose that literal reconstruction of moved predicates is required we handle all the relevant facts. This is <link rid="b41">Takano&apos;s (1995</link>) proposal. The Huang&ndash;Takano proposal provides a simple reason why literal reconstruction is required: traces are bound variables and must, at LF, be in the scope of (i.e., be c-commanded by) their binders.<link rid="fn20">
<sup>20</sup></link> In particular, if a preposed predicate does not reconstruct, it will leave the trace of the subject that it contains without c-commanding antecedent. Thus the behavior of fronted predicates is ultimately due to the Predicate Internal Subject Hypothesis (as Huang suggested), but in two different ways: for anaphors because the predicate always has a trace subject, and for Condition C because this trace forces reconstruction of the fronted predicate.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) argues not only that the Huang&ndash;Takano proposal is insufficient,<link rid="fn21">
<sup>21</sup></link> but also that it is too strong. We will comment on Heycock&apos;s arguments and their inconclusiveness in <link rid="ss42 ss43">sections 5.3.2 and 5.3.3</link>.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss34" level="2">
<heading id="h33" level="2">4.3&ensp;Scope</heading>
<p>We now turn to a more systematic investigation of the interaction of reconstruction for binding and reconstruction for scope. As we will see, such considerations play a major role in determining reconstruction possibilities (as shown, for example, in <link rid="b26">Cresti 1995</link>; <link rid="b40">Heycock 1995</link>; <link rid="b12">Fox 1999</link>), and lead to substantial reformulations of the problem. In this subsection, we discuss scope reconstruction. In the next section we will turn to the interaction of scope and binding reconstruction.</p>
<p>We have already seen all sorts of reconstruction effect for scope, e.g., cases of pronominal binding, reciprocal binding, and quantifier&ndash;predicate interactions. We now focus a bit more on the last of these. Recall that in such sentences as (15) (repeated here as (104)), in which we paraphrase <i>compose</i> as <i>cause to be in existence</i> and <i>perform</i> as <i>cause to be performed</i>:</p>
<p>(104)&ensp;<object id="tu76" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu76_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many songs will you compose?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many songs will you perform?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>we can paraphrase (104a) by (16a) (repeated here as (105a)), and (104b) by either (16b) or (16c) (repeated here as (105b, c)):</p>
<p>(105)&ensp;<object id="tu77" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu77_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, you will cause there to be x many songs in existence?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, you will cause there to be x many songs performed?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, there are x many songs you will cause to be performed?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&equals; How many songs are there that you will perform?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>As outlined above, the difference lies in the scope of the existential quantification rendered here by <i>there are</i> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;with respect to the expression <i>will cause</i>. Reading (105c) is less natural in the case of (104a): we cannot assert the existence of a set of objects with certain properties if these objects do not yet exist (presuming that if the songs are not composed yet, they do not exist).<link rid="fn22">
<sup>22</sup></link> We have called the readings in (105) and (105b) the narrow-scope or narrow readings (since <i>there</i> has narrower scope than <i>will cause</i>) and the reading in (105c) the wide-scope or wide reading.</p>
<p>As has often been noted (see, e.g., <link rid="b42">Dobrovie-Sorin 1994b</link>; <link rid="b40">Heycock 1995</link>), we can unambiguously render the narrow readings of (104a, b) in French as in (106a, b).<link rid="fn23">
<sup>23</sup></link> The wide reading of (104b) is rendered by (106c), which also allows the narrow reading:</p>
<p>(106)&ensp;<object id="tu78" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu78_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Combien vas-tu composer de chansons?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many will you compose of songs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Combien vas-tu chanter de chansons?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many will you sing of songs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>Combien de chansons vas-tu chanter?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many songs will you sing</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Call the construction exemplified in the first two sentences <i>combien</i>-split. Given that <i>combien</i> means &lsquo;what is the number (or quantity) x such that&rsquo;, it is natural to take the position of <i>de chansons</i> to correspond to the locus of the existential quantification &lsquo;there are x many songs&rsquo;. In this way, the surface form of the French narrow-reading question seems to be exactly what we need to express its meaning, as (106a) essentially has the form of (105a). By the same token, (106c) has the form of (105c). It is thus plausible to assume that the ambiguity of the English sentence (104b) is represented at LF by varying what reconstructs:</p>
<p>(107)&ensp;<object id="tu79" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu79_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Reconstruction:</entry>
<entry>how many will you perform songs (narrow reading)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>No reconstruction:</entry>
<entry>how many songs will you perform (wide reading)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This plausibility argument as to what the LF representations of such sentences are finds support from some French facts noted in <link rid="b43">De Swart (1998</link>):<link rid="fn24">
<sup>24</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(108)&ensp;<object id="tu80" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu80_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Combien de chansons les enfants ont-ils tous chant&eacute;(s)?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many of songs the children have-they all sung</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">b.</entry>
<entry>Combien les enfants ont-ils tous chant&eacute; de chansons?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many the children have-they all sung of songs</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, the children all caused there to be x many songs performed?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>For what number x, there are x many songs the children all caused to be performed?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The sentence in (108b) has only a narrow reading, represented by (108c), with the existential quantifier (<i>there</i>) in the scope of the universal quantifier (<i>all</i>) so that the choice of the songs to be performed can vary with each child. Given that floated quantifiers always take their surface scope, this reading is predicted by the assumed LF representation for narrow readings. The sentence in (108a) is ambiguous between the narrow and the wide reading. Under the wide reading, represented by (108d), the existential quantifier (<i>there</i>) is not in the scope of the universal quantifier (<i>all</i>) so that the choice of the songs cannot vary with each child. To make this more concrete, imagine an exam situation in which children have to sing six songs. Three of them are the exact same three for all the children (the imposed program), and the other three are freely chosen by each child (the free program). To (108a), it is possible to truthfully answer &lsquo;three&rsquo; or &lsquo;six&rsquo;. To (108c), only &lsquo;six&rsquo; is a truthful answer.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss35" level="1">
<heading id="h34" level="1">5&ensp;Simultaneous reconstruction requirements</heading>
<p>In this section, we discuss what happens in situations in which the requirements of several binding and/or scope principles must be simultaneously satisfied. We actually already have encountered such situations, but we now discuss them somewhat more systematically. A coherent overall theory of reconstruction should be able to handle all such cases &ndash; certainly a non-trivial task and, if achieved, a non-trivial result.</p>
<p>We begin by discussing interactions between Condition C and pronominal binding. Next we turn to quantifier&ndash;predicate scope and Condition C. Finally, we examine the case of predicate preposing and its interaction with scope considerations and Condition C.</p>
<subsection id="ss36" level="2">
<heading id="h35" level="2">5.1&ensp;Condition C, Condition A, and pronominal binding</heading>
<p>
<link rid="b20">Lebeaux (1991</link>) reports that Condition C effects and the possibilities for pronominal binding correlate. He discusses examples similar to (109) (from <link rid="b12">Fox 1999</link>, in which more such examples are discussed):</p>
<p>(109)&ensp;<object id="tu81" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu81_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Which survey that <u>he</u> could show to <uu>the typical female viewer</uu> would <uu>she</uu> hope <u>no pollster</u> would publish t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which survey that <u>he</u> could show to <uu>her</uu> would <uu>the typical female viewer</uu> hope <u>no pollster</u> would publish t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry morerows="1">c.</entry>
<entry>(Desired answer to both: &lsquo;His most embarrassing.&rsquo;)</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>*Quel sondage qu&rsquo;<u>il</u> pourrait montrer &agrave; <uu>Madame toutlemonde</uu> ne laisserait-t-<uu>elle</uu> <u>aucun journaliste</u> publier t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Quel sondage qu&rsquo;<u>il</u> pourrait <uu>lui</uu> montrer <uu>Madame toutlemonde</uu> ne laisserait-t-<uu>elle</uu> <u>aucun journaliste</u> publier t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In order for the pronoun <i>he</i> to be understood as bound by the quantifier <i>no pollster</i>, reconstruction of the relative clause must take place. However, if reconstruction takes place, this puts the indirect object of the verb <i>show</i> in the c-command domain of the subject of the verb <i>hope</i>. If the latter is a pronoun, and the former is a name or a description, we should observe a Condition C effect, and we do, as in (109a). Otherwise we should not, as in (109b). The deviance of (109a) indicates that Condition C and the condition on pronominal binding cannot be checked on strictly different inputs. If they were, we should be able to satisfy Condition C on some input and the condition on pronominal Binding on another at which the Condition C configuration is not met. This, for example, would be the case if Condition C applied at S-structure but not at LF and pronominal binding were checked at LF but not at S-structure.<link rid="fn25">
<sup>25</sup></link> This reinforces the idea that Condition C applies at LF (but says nothing about whether or not, in addition, Condition C applies elsewhere, e.g., to surface representations).</p>
<p>The same point can be illustrated with reciprocals, which also act as variables bound by their antecedents. This also illustrates an interaction between the locality requirement of Condition A and Condition C. Contrast (110a, b):</p>
<p>(110)&ensp;<object id="tu82" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu82_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*Which stories <i>about </i><u><i>each other&apos;s</i>
</u><i> characterizations of <uu>the typical male viewer</uu>
</i> would <u>he</u> conclude <u>the journalists</u> should publish?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which stories <i>about </i><u><i>each other&apos;s</i>
</u><i> characterizations of him</i> would <uu>the typical male viewer</uu> conclude <u>the journalists</u> should publish?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(110a) does not seem to allow the reading in (111a), but (110b) allows the reading in (111b). Some care is needed to evaluate this contrast, as we want to make sure that the interpretation under which (110a) and (110b) are judged has the relevant distributive readings, which can (roughly) be paraphrased as (111a, b):<link rid="fn26">
<sup>26</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(111)&ensp;<object id="tu83" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu83_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Which stories about the <u>others&rsquo;</u> characterizations of <uu>the typical male viewer</uu> would <uu>he</uu> conclude each <u>journalist</u> should publish?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Which stories about the <u>others&rsquo;</u> characterizations of <uu>him</uu> would <uu>the typical male viewer</uu> conclude each <u>journalist</u> should publish?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss37" level="2">
<heading id="h36" level="2">5.2&ensp;Scope and Condition C</heading>
<p>The conclusion that the LF of the narrow and wide readings is as in (107) directly bears on the relationship between scope and binding with respect to reconstruction, as extensively discussed in <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>). She reports the contrasts (the examples are slightly changed) in (112a, b) which we will discuss in turn. For the first one, imagine the following context in which no prior virtual existence has been established for such surveys (cf. note 23): have the opinions of the typical male viewer been taken into account in designing surveys of his TV viewing habits? Should we send questionnaires out to him to help us formulate the questions? Is it worth it, given the low response rate we get? In the end, when all is counted:</p>
<p>(112)&ensp;<object id="tu84" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu84_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*How many surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u> is <u>he</u> likely to help design t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u> is <u>he</u> likely to challenge t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*How many is <u>he</u> likely to help design surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>How many surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u> is <u>he</u> likely to challenge t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Let us examine these sentences in turn.</p>
<subsection id="ss38" level="3">
<heading id="h37" level="3">5.2.1&ensp;The wide-scope reading</heading>
<p>Let us first consider the meaning of (112b), repeated here. Here, we can easily imagine a context in which the surveys about the typical male viewer already exist, since he is likely to challenge them. This makes the wide reading readily available, which means that the LF (112d) (repeated here) is fine, avoiding a Condition C effect:</p>
<p>(112)&ensp;<object id="tu85" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu85_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How many surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u> is <u>he</u> likely to challenge t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>How many surveys about <u>the typical male viewer</u> is <u>he</u> likely to challenge t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We are now faced with an apparent contradiction. We had concluded that reconstruction of non-adjunct pied-piped material is obligatory to guarantee that we observe Condition C effects. This means that at least the nominal <i>surveys</i> should reconstruct. For scopal reasons, however, it looks as though we want the same nominal not to reconstruct.</p>
<p>This problem becomes more acute in (113):</p>
<p>(113)&ensp;<object id="tu86" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu86_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*How many pictures of <u>a famous artist you know</u> is <u>he</u> looking for t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>LF1: How many pictures of <u>a famous artist you know</u> is <u>he</u> looking for?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>LF2: How many is <u>he</u> looking for pictures of <u>a famous artist you know</u>?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Clearly the sentence in (113a) can receive a wide reading and thus get the LF representation LF1 in (113b). This predicts that under the wide reading there should not be any Condition C effect. But this seems wrong: coreference between the underlined elements is blocked in (113a). To get this result, we would need to postulate instead of LF1 the logical form LF2, given in (113c). But this would wrongly claim that only the narrow reading is available for (113a).</p>
<p>A solution to this problem can be constructed by using <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) theory of movement traces as copies, which we have already seen helps resolve other problems.<link rid="fn27">
<sup>27</sup></link> According to Chomsky&apos;s proposal, a sentence like (114a) would have (114b) as surface syntactic representation, (114c) as input to phonology (Phonetic Form or PF), and (114d) as manipulated surface structure for the purpose of interpretation (LF):</p>
<p>(114)&ensp;<object id="tu87" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu87_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many books are you looking for?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Surface Form: How many books are you looking for how many books?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>What PF sees: How many books are you looking for <strike>how many books</strike>?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>What LF sees: How many <strike>books</strike> are you looking for <strike>how many</strike> books?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Chomsky&apos;s copy theory of movement has several positive aspects. First, it eliminates the need to postulate objects (traces), whose internal structure is not entirely clear (e.g., how do traces obey X-bar theory?). Second, Move is an operation of copying a moving phrase and deleting the original copy. The copy theory turns movement into a simpler operation, essentially identical to the elementary structure-building operation (<i>merge</i>). It differs only in taking as input an object that has served as input for an earlier merger &ndash; <i>move</i> is <i>merge-the-same-object-again</i>, that is, by appealing to a notion of identity of distinct syntactic objects which seem independently required by cases of ellipsis, as <link rid="b29">Chomsky (1995c</link>) notes. The &lsquo;deletion&rsquo; part is now handled independently as part of PF interpretation or LF interpretation, and there can be mismatches between what is deleted in PF and what is deleted in LF, as the paradigm in (114) makes clear.<link rid="fn28">
<sup>28</sup></link>
</p>
<p>Turning back to the problem raised by (113a), we can resolve the contradiction by departing from Chomsky&apos;s proposal and assume that the LF of (113a) is not (113c) but rather a representation in which both the moved copy and the original copy are interpreted at LF.<link rid="fn29">
<sup>29</sup></link> In the case of a narrow reading, reconstruction must be obligatory, as we have now seen several times. In the case of the wide reading, it is important that the moved constituent be interpreted with wide scope, but nothing prevents a copy of this constituent from being interpreted in the original trace position as well. This permits a reconciliation of scope considerations with the obligatory character of reconstruction of pied-piped complements necessary to explain certain Condition C effects.<link rid="fn30">
<sup>30</sup></link>
</p>
<p>The idea that both copies can be interpreted is developed in <link rid="b12">Fox (1999</link>) for different reasons (see also <link rid="b36">Brody 1995b</link>; <link rid="b6">Safir 1999</link>; <link rid="b44">Rizzi 2000a</link>). Fox suggests that the &lsquo;bottom&rsquo; trace is interpreted like a definite description. Other possibilities could be contemplated (<link rid="b6">Safir 1999</link> treats it like a pronoun), but from now on, for ease of exposition, we will represent the lower copy as a demonstrative expression referring back to the top copy when there are two (or more) copies. For the sentence in (115a), this would yield the LF representations (115b) for the narrow reading and (115c) for the wide reading. Taking Fox&apos;s proposal into account, we will understand the LF of (115c) as (115d):</p>
<p>(115)&ensp;<object id="tu88" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu88_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The sentence:</entry>
<entry>How many pictures of <i>a famous artist</i> is <i>he</i> looking for t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>Its narrow-reading LF:</entry>
<entry>How many is <i>he</i> looking for pictures of a famous artist?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>Its wide-reading LF:</entry>
<entry>How many pictures of a famous artist is <i>he</i> looking for pictures of a famous artist?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>Paraphrase of the wide-reading LF:</entry>
<entry>How many pictures of a famous artist are such that <i>he</i> looking for <u>these</u> pictures of a famous artist?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The effect of interpreting both copies in the case of wide readings are clear: in all cases, we see that coreference between <i>he</i> and <i>a famous artist</i> leads to a Condition C violation.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss39" level="3">
<heading id="h38" level="3">5.2.2&ensp;The narrow-scope reading</heading>
<p>Turning now to (112a), its reported deviance might look surprising. Since <i>about the typical male viewer</i> is an adjunct, it should be allowed not to reconstruct and thus should not have to feed Condition C. The reason for the deviance, <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) hypothesizes for similar examples, is that the LF representation of (112a) must be (112c), with reconstruction of the restriction of <i>how many</i>. Indeed, the surveys about the typical male viewer not having been designed yet, only the narrow reading of this question is plausible<i>.</i> In (112b), the wide reading is plausible, thus allowing the LF (112d), which causes no Condition C violation.</p>
<p>Note that in such circumstances, for this reasoning to go through in the case of the narrow reading, it must not be possible to totally reconstruct the nominal head <i>surveys</i> of the preposed constituent without reconstructing the adjunct modifier <i>about the typical male viewer</i> as well. This seems reasonable: the adjunct must, by hypothesis, be predicated of some modifiee, to which it must stand in a syntactically local relation: as a result, it cannot be left stranded in a high position.</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss40" level="2">
<heading id="h39" level="2">5.3&ensp;Predicate movement, scope, Condition C, and predicate-internal subjects</heading>
<subsection id="ss41" level="3">
<heading id="h40" level="3">5.3.1&ensp;Scope reconstruction and islands</heading>
<p>Recall that we concluded that moved predicate phrases always reconstruct. This means that predicate movement should never obviate Condition C effects or increase the set of possible antecedents for a pied-piped anaphor. These two points are again illustrated in (116):</p>
<p>(116)&ensp;<object id="tu89" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu89_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Pleased with <u>an old painter</u>&rsqb;, I think <u>he</u> was t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Pleased with <u>an old painter</u>&rsqb;, <u>he</u> thinks you were t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;t<sub>j</sub> Visit &lsqb;each other&rsqb;<sub>k</sub> &apos;s parents&rsqb;, you think they said &lsqb;Bill and Mary&rsqb;<sub>j</sub> will t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (116a, b), obligatory reconstruction will put the preposed constituent back into position t, thus triggering Condition C effects. In (116c), the presence of t<sub>j</sub> prevents anything other than <i>Bill and Mary</i> from qualifying as antecedent for <i>each other</i>. Note that the Predicate Internal Subject Hypothesis truly derives the required reconstruction from the independent existence of a condition on pronominal and variable binding.</p>
<p>
<link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) provides support for her observation that predicates are limited to taking narrow scope. This support is based on some extraction facts out of <i>wh</i>-islands. Several authors (e.g., <link rid="b45">Cinque 1990c</link>, who attributes the observation to Giuseppe Longobardi) have noted that an amount question (<i>how much</i>, <i>how many</i>) out of <i>wh</i>-islands is only possible if this question receives a wide-scope reading in the sense of the text. Thus we find the facts in (117) (e.g., with <i>how many</i>):</p>
<p>(117)&ensp;<object id="tu90" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu90_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*How many songs do you wonder whether Sue will compose t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>?How many songs do you wonder whether Sue will perform t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>In (117a) (without context), lexical choices strongly favor the narrow reading (the wide reading, <i>how many songs are there such that</i> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;, is implausible given that the songs are not yet composed). In (117b), the wide reading is plausible and the sentence is better (with the reading <i>how many songs are there such that</i> .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;).<link rid="fn31">
<sup>31</sup></link> (See <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">chapter 64</externallink></related>.)</p>
<p>Degree questions (e.g., with <i>how</i> &plus; adjective) behave like narrow-reading amount questions (as noted in <link rid="b46">Rizzi 1990b</link>, citing <link rid="b47">Roberts 1988b</link> and <link rid="b48">Baltin 1992</link>) and unlike wide-reading amount questions:</p>
<p>(118)&ensp;<object id="tu91" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu91_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*How intelligent did she wonder whether she was?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*How afraid of dogs did they ask if he was?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Heycock takes this to suggest that the only (or the only accessible) interpretation degree questions tolerate is the narrow reading; that is, that predicates must reconstruct. (If the wide reading were available, (118a, b) should have the status of (117b) and not of (117a).)</p>
<p>Heycock further argues (following <link rid="b49">Kroch 1989a</link>) that the unavailability of the narrow reading in amount or degree questions out of <i>wh</i>-islands is due to pragmatic infelicity rather than semantic deviance or ungrammaticality. Questions out of <i>wh</i>-islands, they argue, require that the questioned phrase ask the identity of an entity or entities presupposed to exist.<link rid="fn32">
<sup>32</sup></link> In the case of the wide-reading question (117b), repeated here as (119a), the presupposition would be what is given in (119b):</p>
<p>(119)&ensp;<object id="tu92" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu92_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>?How many songs do you wonder whether Sue will perform t?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>There are songs such that you wonder whether Sue will perform them.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This should make it possible to rescue narrow readings for amount and degree questions out of <i>wh</i>-islands. First, Heycock (following Kroch) argues that contexts can be constructed that make amount questions or degree questions out of <i>wh</i>-islands more acceptable. Heycock&apos;s example is (120a), with its interpretation in (120b) and it presupposition in (120c):</p>
<p>(120)&ensp;<object id="tu93" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu93_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How many points are the judges arguing about whether to deduct?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>What is the number such that the judges are arguing about whether to deduct this number of points?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>There is a certain number of points that the judges are arguing about whether to deduct.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Similar facts can be found in French. Normally, <i>combien</i>-split is sensitive to weak islands such as <i>wh</i>-islands or an intervening negation. In French, this is easier to check, since we can guarantee the narrow reading by using <i>combien</i>-split. This type of context indeed makes the approximate translation of (120a) yield the relatively acceptable (121):</p>
<p>(121)&ensp;Combien est-ce que les juges se demandent s&rsquo;il faut d&eacute;duire de points?</p>
<p>We find similar contrasts for negative islands. (122) is hard to interpret:</p>
<p>(122)&ensp;*Combien est ce que Jean n&rsquo;a pas emprunt&eacute; de livres cette ann&eacute;e?</p>
<p>&lsquo;How many hasn&apos;t John borrowed books this year?&rsquo;</p>
<p>Out of context, there is no particular presupposition about there being a number of books that one should borrow. However, this sentence improves greatly if we utter it with the presupposition that there is a certain number of books that John has not borrowed this year.</p>
<p>Consider now (123), asked in a context (familiar to French people) in which there is a small, fixed number of competitive exams to take every year, and every student decides which ones to take and which ones to opt out of. It is then perfectly natural to ask how many competitive exams John decided to opt out of, as in (123a) (with the intended interpretation in (123b)):</p>
<p>(123)&ensp;<object id="tu94" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu94_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">a.</entry>
<entry>Combien est ce que Jean n&rsquo;a pas pass&eacute; de concours cette ann&eacute;e?<link rid="fn33">
<sup>33</sup></link>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;How many hasn&apos;t John taken of competitive exams this year?&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>What is the number/it is not the case that John took this number of exams this year.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Extraction out of <i>wh</i>-islands of degree-modified predicates can also easily be done. For example, in the following context, sentence (124a) is fine: &lsquo;According to reliable sources, Einstein&apos;s sister was just as well informed and just as smart as him and he was extremely proud of her.&rsquo; Just as well informed, I can believe&rsquo; but:</p>
<p>(124)&ensp;<object id="tu95" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu95_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>This smart, I wonder whether she was t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*This proud of <u>Einstein&apos;s</u> sister, I wonder whether <u>he</u> was t.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>This proud of <u>his</u> sister, I wonder whether <u>every student</u> ever was t.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>We must make sure that sentence (124a) is not a case of wide reading but rather a case of felicitous narrow reading, since predicates must always reconstruct, ruling out wide readings in degree questions in principle. First, note that (124b) is still deviant. This shows that a copy of the predicate phrase is interpreted as reconstructed, but does not exclude the presence of an interpreted copy at the top as well. The well-formedness of the third sentence (in an appropriate context) does show that such structures may be interpreted with no copy left at the top (otherwise we would have an unbound pronoun). This does not demonstrate that wide readings are unavailable for preposed predicates, but at least it shows that such examples as (124a) can be treated as cases of narrow readings, i.e., as having the interpretation in (125):</p>
<p>(125)&ensp;There is an amount X such that, I wonder whether she was X smart.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss42" level="3">
<heading id="h41" level="3">5.3.2&ensp;Definite descriptions, predicate-internal subjects, and partial reconstruction</heading>
<p>Heycock also discusses the contrasts in (126):</p>
<p>(126)&ensp;<object id="tu96" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu96_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;How afraid of some question <u>Gore</u> has not prepared for&rsqb; do you think <u>he</u> is now?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;How pleased with the pictures <u>Pollock</u> painted long ago&rsqb; do you think <u>he</u> is now t?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The unacceptability of (126a) is predicted. Forced reconstruction of the preposed predicate phrase puts <i>Gore</i> in the c-command domain of <i>he</i>, thus triggering a Condition C effect. The acceptability of (126b) is unexpected. To deal with this, Heycock suggests that the definite description <i>the pictures that Pollock painted long ago</i> can be assigned wide scope, deriving the representation in (127):</p>
<p>(127)&ensp;&lsqb;The pictures that <u>Pollock</u> painted long ago&rsqb;<sub>k</sub>, how do you think <u>he</u> was pleased with t<sub>k</sub>?</p>
<p>Heycock remarks that if this wide-scope reading becomes less plausible, a Condition C effect reappears. This is the case in (126a), in which it is most natural for the relative clause not to be interpreted with widest scope. The contrast in (128a, b) is similar:</p>
<p>(128)&ensp;<object id="tu97" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu97_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How jealous of <u>a girl that Mary had met at the party</u> did she become?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*How eager for <u>a friend that Mary might confide in</u> would she become?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>It is possible to interpret the underlined indefinite in (128a) as having wide scope (&lsquo;There is a girl that Mary had met at the party: how jealous of her did she become?&rsquo;). Such a wide-scope reading for the indefinite is far less plausible for (128b).</p>
<p>Let us examine how this proposal can be reconciled with earlier conclusions. Consider again (126b), repeated here as (129):</p>
<p>(129)&ensp;&lsqb;How pleased with the pictures Pollock painted long ago&rsqb; do you think he is now?</p>
<p>We must obligatorily reconstruct the predicate and its complement, and scope out the definite description in such a way that it leaves no interpreted copy below the pronoun <i>he</i>. In this instance, this is possible because we need not reconstruct adjuncts, and an adjunct contains the potentially offending name. This yields (130):</p>
<p>(130)&ensp;&lsqb;How the pictures Pollock painted long ago do you think he is pleased with these pictures&rsqb; now?</p>
<p>in which the lower copy does not contain the relative clause.</p>
<p>That this is on the right track seems supported by the contrast between (131a) and (131b):</p>
<p>(131)&ensp;<object id="tu98" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu98_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;How pleased with the pictures <u>an old painter you know</u> painted long ago&rsqb; do you think <u>he</u> is?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*&lsqb;How pleased with the pictures of <u>an old painter you know</u>&rsqb; do you think <u>he</u> is?</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The difference between them is that the potentially offending name is contained in an adjunct in (131a), and can thus fail to reconstruct. In (131b), it is part of the complement structure and thus must be reconstructed, triggering a Condition C effect.</p>
<p>Similarly, it is clear why (132) is a Condition C violation, given the only possible LF representation it could have:</p>
<p>(132)&ensp;<object id="tu99" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu99_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>
</entry>
<entry>I gave <u>him</u> this picture of <u>Bill</u> yesterday.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>LF:</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;This picture of <u>Bill</u>&rsqb;<sub>j</sub>, I gave <u>him</u> this picture of <u>Bill</u> yesterday.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>However, the lack of obviation of Condition C effects in sentences such as in (133) is problematic. They would get the corresponding representations in (134) after scoping out of the definite description (leaving only copies of non-adjunct material), and would thus be predicted to escape Condition C, contrary to fact:</p>
<p>(133)&ensp;<object id="tu100" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu100_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He</u> says that the man who <u>an old painter</u> met left.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>She</u> considers the book <u>a European princess</u> wrote to be unreadable.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>*I told <u>him</u> that the man who <u>an old painter</u> met left.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He<sub>j</sub>
</u> wonders &lsqb;how pleased with the pictures <u>an old painter you know</u> painted long ago&rsqb; you are.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>(134)&ensp;<object id="tu101" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu101_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>The man who <u>an old painter</u> met &lsqb;<u>he</u> says that this man left&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>The book <u>a European princess</u> wrote &lsqb;<u>she</u> considers this book to be unreadable&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>The man who <u>an old painter</u> met &lsqb;I told <u>him</u> that this man left&rsqb;.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;The pictures <u>an old painter you know</u> painted long ago&rsqb; <u>he<sub>j</sub>
</u> wonders &lsqb;how pleased with these pictures&rsqb; you are.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>One way out could be to restrict the distance that the definite description can scope over. If, roughly, it were clause bound, all these problems would disappear. This would predict, however, that (135a) should still be fine (viz. its representation in (135b) after scoping out of the definite description):</p>
<p>(135)&ensp;<object id="tu102" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu102_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>Je <uu>lui</uu> ai donn&eacute; <u>la photo que </u>
<uu>le vieux peintre</uu><u> m&rsquo;a demand&eacute;e</u>.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>I gave <u>him</u> the picture <u>the old painter</u> asked for yesterday.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;The picture an old painter asked for&rsqb;, I gave <u>him</u> this picture.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The French sentence in (135a) given in English in (135b), is clearly much better than (132a) and indeed is perfectly fine, particularly if read with such an intonation that the (underlined) direct object is backgrounded. This, however, may be an effect due to &lsquo;extraposition&rsquo; of the relative clause.</p>
<p>The examples in (136) are sharply out:</p>
<p>(136)&ensp;<object id="tu103" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu103_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>*<u>Il</u> m&rsquo;a donn&eacute; la photo que <u>le vieux peintre</u> m&rsquo;a demand&eacute;e.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>*<u>He</u> gave me the picture <u>the old painter</u> asked for yesterday.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>c.</entry>
<entry>&lsqb;The picture the old painter asked for&rsqb;, he gave me this picture.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>d.</entry>
<entry>He &lsqb;the picture the old painter asked for&rsqb; gave me this picture.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This suggests that if descriptions can scope out within their clause, leaving a copy optionally containing adjunct material, the distance this movement can span is quite restricted. Here the definite description must stay lower than a definite subject. Note that in the initial case in (130), scoping of the definite description is from within a preposed <i>wh</i>-phrase. Clearly this is an area for further research.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss43" level="3">
<heading id="h42" level="3">5.3.3&ensp;What drives predicate reconstruction?</heading>
<p>The structure of (126b) under <link rid="b38">Huang&apos;s (1993</link>) proposal is (137):</p>
<p>(137)&ensp;&lsqb;How t<sub>j</sub> pleased with the pictures Pollock<sub>j</sub> painted long ago&rsqb; do you think <u>he<sub>j</sub>
</u> is now t?</p>
<p>This would seem incompatible with Huang&apos;s proposal, <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>) claims. The presence of t<sub>j</sub> coindexed with <i>he</i> should trigger a Condition C effect (whether Condition C is an Anywhere Principle or only applies at LF). Under a theory assuming that Condition C cannot be violated anywhere, such examples are clearly incompatible with Huang&apos;s proposal, since at some level, t<sub>j</sub> c-commands <i>an old painter</i>. But this problem is more general: this sentence poses a problem for any account assuming that the preposed predicate obligatorily reconstructs in its entirety to t, putting <i>Pollock</i> in the c-command domain of <i>he</i>. To get around this problem, Heycock suggests that definite descriptions can scope out. If Heycock&apos;s proposal is on the right track and the LF representation of (137) is (138):</p>
<p>(138)&ensp;The pictures Pollock painted long ago &lsqb;how do you think he<sub>j</sub> is t<sub>j</sub> pleased with these pictures&rsqb;?</p>
<p>the problem Heycock points out for Huang&apos;s proposal is also solved by her proposal <i>under the assumption that Condition C only applies at LF</i>: once the definite description has been scoped out and the adjunct is not reconstructed, there is no longer a Condition C violation, regardless of the presence of a predicate-internal subject. We conclude that the Huang&ndash;Takano proposal (see <link rid="ss33">section 4.2.3</link>) can be maintained.</p>
<p>In <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>), one additional problem is mentioned regarding Takano&apos;s modification of Huang&apos;s proposal that we have been discussing. The examples of degree questions in (139) allow coreference:</p>
<p>(139)&ensp;<object id="tu104" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu104_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry>a.</entry>
<entry>How much longer than <u>your yacht</u> actually is did John think <u>it</u> was?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>b.</entry>
<entry>How much more intelligent than <u>John</u> actually is did <u>he</u> say <u>he</u> was? </entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>Of course, this would be a problem if Condition C were an Anywhere Principle. Is it so under the assumption that Condition C applies only at LF? To decide whether this indeed constitutes a problem, we must examine what the LFs of (139) can be. In (139b), for example, the <i>than</i> clause is a dependent of <i>more</i>. (In its absence, the <i>than</i> clause could not be present). Thus, the representation in (140) of this amount question seems reasonable:</p>
<p>(140)&ensp;What is the degree D added to the degree to which <u>John</u> is actually intelligent such that <u>he</u> said <u>he</u> was D intelligent?</p>
<p>This makes it basically a narrow-reading amount question on a degree, in which no LF violation of Condition C should occur (the <i>wh</i>-question bears on a degree increase, but the predicate <i>intelligent</i> has narrow scope). As Heycock remarks, that this is a narrow-reading amount question is corroborated by the fact that such questions become unacceptable when originating inside a <i>wh</i>-island:<link rid="fn34 fn35">
<sup>34,35</sup></link>
</p>
<p>(141)&ensp;*How much more intelligent than he is do you wonder whether he was?</p>
</subsection>
</subsection>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss44" level="1">
<heading id="h43" level="1">6&ensp;Conclusion</heading>
<p>We begin with a summary of the conclusions we reached first descriptively. Then we summarize the accounts that these descriptive generalizations seem to suggest in a Principles and Parameters type of model.</p>
<p>Descriptively, we concluded that:</p>
<listgroup id="l10" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>We find reconstruction effects for scope, pronominal binding, and all binding conditions in all types of movement constructions.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction for preposed predicates is always required, with consequences for all relevant conditions: Condition A, Condition C, scope, and pronominal binding.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Regarding Condition C, reconstruction is obligatory sometimes and optional at other times. We took the relevant factor to be a complement&ndash;adjunct distinction, but it is not fully established that this is the relevant distinction.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction for Condition A, scope, and pronominal binding is possible but not required.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction effects correlate to a certain extent: reconstruction for pronominal binding and scope either both take place or both do not.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>If reconstruction for scope or pronominal binding takes place, reconstruction for Condition C does too. (This is only relevant for cases of optional reconstruction for Condition C; that is, it only relates to adjuncts.)</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Reconstruction effects, however, do not always correlate: reconstruction may take place for Condition C without doing so for scope.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>There were cases of impossible reconstruction, which we left unexplained.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>We construed these descriptive generalizations as follows:</p>
<listgroup id="l11" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>All binding conditions and scope computation must be computed on the basis of representations that serve as input for semantic interpretation, which we define as LF. It makes little sense for scope or pronominal binding (in effect a scope principle) to be evaluated anywhere else (at best it would be redundant). We reached similar conclusions for Condition A, although it should be noted that we did not discuss potentially relevant differences between reflexives and reciprocals.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Condition C cannot hold of underlying structures but may of surface structures (depending on the treatment of antecedent-contained deletion and the correctness of the Huang&ndash;Takano approach, among other things).</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Mismatch of scope and binding reconstruction patterns can be handled by taking traces to be copies and requiring that bottom (or bottom-most) copies always be interpreted at LF.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>The obligatoriness of reconstruction for preposed predicates can be tentatively attributed to the Huang&ndash;Takano hypothesis, and to the idea that interpreted traces (which are lower copies) behave as bound variables (and are thus subject to the condition on pronominal binding).</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>It is worth noting that these conclusions are consistent with <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) proposal requiring all binding conditions to be LF conditions only.</p>
<p>Regarding the properties of movement, we reached the following conclusion regarding how to construe the basic operation Move and its interaction with LF principles of scope:</p>
<listgroup id="l12" type="symbol">
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Movement is copying.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>Either or both copies can be interpreted at LF.</p>
</li>
<li level="1">
<number>&bull;&ensp;</number>
<p>The position determining the scope of an XP is that of its highest interpreted copy.</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ndash;</number>
<p>If only the lower copy of an XP is interpreted, this XP receives narrow scope.</p>
</li>
<li level="2">
<number>&ndash;</number>
<p>If the top copy of an XP is interpreted, this XP receives wide scope.</p>
</li>
</listgroup>
<p>Among the issues left unresolved are the existence and exact properties of covert movement (although we have been led to the assumption that covert scoping out is possible, e.g., for definite descriptions), the impact of the analysis of relative clauses on the theory of reconstruction, and the behavior of reflexives.</p>
<p>Descriptively, there are a number of questions we have not discussed. We have not talked about reconstruction effects for negative- or positive-polarity-item licensing (see <link rid="b3">Den Dikken et al. 2000</link> for some relevant discussion). We also have not discussed the properties of reconstruction documented in other languages (e.g., in Arabic: see <link rid="b50">Aoun and Benmamoun 1998</link>; in British English: see <link rid="b51">Elbourne 1999</link>; or in Japanese: see <link rid="b52">Saito 1989</link> on scrambling).</p>
<p>Theoretically, we have limited ourselves to implementing the assumed descriptive generalizations in a Principles and Parameters type of framework, but we have of course not discussed all approaches to reconstruction within it. Among recent works that were not discussed here, there are approaches assuming PF movement (e.g., <link rid="b50">Aoun and Benmamoun 1998</link>; <link rid="b23">Sauerland and Elbourne 2002</link>). The work of <link rid="b6">Safir (1999</link>) incorporates ideas about vehicle change originally proposed in <link rid="b34">May and Fiengo (1994</link>) into the treatment of reconstruction effects (by treating lower copies as pronominals, for example). Putting the burden of the treatment of reconstruction effects onto the semantic rules themselves rather than onto the syntactic input to these interpretive rules is done in flexible composition rules approaches, such as <link rid="b53">Jacobson (1999</link>) or <link rid="b54">Sharvit (1998</link>). More distant treatments of reconstruction effects can be found in <link rid="b55">McCawley (1999</link>) within generative semantics. As mentioned at the outset, it remains to be seen to what extent these alternatives are truly different from what we have covered in the logical structure of the proposals that they make.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ss45" level="1">
<heading id="h44" level="1">NOTES</heading>
<p>Many thanks to the following people who listened, commented on material in here, or (non-exclusive) were endlessly tortured to give judgments: two reviewers, Leston Buell, Guglielmo Cinque, Danny Fox, Edward Garrett, Peter Hallman, Richard Kayne, Hilda Koopman, Martin Prinzhorn, Luigi Rizzi, Fran&ccedil;oise Roth, Barry Schein, Philippe Schlenker, Michel Sportiche, No&eacute;mie Sportiche, Sophie Sportiche, Tim Stowell, Harold Torrence, Jean-Roger Vergnaud, Edwin Williams, and the audiences in my lectures at UCLA since 1994, at the Universit&agrave; di Venezia and the Universit&agrave; di Firenze in the spring of 1999, and at the GLOW summer school in Thermi in the summer of 1999. Thanks also to Howard Lasnik and Susumu Kuno for promptly providing copies of their articles.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn1">
<number>1&ensp;</number>This notion of canonical is far from trivial, of course. Informally, let us think of it in English as the normal immediately postverbal position of direct objects.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn2">
<number>2&ensp;</number>The general issue is that of how movement dependencies should be represented &ndash; antecedent trace binding relations, slash notation, feature percolation, or other possibilities.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn3">
<number>3&ensp;</number>This would include all cases of movement, whether overt or &lsquo;covert&rsquo;, as well as possibly other cases.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn4">
<number>4&ensp;</number>At the right level of abstraction(/formalization), it is likely that most of the superficial differences between our description of the data and others induced by the particular notation we use would disappear. Assuming that the empirical generalizations we accept are correct, this is due to the fact that the notations most often simply directly encode them (a comment about the relative theoretical shallowness of the field at the present stage of its development).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn5">
<number>5&ensp;</number>Standard use takes this to be a case of feature projection instead, taking the string D NP <i><i>which boy</i>
</i> in (7) to obligatorily be a DP (inheriting the D property), and reserves the term &lsquo;pied-piping&rsquo; for cases when such feature projection is optional, as in &lsqb;<sub><sub>&plus;wh</sub>
</sub> which boy&rsqb; and &lsqb;<sub><sub>Optionally &plus;wh</sub>
</sub> with &lsqb;&lsqb;<sub><sub>&plus;wh</sub>
</sub> which boy&rsqb;&apos;s brother&rsqb;&rsqb;.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn6">
<number>6&ensp;</number>Note that we use the term &lsquo;reconstruction&rsquo; as meaning &lsquo;connectivity in case of movement&rsquo;. In particular, we make no assumption here about the mechanism by which these reconstruction effects arise.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn7">
<number>7&ensp;</number>One possible reason sometimes given is that it may allow us to circumvent grammatical constraints on movement. It is also conceivable that pied-piped material may in some respect (e.g., in terms of scope, or in terms of the <i><i>de re</i>/<i>de dicto</i>
</i> distinction) receive different interpretations than non-pied-piped material.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn8">
<number>8&ensp;</number>Consistent with the idea that only pied-piped material reconstructs is the observation that it is difficult to understand the <i><i>wh</i>
</i>-quantifier itself as reconstructed: the number asked does not seem able to vary with the choice of member.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn9">
<number>9&ensp;</number>For a variety of reasons (if P reconstructs in t2, it will be in the scope of A and B), it is more difficult to illustrate this property of reconstruction into intermediate traces with other principles. One option is the following example:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;Which picture that John sold to <u>her</u> did you convince <u>every girl</u> t<sub>1</sub> that he had stolen t<sub>2</sub>?</p>
<p>This sentence seems good with <i>her</i> bound by <i>every girl</i>, and <i>John</i> and <i>he</i> coreferential. Reconstruction of the relative clause <i>picture that John sold to her</i> is required to allow pronominal binding of <i>her</i> by <i>every girl</i>. If reconstruction was in t<sub>2</sub>, it would create a Condition C effect between <i>he</i> and <i>John</i>. However, if reconstruction is in t<sub>1</sub>, no Condition C effect is created. Note that the relative clause is an adjunct and can thus be &lsquo;late inserted&rsquo; in t<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn10">
<number>10&ensp;</number>We are not considering the reading in which each picture is of the other pictures, which may be available but is irrelevant.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn11">
<number>11&ensp;</number>An additional control would raise a name or a pronoun across a name Experiencer, but raising across a non-pronoun is deviant in French (as in German or Dutch, unlike what happens in English):</span>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu105" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu105_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>*Ma place semblait &agrave; Marie avoir &eacute;t&eacute; prise.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;My seat seemed to Mary to have been taken.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>This is only marginally improved by &lsquo;extraposing&rsquo; the Experiencer:</p>
<p>
<object id="tu106" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu106_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(ii)</entry>
<entry>*?Ma place semblait avoir &eacute;t&eacute; prise &agrave; Marie.</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>&lsquo;My seat seemed to have been taken to Mary.&rsquo;</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn12">
<number>12&ensp;</number>The restriction &ldquo;in English&rdquo; is meant to exclude from discussion cases of partial <i><i>wh</i>
</i>-movement (which may also satisfy this description; see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 47 - Partial Wh-Movement.xml" type="file">chapter 47</externallink></related>) and cases of scrambling of <i><i>wh</i>
</i>
</span>-phrases.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn13">
<number>13&ensp;</number>There exist interesting apparent counter-examples, such as:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;Where do you think every kid will hide?</p>
<p>with the reading &lsquo;Every kid will hide in a different place. For each kid, where do you think it is?&rsquo;.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn14">
<number>14&ensp;</number>
<link rid="b29">Chomsky (1995c</link>) has argued that to make sense of Lebeaux&apos;s proposal, we need to abandon the idea of a level of underlying structure in favor of the Minimalist cyclic MERGE approach.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn15">
<number>15&ensp;</number>Throughout, we ignore the lower copy of the <i><i>wh</i>
</i>-element itself.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn16">
<number>16</number>&ensp;Some authors disagree (cf. <link rid="b38">Huang 1993</link>) and detect a significant improvement in the second member of each sentence as opposed to the first one. If this effect is real, a principle like P4 below in the text cannot be right in general.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn17">
<number>17&ensp;</number>This would also be necessary in treatments such as <link rid="b56">Reinhart&apos;s (1983a</link>), which crucially appeal to the meaning of the sentence and comparisons between ways of expressing it.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn18">
<number>18&ensp;</number>It is not entirely clear that such an analysis is generally tenable for ACD given the availability of cases such as:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;I wanted everyone you did to leave.</p>
<p>in which Extraposition seems unavailable for the relative. If <i>you did</i> was extraposed, the infinitive would have had to extrapose too, but extraposition of infinitivals seems unavailable (viz. <i>*I wanted you tomorrow to leave</i>). Moreover, there may be another difficulty found in the following type of acceptable example:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;If the journalists always agreed to show <u>him</u> the stories about <uu>her</uu> that <uu>no model</uu> would want <u>a known gossiper</u> to see&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.</p>
<p>These are cases which have been argued to involve raising the head of the relative clause from inside the relative clause (cf. <link rid="b31">Vergnaud 1974</link>; <link rid="b30">Kayne 1994</link>): here the head of the relative presumably must originate inside the relative clause (so that it can reconstruct and get <i>her</i> bound by <i>no model</i>), and thus this construction cannot involve late adjunction of the relative clause in an extraposed position.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn19">
<number>19&ensp;</number>Note that if LF is constructed and interpreted cyclically, the span of A-movement cannot be larger than one cycle (otherwise the Condition C problems with A-movement reappear).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn20">
<number>20&ensp;</number>If trace are copies, such copies must be properly construed so that they are scopally dependent.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn21">
<number>21&ensp;</number>Apart from the arguments of the text above, Heycock argues that the following pair undermines Huang&apos;s approach:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;*I would never consider <u>her Sally&apos;s</u> worst enemy.</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;*<u>Sally&apos;s</u> worst enemy, I would never consider <u>her</u>.</p>
<p>According to Heycock, the preposed constituent in (ii) could not contain the trace of <i>her</i> because it is a DP, <i>a DP only can have one specifier</i>, and Sally occupies this specifier position. This argument seems less strong as it relies on the italicized assumption, which basically contradicts the Predicate Internal Subject Hypothesis (<i>her</i> is the subject of the predicate <i>Sally&apos;s worst enemy</i>), and should thus be taken to be incorrect, pending strong evidence to the contrary&ndash;evidence lacking at the moment. (There is some evidence that argument DPs can have only one overt specifier, but this hardly bears on the question at hand.) Heycock also points out other arguments that we will review in <link rid="ss43">section 5.3.3</link>.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn22">
<number>22&ensp;</number>This is plausible without relevant context. It would be naive to conclude that the reading in (105c) is unavailable for the first question in general. Such a question can very well be asked with that reading in a context in which the songs have a virtual if not actual existence. For example, knowing that six different songs must be composed for a movie, one can ask one of the composers:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;How many of these songs will you compose?</p>
<p>with the reading in (105c). As Tim Stowell points out (p.c.), the same remark applies to examples of this sort:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;I am building the house.</p>
<p>which seem paradoxical as the object of the verb of creation is definite (and thus referring to some pre-existing entity). Even examples similar to <link rid="b40">Heycock&apos;s (1995</link>) below, carefully chosen to eliminate this possibility, can be circumvented in an appropriate context:</p>
<p>(iii)&ensp;How many stories about John is she likely to invent?</p>
<p>could be uttered felicitously with a wide reading if we interpret this not as an actual present but as a historical present (reviewing the woman&apos;s life and knowing all the stories she invented, we can mentally place ourselves at some stage of her life and utter (iii) meaning &lsquo;(Of all the stories she will invent in her life) how many of these is she likely to invent at this point)?&rsquo; In what follows, we always assume that we are not in such contexts in the narrow-scope examples.</p>
<p>
<span id="fn23">
<number>23&ensp;</number>To the author&apos;s ear, only the narrow reading remains available even if we modify the sentence to allow for a pre-established set of songs in discourse, as in:</span>
</p>
<p>
<object id="tu107" type="table" position="fixed" format="inline">
<objectsource>
<insitu id="tu107_source">
<tbl frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody>
<row><entry morerows="1">(i)</entry>
<entry>Combien vas-tu chanter de chansons apprises l&rsquo;an dernier?</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>how many will you sing songs learned last year</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</tbl>
</insitu>
</objectsource>
</object>
</p>
<p>The construction <i>combien .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;de</i> differs from the (partitive) construction <i>combien .&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;des</i> (where des &equals; de &plus;les), as in:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;Combien vas-tu chanter des chansons apprises l&rsquo;an dernier?</p>
<p>which also allows moving <i>combien</i> by itself but uses a different (extraposed) intonation and is ambiguous. See also <link rid="b12">Fox (1999</link>: 153, fn. 20).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn24">
<number>24&ensp;</number>Two remarks on these data: first, the agreement on the past participle in (108a) is indicated as optional. The correct description is more complex: it depends on the reading that is assigned to the question: (impossible with the narrow reading, optional with the wide reading). See <link rid="b57">Obenauer (1994</link>) for relevant discussion. Second, de Swart reports the French facts differently: she reports that under the wide reading, the universal quantifier <i><i>tous</i>
</i> can take scope of the <i><i>wh</i>
</i>-word <i><i>combien</i>
</i> (so that the number varies with each child). I think such a reading &ndash; a pair-list reading &ndash; is impossible with a floated Q, but would be possible with a non-floated Q (i.e., in <i><i>Combien de chansons tous les enfants ont-ils chant&eacute;?</i>
</i>).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn25">
<number>25&ensp;</number>Recall that the condition on pronominal binding cannot fail to be checked at the level at which interpretation is actually performed, i.e., LF, by definition, so the only possibility for strictly different inputs for Condition C and pronominal binding is if Condition C applies to surface or underlying structures (if they are different from LF structures).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn26">
<number>26&ensp;</number>In particular, parasitic readings should be avoided, e.g.:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;Stories about each other&apos;s characterizations &equals; Each story is about the characterization of the other stories</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;Stories about each other&apos;s characterizations &equals; Each one&apos;s story about the others&rsquo; characterizations</p>
<p>
<span id="fn27">
<number>27&ensp;</number>This idea is already present in various form in earlier literature, e.g., <link rid="b58">Burzio (1986</link>). Chomsky, however, uses and justifies it in ways consistent with our present discussion.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn28">
<number>28&ensp;</number>One problem with copy theory is that portions of the resulting interface representations (in <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s 1995c</link> sense) are allowed to be ignored. This raises questions regarding the empirical content of the &lsquo;bare output&rsquo; (or &lsquo;legibility&rsquo;) conditions crucial to <link rid="b29">Chomsky&apos;s (1995c</link>) minimal design conjecture.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn29">
<number>29&ensp;</number>This proposal takes care of all the problems raised in <link rid="b40">Heycock (1995</link>: <link rid="ss44">section 6</link>) for the idea that Condition C applies only at LF.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn30">
<number>30&ensp;</number>Another option would be to get the wide reading from a representation like:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;How many you are looking for pictures?</p>
<p>and let the indefinite <i>pictures</i> take wide scope by other mechanisms (e.g., choice function). Space precludes a discussion of this option. Let us remark that it would wrongly predict impossible answers to questions such as (108a).</p>
<p>
<span id="fn31">
<number>31&ensp;</number>It is not relevant here why such a difference is observed. For proposals, see <related relationship="sibling" type="samework"><externallink id="chapter 64 - Strong vs. Weak Islands.xml" type="file">chapter 64</externallink></related> and references therein.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn32">
<number>32&ensp;</number>There are other proposals similar in spirit if not in detail to this idea (see <link rid="b59">Szabolcsi and Zwarts 1993</link>, for example).</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn33">
<number>33&ensp;</number>Such facts show that there cannot be an absolute prohibition on certain types of quantifiers (<i><i>combien</i>
</i>) crossing over others (negation). This would call at the very least for refinements of approaches to these questions, such as <link rid="b46">Rizzi&apos;s (1990b</link>) Relativized Minimality approach.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn34">
<number>34&ensp;</number>By the Heycock&ndash;Kroch proposal mentioned in <link rid="ss41">section 5.3.1</link>, these questions should improve in a context with the right presupposition.</span>
</p>
<p>
<span id="fn35">
<number>35&ensp;</number>Heycock mentions one more example of the same kind. She gives:</span>
</p>
<p>(i)&ensp;*How much faster than <u>John</u> did <u>he</u> see Mary running?</p>
<p>but native speakers rejected even a variant of it without coreference, due to the clash between the tense of the elided VP and its antecedent (running). If the tense clash is resolved as in:</p>
<p>(ii)&ensp;How much faster <u>than </u>
<uu>John</uu><u> did</u> does <uu>he</uu> think Mary ran?</p>
<p>the sentence seems fine. Note also that the underlined part would be barred from reconstructing all the way down, because it would be a paradoxical antecedent-contained deletion structure.</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="s1-2" type="backmatter">
<subsection id="ss46" level="1" type="references">
<heading id="h45" level="1">REFERENCES</heading>
<reference id="b50" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Aoun</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Joseph</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Elabbas</forenames><x> </x><surname>Benmamoun</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Minimality, Reconstruction and PF Movement</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>29</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">569</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">597</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b48" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Baltin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mark</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">On the Characterization and Effects of D-Linking: Comments on Cinque</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Current Issues in Comparative Grammar</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>Freidin</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
<miscellaneoustext> (ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">249</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">256</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Kluwer.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b7" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Barss</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Andrew</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Chains and Anaphoric Dependencies. PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b24" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Barss</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Andrew</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Paths, Connectivity and Featureless Empty Categories</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Constituent Structure</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Anna</forenames><x> </x><surname>Cardinaletti</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Guglielmo</forenames><x> </x><surname>Cinque</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Guliana</forenames><x> </x><surname>Giusti</surname>
</name>
</namegroup>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext><x>.), </x><page type="first">9</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">34</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b25" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Belletti</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Adriana</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Luigi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rizzi</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Psych Verbs and Theta Theory</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>6</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">291</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">352</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Bouchard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Denis</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date><x>). </x><title type="book">On the Content of Empty Categories</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Foris.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b36" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Brody</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Michael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Lexico-Logical Form: A Radically Minimalist Theory</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b58" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Burzio</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Italian Syntax: A Government-Binding Approach</title><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Knowledge of Language: Its Nature, Origin and Use</title><x>. </x><address>New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Praeger.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b29" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Chomsky</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Noam</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Minimalist Program<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b28" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cinque</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Guglielmo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1984">1984</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). A-Bar Bound Variable vs. Pro. Unpublished manuscript, University of Venice</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b45" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cinque</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Guglielmo</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990c</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Types of A&prime;-Dependencies<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b26" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Cresti</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Diana</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Extraction and Reconstruction</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>3</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">79</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">122</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b3" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dikken</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Marcel<x> </x>den</forenames>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Andr&eacute;</forenames><x> </x><surname>Meinunger</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Chris</forenames><x> </x><surname>Wilder</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pseudoclefts and Ellipsis</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Studia Linguistica</title><x> </x><volume>54</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">41</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">89</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b42" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Dobrovie-Sorin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carmen</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Syntax of Romanian: Comparative Studies in Romance</title><x>. </x><address>Berlin/New York</address><x>: </x><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b51" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Elbourne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Paul</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Some Correlations Between Semantic Plurality and Quantifier Scope</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 29</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Pius</forenames><x> </x><surname>Tamanji</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Kiyomi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kusumoto</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">81</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">92</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b12" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Economy and Semantic Interpretation<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b16" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Antecedent Contained Deletion and the Copy Theory of Movement</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>33</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">63</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">96</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b33" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Jon</forenames><x> </x><surname>Nissenbaum</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Extraposition and Scope: A Case for Overt QR</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Eighteenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Sonya</forenames><x> </x><surname>Bird</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Andrew</forenames><x> </x><surname>Carnie</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Jason<x> </x>D<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Haugen</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Peter</forenames><x> </x><surname>Norquest</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">132</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">144</page><x>. </x><address>Somerville</address><x>: </x><publisher>Cascadilla Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b27" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Fox</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Danny</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Jon</forenames><x> </x><surname>Nissenbaum</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Condition A and Scope Reconstruction. Unpublished manuscript, Cambridge, MIT/Harvard University</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b18" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Freidin</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Fundamental Issues in the Theory of Binding</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Studies in the Acquisition of Anaphora</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Barbara</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lust</surname>
</name></namegroup><miscellaneoustext> (Ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x><page type="first">151</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">188</page><x>. </x><address>Dordrecht</address><x>: </x><publisher>Reidel.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heim</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Irene</forenames>
</name><x>, </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Howard</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lasnik</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>May</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reciprocity and Plurality</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>22</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">63</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">103</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b40" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heycock</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Caroline</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Asymmetries in Reconstruction</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>26</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">547</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">570</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b1" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Heycock</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Caroline</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Anthony</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kroch</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Pseudocleft Connectedness: Implications for the LF Interface Level</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>30</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">365</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">398</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b38" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Huang</surname><x>, </x><forenames>C.-T<x>. </x>James</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reconstruction and the Structure of VP</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>24</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">103</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">138</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b53" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Jacobson</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Pauline</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Towards a Variable-Free Semantics</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Journal of Philosophy</title><x> </x><volume>22</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">117</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">184</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b30" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kayne</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Richard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">The Antisymmetry of Syntax<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b49" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kroch</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anthony</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Amount Quantification, Referentiality and Long <i>Wh-</i>Movement. Unpublished manuscript, University of Pennsylvania</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b5" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Kuno</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Susumu</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Binding Theory in the Minimalist Program. Unpublished manuscript, Harvard University</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b15" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lasnik</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Howard</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Some Reconstruction Riddles</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Twenty-second Annual Penn Linguistics Colloquium</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Alexis</forenames><x> </x><surname>Dimitriadis</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Hikyoung</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lee</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Christine</forenames><x> </x><surname>Moisset</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Alexander</forenames><x> </x><surname>Williams</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">83</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">98</page><x>. </x><address>Philadelphia</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Pennsylvania.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lebeaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Distributional Difference between Reciprocals and Reflexives</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>14</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">723</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">730</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b19" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lebeaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988b</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Language Acquisition and the Form of Grammar. PhD dissertation</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Amherst, University of Massachusetts</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b20" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lebeaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1991">1991</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Relative Clauses, Licensing and the Nature of Derivations</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Perspectives on Phrase Structure: Heads and Licensing</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Rothstein</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (ed.)</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</namegroup><x> </x><address>San Diego</address><x>: </x><publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b11" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Lebeaux</surname><x>, </x><forenames>David</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Where Does the Binding Theory Apply?: Technical Report. Unpublished manuscript</miscellaneoustext><x>, </x>
<address>Research Institute, NEC</address><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b13" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>May</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1985">1985</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Logical Form: Its Structure and Derivation</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b34" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>May</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Robert</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Robert</forenames><x> </x><surname>Fiengo</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Indices and Identity</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b55" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>McCawley</surname><x>, </x><forenames>James</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Why Surface Syntactic Structure Reflects Logical Structure As Much As it Does, but Only That Much</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Language</title><x> </x><volume>75</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">34&ndash;62</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Nissenbaum</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jon</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Investigations of Covert Phrase Movement. PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b57" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Obenauer</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Hans-Georg</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1994">1994</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Aspects de la Syntaxe A&prime;. PhD thesis, University of Paris 8</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Pollard</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Carl</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Ivan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Sag</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1992">1992</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Anaphors in English and the Scope of the Binding Theory</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>23</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">261</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">305</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b56" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1983">1983a</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Anaphora and Semantic Interpretation<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>London/Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>Croom Helm/University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b39" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Reinhart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Tanya</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Eric</forenames><x> </x><surname>Reuland</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reflexivity</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>24</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">595</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">652</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b17" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Riemsdijk</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henk<x> </x>C<x>. </x>van</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Edwin</forenames><x> </x><surname>Williams</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1981">1981</date><x>). </x><title type="document">NP Structure</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Review</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">171</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">217</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b46" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1990">1990b</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Relativized Minimality</title><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b44" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Rizzi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Luigi</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Reconstruction, Weak Island Sensitivity and Agreement. Unpublished manuscript, University of Siena</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b47" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Roberts</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Ian</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1988">1988b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Thematic Interveners</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Rivista di Grammatica Generativa</title><x> </x><volume>13</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">111</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">136</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b10" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Romero</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Maribel</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997a</date><x>). </x><title type="document">The Correlation between Scope Reconstruction and Connectivity Effects</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Sixteenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Emily</forenames><x> </x><surname>Curtis</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>James</forenames><x> </x><surname>Lyle</surname>
</name><x>, and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Gabriel</forenames><x> </x><surname>Webster</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">351</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">366</page><x>. </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b6" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Safir</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Kenneth</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Vehicle Change and Reconstruction in A-Bar Chains</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>30</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">587</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">620</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b52" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Saito</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Mamoru</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1989">1989</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Scrambling as Semantically Vacuous A&prime;-Movement</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Alternative Conceptions of Phrase Structure</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Mark</forenames><x> </x><surname>Baltin</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Anthony</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kroch</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">182</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">200</page><x>. </x><address>Chicago</address><x>: </x><publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b22" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sauerland</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Uli</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999c</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Scope Reconstruction without Reconstruction</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the Seventeenth West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Kimary<x> </x>N<x>.</x>
</forenames><x> </x><surname>Shahin</surname>
</name><x>, </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Susan</forenames><x> </x><surname>Blake</surname>
</name><x>
</x><x>, </x><miscellaneoustext>and</miscellaneoustext><x> </x>
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Eun-Sook</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kim</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">582</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">596</page><x>. </x><address>Cambridge</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b23" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sauerland</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Uli</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Paul</forenames><x> </x><surname>Elbourne</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2002">2002</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Total Reconstruction, PF Movement, Derivational Order</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>33</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">283</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">320</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b4" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Schlenker</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Philippe</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2003">2003b</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Clausal Equations: A Note on the Connectivity Problem</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language and Linguistic Theory</title><x> </x><volume>21/1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">157</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">214</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b54" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sharvit</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Yael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Possessive <i>Wh</i>-Expressions and Reconstruction</title>
<x>. </x><miscellaneoustext>In</miscellaneoustext><x>: </x>
<title type="book">Proceedings of the North Eastern Linguistic Society 28</title><x>. </x><namegroup type="editors">
<name type="editor">
<forenames>Pius</forenames><x> </x><surname>Tamanji</surname>
</name><x> and </x><name type="editor">
<forenames>Kiyomi</forenames><x> </x><surname>Kusumoto</surname>
</name>
<miscellaneoustext> (eds</miscellaneoustext>
</namegroup><x>.), </x><page type="first">409</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">423</page><x>. </x><address>Amherst</address><x>: </x><publisher>Graduate Linguistics Student Association.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b2" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sharvit</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Yael</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Connectivity in Specificational Sentences</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>7</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">299</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">339</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b8" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1997">1997</date><x>). </x><address>Reconstruction and Constituency</address><x>: </x><publisher>Talk given at MIT, Cambridge.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b9" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1999">1999</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Reconstruction, Constituency and Morphology</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">GLOW Newsletter</title><x> </x><volume>42</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">56</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">57</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b32" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2000">2000</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Sources for Relative Clauses. Unpublished manuscript, UCLA</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b21" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Sportiche</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Dominique</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="2003">2003</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). Some Apparent Paradoxes in Reconstruction. Unpublished manuscript, UCLA</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b43" type="book">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Swart</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Henri&euml;tte<x> </x>de</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1998">1998</date><x>). </x><title type="book">Introduction to Natural Language Semantics<x>.</x>
</title><x> </x><address>Stanford</address><x>: </x><publisher>CSLI Publications.</publisher>
</reference>
<reference id="b59" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Szabolcsi</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Anna</forenames>
</name><x> and </x><name type="author">
<forenames>Frans</forenames><x> </x><surname>Zwarts</surname>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1993">1993</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Weak Islands and an Algebraic Semantics of Scope Taking</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Natural Language Semantics</title><x> </x><volume>1</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">235</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">284</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b41" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Takano</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Yuji</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1995">1995</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Predicate Fronting and Internal Subjects</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>26</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">327</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">340</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b31" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Vergnaud</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Jean-Roger</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1974">1974</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). French Relative Clauses. PhD dissertation, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b37" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Williams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edwin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1980">1980</date><x>). </x><title type="document">Predication</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>11</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">203</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">238</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b35" type="journal">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Williams</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Edwin</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1986">1986</date><x>). </x><title type="document">A Reassignment of the Functions of LF</title><x>. </x><title type="journal">Linguistic Inquiry</title><x> </x><volume>17/2</volume><x>: </x><page type="first">265</page><x>&ndash;</x><page type="last">299</page><x>.</x>
</reference>
<reference id="b14" type="other">
<namegroup type="author">
<name type="author">
<surname>Zubizarreta</surname><x>, </x><forenames>Maria-Luisa</forenames>
</name>
</namegroup><x> (</x><date date="1982">1982a</date>
<miscellaneoustext>). On the Relation of the Lexicon to Syntax. PhD dissertation, Cambridge, MIT</miscellaneoustext><x>.</x>
</reference>
</subsection>
</section>
</document>
</content> 
